<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Ramsgate, Wednesday, 31 May 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let083"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b80 V/1962 (sheet 1) and d301 V/1972 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>083</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>67</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>081</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-05-31">Wednesday, 31 May 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Ramsgate</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0080" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0080" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000083_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="d 0301" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001001665_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="VGM001001665_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="d 0301 V/1972" xml:id="surf-extra-2v">
<graphic url="VGM001001665_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic url="VGM001001665_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Ramsgate 31 Mei 1876</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Bravo dat Gij 21 Mei te Etten zijt geweest, gelukkig <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>waren er dus 4 van de 6 te huis.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Pa schreef <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>mij uitvoerig hoe alles dien dag geweest was. <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Dank voor Uw laatsten brief ook.─</p><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Heb ik U reeds geschreven van dien storm dien <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ik laatst zag? De zee was geelachtig, vooral <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>digt bij het strand; aan den horizon eene streep <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>licht en daarboven de ontzaggelijk groote donkere <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>grijze wolken waaruit men den regen in schuine <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>strepen zag nederkomen. De wind deed het stof <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>van het witte paadje op de rotsen in zee stuiven <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>en bewoog de bloeijende meidoornstruiken en <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>muurbloemen die op de rotsen groeijen.─</p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Rechts velden jong groen koren en in de verte <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>de stad die er met hare torens, molens<c type="kk">,</c> leijen <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>daken en in gothieken stijl gebouwde huizen en <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>beneden de haven tusschen de 2 in zee uitstekende <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>dammen uitzag als de steden die Albert Durer <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>wel etste.─ Ook heb ik verleden zondag nacht de zee gezien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>alles was donker grauw maar aan den horizon begon <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>den dag toch aan te breken. ’t Was nog heel vroeg 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>maar toch zong de leeuwrik reeds. En de nachtegalen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>in de tuinen aan zee. In de verte het licht <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>van den vuurtoren<c type="kk">,</c> het wachtschip &amp;c.─</p><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Dien zelfden nacht keek ik uit het raam van <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>mijne kamer naar de daken der huizen die men van daar <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ziet en naar de toppen der iepen<c type="kk">,</c> donker tegen de <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>nachtlucht. Boven die daken één enkele ster maar <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>een mooie groote vriendelijke<c type="kp">.</c> En ik dacht aan <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ons allen en ik dacht aan mijne reeds vervlogen jaren en <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>aan ons t’huis<c type="kk">,</c> en de woorden en het gevoel kwa<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>men op “Bewaar mij te zijn een zoon die beschaamd <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>maakt<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> geef mij Uw zegen nog, niet omdat ik dien <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>verdien maar om mijner Moeder wil.─ Gij zijt <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Liefde, bedek alle dingen.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Zonder Uw voortdurenden zegen lukt <lb n="37a" xml:id="l-37a"/>ons niets”.─</p><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Hierbij een teekeningetje van het gezigt uit het raam <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>van de school waardoor de jongens hunne Ouders <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>nazien als die hun hebben bezocht en weder naar <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>het station teruggaan.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Menigeen zal het gezicht <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>uit dat raam wel nooit vergeten. Gij hadt het <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>deze week toen wij regenachtige dagen hadden <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>eens moeten zien<c type="kk">,</c> vooral in de schemering als de 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>lantaarns worden aangestoken en het licht <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>daarvan in de natte straat weerkaatst.─</p><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">In die dagen was Mr Stokes soms niet in zijn <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>humeur en als de jongens wat te veel leven naar <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>zijn zin maakten gebeurde het wel zij <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>s’avonds hun brood en thee niet kregen.─ <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Gij hadt hen dan eens uit dat raam moeten <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>zien staan kijken, daar was wel iets melan<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>kolieks in; zij hebben zoo weinig anders dan <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>hun eten en drinken om op te hopen en om <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>van den eenen dag op den anderen te komen<c type="kp">.</c><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/> Ook zou ik wel willen gij hen eens het don<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>kere trapje en gangetje door naar de tafel <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>zaagt gaan.─ Daarop schijnt de vriendelijke <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>zon echter.─</p><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Eene andere eigenaardige plaats is ook de <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>kamer met verrotten vloer waar de 6 kommen <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>waar zij zich wasschen staan, en maar een <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>flaauw licht door het raam met gebroken ruiten <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>op de waschtafel valt; dat is wel min of meer een <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>melankoliek gezicht.─ Wel gaarne zou ik met <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>hen een winter passeeren of gepasseerd hebben, om <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>eens te weten hoe dat is.─</p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">De jongelui maken een olievlak op Uw teekeningetje,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>vergeef het hun.─</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Hierbij nog een woordje voor Oom Jan.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">En nu goeden avond, mocht iemand naar mij <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>vragen dan goeden dag. Komt gij nog wel eens bij <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Borchers<c type="kp">.</c> Zoo gij hem ziet<c type="kk">,</c> groet hem dan en ook <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>Willem Valkis en allen bij Roos.─ In gedachten <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>een handdruk van</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Uw liefh.</p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Ramsgate, 31 May 1876</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Bully for you, being in Etten on 21 May, happily there were 4 of the 6 at home.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> wrote to me in detail about everything that happened that day. Thanks, too, for your last letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Have I already written to you about the storm I saw recently? The sea was yellowish, especially close to the beach; a streak of light on the horizon and, above this, tremendously huge dark grey clouds from which one saw the rain coming down in slanting streaks. The wind blew the dust from the small white path on the rocks into the sea and tossed the blossoming hawthorn bushes and wallflowers that grow on the rocks.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">On the right, fields of young green wheat, and, in the distance, the town with its towers, mills, slate roofs and houses built in Gothic style, and, below, the harbour between the 2 jetties running out into the sea, looking like the cities <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Albrecht Dürer</rs> used to etch. I also saw the sea last Sunday night, everything was dark grey, but day was beginning to break on the horizon. It was still very early, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> and yet a lark was already singing. And the nightingales in the gardens on the sea-front. In the distance the light of the lighthouse, the guard-ship &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">That same night I looked out of the window of my room onto the roofs of the houses one sees from there and the tops of the elms, dark against the night sky. Above those roofs, one single star, but a nice, big friendly one. And I thought of us all, and I thought of the years of my life that had already passed, and of our home, and the words and feeling came to me, ‘Keep me from being a son that causeth shame,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> give me Your blessing, not because I deserve it, but for my Mother’s sake. Thou art Love, beareth all things.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Without your constant blessing we can do nothing.’</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Herewith a little drawing of the view from the school window where the boys stand and watch their parents going back to the station after a visit.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Many a boy will never forget the view from that window. You should have seen it this week when we had rainy days, especially in the twilight when the 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> street-lamps are being lit and their light is reflected in the wet street.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs> was sometimes moody during those days, and when the boys were too boisterous for him it sometimes happened that they didn’t get their bread and tea in the evening. You should have seen them then, standing at the window looking out, it was really rather sad. They have so little apart from their food and drink to look forward to and to get them through the day. I’d also like you to see them going down the dark stairs and small corridor to table. On that, however, the friendly sun shines.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Another extraordinary place is the room with the rotten floor where there are 6 basins at which they wash themselves, with only a feeble light falling onto the washstand through a window with broken panes. It’s quite a melancholy sight, to be sure. How I’d like to spend or to have spent a winter with them, to know what it’s like.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">The youngsters are making an oil stain on your little drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> forgive them. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Herewith a few words for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">And now good-night, if anyone should ask after me bid them good-day. Do you still visit <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_298">Borchers</rs> once in a while? Give him my regards if you see him, and also <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem Valkis</rs> and everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’. A handshake in thought from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Your loving</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Ramsgate 31 Mei 1876’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Mr and Mrs van Gogh’s twenty-fifth anniversary on 21 May <ref target="let064.xml">(64)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> and Theo were in Etten on 21 May; <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and Vincent, who were both living in England, could not attend the celebration.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 10:5, Prov. 17:2 and Prov. 19:26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Cf. 1 Cor. 13:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The enclosed drawing was <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_6"><hi rend="italics">View of Royal Road, Ramsgate</hi></rs> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_6">F Juv. XXVII / JH Juv. 5</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 60, cat. no. 8. Van Gogh also sent ‘a nice little drawing of his house’ to his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> (FR b2752).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The oil stain is visible at the lower right.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan (Johannes) van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    