<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Monday, 21 and Tuesday, 22 May 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let115"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b114 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>115</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>96</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>115</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-05-21">Monday, 21 and Tuesday, 22 May 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0114" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000123_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="VGM001000123_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0114" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000123_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="VGM001000123_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Amsterdam 21 Mei 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Dank voor Uw brief en voor de Kerkelijke Attestatie,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> het is jammer Gij op <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Pinkster<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> niet naar Etten zijt geweest, en van harte hoop ik Gij een volgenden <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Zondag zult kunnen gaan. Hebt Gij die Attestatie gemakkelijk gekregen? <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>dank voor Uwe moeite.–</p><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Gisteren was ik des morgens in de vroegkerk<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en hoorde eene preek<c type="kk">,</c> “Ik zal <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>niet eeuwig twisten met den mensch”<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> hoe na een tijd van teleurstelling en <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>grief er in het leven een tijd kan komen waarin de innigste verlangens <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>en wenschen kunnen worden vervuld. s’morgens 10 uur hoorde ik Oom <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Stricker over Hand<c type="kp">.</c> II:1-4<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> de uitstorting van den Heiligen Geest. Eene <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>zeer mooie<c type="kk">,</c> hartelijke, warme toespraak, heden morgen ga ik Oom weer <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>hooren en moet daar nu heen, schrijf U straks wat de tekst was.–</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Het is regenachtig weer van daag en eene lange wandeling<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> langs den Buitenkant <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>naar de Noorderkerk.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> De stad zag er daar bij den Schreijerstoren<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en daar waar men <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ook gezigt heeft op het IJ uit als een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van J. Maris<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> De tekst was I Korinthe 12:13<c type="kk">,</c> Want <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>ook wij allen zijn door éénen Geest tot één ligchaam gedoopt<c type="kp">.</c> Er zijn mooie kerken <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>hier<c type="kp">.</c> Deze week ben ik tot de Zuiderzee<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> gewandeld over een dijk naar Zeeburg.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Dan komt men langs het Jodenkerkhof<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> waar ik ook op geweest ben<c type="kp">.</c> Het is zeer een<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>voudig<c type="kk">,</c> vol regtopstaande oude zerken met Hebreeuwsche opschriften en vlier<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>boomen hier en daar en begroeid met lang donkerkleurig gras. Gisteren <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>(Zondag) middag ben ik met Oom Jan naar Baarn<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> geweest<c type="kk">,</c> wat is het daar <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>mooi<c type="kk">,</c> wij wandelden in de lanen van sparren en beuken in het bosch en zagen <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>de zon ondergaan achter het eikenhakhout. Gij kunt wel denken het daar aan <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>de werf en het dok en den IJ kant s’avonds, zoo als b.v. gisteren toen wij te huis kwamen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>mooi is, en er is dan zulk eene heerlijke lucht van teer die doet denken aan de <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>mastbosschen.</p><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Oom gaf mij gisteren eenige oude zwarte handschoenen en dassen, dacht <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>wij die broederlijk wilden deelen<c type="kp">.</c>– Gij ontvangt ze dezer dagen als stalen zonder waarde,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> want zwarte handschoenen dat is een goed <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ding<c type="kk">,</c> goed zoo als b.v. klimop en “mosses green and lichens fair”<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en goed als is <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>de vaste gewoonte om naar de kerk te gaan.–</p><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Dezen middag ga ik naar Oom Stricker die mij heeft gevraagd daar te komen, Vos<c type="kk">,</c> Kee<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en het meisje van Paul<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> zullen er ook zijn.</p><lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Kent Gij eene oude Engelsche gravure “The vicars daughter”<c type="kk">,</c> die hangt te <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Baarn<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en trof mij gisteren<c type="kk">,</c> let er eens op als Gij te Baarn komt<c type="kp">.</c> De stemming <lb n="35a" xml:id="l-35a"/>herrinnert aan Die Abendglocke.–<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">En toch vind ik het zoo jammer er daar en ook in de mooie kamers van <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Oom Jan nergens iets hangt als Christus Consolator<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> of Ecce Homo. De laatste hangt <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>immers op Uw kamertje, ten minste ik meen die te hebben opgemerkt<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-21"/> wen er U maar <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>aan die overal waar Gij een kamertje hebt op te hangen, want dat is regt en dat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>komt U toe.–</p><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Dezen morgen zag ik in de kerk een oud vrouwtje, waarschijnlijk stooven<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>zetster,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> die mij zoo deed denken aan die ets van Rembrandt<c type="kk">,</c> eene vrouw <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>die in den Bijbel heeft gelezen en met het hoofd op de hand geleund<c type="kk">,</c> is <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>in slaap gevallen.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Ch<c type="kp">.</c> Blanc schrijft er zoo mooi en met zooveel gevoel over<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>en ik meen ook Michelet in zijn: il n’y a point de vieille femme.–<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Ook het <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>gedicht van de Genestet: “Haar pad in t’leven loopt eenzaam af”<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> doet er aan denken.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Zouden wij ook aan den avond van ons leven<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> zijn als t’ware vóór wij het zelf <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>weten – als wij de dagen voelen omvliegen en steeds sneller voorbijgaan – is het <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>mij wel eens goed dat te gelooven en te vertrouwen<c type="kk">,</c> “l’homme s’agite et Dieu le mène”.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/></p><lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Zijt Gij de Pinksterdagen s’morgens in de zaak geweest? Ik hoop Gij het toch <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>goed zult gehad hebben.–</p><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">22 Mei<c type="kp">.</c> Gisteren avond was ik bij Oom Stricker waar het gezellig <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>was<c type="kp">.</c> Vos, Kee, het meisje van Paul en Jan<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> waren er en het was over <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>11 toen ik t’huis was, heb toen nog zitten schrijven tot 12, wat zou <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>ik wenschen wij zoo zamen hier en daar heen konden gaan, had <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>er U gisteren avond wel bij willen hebben.</p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Schrijf maar weer spoedig een woordje als Gij een oogenblikje <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>hebt. Dezen morgen moet ik nog heel wat werken, ik zie <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wel ’t niet gemakkelijk is en nog wel veel moeielijker zal <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>worden, maar heb toch vaste hoop het zal gelukken, en <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>ook ben ik overtuigd dat al werkende ik zal leeren werken en <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>mijn werk beter en degelijker zal worden. Reeds nu begin ik aan <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Bijbelstudie maar alleen des avonds als het werk voor den dag af <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>is of des morgens vroeg – after all is dat het voornaamste – al <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>is het mijn pligt mij nu aan de andere studie te wijden<c type="kk">,</c> wat ik ook doe.</p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Heb gisteren bij Stricker moeten vertellen van Londen en van Parijs <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>en als ik dat doe zie ik het alles weer voor mij, ook alles in <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>dat verleden kan medewerken ten goede,<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> ik heb ginder veel <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>lief, en och dat heb ik overal gehad waar ik geweest ben, dat voel <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>ik wel als ik door de straten te s’Hage wandel of b.v. te Zundert<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>dien laatsten togt daarheen<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> vergeet ik niet ligt. Voor ik naar <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Stricker ging liep ik nog even op<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> het Trippenhuis<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> om enkele <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>schilderijen nog weer eens te zien<c type="kk">,</c> gij weet wel welke.–</p><lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Nu Theo, groet den een en ander die Gij mogt zien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>schrijf eens spoedig, heb het zoo goed mogelijk, ontvang <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>een fermen handdruk in gedachten en geloof mij </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Amsterdam, 21 May 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Thanks for your letter and for the church’s attestation,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> it’s a pity you didn’t go to Etten for Whitsun;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I sincerely hope you’ll be able to go one Sunday soon. Did you get the attestation easily? Thanks for taking the trouble.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Yesterday morning I went to the early service<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and heard a sermon, ‘I shall not always strive with man’,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> how after a time of disappointment and grief in life a time may come when one’s innermost desires and wishes may be fulfilled. At 10 in the morning I heard <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs> on Acts II:1-4,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> the pouring forth of the Holy Spirit. A very beautiful, warm address from the heart; this morning I’m going to hear Uncle again and must go now, I’ll write and tell you presently what his text was.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">It’s rainy today, and a long walk<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> along Buitenkant to the Noorderkerk.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> There, by the Schreijerstoren,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> where one has a view of the IJ, the city looked like a painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">J. Maris</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> The text was I Corinthians 12:13, For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body. There are some beautiful churches here. This week I walked as far as the Zuiderzee<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> on a dyke going to Zeeburg.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> This takes one past the Jodenkerkhof,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> which I visited as well. It’s very simple, full of old tombstones standing upright with Hebrew inscriptions and elderberries here and there, and covered with long, dark grass. Yesterday (Sunday) afternoon I went with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs> to Baarn,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> how beautiful it is there, we walked in the wood in the avenues of spruce and beech trees and saw the sun go down behind the oak copse. You can imagine how beautiful it is in the evening, around the time we came home yesterday, for example, at the wharf and the dockyard and the shore of the IJ, and there’s such a glorious smell of tar in the air that reminds one of pine-woods.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Yesterday <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle</rs> gave me some old black gloves and scarves. Thought we’d share them in brotherly fashion. You’ll receive them in a day or two as ‘samples without value’,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> because black gloves are a good thing, good like ivy, for example, and ‘mosses green and lichens fair’,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and good like the fixed habit of going to church.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">This afternoon I’m going to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>’s, who asked me to come, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_806">Vos</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_516">Paul’s girl</rs><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> will be there too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">Do you know an old English engraving ‘The vicar’s daughter’? It’s hanging at Baarn<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and struck me yesterday; look out for it if you come to Baarn. Its atmosphere recalls Die Abendglocke.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Nevertheless, I find it such a pity that there, as well as in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs>’s best rooms, there is nothing hanging like Christus Consolator<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> or Ecce Homo. The latter is hanging in your room, surely, at least I thought I noticed it there.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Do make a habit of hanging it up everywhere you live, for that is right and is your due.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">This morning in church I saw a little old woman, probably the foot-stove woman,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> who reminded me so much of that etching by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, a woman who has been reading the Bible and has fallen asleep leaning her head on her hand.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">C. Blanc</rs> writes about it so beautifully and with so much feeling,<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> and I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> does as well in his: there is no such thing as an old woman.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> The poem by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">De Génestet</rs>, ‘Haar pad in ’t leven loopt eenzaam af’<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> also reminds me of it. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Will we also find ourselves in the evening of our life<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> before we know it, as it were? – when we feel the days flying by, passing ever more quickly – it helps me to believe and trust that ‘man proposes, but God disposes’.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Were you at the gallery in the mornings over the Whitsun holidays? I do hope you had a good time all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">22 May. Yesterday evening I was at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>’s, where it was very convivial. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_806">Vos</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_516">Paul’s girl</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_778">Jan</rs><ptr target="#note-t-29"/> were there, and it was after 11 when I got home, then I wrote until 12, how I wish that we could go to places together, I’d have liked you to be with us last night.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14"> Do write a few words again soon, when you have a moment. This morning I still have a lot of work to do, I see that it isn’t easy and will no doubt become much more difficult, yet have unfaltering hope that I’ll succeed, and I’m also convinced that I’ll learn to work by working, and that my work will become better and more substantial. I’ve already begun studying the Bible, but only in the evenings, when I’ve finished my work for the day, or early in the morning – after all, that’s the most important thing – even though it’s now my duty to dedicate myself to studying other things, which I do, of course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15"> Yesterday at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317 bio.xml#_318">the Strickers</rs>’ I had to tell them about London and Paris, and whenever I do that I see it all before me again, all things from that past can also work together for good,<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> I’m fond of much there, and that, ah, I’ve experienced that everywhere I’ve been, I also feel that when I walk the streets of The Hague or Zundert, for example, I shan’t easily forget that last journey there.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> Before I went to the Strickers’ I walked briefly through the Trippenhuis<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> in order to see several paintings again, I’m sure you know which ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Now, Theo, give my regards to one person or another you might see, write soon, I wish you the very best, accept a firm handshake in thought, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 21 Mei 1877’; in <ref target="#l-52">l. 52</ref>, ‘22 Mei’ is given as the date on which the letter was continued.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>An attestation – declaring one’s religious faith and character to be sound and honourable – issued by a church council when one of its members moved to another community.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In 1877, Whit Sunday and Monday fell on 20-21 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Two early services were held on Whit Sunday at 7 a.m.: the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1679">Rev. Theodorus Matthijs Looman</rs>, an adherent of the Réveil, took the service in the Noorderkerk, and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_206">Rev. Lieuwe Steinfort</rs>, an opponent of the independent principles advocated by Abraham Kuyper, conducted the service in the Zuiderkerk (<hi rend="italics">NNBW</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 6:3; cf. also Isa. 57:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">J.P. Stricker</rs> preached at 10 a.m. in the Zuiderkerk. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Read: ‘I took a long walk’. Regarding this walk, see Groot and De Vries 1990, pp. 21-23.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The Noorderkerk is located on the Noordermarkt. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The Schreijerstoren is located at the corner of Prins Hendrikkade (in those days the Kamper Hoofd) and the Gelderse Kade. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh could have been thinking of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jacob Maris</rs>’s painting <hi rend="italics">The Buitenkant with the Schreierstoren, Amsterdam</hi> (Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1823">Ill. 1823</rs>. See also <ref target="let031.xml#n-4">letter 31, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>At that time the Zuiderzee was still connected to the sea; it is now called the IJsselmeer (Lake IJssel).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The modern-day Zeeburgerdijk, called at that time the Sint Anthoniesdijk. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The Jewish cemetery (the ‘Hoogduitsche Joden-Kerkhof’, or High German Jewish Cemetery) near Zeeburgerdijk (now called Flevoweg). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The journey on Whit Sunday to Baarn, a town around 35 km south-east of Amsterdam, was undertaken to visit <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor van Gogh</rs>, who lived in a villa there (cf. FR b2727 and <ref target="let158.xml#n-11">letter 158, n. 11</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>A label put on samples sent by post, which were charged lower postage rates.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Taken from the last verse of the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_134">Mortality</ref>’ (1859) by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_713">Dinah Maria Mulock Craik</rs>:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
  
<p rend="indent">Ye dead leaves, dropping soft and slow,</p>

<p rend="indent">Ye mosses green and lichens fair,</p>

<p rend="indent">Go to your graves, as I will go,</p>

<p rend="indent">For God is also there.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>Published in <hi rend="italics">Poems</hi>. Leipzig 1868, pp. 44-45.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_806">Christoffel Martinus Vos</rs> married <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Cornelia Adriana Stricker</rs> (referred to as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs>) in 1872; Kee was a daughter of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317 bio.xml#_318">J.P. Stricker and W.C.G. Carbentus</rs>, referred to as ‘Uncle Stricker’ (or ‘J.P.S.’) and ‘Aunt Mina’. Christoffel Vos suffered from tuberculosis.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_516">Margaretha A.S. Meyboom</rs> was engaged to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_775">Johannes Paulus (Paul) Stricker</rs>. Margreet later wrote about Vincent: ‘I remember him so well. I met him at the Geldersche Kade [where the Stricker family lived]. It was the tenderness in him that appealed to me. You got the feeling that you couldn’t speak to him other than in a tender, friendly way. That, and his wanting resolutely to go his own way was a combination that attracted me.’ Letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien van Gogh</rs>, The Hague, 13 January 1889 (private collection).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>It is not clear which depiction of <hi rend="italics">The vicar’s daughter</hi> this refers to. It could be the print published at the front of the book <hi rend="italics">Procrastination; or, The vicar’s daughter. A tale</hi>. London 1824 (London, British Library). This anonymous engraving was made in the style of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_208">Thomas Stotthard</rs>. Another possibility is <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_116"><hi rend="italics">The vicar’s daughter</hi></rs> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_64">George Dunlop Leslie</rs>, after which a woodcut was published in the Christmas number of <hi rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> in 1878 (p. 24). There are steel-plate engravings after Leslie’s work, such as <hi rend="italics">News from the war</hi> (1877); perhaps there was also one of <hi rend="italics">The vicar’s daughter</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>There are at least 60 nineteenth-century songs that have the word <hi rend="italics">Abendglocke(n)</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Abendglöcklein</hi> (Evening bell) in the title or in the first line. Eleven of them became known through popular literature or were passed on by word of mouth. The one most likely intended here is the folk song <hi rend="italics">Die Abendglocke</hi> (also <hi rend="italics">Die Abendglöcklein</hi>), known from 1825 and set to music by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1798">Friedrich Silcher</rs>. Not only is it included in a number of songbooks and pamphlets (by 1877 it had appeared in around 12 collections), but it also occurs most frequently in the oral tradition. The song has three couplets and begins as follows:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">Look how the sun is now sinking</p>

<p rend="indent">Behind the wood at night-time!</p>

<p rend="indent">Little bell, rest to us signalling,</p>

<p rend="indent">Listen to its pretty chime!</p>

<p rend="indent">Trustworthy bell, oh how lovely you ring!</p>

<p rend="indent">Ring on, my bell, with all zest,</p>

<p rend="indent">Ring in the hour of sweet rest!</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">(Seht, wie die Sonne dort sinket</p>

<p rend="indent">hinter dem nächtlichen Wald!</p>

<p rend="indent">Glöckchen schon Ruhe uns winket,</p>

<p rend="indent">hört nur, wie lieblich es schallt!</p>

<p rend="indent">Trauliches Glöcklein, du läutest so schön!</p>

<p rend="indent">läute mein Glöcklein, nur zu,</p>

<p rend="indent">läute zur süßen Ruh’!)</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>See <hi rend="italics">Großer Schulliederschatz oder 1000 Jugend- und Volkslieder ... Ein Buch für evangelische Lehrer sowie für alle Freunde gesunden Volksgesanges</hi>. Gütersloh 1868, p. 326, no. 706 and Franz Magnus Böhme, <hi rend="italics">Volksthümliche Lieder der Deutschen im 18. und 19. Jahrhundert</hi>. Leipzig 1895, p. 180, no. 228.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>For the print after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1771"><hi rend="italics">Christus Consolator</hi></rs>, <ref target="let085.xml#n-7">see letter 85, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Regarding the <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1798"><hi rend="italics">Ecce Homo</hi></rs> print which Vincent sent to Theo, <ref target="let105.xml#n-4">see letter 105, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>This woman’s job was to set out the foot-stoves in the church.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Sleeping old woman</hi>, c. 1635-1637 (B350) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1824">Ill. 1824</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>In <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_135"><hi rend="italics">L’Oeuvre complet de Rembrandt</hi></ref>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Charles Blanc</rs> was lyrical about the etching. In his opinion it was difficult to find a work in Rembrandt’s oeuvre that was ‘more sincere, more convincing in life and truth, more charming in its chiaroscuro. The abandonment to sleep and the fatigues of old age are expressed in it in the most endearing way.’ The old woman dozing had to be approached in stockinged feet: ‘I think one has to look at this print in silence, or at least one mustn’t speak loudly, for fear of disturbing a sleep so deserved and so sweet.’ See Blanc 1859-1861, vol. 2, pp. 205-207, no. 244.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>‘Il n’y a point de vieille femme’ (There is no such thing as an old woman) is the title of a chapter in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s book <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref>; <ref target="let027.xml#n-2">see letter 27, n. 2.</ref> Michelet remarked in this book: ‘<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1393">Titian</rs> prefers to paint beautiful ladies of 30 years old. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1336">Rubens</rs> goes without difficulty to 40 and above. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1008">Van Dyck</rs> knows no age; in his work, art is emancipated! He has spurned time. The powerful magician <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> does more: with a gesture, a glance, a ray of light, he dispels it all. Life, goodness, light – that is enough to delight us.’ Ed. Paris n.d., p. 382. See also Pabst 1988, p. 30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>‘Haar pad in ’t leven loopt eenzaam af’ (Her path in life comes to a lonely end) are the opening lines of the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_474">Naar ’t beloofde land</ref>’ by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">P.A. de Génestet</rs> which accompany the print ‘Preparing for the Promised Land’. See De Génestet 1869, vol. 2, pp. 298-299.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>Old age; cf. hymn 180:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>For ‘L’Homme... mène’, <ref target="let035.xml#n-2">see letter 35, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_778">Johannes (Jan) Andries Stricker</rs>, Kee and Paul’s brother.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>Cf. Rom. 8:28.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the journey he made on foot from Oudenbosch to Zundert on 7 April; <ref target="let110.xml">see letter 110</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Through (the rooms of the museum)’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>The Trippenhuis was the forerunner of the Rijksmuseum; <ref target="let004.xml#n-3">see letter 4, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    