<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 5 or Sunday, 6 August 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let254"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b245 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>254</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>223</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>255</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-08-05">Saturday, 5 or Sunday, 6 August 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0245" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000299_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="VGM001000299_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0245" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000299_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="VGM001000299_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">In mijn vorigen brief zult ge een krabbeltje gevonden hebben van <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>dat bewuste perspectiefraam. Daar net kom ik van den Smid <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>vandaan die ijzeren punten aan de stokken heeft gemaakt <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>en ijzeren hoeken aan het raam.</p><lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Het bestaat uit twee lange palen:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Met sterke houten pennen <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/> gaat het raam <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>daaraan vast, ’t zij in de hoogte ’t zij in de breedte.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Dit maakt dat men op ’t strand of op ’t weiland of <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>op een akker een kijkje heeft <hi>als door ’t venster</hi><c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>De loodlijnen &amp; waterpaslijnen van ’t raam<c type="kk">,</c> verder <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>de diagonalen &amp; het kruis – of anders een verdeeling <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>in kwadraten – geven vast &amp; zeker eenige hoofdpunten <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>waardoor men met vastheid een teekening kan <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>maken die de groote lijnen &amp; proporties aangeeft.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Dan ten minste wanneer men gevoel heeft voor <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>de perspectief en begrip van de reden waarom <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>en de wijze waarop de perspectief de lijnen een <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>schijnbare verandering van rigting &amp; de massa’s en vlakken een <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>verandering van grootte geeft. Zonder dat helpt het <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>raam niets of bijna niets en <hi rend="italics">duizelt</hi> men als men er door kijkt.</p><lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Mij dunkt gij zult wel voelen dat het een heerlijk <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ding is dit vizier te braqueeren<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> op de zee<c type="kk">,</c> op de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>groene velden – of s’winters op de besneeuwde vlakte <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>of in den herfst op het grillig netwerk van dunne &amp; dikke <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>stammen &amp; takken, of een stormlucht.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Het stelt – met VEEL oefening – en met <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/><hi rend="italics">langdurige</hi> oefening – iemand in staat om <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>bliksemsnel te teekenen – en<c type="kk">,</c> de teekening <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>vaststaande<c type="kk">,</c> bliksemsnel te <hi rend="italics">schilderen</hi><c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Eigentlijk is het absoluut voor ’t <hi rend="italics">schilderen</hi> goed want <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>lucht – grond – zee – daar <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> het penseel bij komen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>of liever<c type="kk">,</c> om die met teekenen alleen te kunnen <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>uitdrukken is het noodig de penseelsbehandeling te kennen <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>en te voelen<c type="kp">.</c>– Ik geloof ook zeker dat het op mijn <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/><hi rend="italics">teekenen</hi> nog heel wat invloed zal hebben als ik eens een <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>tijd schilder. In Januarij heb ik dat geprobeerd reeds – <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>toen is het echter weer gestopt – de reden van dat stoppen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>was ook bepaald, behalve een paar andere dingen,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> dat ik <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>nog te weifelend was bij ’t teekenen<c type="kp">.</c>– Nu is een half jaar <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>daarover heen gegaan<c type="kk">,</c> geheel toegewijd aan het teekenen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Welnu ’t is met frisschen moed dat ik op nieuw <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>begin. Het raam is werkelijk een mooi stuk <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gereedschap geworden – ’t spijt me gij het niet eens <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>nog gezien hebt. Het kost mij ook nog een aardig <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>duitje – maar ik heb ’t zóó solide laten maken dat <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>ik het niet gaauw verslijten zal. Ik begin dus Maandag <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>met het maken van groote fusains daarmee – en met <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>het <hi rend="italics">schilderen</hi> van kleine studies – lukken die twee <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>dingen dan zullen hoop ik spoedig betere geschilderde dingen volgen.</p><lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Ik zou dus willen dat tegen dat ge weer eens bij me komt <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>het atelier een echt schildersatelier geworden zal zijn<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Dat het in Januarij niet vlotte – ge weet het lag aan verscheiden <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>oorzaken maar après tout<c type="kk">,</c> het kan beschouwd worden als eene <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>averij in de machine – een schroef of een stang die niet <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>sterk genoeg was en door een sterker stuk vervangen moest worden<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Iets wat ik me ook aangeschaft heb is een sterke warme broek <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en daar ik even voor ge kwaamt pas een paar stevige schoenen heb <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>gekocht ben ik tegen weer &amp; wind gewapend. Tegelijk is het mijn <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>bepaald doel om door dit landschap schilderen een paar dingen <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>van <hi rend="italics">techniek</hi> te leeren die ik noodig gevoel te hebben <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>voor mijn FIGUUR. Het uitdrukken van verschillende <hi>stoffen</hi> namelijk<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>en den <hi>toon</hi> en de <hi>kleur</hi>. In een woord<c type="kk">,</c> het uitdrukken <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>van het corps – van de massa – der dingen<c type="kp">.</c> Door Uw komst is het <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>dat ik er nu toe overga, maar vóór ge kwaamt is er geen dag geweest dat ik <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>er niet op deze wijs over gedacht heb – alleen ik had nog wel langer <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>uitsluitend bij zwart &amp; wit en den contour me bepaald – – <hi rend="italics">maar nu ben ik</hi> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/><hi rend="italics">eenmaal in het schuitje</hi>. à dieu kerel, nogmaals een hartelijken <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/><supplied>h</supplied>anddruk en geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="69*" xml:id="l-69s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">t. à t.</p><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">In my last letter you’ll have found a little scratch of that perspective frame. I’ve just come back from the blacksmith, who has put iron spikes on the legs and iron corners on the frame. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">It consists of two long legs:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The frame is fixed to them by means of strong wooden pegs <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>, either horizontally or vertically.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">The result is that on the beach or in a meadow or a field you have a view <hi>as if through a window</hi>. The perpendicular and horizontal lines of the frame, together with the diagonals and the cross — or otherwise a grid of squares — provide a clear guide to some of the principal features, so that one can make a drawing with a firm hand, setting out the broad outlines and proportions.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Assuming, that is, that one has a feeling for perspective and an understanding of why and how perspective appears to change the direction of lines and the size of masses and planes. Without that, the frame is little or no help, and makes your head <hi rend="italics">spin</hi> when you look through it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I expect you can imagine how delightful it is to train this view-finder on the sea, on the green fields — or in the winter on snow-covered land or in the autumn on the fantastic network of thin and thick trunks and branches, or on a stormy sky. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">With CONSIDERABLE practice and with <hi rend="italics">lengthy</hi> practice, it enables one to draw at lightning speed and, once the lines are fixed, to <hi rend="italics">paint</hi> at lightning speed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">It’s in fact especially good for <hi rend="italics">painting</hi>,<hi rend="italics"> </hi>because a brush <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be used for sky, ground, sea. Or, rather, to render them through drawing alone, it’s necessary to know and feel how to work with the brush. I also firmly believe my <hi rend="italics">drawing</hi> would be strongly influenced if I were to paint for a while. I tried it back in January but that came to a halt — the reason for stopping, apart from a few other things,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> was that I was still too hesitant when drawing. Now six months have passed, devoted entirely to drawing. So now I’m beginning anew with fresh heart. The frame really has become an excellent piece of equipment — it’s a pity you still haven’t seen it. It has cost me a pretty penny, too, but I had it made so solidly that I shan’t wear it out in a hurry. On Monday I’ll start doing large charcoal drawings with it, as well as <hi rend="italics">painting</hi> small studies — if those two things come off, I hope that better painted work will soon follow. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">So by the time you next come to see me I would like the studio to have become a real painter’s studio. The fact that I couldn’t get going in January — you know that there were various reasons for that, but in the end it can be seen as a fault in the machine, a screw or a rod that wasn’t strong enough and had to be replaced by a stronger one. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Another thing I’ve bought for myself is a tough, warm pair of trousers, and, since I bought a pair of sturdy shoes just before you came, I’m now fully prepared to face the elements. At the same time my aim is to learn a couple of things about <hi rend="italics">technique</hi> through this landscape painting which I feel I’m in need of for my FIGURES, namely rendering different <hi>fabrics</hi>, and the <hi>tone</hi> and <hi>colour</hi>. In a word, the expression of the body — the mass — of things. It’s as a result of your visit that I’m moving on to this, but before you came not a day passed without my thinking about it along these lines. But I would have gone on for longer with just black and white and the outline. <hi rend="italics">But there’s no turning back now</hi>. Adieu, old chap, again a warm handshake, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>In <ref target="#l-47">ll. 47-50</ref> Van Gogh says that he will start painting the next Monday. Given that on Sunday, 20 August 1882 he writes that he has then been painting for about two weeks (<ref target="let258.xml">see letter 258</ref>), the Monday he is referring to must be 7 August, and the present letter must date from a few days earlier. Moreover, the letter follows <ref target="let253.xml">letter 253</ref> of Saturday, 5 August, because Van Gogh returns to the subject of the perspective frame (<ref target="#l-2">ll. 2</ref> ff.). So the letter can only have been written later on the same Saturday, 5 or on Sunday, 6 August 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Theo’s visit early in August <ref target="let253.xml">(253)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Purchase of extra drawing and painting materials <ref target="let253.xml">(253)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On Van Gogh’s knowledge and use of the perspective frame, <ref target="let235.xml#n-10">see letter 235, n. 10</ref> and <ref target="let253.xml">letter 253</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘richten’ (‘to train’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Among these ‘other things’ was the estrangement that came about between Van Gogh and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs>, who gave him his first painting lessons.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    