<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Sunday, 1 October 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let270"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b257 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>270</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>235</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>271</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-10-01">on or about Sunday, 1 October 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0257" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0257" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000315_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Met een enkel woord berigt ik U de goede ontvangst van <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Uw brief<c type="kk">,</c> voor den inhoud er van dank ik U hartelijk.</p><lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Deze laatste dagen heb ik haast niet anders gedaan <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>als aquarel. Ingesloten een krabbeltje van een groote<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/><lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/> Ge herinnert U misschien wel in ’t begin van de <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Spuistraat het kantoor van de Staatsloterij van Mooiman.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/> Ik kwam daar op een regenachtigen morgen voorbij <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>toen eene menigte menschen daar stonden te wachten <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>om loterijbriefjes te halen. Het waren meestendeels <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>oude vrouwtjes en van die soort van menschen <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>waarvan men niet weet te zeggen wat ze doen <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>of hoe ze leven maar die toch blijkbaar heel wat <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>scharrelen &amp; tobben en zich bewegen in de wereld. <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Natuurlijkerwijs is oppervlakkig beschouwd zoo’n <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>troepje luidjes die blijkbaar zooveel <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>belang stellen in “Heden trekking”<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> iets wat U <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>en mij haast doet lagchen<c type="kk">,</c> in dit opzigt <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>dat de loterij U en mij niet in <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>’t minst schelen kan<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Maar het groepje lui – en hun expressie <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>van wachten – trof mij – en terwijl ik <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>het maakte kreeg het voor mij een grootere<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>diepere beteekenis dan in ’t eerste oogenblik. <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Dan wordt het dunkt mij meer beteekenisvol als <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>men er in ziet – <hi>de armen en het geld</hi><c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Zoo is ’t trouwens met haast alle <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>figuurgroepen<c type="kk">,</c> men moet er wel eens over <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>doordenken eer men inziet waar men voor <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>staat – de nieuwsgierigheid en illusie over de loterij <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>schijnt ons min of meer kinderachtig – maar het wordt <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ernstig als men denkt aan de oppositie van misere <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en dat soort van efforts de perdus van de stakkers om door <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>een loterijbriefje te nemen<c type="kk">,</c> betaald met hun uit den mond gespaarde centen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>mogelijk<c type="kk">,</c> zooals zij zich verbeelden<c type="kk">,</c> gered te worden.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Wat hier ook van zij<c type="kk">,</c> ik heb er een groote aquarel <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>van op touw.</p><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">En ben bovendien bezig aan een van een <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>kerkbank<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> die ik zag in een kleen<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> kerkje op de <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>Geest waar de diakonie mannetjes gaan<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>(men noemt ze hier zeer expressief WEES<hi rend="italics">mannen</hi> <lb n="41a" xml:id="l-41a"/>en <hi rend="italics">wees</hi>vrouwen).–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Het gaat er zoo mee dat<c type="kk">,</c> weer eens druk aan <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>’t teekenen zijnde<c type="kk">,</c> ik soms denk<c type="kk">,</c> er is toch niets <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>zoo prettig als teekenen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Dit is een stuk uit dat brok banken, er zijn nog <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>andere koppen op den achtergrond van mannen.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Zulke dingen zijn echter moeielijk en zullen <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>zoo in eens niet lukken. Het gelukken is soms <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>’t eindresultaat van een heele serie mislukkingen. <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Van weesmannen gesproken – ik werd in ’t schrijven <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>van dezen gestoord door de komst van mijn model.</p><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">En ik heb tot den donker met hem gewerkt – met <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>een groote oude overjas aan waardoor hij een curieus breed figuur kreeg – ik geloof dat <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>gij wel schik zoudt hebben misschien in deze <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>collectie weesmannen in hun zondags- &amp; werkpak. <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Dan pakte ik hem ook nog eens zittende <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>met een pijpje.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Hij heeft een aardigen kalen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>kop – groote ooren (<hi rend="italics">NB. Doove</hi>) <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/> en witte bakkebaarden<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Deze krabbeling maakte ik half in den donker – toch zult ge er <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>zoo ten naasten bij misschien de compositie in zien kunnen – als ’t eenmaal <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>in elkaar staat is zoo iets er gaauw op te krabbelen – om het in elkaar <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>te zetten was minder makkelijk – en ik zeg niet dat het in elkaar staat <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>zoo als ik ’t hebben wilde. Ik zou wel lust hebben het te schilderen <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>met figuren van ± de lengte van een voet, of iets minder<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>de compositie dan nog iets meer in de breedte.</p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Ik weet echter niet of ik het doen zal, ik zou er een <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>groot doek voor moeten hebben en mislukt het mij<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>zijn er misschien al heel wat kosten aan geweest. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Ik denk er bij – ofschoon ik er veel lust in hebben <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zou – ik van zelf tot die dingen kom<c type="kk">,</c> door<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>gaande met types van figuren te maken. <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Dan vloeit het uit de studies naar ’t model <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>vanzelf later voort ’t zij in dezen ’t zij in een <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>anderen vorm doch in ’t zelfde sentiment.</p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Hoe langer hoe meer begin ik te merken hoe nuttig en <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>hoog noodig het is de studies naar ’t model te bewaren, <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>ofschoon die voor anderen minder waarde hebben<c type="kk">,</c> ziet wie <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>ze gemaakt heeft er ’t model in terug en staan de dingen <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>weer levendig voor den geest. Als er eens gelegenheid <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>is denk dan om mij wat van die oude studies terug te <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>sturen. Ik hoop er gaande weg mooier dingen mede te maken<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>’t Spreekt van zelf dat er in die groep figuren waarvan ik een zwart <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>krabbeltje U stuur prachtige dingen van kleur waren<c type="kk">,</c> blaauwe kielen <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>en bruine buizen<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-b"/> witte<c type="kk">,</c> zwarte<c type="kk">,</c> geelachtige arbeidersbroeken<c type="kk">,</c> verkleurde <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>châles<c type="kk">,</c> een groenachtig geworden overjas<c type="kk">,</c> witte mutsen en <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>zwarte hooge hoeden<c type="kk">,</c> slikkerige straatsteenen en laarzen als contrast <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>voor bleeke gezigten of door weer &amp; wind verweerde<c type="kp">.</c>– En daar <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>komt schilderen of aquarelleeren bij te pas. Enfin ik sjouw er op<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>Ik reken er op dat ge nog eens schrijft, niet waar<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>doch nogmaals dank voor de tijdige zending van het geld, <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>dat om krachtig door te gaan hoog noodig is.</p><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">adieu kerel, ontvang een hartelijken handdruk <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>in gedachten &amp; geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="93*" xml:id="l-93s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">t. à t.</p><lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Er is op de aquarel nog iets meer <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>voorgrond – nu vallen de figuren <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>te veel naar voren en domineert men den voorgrond <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>niet genoeg met het oog<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Just a word to say that your letter arrived in good order, I thank you heartily for the contents.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">These last few days I’ve done almost nothing but watercolours. A scratch of a large one is enclosed.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> You may remember <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1742 bio.xml#_1743">Mooijman</rs>’s state lottery office at the beginning of Spuistraat.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I passed it one rainy morning when a throng of people were standing there waiting to get lottery tickets. For the most part they were old women and the sort of people of whom it’s impossible to say what they do or how they live, but who evidently potter along and fret and get on with life. Of course, viewed superficially, a crowd of folk who evidently attach so much importance to ‘Draw today’<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is something that almost makes you and me laugh, because we’re not in the least bit interested in the lottery. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">But the group of people — and their waiting expression — struck me, and it took on a larger, deeper meaning for me while I was working on it than in the first moment. It becomes more meaningful, I believe, if one thinks of it as <hi>the poor and money</hi>. That, in fact, applies to nearly all figure groups: one occasionally has to think about them for a while before one understands what one is seeing. The curiosity and delusion about the lottery seem more or less childish to us, but it becomes serious when one thinks about the other side: misery and forlorn attempts by these poor souls to be saved, so they think, by buying a lottery ticket, paid for with pennies saved by going without food. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Be that as it may, I’m working on a large watercolour of it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I’m also working on one of a church pew<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> that I saw in a small church in the Geest district where the almsmen go<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> (they’re known here very expressively as ORPHAN <hi rend="italics">men</hi> and <hi rend="italics">orphan</hi> women).<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> The way things are going, being busily drawing again, I sometimes think there’s nothing so pleasant as drawing. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">This is part of the bit with pews; there are other men’s heads in the background.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Things like this are difficult, though, and won’t come off in one go. Success is sometimes the outcome of a whole string of failures. Speaking of orphan men, I was interrupted while writing this by the arrival of my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">model</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">And I worked with him until it got dark — wearing a big old overcoat which gave him a curiously broad figure. I believe you might perhaps enjoy this collection of orphan men in their Sunday and working clothes. Then I also tackled him sitting with a pipe.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> He has an interesting bald head — big ears (<hi rend="italics">NB</hi>. <hi rend="italics">Deaf</hi>) <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/> and white sideboards.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">I did this scratch half in the dark, but perhaps it can give you an idea of the composition. Once it has been put together, something like this can be quickly scribbled down. Putting it together was less easy, and I don’t claim that it stands now as I wanted to have it. I would enjoy painting it with figures the length of roughly one foot, or slightly less, with the composition then a little broader. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">However, I don’t know whether I’ll do it. I’d need a large canvas, and if it didn’t work there might be considerable costs involved. I also think — although I would greatly enjoy it — that I’ll come to things like that of my own accord, by continuing to do types of figures. Then later it will come naturally from the studies from the model, either in this or another form, but with the same sentiment. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I’m becoming more and more aware of how useful and very necessary it is to keep studies from the model. Though they have less value for others, the person who has made them recognizes the model in them, and things are brought vividly to mind again. When there’s an opportunity, remember to send some of the old studies back to me. I hope in time to use them to make more beautiful things. It goes without saying that there were wonderful colours in the group of figures of which I’m sending you a black scratch — blue smocks and brown jackets, white, black, yellowish worker’s trousers, faded shawls, an overcoat turned greenish, white caps and black top hats, muddy paving-stones and boots contrasting with pale faces or ones weathered by the elements. And that’s where painting or watercolouring comes in. Well, I’m toiling away at it. I count on you to write again, of course, but thank you again for sending the money in good time, which is badly needed if I’m to carry on vigorously.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Adieu, old chap, accept a hearty handshake in thought, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">There’s a little more foreground in the watercolour — here the figures are too far forward and one’s eye doesn’t grasp the foreground enough.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent thanks Theo for ‘sending the money in good time’ <ref target="#l-90">(l. 90)</ref>. This means that it must have arrived around 1 October. So the letter dates from on or about Sunday, 1 October 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Zuyderland is a model <ref target="let267.xml">(267)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Letter sketch C, <hi rend="italics">The poor and money</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_71">F - / JH 223</rs>), was done after the watercolour with the same title, <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2398">F 970 / JH 222</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The lottery office of the brothers <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1742">Cornelis Josephus</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1743">Jacobus Wilhelmus Mooijman</rs> was at Spuistraat 17 (<hi rend="italics">Adresboek 1882</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The text ‘HEDEN TREKKING Staats Loterij’ (State Lottery draw today) is in both the letter sketch and the watercolour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Church pew with worshippers</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2399">F 967 / JH 225</rs>); letter sketch A (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_69">F - / JH 226</rs>) shows part of this.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘klein’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The church meant is most probably the Bethlehemskerk, the ‘church of the poor’ behind Slijkeinde – this whole district was sometimes known as Geest. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 48, 52, 171. For the name ‘diakoniemannetje’, <ref target="let267.xml#n-20">see letter 267, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For the terms ‘orphan man’ and ‘orphan woman’, <ref target="let268.xml#n-12">see letter 268, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>In choosing this subject Van Gogh may have been influenced by a print after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>’s <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1880"><hi rend="italics">The paupers’ pew</hi></rs> which he had: <ref target="let228.xml">see letters 228</ref> and <ref target="let245.xml">245</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Possibly <hi rend="italics">Old man wearing a blouse, sitting with a pipe</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_385">F 1046 / JH 282</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This small sketch of the back of the head of Van Gogh’s model <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Zuyderland</rs> appears to have been copied from a drawing of the old man seen from the back; <ref target="let268.xml#n-13">see letter 268, n. 13.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘nauwsluitende, korte jasjes zonder panden’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    