<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Monday, 9 March and about Monday, 23 March 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let485"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b434 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>485</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>396</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>489</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-03-09">between about Monday, 9 March and about Monday, 23 March 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0434" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000579_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000579_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0434" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000579_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000579_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000579_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">de koppen die ik U beloofde heb ik eenigen <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>van klaar, doch nog niet geheel droog<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Doch zooals ik reeds schreef<c type="kk">,</c> ze zijn in een donkere <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>hut geschilderd &amp; ’t zijn – studies – in den <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>regelregten zin van ’t woord<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">In vroeger dagen reeds had ik een begin gemaakt <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>met U geteekende studies te sturen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Dat zulks toen niet is doorgegaan is tegen mijn <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>intentie geweest<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Ik werk hard en – stel dat slechts 1 van de 10 <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>of 20 studies die ik maak iets hebbe dat ze de <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>moeite waard doe zijn om te zien – die enkelen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>’t zij meer ’t zij minder in getal<c type="kk">,</c> al zijn ze <hi rend="italics">nu niets</hi> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>waard<c type="kk">,</c> zijn ’t later welligt wel<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Niet op zich zelf zoozeer als in verband <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>met andere studies<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Wat hier ook van zij – ik wil ’t op nieuw eens <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>probeeren en zoodra ze dus geheel droog zijn <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>&amp; ik ze uithalen kan<c type="kk">,</c> stuur ik U een paar koppen <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>en ook een schetsje van een garenwindster<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>En daar hoeft het bepaald niet bij te blijven – <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>want daar meer dan een vol jaar ik haast uitsluitend <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>me heb ingespannen op ’t <hi rend="italics">schilderen</hi><c type="kk">,</c> durf ik wel te beweeren <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>deze iets anders hebben dan de eerste geschilderde studies die <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>ik U zond.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Als ik b.v. laatst die prachtige houthakkers van l’Hermitte<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>zag<c type="kk">,</c> dan weet ik <supplied>zeer wel dat</supplied> een groote afstand me nog scheidt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>van zoo iets zelf te maken<c type="kp">.</c>– Doch wat betreft mijn <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>opvatting en m<supplied>anier</supplied> van zoeken – n.l. steeds direkt <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>buiten of in de <supplied>berookte</supplied><c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> arme hut – encourageert mij <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>’t zien v<supplied>an</supplied> zijn <supplied>werk</supplied> want ik zie (b.v. aan detai<supplied>ls</supplied> <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>in koppen in handen<supplied>) hoe</supplied> artisten als l’Hermitte ’t boerenfiguur <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>niet alleen van op een vrij grooten afstand maar van heel digt bij bestudeerd <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>moeten hebben<c type="kk">,</c> niet <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> terwijl ze met gemak 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>en zekerheid scheppen en composeeren<c type="kk">,</c> doch <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>vóór ze zulks deden<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">On croit que j’imagine – ce n’est pas vrai – <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>je me souviens – zei een die meesterlijk <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>composeeren kon<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Wat mij nu betreft<c type="kk">,</c> ik kan nog geen enkel <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/><hi rend="italics">schilderij</hi> laten zien<c type="kk">,</c> desnoods nog geen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>enkele <hi rend="italics">teekening</hi><c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Maar <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> maak ik wel en juist daarom <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>kan ik me heel best voorstellen de mogelijkheid <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>er een tijd kome dat ik ook grifweg <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>composeeren zal kunnen.</p><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">En trouwens ’t is moeielijk te zeggen waar studie <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>ophoudt en schilderij begint<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Ik denk over een paar grootere doorwerkte dingen <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en als het eens was dat ik helderheid kreeg <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>om de effekten <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>die ik op ’t oog heb weer te geven – in <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>dat geval zou ik die studies in kwestie nog <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>hier houden want dan zou ik ze er zeker voor <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>noodig hebben<c type="kp">.</c>– het is b.v. zoo iets:<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Namelijk figuren tegen ’t licht van een raam in<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik heb er studies van koppen voor<c type="kk">,</c> zoowel tegen ’t licht in als <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>met ’t licht mede en ’t heele figuur heb ik <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>al verscheiden keer onder handen gehad<c type="kk">,</c> garen windende <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>naaister of aardappels schillen<c type="kp">.</c>– En face en en profil<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Of ik ’t echter klaar zal krijgen weet ik niet want <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>het is een moeielijk effekt.</p><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Doch ’k geloof wel er een paar dingen mee geleerd <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>te hebben.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Gegroet<c type="kk">,</c> ik wilde niet langer wachten <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>weer eens te schrijven.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">b. à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I have a few of the heads I promised you ready, but not completely dry yet. But as I already wrote, they were painted in a dark cottage and they are — studies — in the true meaning of the word.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I had already made a start on sending you study drawings in the past.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">It wasn’t my intention that this shouldn’t continue.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I work hard and — suppose that only 1 in 10 or 20 of the studies that I make have something that makes them worth the trouble of looking at them — those few, be it more, be it fewer in number — although they’re worth <hi rend="italics">nothing now</hi>, may well be later.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Not so much in themselves as in conjunction with other studies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Be this as it may — I want to try it again, and so as soon as they’re completely dry and I can varnish them, I’ll send you a few heads and also a little sketch of a yarn-winder.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And it certainly doesn’t have to stop there — for since I’ve devoted myself almost exclusively to <hi rend="italics">painting</hi> for more than a whole year, I dare assert that these have something different from the first painted studies that I sent you.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">For instance, when I saw those magnificent woodcutters by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> recently, then I know very well that a great distance still separates me from making something like that myself. Yet as regards my views and manner of searching — that is, always directly from nature or in the poor, smoke-blackened<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> cottage — seeing his work encourages me, for I see (in details in heads and hands, for instance) how artists like Lhermitte must have studied the peasant figure not only from a fairly great distance but from very close to, not <hi rend="italics">now</hi>, while they create and compose with ease 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> and certainty, but <hi rend="italics">before</hi> they did that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">They think I imagine — it isn’t true — I remember — said one whose composition was masterly.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10"> Now for myself, I can’t yet show a single <hi rend="italics">painting</hi>, not even a single <hi rend="italics">drawing</hi> yet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">But I’m making <hi rend="italics">studies</hi>, and precisely because of this I can very well conceive of the possibility that a time will come when I, too, will be able to compose readily.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">And after all, it’s difficult to say where study stops and painting begins.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">I’m thinking about a couple of larger, more worked-up things, and should I get a clear idea of how to achieve the effects I have in mind — in that case I would still keep the studies in question here, because then I would certainly need them for it. It is, for example, something like this:<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Namely figures against the light from a window.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">I have studies of heads for it, both against the light and facing the light, and I’ve already worked on the whole figure several times, seamstress winding yarn, or peeling potatoes. Full face and in profile.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I don’t know whether I’ll get it finished, though, because it’s a difficult effect.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Still, I think I’ve learned a few things from it.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Regards, I didn’t want to put off writing again any longer.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
      <p>In <ref target="let484.xml">letter 484</ref> written on or about 2 March, Vincent promised to paint some heads and send them to Theo. Now he says he has a few that are finished, but that they are not yet dry. He also says: ‘I didn’t want to put off writing again any longer’ <ref target="#l-65">(ll. 65-66)</ref>. All this in any event places the letter some time after the previous one, and it was certainly written before Mr van Gogh’s stroke on 26 March <ref target="let486.xml">(486)</ref>.</p><p rend="indent">From a letter dated 25 March from Mrs van Gogh to Theo we learn that Theo had lent Vincent a book that he had already had a chance to start reading: ‘Well we saw Vincent got a book to read, so another sign of life, which is always pleasing. He seems to be reading it with great ambition. I’ve already heard him say: that’s a fine book, so you will give him a great deal of pleasure with it’ (FR b2268; this was probably the book by Gigoux discussed later (<ref target="let492.xml">see letters 492</ref> and <ref target="let494.xml">494</ref>)). Since nothing is said about it in the present letter, we assume that this letter must have been written before Vincent received the book, so at least a few days before 25 March. It is not possible to give any more precise date; we have therefore dated the letter between about Monday, 9 and about Monday, 23 March 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>After the brothers had agreed in March 1884 that Vincent would send Theo work in return for a monthly allowance, Vincent made a number of works for Theo; <ref target="let440.xml">see letters 440</ref> ff. Because of the tensions between them this had come to a dead end.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is probably referring here to <hi rend="italics">Woman winding yarn </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2498">F 36 / JH 698</rs>); it measures 40.5 x 31.7 cm and is the only known painting of this subject dating from this period. Cf. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 114-117, cat. no. 21.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The first painted studies that Vincent had sent Theo were works from Drenthe, at the end of September and in November 1883 (<ref target="let389.xml">see letters 389</ref> and <ref target="let406.xml">406</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_216">The woodcutters</rs></hi>: <ref target="let484.xml#n-5">letter 484, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In view of his choice of words in <ref target="let484.xml#l-51">letter 484, l. 51</ref>, it is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘bemoste’ (moss-grown) rather than ‘berookte’ (smoke-blackened).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Given that Van Gogh attributed the saying ‘je me souviens’ (I remember) to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Gustave Doré</rs> in <ref target="let537.xml">letter 537</ref>, this is who he must mean here. <ref target="let537.xml#n-16">See letter 537, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The letter sketches <hi rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Seated woman</hi> (both <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_138 artwork.xml#_139">F - / JH 713</rs>) are after <hi rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_566">F 70 / JH 715</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_567">F 70a / JH 716</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>There are several known works in which these light effects occur; it is not possible to identify the ones Van Gogh is referring to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    