<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let519"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b453 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>519</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>415</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>528</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-07-16">on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0453" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0453" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000605_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Vandaag heb ik een bezoek gehad van <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>Wenkebach<c type="kk">,</c> een schilder uit Utrecht die dagelijks met <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Rappard omgaat<c type="kp">.</c>– Hij maakt landschappen en ik heb <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>zijn naam al dikwijls hooren noemen en hij heeft toen tegelijk <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>met Rappard een medaille gehad in Londen<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Deze heeft <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>mijn werk gezien – die hutten die ik voor U heb <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>en ook de figuurteekeningen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Ik sprak met hem er over dat ik tot mijn leedwezen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>onaangenaamheden met Rappard gehad had die ik <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>me moeielijk anders kon expliceeren dan dat hij met <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>andere lui van den Haag over mijn werk geluld had <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>en dat<c type="kk">,</c> waar hij bovendien in lang niets had gezien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>hij daar zijn hoofd vol gekregen had onwillekeurig.</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Ik liet Wenkebach zien figuren die Rappard <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>vroeger goed vond en tevens die van nu er bij<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>en wees hem hoe ik wel veranderd was in een <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>paar dingen en nog meer <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>veranderen zou<c type="kk">,</c> maar dat hetgeen ik nu <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>zocht zeker niet minder was.</p><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Toen zeide hij dat hij niet twijfelde of <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Rappard zou terugnemen wat hij mij <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>had geschreven<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Ik heb hem verder laten zien hoe wat de kleur <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>betreft ik geen parti pris heb om <hi rend="italics">altijd</hi> donker <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>te schilderen. Een paar van de hutten <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>zijn zelfs zeer licht<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Maar dat het mij te doen is om de hoofdkleuren rood<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>blaauw<c type="kk">,</c> geel<c type="kk">,</c> als grond<c type="kk">,</c> als uitgangspunten <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>te nemen en niet grijs<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">We hebben toen nog al gepraat over kleur en <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>hij zeide toen onder anderen dat hij opgemerkt had Jaap Maris <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>in oude aquarellen ook <hi rend="italics">rosse</hi><c type="kk">,</c> bruingrijze<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>roode toonen gebruikte en vrij veel zelfs – <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>zoodat als men het naast een van zijn teekeningen <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>van nu zou houden het geheel rood er bij wordt. <lb n="35a" xml:id="l-35a"/>En zoo ook over Israels.</p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Met U dit te zeggen doe ik nu ook misschien meer <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>kwaad dan goed omdat het een stuk uit <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>een gesprek is en ik er alles eigentlijk bij moest <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>zeggen<c type="kp">.</c>– Maar wij hebben er al meer over gesproken <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>en dan begrijpt ge misschien van zelf het in zijn <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>verband<c type="kp">.</c>– Om een <hi rend="italics">eerlijk</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <hi rend="italics">degelijk</hi> coloriet te krijgen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>om het <hi rend="italics">vol te houden</hi><c type="kk">,</c> is het – en vooral in dezen <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>tijd<c type="kk">,</c> nu imitateurs (niet de meesters zelf) van de <hi rend="italics">groote</hi><c type="kk">,</c> grijze lui <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>meer en meer<c type="kk">,</c> altijd en overal alles <hi rend="italics">licht</hi> willen schilderen – <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>raadzaam ook in de puissanter gammas <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>zich te oefenen en vol te houden ze te gebruiken. <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>daar de eigentlijke coloristen zich altijd op de <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>kleuren<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Zoo zei Wenkebach b.v. dat hij dat geval van den <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>ouden toren<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> met pleizier zag en het buiten de verf<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>vond dat ik verleden jaar schilderde met <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>veel bitume er in. Hij vond het geheel oorspronkelijk <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>zeide hij. <lb n="53a" xml:id="l-53a"/>andere oude dingen ook<c type="kk">,</c> die watermolen<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> osseploeg<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="53b" xml:id="l-53b"/>laan met herfstboomen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Maar het meest deed me pleizier dat hij de figuren <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>goed vond – hij sprak van Milletachtig.– ik weet echter <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>zeker dat ik ze nog beter zal krijgen als ik maar <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>wat voorspoed heb met de kosten en er krachtig aan <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>doorwerken kan<c type="kp">.</c>– Ik zit daarover echter <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wel wat in en wat deze maand betreft <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>– ik ben <hi rend="italics">absoluut</hi> blut – ik heb geen gulden <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>meer<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Moeielijk zullen we ’t hebben – neem me <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dat niet al te kwalijk want met volhouden <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>is er nog een goede kans om later te oogsten <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>van wat we zaaien.</p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Dat het geld U echter drukt heb ik zorg genoeg over<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>ik wou ik het voor U wat verligten kon<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Als ge naar Holland komt – zou het niet nog eens <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>geprobeerd moeten worden om Tersteeg aan te klampen?– <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Tersteeg is iemand die <hi rend="italics">durft</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <hi rend="italics">als</hi> hij maar overtuigd <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>is – is hij goed ook<c type="kp">.</c>– En Mauve eveneens<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Als de lui die ’t <hi rend="italics">volhouden</hi> om op figuur te <hi rend="italics">blokken</hi> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>heel talrijk waren zou ik zeggen<c type="kk">,</c> er is weinig kans <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>wat hulp te vinden.–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Maar zoo heel talrijk zijn die niet – en noodig worden ze <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>niet minder dan vroeger.</p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Het is voor U alleen moeielijk vol te houden <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>en ik <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> er niets aan doen om de <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>onkosten te verminderen – integendeel<c type="kk">,</c> ik wou ik <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>meer model nog nemen kon. Wat te doen?– <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>Vechten tegen de bierka moet men ’t niet noemen <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>want anderen hebben ’t ook gewonnen en <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>wij zullen ’t ook winnen.</p><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Wat Rappard betreft<c type="kk">,</c> ik heb hem zooeven geschreven ik <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>verlang hij <hi rend="italics">ten eene male</hi> zijn schrijven terugneemt<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Ge ziet echter Theo<c type="kk">,</c> hoe het er op aan komt voet <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>bij stek te houden bij ’t werk<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Ik heb Rappard geschreven dat we waarachtig <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>wel iets anders te bestrijden hebben dan elkaar <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>en dat op dit moment de lui die boeren en <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>’t volk schilderen de handen in elkaar moeten <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>slaan omdat eendragt magt maakt<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>Alleen kan men ’t niet<c type="kk">,</c> althans<c type="kk">,</c> een heele troep <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>die ’t eens is kan meer. Houd gij goeden <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>moed ook want misschien krijgen we <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>meer vrienden en dan wordt het levendiger <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>en wordt het geharrewar onderling misschien <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>een boerenkrijg tegen dat soort schilders zooals <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>men er in alle tegenwoordige jurys nog kan aanwijzen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>die als zij konden de idees<c type="kk">,</c> voor welke Millet baanbreker was<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>ook nu nog zouden tegenhouden. Gegroet – maar als ge kunt<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>stuur me iets<c type="kk">,</c> al is ’t maar tien francs<c type="kk">,</c> om door den tijd te komen<c type="kp">.</c></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">t<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="103*"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I had a visit today from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs>, a painter from Utrecht who sees <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> every day. He makes landscapes and I’ve often heard his name mentioned, and he got a medal in London at the same time as Rappard.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> He has seen my work — those cottages I have for you, and the figure drawings too.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I talked to him about the fact that to my regret I’d had trouble with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, which I could hardly explain otherwise than that he’d been prattling about my work with other people from The Hague, and that since, moreover, he hadn’t seen anything in a long time, he couldn’t help got his head stuffed full there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I showed <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs> figures that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> thought good in the past, and at the same time those that I’m doing now, and pointed out to him how I’d changed in a few things and would change even more, but that what I was looking for now was certainly not inferior.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Then he said that he didn’t doubt that Rappard would take back what he had written to me.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I also showed him how, as regards the colour, I’m not predisposed to <hi rend="italics">always</hi> paint darkly. A couple of the cottages are actually very light.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7"> But that I’m concerned with taking the primary colours red, blue, yellow, as starting-points, as points of departure, and not grey.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">Then we talked quite a bit about colour, and he said among other things that he’d noticed that in old watercolours <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jaap Maris</rs> had also used <hi rend="italics">ruddy,</hi> brown-grey, red tones, and rather a lot in fact — so that if one were to hold it next to one of his present drawings it would look completely red. And the same about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">I may be doing more harm than good by telling you this, because it’s part of a conversation, and I actually ought to tell all of it. But we’ve spoken of it before, and so you may well understand it anyway, in its context. To get an <hi rend="italics">honest, sound</hi> coloration, to <hi rend="italics">sustain</hi> it, it’s advisable — and particularly in this day and age, now imitators of the <hi rend="italics">great</hi>, grey fellows (not the masters themselves) want more and more, always and everywhere, to paint everything <hi rend="italics">light</hi> — to practise in the more powerful spectrums and to persevere in using them, since the actual colourists always on the colours<ptr target="#note-t-3"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Thus <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs> said, for instance, that he liked the thing of the old tower,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> which I painted last year with a lot of bitumen in it, and thought it was beyond the paint.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> He said he found the whole thing original. Other old things, too, that water mill,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ox-plough,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> avenue of autumn trees.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">But what pleased me most was that he thought the figures good — he called them <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>-like. I know for sure, though, that I’ll get them even better if I just have some luck with the expenses and can carry on working hard on them. I’m rather worried about that, though, and as for this month — I’m <hi rend="italics">absolutely</hi> broke — I haven’t a guilder left.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">We’ll have a hard time — but don’t blame me too much, for with perseverance there’s still a good chance later of reaping what we sow.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">I’m worried enough about your money troubles, though, I wish I could lighten them a little for you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">When you come to Holland — shouldn’t you try to approach <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> again? Tersteeg is someone who <hi rend="italics">dares</hi>, <hi rend="italics">provided</hi> he’s convinced — he’s all right. And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> likewise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">If the fellows who <hi rend="italics">persevered</hi> in <hi rend="italics">studying</hi> the figure were very numerous, I’d say there would be little chance of finding some help.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">But they’re not so very numerous — and they’re no less necessary than in the past.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">It’s hard for you to keep going on your own, and I <hi rend="italics">can’t</hi> do anything to reduce the expenses — on the contrary, I wish I could take more models. What’s to be done? One mustn’t say it’s fighting a losing battle, because others have won it, and we’ll win it too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">As for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, I’ve just written to tell him that I want him to retract his letter <hi rend="italics">once and for all</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> You see, though, Theo, how it comes down to sticking to one’s guns in one’s work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">I wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> that we really do have something else to fight besides each other, and that at this moment the fellows who paint peasants and the common people must join hands, because unity is strength. One can’t do it alone, at any rate; a whole troop who agree can do more. Keep your spirits up, too, for perhaps we’ll get more friends, and then it will liven up, and the squabbling among us might perhaps become a peasant battle against the sort of painters one can still point out in all juries nowadays, who even now would try to stifle the ideas for which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> was the pioneer if they could. Regards — but send me something if you can, even if it’s only ten francs, to see me through.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>We have dated the letter on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885. For this <ref target="let515.xml">see letter 515</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>. <ref target="let517.xml">Letters 517</ref> and <ref target="let518.xml">518</ref> were also written the same day. This tallies with Van Gogh’s assertion that he is ‘<hi rend="italics">absolutely</hi> broke’ <ref target="#l-60">(l. 60)</ref> – whereas in <ref target="let513.xml">letter 513</ref> of about 12 July he said that he still had five guilders left. In <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 the present letter was placed in the second half of August, but it is evident from the words ‘when you come to Holland’ <ref target="#l-68">(l. 68)</ref> – which obviously look forward to Theo’s visit at the end of July 1885 – that it must have been written in July</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Meeting with Wenckebach <ref target="let516.xml">(516)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Van Rappard’s reaction to the lithograph of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let503.xml">(503)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p>Theo’s visit to Nuenen <ref target="let510.xml">(510)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Willem Wenckebach</rs> was awarded a bronze medal at the London International and Universal Exhibition (Crystal Palace), which opened on 23 April 1884. We do not know for certain which painting this was (the catalogue has not been traced), but in the light of a report in the <hi rend="italics">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi> its must have been a landscape – this work once belonged to J.L. Beijers of Utrecht. See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s medal: <ref target="let448.xml">letter 448</ref>. On the exhibition: <hi rend="italics">The Times</hi> of 21 April 1884, p. 4 and of 24 April 1884, p. 7; on Wenckebach’s prize and the work: <hi rend="italics">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi> of 25 April 1884, p. 1 (morning edition), of 27 May 1884, p. 1 (Supplement to the evening edition), and <hi rend="italics">Eigen Haard</hi> 31 (1905), p. 422.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
      
<p>See for the paintings of cottages, <hi rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>), <hi rend="italics">Cottage and woman with a goat</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3025">F 90 / JH 823</rs>), <hi rend="italics">Cottage with peasant coming home</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2520">F 170 / JH 824</rs>), <hi rend="italics">Village at sunset</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_574">F 190 / JH 492</rs>), <hi rend="italics">Cottage with woman digging</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2517">F 89 / JH 803</rs>), and <hi rend="italics">Cottage</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_951">F - / JH add 23</rs>), that Vincent in any event had ready for Theo at that time: <ref target="let513.xml#n-1">letter 513, n. 1.</ref> It is not possible to establish exactly which figure drawings he is referring to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This is an unfinished later addition to the letter. We reckon Van Gogh meant ‘colourists always concentrate on the colours’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh probably means the painting <hi rend="italics">The old tower</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2471">F 88 / JH 490</rs>), which he had made in the summer of 1884.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>See for the expression ‘beyond the paint’: <ref target="let439.xml#n-3">letter 439, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Water mill at Gennep</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2490">F 125 / JH 525</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Plowman and a woman planting potatoes</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2483">F 172 / JH 514</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Avenue of poplars in autumn</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2488">F 122 / JH 522</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let517.xml">letter 517</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    