<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Wednesday, 15 August 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let662"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b567 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>662</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>525</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>667</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-08-15">Wednesday, 15 August 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000764_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Tu auras reçu ma dépêche <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>te faisant savoir que le sous lieutenant <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Milliet arrivera à Paris Vendredi matin<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>il arrive à la gare de Lyon à 5.15 du matin <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>et va de là directement au Cercle militaire <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Avenue de l’opéra.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ce sera de part &amp; <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>autre le plus simple que tu ailles le voir <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>là à 7 heures du matin précises<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Naturellement tu pourrais aussi le rencontrer <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>à la gare de Lyon même mais c’est <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>d’abord plus loin<c type="kk">,</c> ensuite il faudrait <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>te lever bien de bonne heure.</p><lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Il a été très-aimable pour moi juste<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>ces derniers jours ci<c type="kp">.</c> Il reviendra à Paris <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>pour une semaine mais passe la <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>plus grande partie de ses vaccances dans <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>le Nord.</p><lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Je suis bien content de voir l’expédition <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>faite et la soeur verra ainsi mes <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>études ce qui ne m’est pas indifférent <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>parceque ainsi elle assistera à une <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>chôse enfin essentiellement de notre <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>vie française à nous<c type="kk">,</c> crue <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>et telle quelle<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Je veux dire<c type="kk">,</c> elle verra la peinture <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>à l’état brut<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Mais fais moi le grand plaisir de <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>lui montrer une ou deux études <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>remises sur chassis et encadrées de blanc<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Tu pourras ôter de leurs chassis &amp; cadres <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>des précédentes<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Car pour que cela ne prenne pas trop <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>de place ne t’embarasse pas de chassis <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>et cadres pour moi<c type="kp">.</c> Car les copains verront <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>bien ce que c’est tel quel et surtout toi <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>aussi<c type="kp">.</c> Plus tard – <hi rend="italics">la Centaine</hi> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>accomplie nous choisirons une <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>dizaine ou quinzaine dans le nombre pour les encadrer.</p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Maintenant j’ai gardé le grand <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>portrait du facteur<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> et sa tete <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>ci jointe est – une seule séance<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Eh bien<c type="kk">,</c> voilà mon fort<c type="kk">,</c> faire un <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>bonhomme rudement dans une <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>séance. Si je me montais, mon <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>cher frère, davantage le cou <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>je ferais toujours ainsi<c type="kk">,</c> je boirais <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>avec le premier venu et je le <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>peindrais – et cela non à la 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>peinture à l’eau mais à l’huile<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>seance tenante à la Daumier<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="50a" xml:id="l-50a"/>Si j’en faisais cent comme ça il y en aurait des bons dans le nombre. <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Et je serais plus francais et plus <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/><hi rend="italics">moi</hi> – et plus buveur<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Cela me tente tant – non pas <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>la boisson mais la peinture de voyou<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Ce qu’ainsi faisant je gagnerais en <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>tant que quant à l’artiste<c type="kk">,</c> le <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>perdrais-je en homme?– Si <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>j’avais la foi de ça je serais <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>un fameux toqué – maintenant je n’en suis pas un de fameux – mais tu <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>vois je n’ai pas l’ambition de <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>cette gloire-là suffisamment pour <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>mettre le feu aux poudres<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">J’aime mieux attendre la génération <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>à venir qui fera en portrait ce que <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/><hi rend="italics">Claude Monet fait en paysage</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>le paysage riche et crâne à la <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>Guy de Maupassant<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Alors je sais que moi je ne suis pas <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>de ces gens-là<c type="kk">,</c> mais les Flaubert et les Balzac <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>n’ont ils pas fait les Zola et les <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Maupassant<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Vive donc non pas <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>nous mais la génération à venir<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Tu es juge assez en peinture pour voir et apprécier <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>ce que je puisse avoir d’originalité et tu l’es <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>également assez pour voir l’inutilité de <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>présenter ce que je fais au public de maintenant <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>car les autres me surpassent en touche plus <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>nette. Cela tient plus au vent et circonstances <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>qu’à ce que je pourrais sans le mistral et <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>sans ces circonstances fatales de jeunesse <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>évaporée<c type="kk">,</c> de pauvreté relative<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>De mon côté je n’insiste aucunément à changer <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>de condition et je me compte même trop heureux <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>de pouvoir continuer tel quel.</p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Pas de réponse de l’ami Russell et certes <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Gauguin en méritait bien une.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">J’ai ajouté à cet envoi un dessin du tableau que <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>je travaille maintenant<c type="kk">,</c> les bateau avec déchargeur <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>de sable.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Si certaines études n’étaient pas tout <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>à fait sèches ce serait tant pis pour elles<c type="kk">,</c> il <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>faudrait les laisser sècher complètement puis <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>laver à grande eau et retoucher en cas de <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>besoin<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Mais le mal ne peut pas être grave <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>et l’occasion était bonne pour les expédier<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Je te serre bien la main et j’espère bien <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>avoir de tes nouvelles vendredi ou samedi<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">t<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">You’ll have received my telegram informing you that Second Lieutenant <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> will arrive in Paris on Friday morning; he arrives at the Gare de Lyon at 5.15 in the morning and from there goes directly to the Cercle Militaire, avenue de l’Opéra.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It will be easiest for both of you if you go to see him there at 7 sharp in the morning.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Of course, you could also meet him at the Gare de Lyon itself, but first of all it’s further away, then you’d have to get up quite early.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">He has been very kind to me, particularly these past few days. He’ll come back to Paris for a week, but is spending the major part of his holidays in the north.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’m very glad to see the package sent off, and in this way our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> will see my studies, which isn’t a matter of indifference to me, because in this way she’ll also experience a thing that is after all an essential part of our French life, raw and just as it is. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I mean, she’ll see painting in its rough state.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">But do me the great pleasure of showing her one or two studies put back on stretching frames and framed in white. You can take the previous ones off their stretching frames and frames.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">And so that they don’t take up too much room, don’t encumber yourself with stretching frames and frames for me. Because the pals will see clearly what it’s like just as it is, and you too, most of all. Later — when we’ve reached <hi rend="italics">the Hundred mark</hi>, we’ll choose around twelve or fifteen of them to frame.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Now, I’ve kept the large portrait of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">postman</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and his head enclosed herewith is — a single sitting.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Well, there you are, there’s my strong point, to do a chap roughly in one sitting. If, my dear brother, I let myself get more carried away, I’d always do that, I’d drink with the first person to come along and I’d paint him — and not in 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> watercolours but in oils, on the spot, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>. If I did a hundred like that there’d be some good ones among them. And I’d be more French and more <hi rend="italics">myself</hi> — and more of a drinker. It tempts me so much — not the drink, but painting ruffians. Would I lose as a man what I gained as an artist, doing that? If I had faith in that, I’d be a famous madman — now I’m not a famous one — but you see I don’t have enough ambition for that particular kind of fame to put the match to the powder.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">I prefer to wait for the generation to come, which will do in portraits what <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs> is doing in landscape</hi>, the rich, bold landscape in the style of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Now I know that I myself am not one of those people, but didn’t the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_596">Flaubert</rs>s and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>s make the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>s and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Maupassant</rs>s?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> So here’s to — not us — but the generation to come. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">You’re enough of a judge of painting to see and to appreciate what originality I may have, and you’re also enough of a judge to see the pointlessness of presenting to today’s public what I’m doing, because the others surpass me in more precise brushwork. It has more to do with the wind and circumstances than with what I could do without the mistral, and without these inevitable circumstances of vanished youth and relative poverty. For my part, I’m in no way set on changing my situation, and I actually count myself only too happy to be able to continue as it is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">No reply from our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> fully deserved one, for sure.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">I’ve added to this consignment a drawing of the painting that I’m working on now; the boats with man unloading sand.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> If some studies weren’t quite dry, it would just be too bad for them; they should be allowed to dry completely, then washed with lots of water and retouched if need be.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> But the damage can’t be serious, and it was a good opportunity to send them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I shake your hand firmly, and I do hope to have news from you on Friday or Saturday.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Given the statement ‘You’ll have received my telegram’ <ref target="#l-1">(l. 1)</ref>, the letter cannot be dated earlier than Wednesday, 15 August (the date the telegram was sent, <ref target="let661.xml">letter 661</ref>). Since Vincent assumes that Theo will receive the letter before Friday morning (‘It will be easiest ... if you go to see him there at 7 sharp in the morning’, <ref target="#l-6">ll. 6-8</ref>), he cannot have written it on Thursday. We have therefore dated it – as did Jo van Gogh-Bonger in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914, and she may have had a postmark to go on – Wednesday, 15 August 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Milliet takes paintings to Paris <ref target="let652.xml">(652)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Willemien’s visit to Paris <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See for the ‘Cercle militaire’: <ref target="let661.xml#n-1">letter 661, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This telegram is <ref target="let661.xml">letter 661</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘justement’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Joseph Roulin </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2672">F 432 / JH 1522</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Joseph Roulin</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2673">F 433 / JH 1524</rs>). By ‘herewith’ Van Gogh means included in the batch <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> took with him (cf. ‘this consignment’ in <ref target="#l-87">l. 87</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had read in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Maupassant</rs>’s<hi rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_497">Des vers</ref> </hi>(1880) that he regarded <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_596">Flaubert</rs> as his teacher; <ref target="let625.xml#n-8">see letter 625, n. 8.</ref> For <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>’s successor, <ref target="let250.xml#n-10">see letter 250, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh expected a response from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> to the batch of drawings he had sent him and to his request that Russell buy a work from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>. <ref target="let652.xml#n-3">See letter 652, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The drawing <hi rend="italics">Quay with sand barges</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2699">F 1462 / JH 1556</rs>), after the painting <hi rend="italics">Quay with sand barges</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2700">F 449 / JH 1558</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This was a common method of removing surplus oil from the surface of the paint, although most artists used water and something like soap. Cf. Carlyle 2001, pp. 212-213.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    