<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 27 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let713"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b730 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>713</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T3</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>718</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-27">Saturday, 27 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0730 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0730 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000987_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0730 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001000988_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="VGM001000988_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0730b V/1962" xml:id="surf-extra-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000988_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic url="VGM001000988_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">le 27 Oct<c type="kp">.</c> 1888</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">En revenant de Bruxelles <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>je trouve ta dépêche &amp; ta lettre;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>en réponse à la première qui m’a <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>fait un grand plaisir je t’envois <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>un mandat car quoiqu’il soit <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>possible que Gauguin ait reçu la <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>lettre que j’adressais à Pont Aven, le <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>croyant encore là-bas, la possibilité <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>existe que vous ne l’ayez pas reçue<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>qu’à deux il soit encore plus difficile <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>que seul pour avoir de quoi vivre.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Pourquoi <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>ne tâches tu pas d’avoir crédit chez un <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>nourisseur pour le cas où comme <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>dernièrement je ne sois pas là ou ne 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>puis pas t’envoyer de l’argent immédiatement<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Je suis bien bien content que Gauguin <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>soit avec toi car je craignais qu’il <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>n’aie rencontré quelque empêchement <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>de venir. Maintenant par ta lettre <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>je vois que tu es malade &amp; que tu te <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>fais des quantités de soucis. Une fois <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>pour toute il faut que je te dise une <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>chose. Je considère comme si la chose <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>d’argent &amp; de vente de tableaux &amp; tout <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>le côté financier n’existe pas, ou plustôt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>que cela existe comme une maladie. <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Comme il est certain qu’avant une <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>révolution formidable, ou probablement <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>plusieurs révolutions<c type="kk">,</c> la question argent <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ne disparaitra pas, il faut la traiter <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>comme la vérole si on l’a. C’est à dire prendre <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>les précautions contre les accidents qui <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>peuvent en résulter, mais sans cela ne <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>pas s’en faire de bile. Tu y penses de trop <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>dans ces derniers temps &amp; quoiqu’il n’y ait <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>pas de symptôme d’accident tu en est <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>souffrant. Par les accidents j’entends la <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>misère &amp; il faut donc<c type="kk">,</c> pour ne pas y arriver<c type="kk">,</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>aller doucement, ne pas faire d’eccès,<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>et eviter les autres maladies pour <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>autant que cela soit possible. Tu parles <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>d’argent que tu me dois &amp; que tu <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>veux me rendre. Je ne connais pas <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>cela. Là où je voudrais que tu arrives <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>cela serait, que tu n’aies jamais <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>la préoccupation. Il faut que je travaille <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>pour de l’argent. Comme à nous deux <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>nous n’en avons pas beaucoup il faut <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>ne pas nous mettre trop sur les bras <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>mais cela pris en considération nous <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>pouvons tenir encore quelque temps <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>même sans vendre quoi que ce soit. <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Si tu sentes le besoin de travailler <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>beaucoup <hi rend="italics">pour toi</hi><c type="kk">,</c> bon, dis le &amp; je <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>pense que nous pouvons marcher tout <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>de même, mais je ne comprends pas <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>le calcul de tant de tableaux à f<hi rend="super">s</hi> 100<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>si l’on veut qu’ils valent f<hi rend="super">r</hi> 100; ils ne <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>valent rien parceque cette ignoble société <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>n’est qu’avec ceux qui n’en ont pas <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>besoin. Mais sachant cela faisons comme <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>elle &amp; disons<c type="kk">,</c> nous n’en avons pas besoin<c type="kp">.</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>est ce qu’un homme averti n’en vaut <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>pas deux. Tu peux<c type="kk">,</c> si tu veux<c type="kk">,</c> faire <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>quelque chose pour moi<c type="kk">,</c> c’est de continuer <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>comme par le passé &amp; nous créer un entourage <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>d’artistes &amp; d’amis, ce dont je suis <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>absolument incapable à moi seul &amp; <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ce que tu as cependant créé plus ou <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>moins depuis que tu es en France. <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Est ce que les artistes commençant, les <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>autres ne suivront pas quand nous <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>en aurons besoin au moment où nous <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>ne pourrons plus travailler comme actuellement? <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Pour moi j’en ai la ferme conviction.</p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Tu ne sais pas comme tu m’affliges <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>quand tu dis que tu auras travaillé tant <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>que tu sentiras que tu n’auras pas vécu. <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>D’abord je crois que cela n’est pas vrai <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>car justement tu vis &amp; de la façon <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>comme les grands &amp; les nobles. Mais de <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>grace avertis moi à temps pour que je ne <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>sens pas que tu aies été dans la misère <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>&amp; que tu aies été malade parce qu’il <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>te manquait le morceau de pain pour <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>vivre. J’espère que la société de Gauguin <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>te soit agréable &amp; que tu te remettras très <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>prochainement. Je n’ai pas encore reçu ses 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>toiles. Est ce qu’il les a expédiées ou est <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>ce qu’elles doivent m’arriver par quelcun?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">A Bruxelles j’ai fait connaissance <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>avec le fils de de Groux, qui lui <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>aussi est artiste.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Malheureusement <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>c’était le dernier soir que j’étais là <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>&amp; je n’ai donc pas pu voir ce qu’il <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>fait. Le mouvement qui se fait içi en <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>art parait très discuté mais aussi <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>approuvé là-bas &amp; il serait bon de <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>créer à Bruxelles aussi une exposition <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>permanente. Demain de Haan <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>vient rester avec moi<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> dont je suis <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>très content, je suis très curieux de <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>savoir ce qu’il va faire car il a <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>envie de se mettre aussitôt au <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>travail. Çi inclus tu trouveras une <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>lettre de n. mère qu’elle me prie <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>de te faire parvenir.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Tasset t’enverra <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>prochainement les couleurs &amp; la toile<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">A bientôt &amp; bonne poignée de mains<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>aussi à Gauguin<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">27 Oct. 1888</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">On returning from Brussels I find your telegram and your letter;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in reply to the first, which gave me great pleasure, I’m sending you a money order, because although it’s possible that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> has received the letter that I addressed to Pont-Aven, thinking him still over there, the possibility exists that the two of you may not have received it, that it may be even more difficult for two together than one alone to have enough to live on.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Why don’t you try to obtain credit with the owner of a restaurant for occasions when, as just recently, I’m not there, or am 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> unable to send you money immediately?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I’m very, very pleased that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is with you, because I was afraid he’d found some obstacle to his coming. Now, from your letter I can see that you’re ill and that you’re giving yourself masses of worries. I must tell you something once and for all. To me it’s as if the matter of money and sales of paintings and the whole financial side doesn’t exist, or rather, that it exists like an illness. Since it’s certain that the money question won’t disappear before a tremendous revolution, or probably several revolutions, we have to treat it like the pox, if we have it. That’s to say, take precautions against the accidents that can result from it, but otherwise not worry oneself sick about it. You’ve been thinking about it too much recently, and even though there’s no symptom of an accident, you’re suffering as a result. By accidents I mean poverty, and so it’s important, in order to avoid it, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> to tread carefully, not to overdo it, and to avoid other kinds of illness as far as possible. You talk about money that you owe me and that you wish to pay back to me. I know nothing of that. What I’d like to see you achieve would be that you never had that concern. I must work to earn money. Since the two of us don’t have much of it, we mustn’t overburden ourselves, but taking that into consideration we can hold out for some time yet, even without selling this or that. If you feel the need to do a great deal of work <hi rend="italics">for yourself</hi>, good, say so, and I think we’ll be able to manage anyway, but I don’t understand the calculation of so many paintings at 100 francs, if we want them to be worth 100 francs; they’re worth nothing, because this unworthy society is only on the side of those who have no need of it. But knowing that, let’s do likewise and say, we have no need of it. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> Is not forewarned forearmed? You can, if you wish, do something for me; that’s to continue as in the past and create for us a circle of artists and friends, something which I’m utterly incapable of doing by myself and which you, however, have more or less created since you’ve been in France. If the artists start out, will the others not follow when we need them, at a time when we can no longer work as at present? I’m firmly convinced of it, myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">You don’t know how you grieve me when you say that you’ll have worked so much that you’ll feel that you haven’t lived. First of all, I believe that isn’t true, because you are in fact living, and in the same way as great men and noblemen. But for pity’s sake, let me know in good time, so that I don’t feel that you’ve been in poverty and that you’ve been ill because you didn’t have a crust of bread to live on. I hope that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s company will be pleasant for you and that you’ll soon recover. I haven’t received his 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> canvases yet. Did he send them, or should they reach me via someone?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">In Brussels I met <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1064">Degroux’s son</rs>, who’s also an artist.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Unfortunately it was the last evening I was there and so I couldn’t see what he’s done. The movement that’s being formed here in art seems much debated but also approved of over there, and it would be good to create a permanent exhibition in Brussels as well. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>’s coming to live with me tomorrow, which I’m very pleased about; I’m very curious to know what he’s going to do, because he’s eager to get down to work right away. You’ll find enclosed a letter from our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>, which she asks me to pass on to you.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs> will send you the colours and the canvas shortly.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">More soon, and good handshake, to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> as well.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘le 27 Oct_ 1888’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>Theo enclosed a letter from Mrs van Gogh, which has not survived.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Theo’s sale of Gauguin’s <hi rend="italics">Breton women chatting </hi><ref target="let711.xml">(711)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>De Haan’s stay with Theo <ref target="let711.xml">(711)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let711.xml#n-2">See letter 711, n. 2,</ref> for Theo’s trip to Brussels. The letter from Vincent is <ref target="let712.xml">712</ref> of about 25 October; he had sent the telegram straight away to tell Theo about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s arrival on 23 October.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo had sent <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> 500 francs from the sale of his painting <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_117">Breton women chatting</rs></hi>; <ref target="let711.xml#n-3">see letter 711, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘excès’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let704.xml#n-1">See letter 704, n. 1,</ref> for the batch of paintings <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> sent from Pont-Aven.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1064">Henry Degroux</rs>, Charles’s son, was a member of the Belgian society of artists Les Vingt. As such he objected to Van Gogh’s participation in Les Vingt’s seventh Salon in 1890. He withdrew his own entry, ‘not wishing, as far as I am concerned, to find myself in the same room as the laughable vase of sunflowers by Mr Vincent, or by any other <hi rend="italics">agent provocateur</hi>’ (ne voulant pas quant à moi, me trouver dans la même salle que l’inénarable [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>] pot de soleils de monsieur Vincent, ou de tout autre agent provocateur) as he wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Octave Maus</rs>. Les Vingt subsequently voted to exclude Degroux. See exhib. cat. Brussels 1993, p. 51.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habiter chez’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> had sent Theo this letter for Vincent, which has not survived, on 25 October (FR b2423).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Vincent had put in a new order for canvas and paint in <ref target="let710.xml">letter 710</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    