<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Tuesday, 9 or Wednesday, 10 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let700"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b592 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>700</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>548</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>705</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-09">Tuesday, 9 or Wednesday, 10 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0592" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0592" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000805_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">hier je t’ai envoyé une dépeche <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>pour te demander encore vingt francs.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> je <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>n’aurai que cela pour me nourrir toute la semaine <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>mais enfin j’ai mes cadres et quelques chassis<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Seulement pour la prochaine lettre<c type="kk">,</c> qu’elle <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>ne vienne pas plus tard que Dimanche car <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>le siège est dur<c type="kk">,</c> bien dur de ces jours ci<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Mais nous le tiendrons et je me sens <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>bien calme dans tous ces tremblements <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>que nous traversons.</p><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Juste au moment où je t’écris ces mots <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>je reçois avis de l’arrivée de la toile de <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Tasset.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Parfait<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Les cadres en noyer font bien pour les <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>études. Et je crois que le prochain envoi <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>décidera quelque chôse et que <hi rend="italics">nous</hi> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/><hi rend="italics">brûlons</hi> de vendre.</p><lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Soyons prudent et comme nous sommes <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ne bougeons pas de l’idée que non <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>pas seulement pour nous mais aussi pour <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>faire réussir cet atelier il faut que <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>nous regagnons l’argent dépensé durant <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>les annees improductives. Avec du <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>calme nous ferons tout cela<c type="kk">,</c> c’est <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>d’ailleurs notre droit et nous avons assez souvent <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>souffert pour cela.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Mais je te prie<c type="kk">,</c> cherche à te reconcilier avec <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>les Bague.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> C’est à dire nous nous faisons <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>trop vieux pour lutter contre les maisons <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>existantes et la meilleure politique sera <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>probablement de continuer tout doucement <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>au jour le jour. Fonder une nouvelle maison <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>cela coûte fort cher et se servir des existantes <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>cela ne coûte rien du tout.</p><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Alors si tu vois Bague explique lui que <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>venant dans une nature toute nouvelle pour <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>moi j’ai commencé à faire des études à droite <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>à gauche dont je t’ai fait deux envois. <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>Mais que si <hi rend="italics">tableaux</hi> il y a là-dedans <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>c’en sont tout au plus 2 ou trois<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">ainsi le verger blanc<c type="kk">,</c> le grand verger rose <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>et la moisson avec une ruine dans le fond.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Actuellement cependant je suis en train <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>de me concentrer. Maintenant les nouvelles <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>choses<c type="kk">,</c> ah cela nous coûte cher et nous <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ne serons pas fort commodes pour les vendre<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>il faudra qu’ils y mettent ce que cela vaut<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>Espérons que nous ne soyons pas trop <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>aux abois<c type="kk">,</c> avec de la patience <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>cela ne nous sera pas trop difficile 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>de faire comme Mauve ou Mesdag <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>qui<c type="kk">,</c> pouvant attendre et tenir la chôse un peu plus <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>cher<c type="kk">,</c> ont tout de même vendu.</p><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Nous n’epargnons rien de ce que nous <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>avons pour obtenir quelqu’effet riche de <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>couleur. Et je crois que l’idee de <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>gagner quelque chôse tout aussi bien pour <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>les copains que pour nous<c type="kk">,</c> nous donnera <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>de l’aplomb. Et dans les affaires<c type="kk">,</c> si <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>nous n’avons pas de plan fixe<c type="kk">,</c> tout ce que <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>nous ferons sera pourtant basé sur ce <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>sentiment profond que nous avons de l’injustice <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>existante dont souffrent les artistes que <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>nous connaissons et du<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> désir de changer <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>cela tant que nous pourrons. Avec cette <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>idée-là nous pouvons travailler avec calme <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>et volonté et n’avons en somme rien <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>à craindre de personne. Je travaille <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>à un portrait de la mère parceque la photographie <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>noire m’impatientait trop<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Ah comme on pourrait faire des portraits <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>sur nature avec la photographie et <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>la peinture. J’ai toujours espoir que dans <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>le portrait il nous attend encore une belle <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>revolution.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">J’écris à la maison pour avoir le portrait de notre <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>père aussi<c type="kp">.</c> Pour moi je ne veux pas des <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>photographies noires et je désire tout de même <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>avoir un portrait. Celui de la mère<c type="kk">,</c> une toile de 8<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>sera cendré sur fond vert et le vetement <hi rend="italics">carmin</hi><c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>Je ne sais si cela sera ressemblant mais enfin <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>je veux une impression de couleur blonde<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>Tu le verras un jour et si tu veux j’en ferai pour toi <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>aussi<c type="kp">.</c>– Ce sera encore en pleine pâte<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Eh bien mon cher Theo pour ta lettre prochaine <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>fais la moi avoir Dimanche.</p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Cela ira j’ose croire car nous brulons tout <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>de meme de vendre et ce que je prépare maintenant <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>nous mettra à même de montrer quelque chôse <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>à l’epoque de l’exposition. Ce sera une année <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>de dur travail mais nous aurons des bons moments <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>après et même entre temps. Je fais de tête une etude <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>de bordel pour Bernard.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> As tu vu que le dessin de <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>moi<c type="kk">,</c> que j’ai ajouté aux dessins Bernard<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> represente la maison<c type="kp">.</c> Tu pourras te faire une <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>idee de la couleur<c type="kp">.</c> J’ai une toile de 30 de ce dessin-là<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Poignée de main et bien merci de la toile<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>nous allons ainsi encore pouvoir livrer bataille.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">t<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Je <hi rend="italics">tiendrai cela ferme</hi><c type="kk">,</c> lorsque <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>cette decoration à laquelle je travaille <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>soit finie il faut qu’elle vaille <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>dix mille<c type="kk">,</c> que cela me soit commode ou pas<c type="kk">,</c> c’est mon but ferme <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>et fixe<c type="kk">,</c> nous avons depensé de l’argent et il faut qu’il nous revienne.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Yesterday I sent you a telegram to ask you for another twenty francs.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> That’s all I’ll have to feed myself for the whole week, but at least I have my frames and a few stretching frames.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Only for the next letter, it shouldn’t come later than Sunday, because the siege is hard, very hard, these days. But we’ll sit it out, and I feel quite calm in all this agitation that we’re going through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">At the very moment when I wrote these words to you I received news of the arrival of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs>’s canvas.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Perfect!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">The walnut frames do well for the studies. And I believe that the next consignment will decide something, and that <hi rend="italics">we’re on the point</hi> of selling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Let’s be prudent, and as we are let’s not move from the idea that not only for ourselves but also in order to make this studio succeed, we must regain the money spent during the unproductive years. With calmness we’ll do all that; besides, it’s our right, and we’ve suffered for it often enough. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">But I beg you, try to be reconciled with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_254">Bague</rs>s.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> That’s to say, we’re growing too old to struggle against the existing firms, and the best policy will probably be to continue very quietly from day to day. It costs a great deal of money to set up a new firm, and to make use of the existing ones, that costs nothing at all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">So if you see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_254">Bague</rs>, explain to him that, coming to a countryside that was quite new to me, I began to do studies right and left, of which I’ve sent you two consignments. But that if there are <hi rend="italics">paintings </hi>among them, there are 2 or three of them at most.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">So, the white orchard, the large pink orchard and the harvest with a ruin in the background.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">At present, though, I’m busy gathering my thoughts. The new things now, ah, they’re costing us dear and we won’t be very accommodating about selling them; they must bring in what they’re worth. Let’s hope we won’t be in too tight a corner; with patience it won’t be too difficult 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> for us to do the same as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1218">Mesdag</rs>, who, being able to wait and keep things a little dearer, still sold.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">We’re sparing nothing of what we have, in order to obtain some rich effect of colour. And I believe that the idea of earning something as much for the pals as for ourselves will give us confidence. And in our business dealings, although we have no fixed plan, everything we do will nevertheless be based on that deep sense that we have of the present injustice suffered by the artists whom we know, and of the desire to change it as far as we can. With that idea, we can work with calmness and determination, and in short, we have nothing to fear from anyone. I’m working on a portrait of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> because the black photograph was making me too impatient.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Ah, what portraits we could make from life with photography and painting! I always have hopes that a great revolution still awaits us in portraiture. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">I’m writing home to have our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>’s portrait too. Myself, I don’t want black photographs, and yet I still want to have a portrait. The one of our mother, a no. 8 canvas, will be ashy, on a green background, and her clothes <hi rend="italics">carmine</hi>. I don’t know if it will be a good resemblance, but I want an impression of blond colouring, at least. You’ll see it one day, and if you like I’ll do one for you too. It will be in heavy impasto again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Ah well, my dear Theo, for your next letter, let me have it on Sunday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Things will go well, I dare believe, because we’re on the point of selling all the same, and what I’m preparing now will put us in a position to show something at the time of the exhibition. It will be a year of hard work, but we’ll have good times afterwards, and even in the meantime. I’m doing a study of a brothel for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, from memory.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Did you see that my drawing, which I added to the Bernard drawings,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> shows the house? You’ll be able to form an idea of the colour. I have a no. 30 canvas of that drawing.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Handshake, and many thanks for the canvas; now we’ll be able to join battle once more.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">I’ll <hi rend="italics">stick firmly to this</hi>, when<hi rend="italics"> </hi>this decoration on which I’m working is finished, it’ll have to be worth ten thousand, whether it’s easy for me or not; that’s my firm and fixed aim; we’ve spent money and it must come back to us.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Van Gogh writes that he sent a telegram ‘yesterday’ asking for 20 francs (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). Since he urgently requested 20 francs in <ref target="let699.xml">letter 699</ref> of Monday, 8 October (he had already spent the money he had received that day), it seems likely that he would have sent the telegram that same day, Monday, or certainly on Tuesday. This date tallies with his asking Theo in the present letter – not once, but twice – to be sure to see to it that the allowance got to Arles by <hi rend="italics">Sunday</hi> (<ref target="#l-6">ll. 6</ref> and <ref target="#l-85">85-86</ref>). We consequently date it Tuesday, 9 or Wednesday, 10 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Framing paintings for the decoration <ref target="let673.xml">(673)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>First consignment of paintings from Arles <ref target="let606.xml">(606)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p>Second consignment of paintings from Arles <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p>Van Gogh’s ambition to exhibit work at the 1889 World Exhibition <ref target="let590.xml">(590)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p>Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had also urgently requested this extra 20 francs (a ‘louis’) in <ref target="let699.xml">letter 699</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let683.xml">See letters 683</ref> and <ref target="let687.xml">687</ref> for this order for stretching frames and frames. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This order for canvas is mentioned in <ref target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let699.xml#n-6">See letter 699, n. 6,</ref> for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_254">Bague</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">The white orchard </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2576">F 403 / JH 1378</rs>), <hi rend="italics">The pink orchard </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2578">F 555 / JH 1380</rs>) (<ref target="let607.xml#n-2">see letter 607, n. 2</ref>) and <hi rend="italics">The harvest </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2621">F 412 / JH 1440</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘sur le’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Van Gogh’s mother (after a photograph) </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2729">F 477 / JH 1600</rs>). <ref target="let678.xml#n-16">See letter 678, n. 16,</ref> for the photograph on which Van Gogh based this painting. The work measures 40.5 x 32.5 cm and is therefore a ‘no. 6 canvas, figure’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This painting of a brothel is not known. <ref target="let698.xml#n-6">See letter 698, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let697.xml#n-10">See letter 697, n. 10,</ref> for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s set of drawings titled <hi rend="italics">At the brothel</hi>. The drawing of the house is <hi rend="italics">The Yellow House (‘The street’) </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2722">F 1413 / JH 1591</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The painting is <hi rend="italics">The Yellow House (‘The street’) </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2721">F 464 / JH 1589</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    