<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Saturday, 6 July 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let787"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b647 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>787</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>599</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>790</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-07-06">Saturday, 6 July 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0647" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0647" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000883_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Cher frère &amp; soeur.</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">La lettre de Jo<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> m’apprend ce matin <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>une bien grosse<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> nouvelle, je vous en félicite, et suis très <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>content de l’apprendre. J’ai été bien touché de votre <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>raisonnement alors que vous dites qu’étant ni l’un ni <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>l’autre en aussi bonne santé que paraisse désirable à pareille <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>occasion<c type="kk">,</c> vous ayez éprouvé comme un doute<c type="kk">,</c> et en tous cas un <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>sentiment de pitié pour l’enfant à venir a traversé votre âme<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Cet enfant dans ce cas-là a-t-il même avant sa naissance <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>été moins aimé que l’enfant de parents très sains desquels <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>le premier mouvement eut été une joie vive? Certes non<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Nous connaissons si peu la vie qu’il est si peu de notre <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>compétence de juger du bon &amp; du mauvais<c type="kk">,</c> du juste ou de <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>l’injuste et dire que l’on soit malheureux parce que <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>l’on souffre n’est pas prouvé. Sachez que l’enfant de <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Roullin leur est venu souriant et très bien portant <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>alors que les parents étaient aux abois<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Donc prenez cela <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>comme cela est, attendez avec confiance et possedez votre <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>âme avec une longue patience ainsi que le dit une bien <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>vieille parole et avec bonne volonté<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Laissez faire la nature.</p><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Pour ce que vous dites de la santé de Theo, tout en <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>partageant de tout mon coeur, ma chère soeur, vos <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>inquiétudes je dois pourtant vous rassurer, precisément <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>parceque j’ai vu que sa santé est, comme d’ailleurs <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>la mienne, plutôt changeante et inégale que <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>faible.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">J’aime beaucoup à croire que les maladies <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>nous guerissent parfois c.à.d. que alors que <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>le malaise sort en crise c’est une <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>chôse nécessaire au recouvrement d’un état <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>de corps normal. Non<c type="kk">,</c> dans la suite du <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>mariage il reprendra ses forces ayant encore de la réserve <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>de jeunesse et de puissance de se refaire<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">J’en suis bien content de ce qu’il ne soit plus <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>seul et vraiment je n’en doute pas que dans la suite il <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>reprenne son tempérament d’autrefois. Et puis surtout <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>lorsqu’il sera père et que le sentiment de paternité lui <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>viendra ce sera autant de gagné.</p><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Dans ma vie de peintre et surtout lorsque je suis à la campagne <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>il m’est moins difficile à moi d’être seul parceque à la campagne <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>on sent plus aisément les liens qui nous <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>unissent tous. Mais en ville<c type="kk">,</c> comme lui y a fait ses <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>dix ans de suite chez les Goupil à Paris<c type="kk">,</c> c’est pas <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>possible d’exister seul. Ainsi avec de la patience cela <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>reviendra.</p><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Je vais demain à Arles chercher des toiles qui sont encore <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>par là<c type="kk">,</c> que je vous enverrai sous peu<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Et je vais <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>vous en envoyer aussitôt que possible pour essayer <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>de vous faire avoir<c type="kk">,</c> tout en étant en ville<c type="kk">,</c> des idées <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>de paysan.</p><lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">J’ai causé ce matin un peu avec le medecin d’ici<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – il <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>me dit – ce qui était absolument ce que j’avais deja pensé – <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>qu’il faut attendre un an avant de se croire gueri puisqu’un <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>rien pourrait faire revenir une attaque.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Alors il m’a offert de prendre ici mes meubles pour <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>que nous n’ayons pas doubles frais<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Demain j’irai <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>causer de cela à Arles avec M. Salles.</p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Lorsque je suis venu ici j’ai laissé à M. Salles 50 francs <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>pour régler l’hospice à Arles<c type="kk">,</c> il est certain qu’il en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>aura de reste. Mais ayant encore assez souvent <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>eu besoin de différentes choses<c type="kk">,</c> ici le surplus <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>qu’avait M. Peyron est épuisé. Je suis un <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>peu surpris moi qu’en vivant avec la plus grande <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>sobrieté possible et regularité depuis 6 mois<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>sans avoir mon atelier libre<c type="kk">,</c> je ne dépense pas <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>moins ni ne produis davantage que l’année <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>précédente relativement moins sobre. et <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>interieurement je ne me sens ni plus ni moins <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>de remords &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c> si on veut. Suffit pour dire <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>que tout ce qu’on appelle bien &amp; mal est <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>pourtant à ce qui me parait assez relatif<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Je vis sobre ici parceque j’ai la possibilité de le faire<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>je buvais autrefois parceque je ne savais plus <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>comment faire autrement. Enfin cela m’est <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>d’un égal!!! La sobrieté<c type="kk">,</c> très calculée c’est vrai<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>mène cependant à un état d’être où la pensée<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>si on en a<c type="kk">,</c> va plus couramment. Enfin c’est <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>une différence comme de peindre gris ou coloré<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Je vais en effet peindre plus gris<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Seulement au lieu de payer de l’argent à un proprietaire <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>on le donne à l’asile<c type="kk">,</c> je ne vois pas la différence – <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>et ce n’est guère meilleur marché<c type="kp">.</c> Le travail est <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>en dehors et m’a toujours coûté beaucoup.</p><lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Je te remercie beaucoup de l’envoi de couleurs <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>et de toile dont je suis très content.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> J’espère <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>aller refaire des oliviers. Des vignes il y en a <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>malheureusement très peu ici<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">La santé va pourtant bien et j’ai un sentiment <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>assez pareil à ce que j’ai eu etant beaucoup <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>plus jeune alors que j’étais aussi très sobre<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>on disait alors trop je crois. Mais c’est <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>égal<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>je chercherai à me débrouiller<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Pour ce qui est d’être le parrain d’un fils de toi<c type="kk">,</c> alors <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>que d’abord cela peut être une fille<c type="kk">,</c> vrai, dans les circonstances <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>je préférerais attendre jusqu’à que je ne sois plus ici<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>Puis la mère certes y tiendrait un peu qu’on l’appèle <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>après notre père, moi pour un trouverais cela plus <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>logique dans les circonstances.</p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Je me suis beaucoup amusé hier en lisant measure for <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>measure<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Puis j’ai lu Henry VIII où il y a de si beaux <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>passages ainsi celui de Buckingham et les paroles de <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>Wolsey après sa chute<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Je trouve que j’ai de la chance de pouvoir lire ou relire <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>cela à mon aise et puis j’espère bien lire <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>enfin Homère. Dehors les cigales chantent <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>à tue tête<c type="kk">,</c> un cri strident dix fois plus fort que celui <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>des grillons et l’herbe toute brûlée prend des <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>beaux tons de vieil or. Et les belles villes du <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>midi sont à l’etat de nos villes mortes le long <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>de la Zuyderzee autrefois animées.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Alors <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>que dans la chute et la decadence des choses<c type="kk">,</c> les <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>cigales chères au bon Socrate ont resté<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Et ici <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>certes ils chantent encore du vieux grec.</p><lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Si notre ami Isaacson les entendait il <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>s’épanouirait<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p><lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Ce que Jo écrit de ce que vous mangiez toujours <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>à la maison<c type="kk">,</c> c’est parfait<c type="kp">.</c> Enfin<c type="kk">,</c> je trouve <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>que cela va fort bien et encore une fois <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>tout en partageant de tout mon coeur <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>toutes les inquietudes qu’on voudra sur la santé <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>de Theo<c type="kk">,</c> chez moi l’espoir prédomine que dans <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>ce cas un état plus ou moins maladif n’est <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>que le résultat des efforts de la nature pour <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>se redresser. Patience. Mauve pretendait <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>toujours que la nature etait bonne et même <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>bien davantage que d’habitude on croyait<c type="kp">.</c> Y a-t-il <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>quelque chôse dans son histoire qui prouve qu’il se soit <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>trompé. Ses mélancolies des derniers temps croiriez vous? <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>Je serais moi porté à croire autre chôse<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">A bientôt<c type="kk">,</c> mais j’ai voulu tout de suite vous <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>écrire que cette nouvelle de ce matin me fait <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>bien plaisir. Poignées de main et </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">t. à v<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dear brother and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">sister</rs>.</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s letter<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> tells me a very great piece of news this morning, I congratulate you on it, and am very pleased to hear it. I was very touched by your reasoning when you say that as neither of you are in as good health as appears desirable on an occasion like this, you had a kind of doubt, and in any case a feeling of pity for the child to come traversed your soul. This child in this case, has it, even before its birth, been less well loved than the child of very healthy parents, whose first impulse would have been a keen joy? Surely not. We know so little about life that we’re not really in a position to judge between good and bad, just or unjust, and to say that one is unhappy because one suffers hasn’t been proved. You should know that Roulin’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_651">child</rs> came to them smiling and very healthy, while the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647 bio.xml#_648">parents</rs> were at bay.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> So take it as it is, wait with confidence and possess your soul with a long patience as an old saying has it, and with good will.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Let nature take its course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">As to what you say about Theo’s health, my dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">sister</rs>, while sharing your anxieties with all my heart I must nevertheless reassure you, precisely because I’ve seen that his health is changeable and uneven rather than weak, as is mine, for that matter.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I very much like to believe that illnesses sometimes cure us, i.e. that when the illness comes to a crisis it’s a thing necessary to the recovery of a normal state of body. No, subsequent to the marriage he’ll regain his strength, still having the reserve of youth and power to restore him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’m very pleased that he’s no longer alone, and truly I don’t doubt that he’ll regain his former temperament after a while. And then above all when he’s a father and the feeling of fatherhood comes to him, that will be a considerable gain.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">In my life as a painter, and above all when I’m in the country, it’s not so difficult for me to be alone, because in the country one feels the bonds that unite us all more easily. But in town, as he has done his ten consecutive years with the Goupils in Paris, it isn’t possible to live alone. So with patience it will return.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">I’m going to Arles tomorrow to fetch the canvases that are still over there, which I’ll send you shortly.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And I’m going to send you some as soon as possible to try to give you peasant thoughts, even though you’re in town.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">This morning I talked a little with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">doctor</rs> here<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – he told me – which was absolutely what I had already thought – that one must wait a year before believing oneself to be cured, since the smallest thing could bring on another attack.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Then he offered to take my furniture here so that we don’t have double expenses.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Tomorrow I’ll go and talk about that in Arles with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">When I came here I left 50 francs with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs> to settle up with the hospital in Arles, he’ll certainly have some over. But having again quite often needed various things, the surplus that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> had here is exhausted. I’m a little surprised myself that in living with the greatest possible sobriety and regularity for the last 6 months, without having my independent studio, I’m not spending less or producing more than the previous, relatively less sober year. And inwardly I feel neither more nor less remorse &amp;c. if you like. Suffice to say that everything one calls good and bad is however quite relative, it seems to me. I live soberly here because I have the opportunity to. I drank before because I no longer knew how to do otherwise. Anyway it’s all the same to me!!! Sobriety, very calculated it’s true, nevertheless leads to a state of being in which thought, if you have any, flows more easily. Anyway it’s a difference like painting grey or coloured. I’m in fact going to paint more greyly.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Only instead of paying money to a landlord we’re giving it to the asylum, I don’t see the difference – and it’s scarcely cheaper. The work is a thing apart, and has always cost me a lot.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">I thank you very much for the consignment of colours and canvas, which I’m very pleased with.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I hope to go and redo the olive trees. There are unfortunately very few vineyards here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">My health is good, though, and I have a feeling quite similar to the one I had when I was much younger, when I was also very sober, too much so, I believe they used to say. But it’s all the same,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I’ll try to get by.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">As regards being godfather to a son of yours, while first of all it could be a girl, truly, in the circumstances I would prefer to wait until I’m no longer here. Then <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> would certainly set her heart a little on him being called after our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>, I for one would find that more logical in the circumstances.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I enjoyed myself very much yesterday reading Measure for measure.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Then I read Henry VIII, in which there are such beautiful passages, like the one about Buckingham, and Wolsey’s words after his downfall.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I think I’m lucky to be able to read or re-read this at my leisure, and then I very much hope to read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_655">Homer</rs> at last. Outside the cicadas are singing fit to burst, a strident cry ten times louder than that of the crickets, and the scorched grass is taking on beautiful tones of old gold. And the beautiful towns of the south are in the state of our dead towns along the Zuiderzee, which were formerly lively.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> While in the downfall and the decline of things, the cicadas dear to good old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs> have remained.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> And here, certainly, they’re still singing old Greek.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">If our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> heard them, his face would light up.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">What <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> writes about you always eating at home, that’s perfect. Anyway, I think that’s going very well, and once again, while sharing with all my heart all possible worries about Theo’s health, within me the hope predominates that in this case a more or less sickly condition is only the result of the efforts of nature to right itself. Patience. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> always claimed that nature was good, and even a lot more than one usually thought. Is there anything in his past that proves that he was wrong. His fits of melancholy in his last days, do you think? I myself would be inclined to believe otherwise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">More soon, but I wanted to write to you straightaway that this morning’s news gives me great pleasure. Handshakes and</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>This letter is Vincent’s reply to Jo’s letter of 5 July, which he received ‘this morning’ (<ref target="let786.xml">letter 786</ref>). We have therefore dated the letter to Saturday, 6 July 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let786.xml">letter 786</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s choice of words is an allusion to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s ‘grossesse’ (pregnancy).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_651">Marcelle</rs>, the daughter of Joseph and Augustine Roulin, was born on 31 July 1888. <ref target="let653.xml">See letter 653</ref>. Van Gogh responds here to what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> wrote in her letter about the portrait of Marcelle (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2753">F 441 / JH 1641</rs>) (<ref target="let786.xml">see letter 786</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Derived from Luke 21:19.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Regarding this consignment, <ref target="let789.xml">see letter 789</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Théophile Peyron</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had stored his furniture in a room he rented from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">Mr and Mrs Ginoux</rs>. <ref target="let760.xml#n-4">See letter 760, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This is a pun on the French word ‘gris’, which can mean both ‘grey’ and ‘tipsy’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had ordered paint in <ref target="let783.xml">letter 783</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>After ‘egal’ Van Gogh crossed out ‘je ne cherche pas a contenter tout le monde’ (‘I don’t seek to please everyone’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_89">Measure for measure</ref></hi> (1604-1605) is a complicated tragi-comedy with several sub-plots. The Duke of Vienna temporarily relinquishes his power in order to investigate, in disguise, the deterioration of morals – in particular the laxity in sexual morals – in his duchy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_409">Henry <hi>viii</hi></ref></hi> (1623), act 2, scene 1, is a ‘mirror for magistrates’. While Henry <hi>viii</hi> tries to overcome the problems created by his divorce, the fallen characters comment on their own ruin. Thus Henry, Duke of Buckingham and Earl of Stafford (1454-1483), is accused of high treason and sentenced to death. On the scaffold he addresses the crowd that has quickly gathered to witness his execution:</p>

<p rend="indent">‘You few that lov’d me,</p>

<p rend="indent">And dare be bold to weep for Buckingham,</p>

<p rend="indent">His noble friends and fellows, whom to leave</p>

<p rend="indent">Is only bitter to him, only dying;</p>

<p rend="indent">Go with me like good angels to my end,</p>

<p rend="indent">And as the long divorce of steel falls on me,</p>

<p rend="indent">Make of your prayers one sweet sacrifice</p>

<p rend="indent">And lift my soul to heaven. Lead on a’ God’s name.’</p>

<p>The manipulative Cardinal Wolsey (1471-1530), Archbishop of York, loses his wealth and power when his crimes are revealed. He forfeits his royal protection and is attacked from all sides. Full of remorse, Wolsey addresses his servant with great emotion (act 3, scene 2):</p>

<p rend="indent">‘And when I am forgotten, as I shall be,</p>

<p rend="indent">And sleep in dull cold marble, where no mention</p>

<p rend="indent">Of me more must be heard of, say I thaught thee;</p>

<p rend="indent">Say Wolsey, that once trod the ways of glory,</p>

<p rend="indent">And sounded all the depths and shoals of honour,</p>

<p rend="indent">Found thee a way (out of his wrack) to rise in ...</p>

<p rend="indent">Cromwell, I charge thee, fling away ambition,</p>

<p rend="indent">By that sin fell the angels; how can man then,</p>

<p rend="indent">The image of his maker, hope to win by it?</p>

<p rend="indent">Love thyself last, cherish those hearts that hate thee;</p>

<p rend="indent">Corruption wins not more than honesty.’</p>

<p>See <hi rend="italics">Henry <hi>viii</hi></hi>. Ed. R.A. Foakes. 3th ed. London 1957, pp. 55, 124.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Until the mid-eighteenth century, such Zuiderzee towns as Monnickendam, Edam, Hoorn, Enkhuizen and Medemblik were prosperous centres of trade. After this, they faced a period of economic decline. See <hi rend="italics">Almere historisch</hi>. Gemeente Almere 1993.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Reference to the dialogue in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1796">Plato</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_514">Phaedrus</ref></hi>, 230c and 259b-e, in which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs> recounts the myth of the cicadas, devoted to the Muses. Enjoying the peace and quiet of nature, the philosopher is pleasantly accompanied by the chirring of the insects: ‘How lovely and perfectly charming the breeziness of the place is! and it resounds with the shrill summer music of the chorus of cicadas’. See <hi rend="italics">Plato</hi>. With an English translation by H.N. Fowler and an introduction by W.R.M. Lamb. London and New York. 1919, pp. 422-423, 510-513. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Vincent is probably responding to something Theo wrote to him about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    