<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Auvers-sur-Oise, Thursday, 5 June 1890. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let878"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b688 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>878</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>639</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>882</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-06-05">Thursday, 5 June 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0688" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0688" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000936_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Beste Moeder,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Wel bedankt voor uw <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>laatsten brief dien ik nog niet beantwoordde<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Wil heeft mij verteld dat U nog naar Nunen <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>zijt geweest<c type="kk">,</c> wat ik mij zoo erg goed kan begrijpen <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>en reeds verlangend ben van U te hooren hoe <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>U daar de dingen gevonden hebt en oude <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>vrienden hebt bezocht.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> De tijd gaat snel voorbij<c type="kk">,</c> al <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>duren sommige dagen lang. En het was met <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>veel belangstelling dat ik hoorde dat Wil in het <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>hopitâl Wallon werkzaam is geweest.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Het was <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>eigentlijk mijn plan niet om reeds weer <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>naar Parijs terug te gaan<c type="kk">,</c> ik had er nog een jaar <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>gebleven als niet de laatste keer ik niet wel was <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik het bepaald gedeeltelijk moest toeschrijven aan <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>den invloed die de ziekte van anderen op mij maakte<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Waarom ik besloot dat het tijd was te veranderen <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>van omgeving<c type="kk">,</c> wilde ik mijn betrekkelijke <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>werkkracht en wat mij rest van gezond verstand <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>behouden. Dat schreef ik nog heden aan D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Peyron<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>ik had er met hem woorden over gehad maar wij <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>waren toch goed gescheiden en hij had Theo naar <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>tijding van me gevraagd.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ik hield veel van <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>hem en wederkeerig maakte hij een onderscheid <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>in mijn voordeel tusschen mij en anderen van <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>zijn patienten.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">En het is zoo dat als ik er ooit wilde terug <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>komen ik er als bij vrienden zijn zoude.</p><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Doch het genoegen Theo terug te zien en kennis <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>te maken met Jo die mij verstandig en hartelijk <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>en eenvoudig voorkomt en met mijn nieuw <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>naamgenootje<c type="kk">,</c> en verder terug te zijn <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>onder de schilders en weer verdiept in al de <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>strijd en discussie en vooral arbeid in <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>het wereldje op zich zelf van de schilders<c type="kk">,</c> al <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>die afleiding werkt naar ’t me voorkomt <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>gunstig in zoover dat de symptomen van <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>de kwaal (die er als de thermometer van zijn) geheel verdwenen dezer dagen – <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>ofschoon men naar ik leerde daar niet <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>heel vast staat op mag maken.</p><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">De dokter hier heeft mij veel sympathie <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>betoond<c type="kk">,</c> ik kan er aan huis komen zoo <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>dikwijls ik wil en hij is goed op de hoogte <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>van wat er onder de schilders dezer dagen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>behandeld wordt. Hij is zelf zeer zenuwachtig<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>vooral denkelijk is dat er niet beter op geworden <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>sedert den dood van zijne vrouw. Hij heeft <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>twee kinderen<c type="kk">,</c> een meisje van 19 en een <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>jongen van 16.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Hij zegt mij dat het <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>werken nog t’beste is om in mijn geval <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>er boven op te blijven.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Nu<c type="kk">,</c> in de laatste 14 dagen of 3 weken <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>die ik te S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy was heb ik nog gewerkt <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>van s’morgens vroeg tot s’avonds zonder <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>ophouden<c type="kp">.</c> En ben maar een paar dagen <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>te Parijs gebleven en hier dadelijk weer <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>aan den gang gegaan.</p><lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Theo wachtte me aan de spoor op en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>mijn eerste indruk was hij bleeker zag <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>dan toen ik vertrok. Maar al pratende <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>en toen ik hem t’huis aan den gang <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>zag viel het mij mede – ofschoon hij hoestte<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – toch is het <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>werkelijk waar hij er in dien tijd <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>op achteruit ging. Al bleef ’t dus t’zelfde<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>zou ik haast durven gelooven dat dit <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>reeds wat gewonnen mag worden <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>gerekend. En het volgend jaar hij <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>eer sterker dan zwakker zal worden. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Het is een geduldwerk<c type="kk">,</c> zijn gestel en <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>het leven in zijn omstandigheden.</p><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Enkele bijzonderheden hoorde ik van hen <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>betreffende Cor. Als U schrijft groet <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>hem regt hartelijk voor me en vertel <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>hem eens ik weer terug ben. Ik zou <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>hem wel schrijven maar het is een <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>zoo heel ander vak<c type="kk">,</c> het zijne en het <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>mijne.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Theo’s vacantie nadert en dus zult U <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>hen betrekkelijk spoedig terugzien. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Zij hebben plan ook een paar dagen <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>naar hier te komen, want wij hebben <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>elkaar maar weinig en kort en gehaast <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>gezien.</p><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Het is hier ongelukkig duur in het dorp <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>maar Gachet<c type="kk">,</c> de dokter<c type="kk">,</c> zegt me het <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>in al de dorpen in den omtrek al mee net <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>eender is en hij zelf er ook veel van <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>te lijden heeft bij vroeger vergeleken. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>En in de eerste tijden dien ik nog in de <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>buurt van een dokter dien ik ken te <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>blijven. En hem kan ik in schilderijen <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>betalen<c type="kk">,</c> en een ander zou ik dat niet <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>kunnen<c type="kk">,</c> in geval er eens iets gebeurde <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>dat ik zijn hulp noodig had.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Nu zeg ik U goeden dag want ik moet <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>er op uit<c type="kp">.</c> hopende U zelf en Wil in <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>goede gezondheid deze zult ontvangen <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>en in gedachten omhelsd.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Uw liefh<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Thank you very much for your last letter, which I haven’t answered yet. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> told me that you’d been to Nuenen again, which I can understand so very well, and am already longing to hear from you how you found things there and visited old friends.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Time passes quickly, although some days drag. And it was with much interest that I heard that Wil’s been working in the Walloon hospital.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I didn’t actually intend to go back to Paris again; I would have stayed there another year had it not been that the last time I wasn’t well I definitely had to attribute it in part to the effect that other people’s illness had on me.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Why I decided that it was time to change surroundings, if I wanted to preserve my capacity for work, such as it is, and what remains to me of common sense. I wrote that to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Dr Peyron</rs> this very day. I’d had words with him about it, but we still parted on good terms, and he’d asked Theo for news of me.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I was very fond of him, and for his part he made a distinction to my advantage between me and others of his patients. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">And it’s the case that if I ever wanted to go back it would be as if I were with friends.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">But the pleasure of seeing Theo again and meeting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, who seems to me sensible and warm-hearted and uncomplicated, and my new <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">little namesake</rs>, and further to be back among painters and immersed again in all the conflict and discussion and above all work in the painters’ little world of their own, all this distraction has a favourable effect, it seems to me, in so far as the symptoms of the malady (which are like its thermometer) have disappeared altogether recently — although I’ve learned that one may not make too much of that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">doctor</rs> here has been very kind to me; I can go to his home as often as I like, and he’s very well informed about what’s going on among painters these days. He’s very nervous himself; most probably that hasn’t improved since his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_390">wife</rs>’s death. He has two children, a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_391">girl</rs> of 19 and a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_388">boy</rs> of 16.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> He tells me that in my case working is still the best way to keep on top of it.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Well, in the last fortnight or 3 weeks that I was in St-Rémy I worked from early in the morning until the evening without stopping. And only stayed in Paris for a few days, and got started again straightaway here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Theo was waiting for me at the station, and my first impression was that he looked paler than when I left. But talking to him and seeing how he was at home, I was encouraged — although he was coughing<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — but it really is true that he has <hi rend="italics">not</hi> got worse during that time. So even if it were to remain the same, I would almost dare believe that this might already be counted as something gained. And next year he’ll get stronger rather than weaker. It’s a matter of patience, his constitution and the circumstances of his life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I heard some details about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> from them. Give him my warmest regards when you write and tell him that I’m back again. I’d write to him, but it’s such a very different profession, his and mine.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Theo’s holidays are approaching and so you’ll be seeing them again quite soon. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> They’re also planning to come here for a couple of days, because we only saw each other briefly and hurriedly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">It’s cripplingly expensive in the village here, but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Gachet</rs>, the doctor, tells me it’s just the same in all the villages around here, and he’s really feeling the pinch himself compared with before. And to start with I need to stay close to a doctor whom I know. And I can pay him in paintings, and I wouldn’t be able to do that with somebody else, should something happened so that I needed his help.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Well, I’ll say goodbye now because I have to go out. Hoping that you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> will receive this in good health, and embraced in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Your loving</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>From a letter Mrs van Gogh wrote to Theo on 6 June 1890, it appears that the present letter and <ref target="let879.xml">letter 879</ref> to Willemien both arrived that day in Leiden (FR b2929). We have therefore dated both letters to Thursday, 5 June 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>The letter arrived at the same time as <ref target="let879.xml">letter 879</ref> to Willemien, so they must have been sent at the same time.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Visit to Paris <ref target="let872.xml">(872)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> had lived in Nuenen from June 1882 to March 1886.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
    
<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>, who lived with her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> at Herengracht 100 in Leiden, was registered from 4 May to 16 June 1890 as a ‘proefzuster’ (apprentice nurse) at the ‘Hôpital Wallon’ in Leiden. This hospital of the Walloon Church had been located at Rapenburg 12 since 1886. See <hi rend="italics">GAL</hi>, <hi rend="italics">Naamlijst van de verpleegsters en dienstpersoneel (List of names of the nurses and staff) 1887-1924</hi>; and Th.H. Lunsingh Scheurleer <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,<hi rend="italics"> Het Rapenburg. Geschiedenis van een Leidse gracht. </hi>Vol. 4a: ‘Leeuwenhorst’. Leiden 1989, pp. 147-148.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Regarding Van Gogh’s last attack in Saint-Rémy, <ref target="let857.xml">see letter 857</ref>, <ref target="#n-1">n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo wrote this in <ref target="let876.xml">letter 876</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Paul Gachet’s wife, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_390">Blanche Elisa Castets</rs>, had died in 1875. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_388">Paul Gachet Jr</rs> was 16 years old; <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_391">Marguerite</rs> was 20. They were both born on 21 June. See exhib. cat. Paris 1999, pp. 19 (n. 15), 80 (n. 4).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> had written to his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> on 4 May 1890: ‘Theo has gone to see the homœopath Love because of his cough. He hasn’t been at all well lately’ (FR b1851).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>, who worked for the Cornu Copia Gold Company in Germiston (near Johannesburg), became an official of the Nederlandsch Zuid-Afrikaansche Spoorweg Maatschappij (railway company) at Pretoria. He and Vincent were not close; cf. <ref target="let600.xml#n-12">letter 600, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Gachet</rs> had 26 paintings by Van Gogh in his possession. We know that he received a number of them from Van Gogh himself. Of the others, it is not known whether he received them from Vincent or from Theo (after Vincent’s death), or whether he acquired them elsewhere. For Gachet’s collection, see exhib. cat. Paris 1999.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    