<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Auvers, Tuesday, 10 June 1890. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let881"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b689 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>881</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>640</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>885</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-06-10">Tuesday, 10 June 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0689" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0689" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000937_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Chers frère &amp; soeur,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">la journée de dimanche <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>m’a laissé un souvenir bien agreable. <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ainsi on sent bien qu’on est moins loin <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>les uns des autres, et j’espère que nous <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>nous reverrons souvent.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Depuis <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Dimanche j’ai fait deux études de <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>maisons dans la verdure;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> à côté de <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>la maison où je suis il est venu <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>s’établir toute une colonie d’américains <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>qui font de la peinture mais je n’ai <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>pas encore vu ce qu’ils font.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Reflexion faite<c type="kk">,</c> pour ce qui est de <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>prendre cette maison ou bien une <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>autre voici ce qu’il y a. Ici je <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>paye un franc par jour pour mon coucher<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> donc <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/><hi rend="italics">si j’avais les meubles</hi> la différence <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>de 365 francs ou de 400 ne serait <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>pas à mon avis d’importance très <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>grande et alors j’aimerais bien <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>que vous autres eussiez en même <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>temps que moi un pied à terre à la <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>campagne<c type="kp">.</c>– Mais je commence <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>à croire que je doive considérer <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>les meubles comme perdus.– 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>Mes amis où ils sont<c type="kk">,</c> à ce que <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>je m’imagine ne se dérangeront <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>pas pour me les envoyer moi n’étant <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>plus là.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> C’est surtout la paresse <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>traditionnelle et la vieille histoire <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>traditionnelle que de leur côté les <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>étrangers de passage laissent des <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>meubles provisoires à l’endroit où <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>ils sont. Mais je viens encore de <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>leur écrire pour la troisième fois<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>que j’en ai danger,<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> j’ai dit dans <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>ma lettre que si je n’avais pas <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>de leurs nouvelles je me sentirais <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>obligé de leur envoyer un louis<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>pour les frais d’expédition. Probable <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>que cela fera de l’effet mais c’est une <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>impolitesse<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Que veux tu, dans le midi ce n’est <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>pas tout à fait comme dans le <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>nord. Les gens y font ce qu’ils veulent <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>et ne se donnent pas le mal de <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>réfléchir ou d’être prévenant pour <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>les autres si l’on n’est pas là<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Du moment qu’on est à Paris on est <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>comme dans l’autre monde. et 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>je crois qu’ils ne se dérangeront <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>probablement pas<c type="kk">,</c> à plus forte raison <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>qu’ils n’aimeront pas à se mêler <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>davantage de cette affaire dont ils ont <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>beaucoup causé à Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">C’est drôle tout de même que le <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>cauchemar aie cessé ici à tel point<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>je l’ai toujours dit à M<c type="kp">.</c> Peyron que le retour dans le nord m’en debarasserait <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>mais drole aussi que sous la direction <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>de celui là qui pourtant est très capable <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>et me voulait décidemment du bien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>cela avait plustôt agravé.<ptr target="#note-t-b"/></p><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">De mon côté aussi cela me fait de <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>la peine de remuer tout cela en écrivant <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>aux gens.</p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Je trouvais que le petit a bonne mine <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>et vous autres aussi; il faudra vite <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>revenir.</p><lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">De messager, il n’y en a pas d’ici directement <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>à Paris mais il y en a de Pontoise<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Or de Pontoise à ici il y en a tous <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>les jours. Veuille donc prier le <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>père Tanguy de se mettre incontinent <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>à l’oeuvre pour declouer toutes les <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>toiles qui sont sur chassis là-haut <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>dans la mansarde.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Il fera des <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>rouleaux des toiles<c type="kk">,</c> des paquets <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>des chassis.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Alors ou bien j’enverrai le messager <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>de Pontoise ou bien je viendrai <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>dans une quinzaine une fois avec <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>M. Gachet en prendre une partie<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>J’en ai vu chez toi aussi dans <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>le tas qui est sous le lit<c type="kk">,</c> beaucoup <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>que je peux retoucher, je crois, à <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>leur avantage. Je regrette bien <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>ne pas voir l’exposition Raffaelli.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>surtout je voudrais aussi voir <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>ton arrangement de ces dessins sur de la cretonne<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>comme tu disais.</p><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Un jour ou un autre je crois <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>que je trouverai moyen de faire <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>une exposition à moi dans un <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>café<c type="kp">.</c> Je ne detesterais pas d’exposer <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>avec Cheret qui doit avoir des idées <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>là-dessus certainement.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> A bientôt<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Je vous serre bien la main <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>vous souhaitant prosperité<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>surtout avec le petit<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">b. à v.</p><lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dear brother and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Sunday has left me a very pleasant memory. In this way we really feel that we’re not so far from one another, and I hope that we’ll see each other again often.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Since Sunday I’ve done two studies of houses in the greenery;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> a whole colony of Americans has installed itself beside the house where I am. They paint, but I haven’t yet seen what they do.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">On reflection, as regards taking that house or another one, here’s what there is. Here I pay one franc a day for my bed,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> so <hi rend="italics">if I had the furniture</hi> the difference between 365 francs and 400 wouldn’t, in my opinion, be of very great importance, and then I’d very much like you to have a pied-à-terre in the country at the same time as myself. But I’m beginning to believe that I must consider the furniture lost. 
    <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> As far as I can imagine, my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">friends</rs> where it is won’t put themselves out to send it to me, as I’m no longer there.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> It’s above all the traditional laziness and the old traditional story that on their side strangers who pass through leave the temporary furniture in the place where it is. But I’ve just written to them again for the third time that I have urgent need of it,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I said in my letter that if I didn’t have news of them I would feel obliged to send them a louis<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> for the costs of sending it. That will probably have some effect, but it’s impolite.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">What can you do, in the south it isn’t entirely as it is in the north. The people there do what they want and don’t give themselves the trouble of thinking or paying attention to others if one isn’t there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The moment you’re in Paris it’s like being in the otherworld. And 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I think that they probably won’t put themselves out, all the more so because they won’t like to get more mixed up in this business which people have talked so much about in Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">It’s odd, all the same, that the nightmare should have ceased to such an extent here. I always told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> that the return to the north would rid me of it, but odd, too, that it had got rather worse under the latter’s supervision, although he’s very capable and definitely wished me well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">On my side, too, it causes me distress to stir all this up by writing to people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I thought that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">little one</rs> looks well, and you two also; you must come back quickly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">As regards a carrier, there’s none from here directly to Paris, but there is one from Pontoise. Now there’s one every day from Pontoise to here. So please would you ask <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy</rs> to set to work with all speed to take all the nails out of the canvases that are on stretching frames up there in the attic.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> He can make rolls of the canvases, parcels of the stretching frames.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Then either I’ll send the carrier from Pontoise or else I’ll come in a fortnight one time with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Mr Gachet</rs> and take some. At your place, too, in the pile under the bed, I’ve seen many that I can retouch, I believe, to their advantage. I really regret not seeing the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> exhibition.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I would especially also like to see your arrangement of those drawings on cretonne,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> as you were saying.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">One day or another I believe I’ll find a way to do an exhibition of myself in a café. I wouldn’t detest exhibiting with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_934">Chéret</rs>, who must certainly have ideas on that.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> More soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">I shake your hand firmly, wishing you good fortune, especially with the<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418"> little one</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Theo wrote to Vincent on Thursday, 5 June that he and Jo and little Vincent would visit him in Auvers on Sunday (<ref target="let880.xml">letter 880</ref>). This visit took place on 8 June (FR b1853). The present letter was written shortly thereafter. Because Jo van Gogh-Bonger dated the <ref target="let010.xml">letter 10</ref> June 1890 in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914, and she possibly had a postmark to rely on, we have maintained the dating to Tuesday, 10 June 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The brothers would see each other once more – on Sunday, 6 July, in Paris – before Vincent wounded himself on 27 July. <ref target="RM24.xml">See RM24</ref> and Hulsker 1990-1, pp. 435-436.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It cannot be said with certainty which two studies these were. The possibilities include <hi rend="italics">Houses</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_922">F 759 / JH 1988</rs>), <hi rend="italics">Thatched cottages and houses</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_923">F 805 / JH 1989</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Thatched cottages</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_924">F 792 / JH 1987</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>It is not known which painters were among this ‘colony of Americans’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Vincent was staying at the Auberge <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_610">Ravoux</rs>. During Theo’s visit, the brothers had apparently discussed the possibility of renting a house together.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Coincidentally, on the day Van Gogh wrote this, he received word from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Marie Ginoux</rs> about his furniture (<ref target="let882.xml">see letter 882</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The first of these letters is <ref target="let871.xml">letter 871</ref>; the other two are not known. Van Gogh’s third letter crossed <ref target="let882.xml">letter 882</ref> from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Madame Ginoux</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘besoin urgent’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>A louis was a coin worth 20 francs.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the commotion caused in Arles by the first attack of his illness. <ref target="let750.xml">See letter 750</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘cela s’était plutôt aggravé’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Theo rented a room at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s, where he stored Vincent’s paintings (<ref target="let792.xml">see letter 792</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>For the exhibition of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>’s work, <ref target="let876.xml#n-1">see letter 876, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Cretonne is a strong linen fabric. Theo must have told Vincent something he also wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>: ‘The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> exhibition is attracting a lot of people and things are also being sold, but I liked the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs>s more ... On this occasion I had electric light installed that is very satisfactory and will be particularly useful this winter. One highly original idea of Raffaëlli was to cover the walls of one of the rooms in the gallery completely with light cretonne. It looks rather odd but very jolly and the paintings look good against it’ (FR b931, 2 June 1890).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_934">Jules Chéret</rs> was known especially for his posters announcing concerts in theatres and café-chantants. Perhaps this is why Van Gogh associates an exhibition in a café with him in particular. Chéret’s work was exhibited in Paris: in 1888 at Theo’s in boulevard Montmartre (three posters), in 1889 at Durand-Ruel’s, and in 1889-1890 in the Théâtre d’Application. See K.G. Saur, <hi rend="italics">Allgemeines Künstler-Lexicon. Die bildenden Künstler aller Zeiten und Völker</hi>. Munich and Leipzig 1998, vol. 18, pp. 439-443, Merlhès, <hi rend="italics">Correspondance Gauguin</hi> 1984, p. 512, and exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 206.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    