<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Tuesday, 31 December 1889 or Wednesday, 1 January 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let833"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b669 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>833</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>620</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>835</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-01-31">Tuesday, 31 December 1889 or Wednesday, 1 January 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0669 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0669 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000912_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0669 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001000913_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000913_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0669 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="VGM001000913_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000913_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">mon cher frère,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Merci beaucoup de ta <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>lettre du 22 Dec<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> contenant un billet <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>de 50 fr.; d’abord je te souhaite à toi et <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>à Jo une heureuse année et regrette <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>de t’avoir peutetre, bien involontairement <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>néamoins, causé de l’inquiétude, car <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>M. Peyron a dû t’écrire que j’ai encore <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>une fois eu la tête bien dérangée.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">A l’heure que je t’écris je n’ai pas <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>encore vu M. Peyron donc je ne sais <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>pas s’il t’a écrit quelquechôse sur mes <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>tableaux. Il est venu me parler pendant <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>que j’étais malade qu’il avait reçu de <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>tes nouvelles et si je voulais exposer <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>mes tableaux oui ou non<c type="kp">.</c> Alors je lui <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>avais dit que j’aimais encore mieux <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>ne pas les exposer<c type="kp">.</c> Ce qui n’avait pas de <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>raison d’être et j’espère donc qu’ils sont <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>partis quand même. Mais enfin je <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>regrette de ne pas avoir pu aujourd’hui <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>voir M. P. pour savoir ce qu’il t’a écrit<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Enfin, cela ne me parait pas important <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>en somme<c type="kk">,</c> puisque tu dis que ça part le <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>3 Janvier seulement<c type="kk">,</c> tu recevras celle–ci <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>à temps encore.</p><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Quel malheur pour Gauguin cet enfant <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>tombé de la fenêtre et lui ne pouvant pas <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>être là,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> je pense souvent à lui<c type="kk">,</c> comme <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>il a ses misères celui là malgré son activité <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>et tant de qualités hors ligne.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Je trouve parfait que la soeur <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>vienne t’assister lorsque Jo accouchera<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Puisse cela marcher bien – je <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>pense beaucoup à vous autres<c type="kk">,</c> je <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>vous l’assure<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Maintenant ce que tu dis de <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>mon travail certes cela m’est agréable <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>mais je pense toujours à ce sacré <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>métier dans lequel on est pris comme <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>dans un filet et où l’on devient moins <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>pratique que les autres<c type="kp">.</c> Enfin inutile <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>hélas de se faire du mauvais sang sur <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>cela – et il faut faire comme on peut. <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Drôle que j’avais travaillé avec un <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>calme parfait à des toiles que tu <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>verras bientôt et que tout à coup <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>sans raison aucune l’égarement m’a <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>encore repris.</p><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Si Gauguin était <hi rend="italics">trop</hi> aux abois je <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>crois que je lui proposerais encore d’aller <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>vivre ensemble là où il reste<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/> pouvant <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>nous nourrir à deux de ce que cela <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>coûte ici pour moi seul.</p><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Je ne sais ce que va me conseiller <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>M. Peyron mais tout en tenant <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>compte de ce qu’il me dira je crois 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>que lui moins que jamais osera se <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>prononcer sur la possibilité pour moi <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>de vivre comme auparavant. Il est <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>à craindre que ces crises reviendront. <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Mais ce n’est pas du tout une raison <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>pour ne pas essayer un peu de se <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>distraire.</p><lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Car l’entassement de tous ces aliénés <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>dans ce vieux cloitre<c type="kk">,</c> cela devient <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>je crois une chôse dangereuse où <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>l’on risque de perdre tout ce qu’on <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>pourrait encore avoir gardé de bon sens<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Non pas que j’y tienne à ceci ou à <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>cela de préférence<c type="kk">,</c> je me suis habitué <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>à l’existence ici mais faudra pas <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>oublier d’essayer un peu le contraire<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Quoi qu’il en soit tu vois que je t’ecris <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>avec un calme relatif.</p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Très intéressant ce que tu écris <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>de la visite de M. Lauzet. je <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>crois que lorsque je t’enverrai les <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>toiles qui sont encore ici il reviendra <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>bien encore une fois et si j’étais là 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>je crois que je me mettrais aussi à <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>lithographier<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Peut être ces toiles en question feraient <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>l’affaire de Reid<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Surtout il faut que je ne perde pas mon <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>temps<c type="kk">,</c> je vais me remettre au travail <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>aussitôt que m. Peyron le permettra <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>et s’il ne le permet pas<c type="kk">,</c> alors je coupe <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>net avec ici<c type="kp">.</c> C’est cela qui me tient <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>encore relativement en équilibre <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>et j’ai encore un tas d’idées pour <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>de nouveaux tableaux.</p><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Ah pendant que j’etais malade il <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>tombait de la neige humide et fondante<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>je me suis levé la nuit pour regarder <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>le paysage – jamais jamais la <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>nature m’a paru si touchante et si <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>sensitive.</p><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Les idées relativement superstitieuses <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>qu’on a ici sur la peinture me rendent <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>melancoliques plus que je ne saurais <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>te dire parfois parce que c’est toujours <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>au fond un peu vrai qu’un peintre <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>comme homme est trop absorbé par <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>ce que voient ses yeux et ne maitrise <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>pas assez le reste de sa vie<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/><lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Si tu voyais la lettre que Gauguin <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>m’a écrit la derniere fois<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> tu en serais <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>touché comme il pense droit<c type="kk">,</c> et <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>un homme si fort presqu’immobilisé <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>c’est malheureux ça<c type="kp">.</c> Et Pissarro aussi<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>Guillaumin de même<c type="kp">.</c> Quelle <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>affaire quelle affaire.</p><lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Je viens de recevoir une lettre <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>de la mère et de Wil aussi<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Ces jours ci tu auras avec Jo bien <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>des angoisses par moments et <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>un mauvais passage à passer. <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>Mais ce sont de ces chôses sans quoi <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>la vie ne serait pas la vie et cela <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>rend grave. C’est une bien bonne <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>idée que Wil va être là.</p><lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Pour ce qui me regarde ne t’inquiètes <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>pas trop<c type="kk">,</c> je me defends avec calme <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>contre la maladie et je crois que <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>de ces jours ci je pourrai reprendre le <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>travail.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/><lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Et cela me sera encore une <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>leçon de chercher à travailler <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>avec droiture sans trop d’arriere <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>pensées qui troublent la conscience<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>Un tableau<c type="kk">,</c> un livre<c type="kk">,</c> il ne <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>faut pas les mepriser et si c’est <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>mon devoir de faire cela il ne <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>faut pas que je désire autre <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>chôse.</p><lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Il est temps que cette lettre parte<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>encore une fois merci de la <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>tienne et bonne poignée <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>de main à toi et à Jo<c type="kk">,</c> crois <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>moi </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">tout à toi</p><lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Thanks very much for your letter of 22 Dec.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> containing a 50-franc note; first I wish you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> a happy New Year and am sorry for having perhaps made you anxious, quite unwittingly nonetheless, for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> must have written to you that my mind has once again been very disturbed.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">At the moment of writing to you I haven’t yet seen <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs>, so I don’t know if he’s written anything to you about my paintings. He came to tell me while I was ill that he’d received news from you, and if I wanted to exhibit my paintings, yes or no. So I told him that I’d much rather not exhibit them. Which had no justification, and so I hope that they’ve gone off all the same. But anyway, I regret not having been able to see Mr P. today to find out what he wrote to you. Anyway, this doesn’t appear very important to me on the whole, since you say that they only go off on 3 January, you’ll still receive this in time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">What a misfortune for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">child</rs> falling out of the window and he unable to be there,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I often think of him, what troubles that one has, despite his energy and so many matchless qualities.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I consider it perfect that our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> is coming to help you when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> has her confinement. May it go well – I think a great deal of you both, I can assure you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Now what you say about my work certainly is agreeable to me, but I still think of this bloody profession in which one is caught as if in a net and in which one becomes less practical than others. Anyway, useless alas to fret about this – and one must do as one can. Odd that I’d worked perfectly calmly on canvases that you’ll soon see, and that all at once, without any reason, the confusion took hold of me again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> was in <hi rend="italics">too</hi> much of a fix I think I’d again suggest to him going to live together where he’s staying, as we’d be able to feed the two of us on what it costs here for myself alone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I don’t know what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> is going to advise me to do, but while taking account of what he’ll tell me I think 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> that he’ll dare less than ever to pronounce on the possibility of me living like before. It’s to be feared that these crises will recur. But it’s not at all a reason for not trying a to distract oneself a little.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">For the crowding together of all these lunatics in this old cloister is, I believe, becoming a dangerous thing in which one risks losing all the good sense one might still have retained. Not that I’m set on this or that by preference, I’ve become used to life here, but mustn’t forget to try the opposite a little. Whatever the case, you can see that I’m writing to you with relative calm.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Very interesting what you write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Mr Lauzet</rs>’s visit. I think that when I send you the canvases that are still here he’ll certainly come back once more, and if I were there 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I think I’d also start doing lithographs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Perhaps the canvases in question would fit the bill for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Above all I mustn’t waste my time, I’m going to set to work again as soon as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> will allow it, and if he doesn’t allow it then I’ll make a clean break with here. It’s that that keeps me still relatively balanced, and again I have a whole lot of ideas for new paintings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Ah, while I was ill, damp, melting snow was falling, I got up in the night to look at the landscape – never, never has nature appeared so touching and so sensitive to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">The relatively superstitious ideas people have here about painting make me more melancholy than I could tell you sometimes, because there’s always basically some truth in it that as a man a painter is too absorbed by what his eyes see and doesn’t have enough mastery of the rest of his life.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">If you saw the letter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote me last time<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> you’d be touched by how upright his thoughts are, and for such a strong man to be almost immobilized is an unhappy thing. And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> too, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> the same. What a business, what a business.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I’ve just received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>, and from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">In the next few days you’ll have many anxieties with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> at times, and a bad time to get through. But these are things without which life wouldn’t be life, and that makes one solemn. It’s a really good idea that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs>’s going to be there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">As for me, don’t worry too much. I’m calmly defending myself against the illness, and I think that I’ll be able to get back to work one of these days.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">And this will be another lesson to me to try and work straightforwardly and without too many reservations that trouble the consciousness. A painting, a book, these mustn’t be despised, and if it’s my duty to do this, I mustn’t wish for something else.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">It’s time for this letter to go off, thanks again for yours, and good handshake to you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent wishes Theo and Jo a happy new year <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>. He assumes that Theo will receive the present letter before the paintings are sent on 3 January <ref target="#l-24">(l. 24)</ref>. For this reason we have dated the letter to Tuesday, 31 December 1889 or Wednesday, 1 January 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Willemien is staying with Theo and Jo <ref target="let825.xml">(825)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p>Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let830.xml">letter 830</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had had another attack, exactly one year after the first. He said in <ref target="let836.xml">letter 836</ref> that this one ‘ended in a week’ (meaning from about 24 December to about 30 December); <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> wrote: ‘perhaps the thought of last year made him extremely anxious on Christmas Day’ (FR b4299). Theo’s <ref target="let835.xml">letters 835</ref> and <ref target="let838.xml">838</ref> reveal that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Peyron</rs> had written to tell him that Vincent had tried to poison himself by eating paint, as he had done during the previous attack (<ref target="let797.xml#n-6">see letter 797, n. 6</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s son <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">Jean-René</rs> had fallen out of a window. <ref target="let830.xml#n-14">See letter 830, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habite’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let828.xml">letter 828</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    