<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 17 March 1873.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let005"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b5 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>005</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>5</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>005</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1873-03-17">Monday, 17 March 1873</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0005" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0005" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000005_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">den Haag 17 Maart 1873</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het wordt tijd dat je weer eens iets van mij hoort, &amp; ik ben ook verlangend om te hooren hoe het je gaat &amp; hoe of het met Oom Hein is, en hoop dus dat je mij als je tijd kunt vinden eens schrijven zult.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Je hebt zeker al gehoord dat ik naar Londen ga, &amp; dat waar<c type="shy">-</c>schijnlijk heel spoedig.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik hoop zoo wij elkaar voor dien tijd nog eens zien zullen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Als ik maar eenigzins kan, ga ik met Paschen naar Helvoirt,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> maar dat zal afhangen van de nouveautés, waar Iterson mede op reis gaat.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Voor hij 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>terug is zal ik niet weg kunnen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Het zal te L. een heel ander leven voor mij zijn, daar ik waarschijnlijk alleen op een kamer zal moeten wonen &amp; dus voor veel zaken zal moeten zorgen waar ik nu geen last van heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik ben zeer verlangend om L. te zien, zoo als je wel denken kunt, maar toch spijt het mij van hier te moeten gaan. Nu het bepaald is dat ik weg moet merk ik pas hoe ik aan den Haag gehecht ben. Maar enfin, dat is nu niet anders &amp; ik ben van plan de dingen maar niet te zwaar op te nemen.– Ik vind het heerlijk voor het Engelsch, ik kan dat wel goed verstaan, maar spreken gaat toch lang zoo goed niet als ik zou willen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Van Anna heb ik gehoord dat je je portret hebt laten maken,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> als je er nog een missen kunt recommandeer ik mij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Hoe gaat het met Oom Hein, zeker wel niet beter &amp; hoe maakt Tante het. Kan Oom zich nog al bezig houden, &amp; heeft hij veel pijn. Groet hen hartelijk voor mij, ik denk zoo dikwijls aan hen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Hoe gaat het in de zaak, zeker zal het wel druk zijn; bij ons ook.─ Je zult nu al zoo wat op de hoogte komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Hoe is het in je kosthuis, blijft dat bevallen, dat is een voornaam ding.─ Je moet mij vooral meer schrijven wat je alzoo ziet. Ik ben Zondag voor 14 dagen naar Amsterdam geweest, om eene tentoonstelling te zien van de schilderijen die van hier naar Weenen gaan.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Dat was zeer interessant &amp; ik ben nieuwsgierig 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>wat voor figuur de Hollanders te Weenen maken zullen.</p> 
<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik ben zeer nieuwsgierig naar de Engelsche schilders, wij zien daar zoo weinig van, daar bijna alles in Engeland blijft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Te Londen is van Goupil geen winkel maar er wordt alleen aan den handel geleverd.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Oom Cent komt in ’t laatst van deze maand hier<c type="kk">/</c> ik verlang zeer van hem nog een &amp; ander te hooren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Bij Haanebeek &amp; Tante Fie<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> vragen zij gedurig naar je &amp; laten zij je groeten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Wat heerlijk weer tegenwoordig, ik profiteer er maar zooveel van als ik kan, verl. Zondag ben ik al met Willem<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> uit roeien geweest. Wat zou ik dezen zomer nog graag hier gebleven zijn, maar wij moeten het maar nemen zoo als het is. En nu, adieu, heb het goed &amp; schrijf mij eens. Zeg Oom &amp; Tante, Schmidt &amp; Eduard<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> voor mij goeden dag. Ik hoop maar op Paschen. Steeds</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">je liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Mijnheer &amp; Jufvr. Roos &amp; Willem laten je ook groeten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Daar juist ontvang ik je brief, dank er voor. Ik ben zeer in mijn schik met het portret, het is best uitgevallen. Als ik iets naders hoor over mijn naar Helvoirt gaan schrijf ik het je dadelijk; ik zou het heel aardig vinden als wij op den zelfden dag kwamen. Adieu.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Theo ik moet je toch nog eens recommandeeren om pijpen te gaan</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">rooken, dat is zoo goed als je het land eens krijgt; zooals mij dat tegenwoordig nog al eens overkomt.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">The Hague, 17 March 1873</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It’s time you heard from me again, and I’m also longing to hear how you are and how <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle Hein</rs> is doing, so I hope you’ll write to me when you can find the time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You’ll have heard that I’m going to London, and probably very soon.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I do hope we’ll be able to see each other before then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’ll go to Helvoirt at Easter<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> if I possibly can, but it will depend on the <hi rend="italics">nouveautés</hi> that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_461">Iterson</rs> takes along on his trip.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I won’t be able to leave 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> until he gets back.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Life in L. will be very different for me, for I’ll probably have to live alone in lodgings, and will therefore have to deal with many things that I needn’t trouble myself with now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’m looking forward to seeing L. very much, as you can imagine, and yet I’m sorry to have to leave this place. I’m only just noticing how attached I am to The Hague, now that it’s been decided I must go away. Still, it can’t be helped, and I intend not to take things too hard. I think it’s wonderful for my English, which I understand well, though I don’t speak it nearly as well as I’d like.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I heard from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> that you had your portrait taken.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> If you can spare another, I commend myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">How is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle Hein</rs>? Certainly no better, and how is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1613">Aunt</rs> doing? Can Uncle keep himself occupied, and is he in a lot of pain? Give them my warm regards, I think of them so often.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">How is business with you? It must be busy, as it is here. You probably know your way around by now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">How is your boarding-house? Is it still to your liking? That’s important. Above all, you must write more about the kind of things you see. Sunday a fortnight ago  I was in Amsterdam to see an exhibition of the paintings going to Vienna from here.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> It was very interesting, and I’m curious 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> as to the impression the Dutch will make in Vienna.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"> I’m very curious about the English painters, we see so little of them, because almost everything stays in England.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Goupil has no gallery in London; they only supply the trade.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Cent</rs> is coming here at the end of the month, I’m longing to hear more from him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_442 bio.xml#_443">The Haanebeeks</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_13">Aunt Fie</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ask after you constantly, and send you their regards.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">What wonderful weather we’ve been having, I’m taking advantage of it as much as I can. Last Sunday I went rowing with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> How much I’d have liked to stay here this summer, but we must take things as they come. And now, adieu, I wish you well, and write to me. Bid good-day to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1613">Aunt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_624">Schmidt</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1069">Eduard</rs> from me.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> As to Easter, I’m just hoping. Ever,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Your loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">Mr and Mrs Roos</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem</rs> also send you their regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I just received your letter, for which I thank you. I’m very pleased with the portrait, it turned out well. If I hear anything more about my trip to Helvoirt I’ll write to you immediately. It would be nice if we could arrive on the same day. Adieu.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Theo, I must again recommend that you start smoking a pipe. It does you a lot of good when you’re out of spirits, as I quite often am nowadays.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘den Haag 17 Maart 1873’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Uncle Hein’s illness <ref target="let003.xml">(3)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The directors of Goupil &amp; Co. had decided, after consulting <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>, to transfer Vincent to the London branch. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘our Vincent, whom Uncle Cent and the other Gentlemen have decided will go to London this summer’ (FR b2597, 1 February 1873).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Vincent and Theo were both at their <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs>’ house in Helvoirt (North Brabant) for Easter (13 April) (FR b2617 and b2618).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>What is meant are the new editions issued by Goupil &amp; Co., in which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_461">Teunis van Iterson</rs> tried to interest booksellers, printsellers and art dealers during a sales trip. Van Iterson was an employee of Goupil &amp; Co. in The Hague.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> reported to Theo: ‘Vincent writes that he finds it strange, always hurrying during the day and then afer 7 p.m. such a quiet evening. Didn’t we write to you about the two parrots at his house, one of whom spoke better English than Vincent himself? I wasn’t sure whether or not he meant the ladies, but <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Cent</rs> says that having parrots in the drawing room is very common and further inquiry revealed that they were in fact birds’ (FR b2644, 19 July 1873).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>It is not known which portrait this refers to. Theo had sent the portrait to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>, via his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526 bio.xml#_524">parents</rs>, shortly before 19 February (FR b2604).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>On 2 March Van Gogh visited the Dutch exhibit going to the ‘Internationale Tentoonstelling te Wenen’ (International Exhibition at Vienna), which was held from 19 February to 2 March 1873 in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arti et Amicitiae</hi>. See J.J. Heij, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Een vereeniging van ernstige kunstenaars. 150 jaar Maatschappij Arti et Amicitiae 1839-1989</hi>. Amsterdam 1989, p. 143. The paintings were exhibited from 1 May to 1 November 1873 in the Dutch pavilion at the World Exhibition in Vienna; the Netherlands was represented by 167 works of art out of a total of 6,600. See Jutta Pemsel, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Die Wiener Weltausstellung von 1873. Das gründerzeitliche Wien am Wendepunkt</hi>. Vienna and Cologne 1989, p. 67. Cf. also Sweetman 1988, p. 43.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The London office of Goupil &amp; Co., 17 Southampton Street, was at first only a stockroom without a shop, an outlet for the wholesale trade of the reproductions published by Goupil. In 1875 the London branch established a gallery open to the public; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let027.xml">see letters 27</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let029.xml">29</ref>. Works of art were also sold there, however (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let015.xml">letter 15</ref>). See also exhib. cat. Nottingham<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1974, p. 8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_13">Sophia (Fie) Cornelia Elisabeth Carbentus-Van Bemmel</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem Marinus Valkis</rs> was, like Van Gogh, a boarder at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642">W.M. Roos</rs>’s.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1069">Edouard Hamman</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    