<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. London, Friday, 13 June 1873.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let009"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b9 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>009</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>9</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>009</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1873-06-13">Friday, 13 June 1873</date>
                            <placeName>London</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0009" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0009" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000009_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Londen 13 Juni 1873.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Je zult wel verlangen om wat van mij te hooren, en ik wil je dus niet langer op een brief laten wachten.–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Van huis hoorde ik dat je tegenwoordig bij den Hr. Schmidt in huis zijt &amp; dat Pa bij je is geweest. Ik hoop van harte dat dit je beter zal bevallen dan je vorige kosthuis &amp; twijfel daar ook niet aan.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Schrijf mij eens spoedig, ik verlang daar zeer naar &amp; vertel mij eens hoe je 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>nu je dag doorbrengt &amp;c. Schrijf mij ook vooral eens wat je al zoo voor schilde<c type="shy">-</c>rijen gezien hebt in den laatsten tijd &amp; ook of er wat nieuws in etsen of lithographiën is uitgekomen<c type="kp">_</c> Je moet mij daar maar goed van op de hoogte hou<c type="shy">-</c>den, want in dat genre zie ik hier niet veel, daar de zaak hier alleen magazijn is.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het gaat mij, de omstandig<c type="shy">-</c>heden in aanmerking ge<c type="shy">-</c>nomen, zeer goed.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik heb een kosthuis gekregen waar het mij voorloopig zeer goed bevalt.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Er zijn nog 3 Duitschers in huis die veel van muziek hou<c type="shy">-</c>den &amp; zelf piano spelen &amp; zingen, wat de avonden 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>heel gezellig maakt. Ik heb het hier niet zoo druk als in den Haag, daar ik maar van s’morgens 9 tot s’avonds 6 uur in de zaak behoef te zijn &amp; Zatur<c type="shy">-</c>dags reeds om 4 uur gedaan heb.– Ik woon in eene der voorsteden van Londen, waar het betrekkelijk stil is, het heeft wel iets van Tilburg,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> of zoo.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Te Parijs had ik zeer prettige dagen &amp; heb zoo als je denken kunt veel genoten van al het moois dat ik op de tentoonstelling<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> &amp; in de Louvre &amp; Luxembourg<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> gezien heb.– De zaak te Parijs is prachtig &amp; veel grooter dan ik mij had voorgesteld.– Vooral de Place de l’Opera.–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het is hier zeer duur leven<c type="kk">/</c> in mijn kosthuis verwoon 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>ik 18 shillings per week behalve de wasch &amp; ik moet dan nog in de stad eten.–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">ll. zondag ben ik met Mr. Obach, mijn chef<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> naar buiten ge<c type="shy">-</c>weest, naar Boxhill, dat is een hoogen heuvel (zoowat 6 uur van L.)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> gedeeltelijk krijt &amp; begroeid met palm, en aan de eene zijde een bosch van hooge eikenboomen. Het land is hier prachtig mooi, heel iets anders dan Holland of België.– Overal ziet men prachtige parken met hooge boomen &amp; heesters. Men mag daar in wande<c type="shy">-</c>len. Met de Pinksterdagen<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> heb ik ook een mooie toer gemaakt met die Duitschers, maar die heeren verteeren zeer veel geld &amp; in het ver<c type="shy">-</c>volg zal ik niet meer met hen uitgaan.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Het deed mij genoegen van Pa te hooren dat het met Oom H. redelijk gaat<c type="kp">_</c> Wil hem &amp; Tante hartelijk van mij groeten<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> &amp; het een en ander van mij ver<c type="shy">-</c>tellen.– Zeg ook de Hr. Schmidt &amp; Eduard<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> van mij goeden dag &amp; schrijf mij eens spoedig. Adieu<c type="kk">/</c> heb het goed.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">mijn adres is:</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">care of Messrs Goupil &amp; C<hi rend="super">o</hi></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">17 Southampton Street</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Strand</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">London.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">London, 13 June 1873.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You’re probably longing to hear from me,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> so I don’t want to keep you waiting for a letter any longer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I heard from home that you’re now staying with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_624">Mr Schmidt</rs>, and that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> has been to see you. I sincerely hope that this will be more to your liking than your previous boarding-house, and don’t doubt that it will be.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Write to me soon, I’m longing to hear from you, and tell me how you’re 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> spending your days at present, &amp;c. Write to me especially about the paintings you’ve seen recently, and also whether anything new has been published in the way of etchings or lithographs. You must keep me well informed about this, because here I don’t see much in that genre, as the firm here is just a stockroom.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’m very well, considering the circumstances.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ve come by a boarding-house that suits me very well for the present.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> There are also three Germans in the house who really love music and play piano and sing themselves, which makes the evenings 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> very pleasant indeed. I’m not as busy here as I was in The Hague, as I only have to be in the office from 9 in the morning until 6 in the evening, and on Saturdays I’m finished by 4 o’clock. I live in one of the suburbs of London, where it’s comparatively quiet. It’s a bit like Tilburg<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> or some such place.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I spent some very pleasant days in Paris and, as you can imagine, very much enjoyed all the beautiful things I saw at the exhibition<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and in the Louvre and the Luxembourg.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> The Paris branch is splendid, and much larger than I’d imagined. Especially the Place de l’Opéra.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Life here is very expensive. I pay 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> 18 shillings a week for my lodgings, not including the washing, and then I still have to eat in town.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Last Sunday I went on an outing with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_547">Mr Obach</rs>, my superior,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> to Box Hill, which is a high hill (some 6 hours from L.),<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> partly of chalk and covered with box trees, and on one side a wood of tall oak trees. The countryside here is magnificent, completely different from Holland or Belgium. Everywhere one sees splendid parks with tall trees and shrubs, where one is allowed to walk. During the Whitsun holiday<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I also took a nice trip with those Germans, but those gentlemen spend a great deal of money and I shan’t go out with them any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I was glad to hear from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle H</rs>. is reasonably well. Would you give my warm regards to him and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1613">Aunt</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and give them news of me? Bid good-day to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_624">Mr Schmidt</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1069">Eduard</rs> from me,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and write to me soon. Adieu, I wish you well.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">My address is:</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Care of Messrs Goupil &amp; Co.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">17 Southampton Street</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Strand</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">London.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Londen 13 Juni 1873.’ Van Gogh filled in ‘13’ later.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had started working – presumably on Monday, 19 May or shortly thereafter – at Goupil’s London branch.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_624">Tobias Victor Schmidt</rs> lived in the Goupil building in Brussels: 58 rue Montagne de la Cour (Hofbergstraat). In a draft of the biographical introduction to her edition of the letters (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914), Jo van Gogh-Bonger wrote: ‘[Theo] lived in the house of a minister, which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> found very safe ─ but it was dirty and dismal and he felt so alone and unhappy, he slept alone in the attic, where he was so afraid. He was still so young (15) but he never wrote home about it and bore it well, until finally, when he <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">couldn’t</hi> stand it any longer, Schmidt asked him to come and live with him. Then everything was much more pleasant and enjoyable ─ in that young bachelor’s household, because Schmidt wasn’t married and Theo prepared their breakfast in the morning and fared very well’ (FR b3262). It is not impossible that there was some connection between Theo’s dissatisfaction with his lodgings and the circumstances of Reverend <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_313">Van den Brink</rs>’s family, to which a daughter, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1617">Catharina Alberta</rs>, had been born shortly before this time who was long sickly and eventually died in August (FR b2660 and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">SAB</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Regarding Goupil’s London branch, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let005.xml#n-7">see letter 5, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The address of Van Gogh’s boarding-house is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>From September 1866 until March 1868, Van Gogh had attended the Hogere Burger School (High School) in Tilburg, a city in the province of North Brabant.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>What is meant is the Salon, the annual exhibition of Living Masters, which had opened on 5 May 1873 in the Palais des Champs-Elysées.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The collections of the Musée du Louvre and of the Living Masters in the then Musée du Luxembourg, located to the east of the Palais du Luxembourg (in 1937 this museum was closed and the collection was removed to the Musée d’art moderne; a large part of this collection is now kept in the Musée d’Orsay).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Goupil &amp; Co. had three galleries in Paris, one at rue Chaptal 9, one at boulevard Montmartre 19 and a branch at place de l’Opéra 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>At first Van Gogh earned £ 90 a year (the average exchange rate was a little over 12 guilders to the pound, which amounted to an annual salary of 1,090 guilders), but, as <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo, ‘he still has to live frugally owing to the great hardship there; the boarding-house and his midday meal cost him 890 guilders a year’ (FR b2639, 2 July 1873).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The German <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_547">Charles Obach</rs>, director of Goupil &amp; Co. in London. Van Gogh went on this outing with Obach and his family on Sunday, 8 June (FR b2634).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Box Hill is near Dorking in Surrey, to the south-west of London, and could be reached by train. The ‘6 hours’ that Van Gogh talks about here is the time it took to walk that distance.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>That year Whit Sunday and Monday fell on 1 and 2 June.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle Hein</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1613">Aunt Mietje</rs> in Brussels.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1069">Edouard Hamman</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    