<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willem and Caroline van Stockum-Haanebeek. London, between about Thursday, 16 October and Friday, 31 October 1873.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let014"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b31 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b31 V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>014</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>11a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>014</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1873-10-16">between about Thursday, 16 October and Friday, 31 October 1873</date>
                            <placeName>London</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willem van Stockum and Caroline van Stockum-Haanebeek</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0031" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0031" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000033_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0032" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000034_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000034_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0032" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000034_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000034_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Londen Oct<c type="kp">_</c> 1873</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Beste Carolien en Willem,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Hartelijk dank voor je brief van heden morgen, dat was eene heerlijke verrassing, ik ben blij het jelui zoo goed gaat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Onze Anna is door haar Engelsch examen gekomen &amp; door dat voor de handwerken, gij kunt denken hoe zij &amp; wij allen het heer<c type="shy">-</c>lijk vinden.─<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Pa &amp; Moe hebben haar voorgesteld om nog tot aanst. April op school te blijven &amp; dan het Fransch te probeeren; maar als zij het liever niet doet hoeft zij niet.─ Ik zou zoo graag willen dat er hier iets voor haar te vinden was; gij weet wij daar wel eens over gesproken hebben.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Gij weet reeds dat Theo naar den Haag komt, ik vind dat eene goede verandering voor hem, hoewel het hem moeite 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>zal kosten, het mooie gezellige Brussel te verlaten.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Van je Pa<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> heb ik eenigen tijd geleden ook een brief gehad &amp; dien reeds beantwoord, gij zult dus waarschijnlijk reeds gehoord hebben dat het mij hier steeds goed blijft gaan &amp; ook een &amp; ander van mijne nieuwe woning hebben vernomen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Wat gij van den winter zegt is quite right, ik denk er ook zoo over; ik voor mij weet haast niet van welk jaargetijde ik het meest houd; ik geloof van allen even veel.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het is opmerkelijk dat de oude schilders bijna nooit herfst geschil<c type="shy">-</c>derd hebben &amp; dat de moderne er zulk eene bizondere voorliefde voor hebben.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Hierbij een paar kleine photogr. die hoop ik naar je zin zullen zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Hier heeft men bijna geen albums zooals die in Holland, maar zoo<c type="shy">-</c>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>genaamde “scrapbooks” waarin men de photographiën zet zooals ik ze in dezen brief doe, (daardoor komt het dat wij de photogr. hier onopgeplakt hebben)<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> hetgeen voorheeft dat men allerlei for<c type="shy">-</c>maten op het zelfde blad kan schikken zoo als men wil.─ Ik zou je aanraden je een soort schrijfboek met wit papier aan te schaffen &amp; daar dezen in te zetten, om mede te beginnen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">“Un Baptême” is naar Anker,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> een Zwitser, die allerlei sujetten geschilderd heeft, allen even fijn gevoeld &amp; intiem.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">“Puritans going to church” is naar Boughton,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> een der beste schilders hier; een Amerikaan, hij houd zeer veel &amp; terecht van Longfellow, ik ken 3 schilderijen van hem<c type="kk">/</c> ge<c type="shy">-</c>nomen uit “the Courtship of Miles Standish”.─<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Door het zien van die Sch<hi rend="super">ijen</hi> ben ik er toe gekomen Miles Standish &amp; Evangeline<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> nog eens te lezen, hoe het komt weet ik niet, maar ik heb nooit geweten, dat het <hi rend="italics">zoo</hi> mooi was als ik het nu vind.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">“Le bon frère” is naar van Muyden<c type="kk">/</c> een Zwitsersch schilder<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> “encore plus de modestie que de talent.”─<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>de H<hi rend="super">r</hi> Post te s’Hage heeft dit sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Als ge eens bij ons in den winkel komt vraag dan eens om zijn (v<c type="kp">_</c> Muyden’s) “Réfectoire”<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> te zien.─ Van deze photographie<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> bestaan niet meer dan 4 of 5 exemplaren daar het nega<c type="shy">-</c>tief gebroken is.─ Laat het eens bij gele<c type="shy">-</c>genheid aan Mr. Tersteeg zien.─<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> “La lune de miel” is naar Eugène Feyen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> een der weinige schilders die het intieme moderne leven schilderen zooals het werkelijk is, &amp; er geen modeplaatjes van maken. Die phot. “Der Wirthin Töchterlein” ken ik en vind ik zeer mooi.─<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Het is goed dat gij Bouguereau mooi vindt.─ Het is niet iedereen gegeven het goede &amp; schoone zoo op te merken &amp; te voelen als gij doet.─ En nu ga ik eindigen, ik sluit hier nog een schilderij van den herfst in door Michelet.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik hoop gij dezen zult kunnen lezen, ik heb maar voortgeschre<c type="shy">-</c>ven zonder er aan te denken dat men moet zorgen dat een brief leesbaar is.─ à Dieu, het beste Ulieden toegewenscht; veel groeten in de Poten<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> &amp; als gij verdere vrienden ziet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Vincent. </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Je vois d’ici une dame,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> je la vois marcher pensive dans un jardin peu étendu, &amp; défleuri de bonne heure, mais abrité, comme on en voit derrière nos falaises en France, ou les dunes de la Hollande. Les arbustes exotiques sont déjà rentrés dans la serre. Les feuilles tombées dévoilent quelques statues.─ Luxe d’art qui con<c type="shy">-</c>traste un peu avec la très-simple toilette de la dame, modeste, grave, où la soie noire (ou grise) s’égaye à peine d’un simple ru<c type="shy">-</c>ban lilas.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Parée de rien, on peut le dire, elle n’en est pas moins élé<c type="shy">-</c>gante.─ Elégante pour son mari &amp; simple au profit des pauvres.─ Elle atteint le bout de l’allée, se retourne.─ Nous pouvons la voir. Mais ne l’ai je pas vue déja aux musées d’Amsterdam ou de la Haye? Elle me rap<c type="shy">-</c>pelle une dame de Philippe de Champagne (NB. au Louvre) qui m’était 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>entrée dans le coeur, si candide, si honnête, suffissament intelligente, simple pourtant, sans finesse pour se démêler des ruses du monde. Cette femme m’est restée trente années, me revenant obstinément, m’in<c type="shy">-</c>quiétant, me faisant dire “Mais comment se nommait-elle? Que lui est-il arrivé? a-t-elle eu un peu de bonheur? Et comment s’est-elle tirée de la vie?” Celle-ci me rappelle encore un autre portrait, un van Dyck, une pauvre dame, fort blanche, maladive. Le pâle satin de sa peau d’incomparable finesse, orne un corps souffrant, qui mollit.─ Dans ses beaux yeux flotte une grande mélancolie, celle de l’âge ─ des chagrins de coeur ─ du climat aussi peut-être. C’est le regard vague, lointain, d’une personne qui a eu habituellement sous les yeux le vaste Océan du Nord, la grande mer grise, déserte, sauf le vol du goëland.─</p> <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Jules Michelet</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Les aspirations de l’automne.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">London, Oct. 1873</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_761">Caroline</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_760">Willem</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Many thanks for your letter of this morning. It was a wonderful surprise, I’m happy you’re doing so well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> has passed her examinations in English and in needlework, you can imagine how delighted she and all of us are.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> have suggested that she stay at school until next April, and in that case attempt French, but if she’d rather not she needn’t do it. I’d like it so much if something could be found for her here; we’ve talked about this before, as you know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You already know that Theo is coming to The Hague, I think it a good change for him, even though it will be difficult for him 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> to leave beautiful, convivial Brussels.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I also received a letter from your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_442">Pa</rs><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> some time ago and have already answered it, so you’ll probably have heard that things are continuing to go well for me here, and also know a thing or two about my new lodgings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">What you say about winter is quite right, I think so too. I myself almost don’t know which season I like best; I believe all of them, equally well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">It’s striking that the old painters almost never painted the autumn and that the moderns have such a particular preference for it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Herewith a couple of small photos which I hope will be to your liking. Here there are practically no albums like those we have in Holland, but rather so-
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>called ‘scrapbooks’ in which one puts photographs, as I’ve done in this letter (which explains why we don’t put the photos in mounts here),<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> the advantage of which is that one can arrange all shapes and sizes on the same sheet however one wants. I would advise you to buy a kind of writing-book with blank pages and to put these in it, for a start.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">‘A baptism’ is after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Anker</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> a Swiss, who has painted all manner of subjects, all equally sensitive and intimate.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">‘Puritans going to church’ is after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> one of the best painters here; an American, he’s very fond of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">Longfellow</rs>, and rightly so. I know 3 paintings by him based on ‘The courtship of Miles Standish’.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Seeing the paintings prompted me to read Miles Standish and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_8">Evangeline</ref><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> again, I don’t know why, but I never knew they were as beautiful as I find them now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">‘The good friar’ is after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Van Muyden</rs>, a Swiss painter,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> having ‘as yet more modesty than talent’.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_598">Mr Post</rs> in The Hague has this painting.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> If you visit our gallery ask to see his (Van Muyden’s) ‘Refectory’.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> There are no more than 4 or 5 copies of this photograph,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> because the negative is broken. Show it to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> when you have the opportunity.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> ‘The honeymoon’ is after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1010">Eugène Feyen</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> one of the few painters who paint intimate modern life as it really is and don’t turn it into fashion plates. I know the photo of ‘The landlady’s daughter’<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and I find it very beautiful. It’s good that you find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_890">Bouguereau</rs> beautiful. Not everyone is as capable as you are of noticing and feeling good and fine things. And now I’ll stop; I’m enclosing another picture of autumn, by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I hope you’ll be able to read this; I just kept on writing without thinking that one should take care to make a letter legible. Adieu, I wish you both the best; many regards to those in the Poten<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> and to any other friends you might see.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">From here I see a lady,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> I see her walking, pensive, in a garden that is not very big and has lost its flowers quite early, but is sheltered, like the ones one sees behind our cliffs in France or the dunes of Holland. The exotic shrubs have already gone back into the greenhouse. The fallen leaves reveal some statues. A sumptuousness of art, which contrasts slightly with the very simple attire of the lady — modest, grave — the black (or grey) silk of which is barely brightened by a plain lilac ribbon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Unadorned, this we can say, she is no less elegant. Elegant for her husband and simple for the benefit of the poor. She reaches the end of the avenue, turns. We can see her. But have I not seen her before in the museums of Amsterdam or The Hague? She reminds me of a lady by Philippe de Champaigne (NB in the Louvre), who had found 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> her way into my heart, so ingenuous, so honest, sufficiently intelligent, yet simple, without the subtlety to extricate herself from the snares of the world. This woman has remained with me for thirty years, obstinately returning to me, worrying me, making me say, ‘But what was she called? What became of her? Did she have a little happiness? And how did she manage to get through life?’ She reminds me of another portrait, a Van Dyck, a poor woman, very pale, unhealthy. The pale satin of her incomparably delicate skin clothes a sickly body, which is beginning to slacken. A great melancholy fills her lovely eyes, the melancholy of old age? Of heartbreaks, of the climate too, perhaps. It is the vague, distant look of someone who has lived within sight of the vast North Sea, the great grey sea, deserted but for the flight of the seagull.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Les aspirations de l’automne.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Londen Oct_ 1873’. Van Gogh appears already to have heard that his sister Anna passed her exam in needlework, which had taken place on 13 October (FR b2669, 13 October 1873). It is reasonable to assume that he could not have heard about it any earlier than on or about 16 October, which is why we have dated the letter between then and the end of the month. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s move <ref target="let013.xml">(13)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s transfer to The Hague <ref target="let013.xml">(13)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> had passed her exam in English around 3 October (FR b2666), and her exam in needlework shortly before 13 October (FR b2669).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_442">Carl Adolph Haanebeek</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>After writing this letter, Van Gogh made sixteen incisions, in which he mounted the four photographs he sent with the letter. Such photographs, which measured 6 x 9 cm, were usually glued to pieces of cardboard and sold as ‘Cartes de visite’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Albert Anker</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A baptism</hi>, 1864 (Lagnau, formerly Amtsersparniskasse). Also published in the ‘Galerie photographique’ of Goupil, no. 303 (Paris, BNF, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1655">Ill. 1655</rs>. Van Gogh sent the version from the ‘Carte de visite’ series.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">George Henry Boughton</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_18"><hi rend="italics">Early Puritans</hi></rs>. For this ‘Carte de visite’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let011.xml#n-5">see letter 11, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_7">The courtship of Miles Standish</ref>’, a narrative poem by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">Henry Wadsworth Longfellow</rs>, first appeared in 1858 in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The courtship of Miles Standish and other poems</hi>. See Longfellow 1886-1891, vol. 2, pp. 283-348. The poem relates a love story that took place at the time of the first Pilgrim Fathers in Plymouth, North America.</p>
      
<p rend="indent">Van Gogh probably knew ‘3 paintings’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs> from reproductions. One of them will have been The march of Miles Standish, which was exhibited in the Royal Academy (no. 493) in 1869. The print made after it by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1532">George C. Finden</rs> appeared in The Art Journal, N.S. vol. 11 (1 May 1872), between pp. 140-141. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1656">Ill. 1656</rs>. It is not clear which other two paintings Van Gogh had in mind. Boughton made a number of depictions of ‘The Puritans in America’ and related subjects, and it is possible that Van Gogh associated several of them with the story of Miles Standish. See Werness 1985.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_8">Evangeline, a tale of Acadie</ref>’ (1847). See Longfellow 1886-1891, vol. 2, pp. 7-106. The story takes place in the early period of British colonization in Acadia (Nova Scotia in North America), when the Acadians were driven from their land during the Anglo-French War in Canada (known in Europe as the Seven Years’ War and in America as the French and Indian War). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le bon frère</hi> (The good friar) is a reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Jacques Alfred van Muyden</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_19"><hi rend="italics">Le bon moine</hi></rs> (The good monk), a photograph of which was included in the ‘Carte-album’ series (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1657">Ill. 1657</rs>. Van Gogh sent the version from the ‘Carte de visite’ series.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Possibly a quotation from a contemporary art critic’s comments on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Van Muyden</rs>’s work.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The banker <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_598">Franciscus Hermanus Marinus Post</rs>. The canvas was offered for sale under the title <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_19"><hi rend="italics">Le frère quêteur</hi></rs> (The friar collector) (1866) at the sale of the Post Collection in 1891 and sold for 910 guilders to F. Muller &amp; Co. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Catalogue de la collection de tableaux modernes de monsieur ‘P***’, amateur, à la Haye ...</hi> Amsterdam 1891, p. 65, cat. no. 63.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Van Muyden</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Refectory of the Capuchins at Albano, near Rome</hi> (1855), a reproduction of which appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 33 (5 February 1859), p. 85 (at that time in the possession of ‘General Dufour’). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1658">Ill. 1658</rs>. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Refectory</hi> does not occur in the ledgers (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RKD, Goupil Ledgers</hi>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is likely referring to the photograph of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The good monk</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>At this time Van Gogh was also writing to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> remarked to Theo: ‘Mr Tersteeg also wrote very kindly about Vincent. He could tell from his letters that he was feasting his eyes and ears to the full’ (FR b2668, on or about 4 October 1873).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>‘Carte de visite’ by (Jacques) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1010">Eugène Feyen</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La lune de miel</hi> (The honeymoon), 1869 (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1659">Ill. 1659</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>No reproduction of an art work with this title has been found. (The title is undoubtedly connected with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_841">Ludwig Uhland</rs>’s poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_9">Der Wirthin Töchterlein</ref>’, which Van Gogh knew; see Pabst 1988, pp. 34, 41-45.)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>See the appendix at the end of the letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Lange Poten 10 in The Hague, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_761">Caroline</rs>’s parental home.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>A parenthetical expression has been omitted here: ‘(celle que ce livre a prise jeune et conduite au déclin de l’âge)’ (‘the one this book took up when she was young and has followed into the twilight of her life’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>The quotation was taken from the chapter ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_10">Les aspirations de l’automne</ref>’ (The longing for autumn) of <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> (1858) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, part 5, chapter 5 (see Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, pp. 388-389). Van Gogh added ‘(NB au Louvre)’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-235">(l. 235)</ref>. The painting referred to, known as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Portrait of a woman</hi> (Paris, Musée du Louvre), was previously attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_937">Philippe de Champaigne</rs> but is now viewed as anonymous French, seventeenth century. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1661">Ill. 1661</rs>. This prose excerpt had a special meaning for Van Gogh and will be mentioned again later; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let035.xml">see letters 35</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let089.xml">89</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let090.xml">90</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let102.xml">102</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let132.xml">132</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let133.xml">133</ref>. Cf. also Pabst 1988, pp. 65, 90.</p>

<p rend="indent">Many of Van Gogh’s ideas about love and women prove to have been inspired by the literature he read: above all by the books <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> (1858) and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12"><hi rend="italics">La femme</hi></ref> (1860). He went so far as to describe these didactic treatises on the ideal relationship between man and woman – they should become two-in-one and together bring about something real – as his gospel.</p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> argues that a woman can only really be happy within marriage and under the guidance of the right man. He sets out the tasks and duties of each party and explains how the security and support provided by the husband, combined with the devotion and purity of the wife, can lead to a ‘divine unity’. Michelet advocated a vigorous and active love. Men who were not prepared to protect and rescue a woman should be ashamed of themselves.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh had a copy of <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’Amour</hi></ref>. Paris (Hachette) 1861 with his name ‘Vincent’ inscribed at the front. See V.W. van Gogh, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les sources d’inspiration de Vincent van Gogh</hi>. Exhib. cat. Paris (Institut Néerlandais). Paris 1972, p. 22 (cat. no. 56).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    