<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Ramsgate, Friday, 28 April 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let079"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b76 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>079</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>63</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>077</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-04-28">Friday, 28 April 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Ramsgate</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0076" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000079_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000079_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0076" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000079_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000079_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000079_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Ramsgate 28 April 1876</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Nog menig jaar na dit; van harte gelukgewenscht met dezen dag,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> moge onze liefde voor elkander maar toenemen met het ouder worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zoo blij ben ik dat wij zooveel met elkaar gemeen hebben, niet alleen de herinneringen aan vroeger maar ook dat gij in de zelfde zaak zijt waarin ik tot nog toe was en dus zooveel menschen en plaatsen kent die ik ook ken, en dat gij zooveel liefde hebt voor natuur en kunst.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dien brief waarin Anna’s advertentie was zult gij wel in orde ontvangen hebben.– Ook in de Daily News staat eene advertentie,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en nu moeten wij maar hopen dat zich iets zal openbaren.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Mr. Stokes heeft mij verteld dat hij plan heeft om na de vacantie te gaan verhuizen, natuurlijk met de geheele school, naar een dorp aan den Theems<c type="kk">/</c> een uur of 3 van Londen. Dan zou hij de school wat anders inrichten en misschien uitbreiden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu vertel ik U nog maar eens van eene wandeling die wij gisteren deden. Het was naar een inham van de zee, en de weg daarheen ging door de akkers 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>met het jonge koren en langs heggen van meidoorn enz.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Toen wij er kwamen hadden wij links een hooge steile kant van zand en steen, zoo hoog als een huis van 2 verdiepingen. Boven daarop stonden oude knoestige Meidoornstruiken waarvan de zwarte of met grijs korstmos bedekte stammen en takken door den wind allen den zelfden kant uit waren gebogen, ook enkele vlierstruiken.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">De grond waar wij liepen was geheel bedekt met groote grijze steenen, krijt en schelpen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Rechts de zee, die zoo kalm was als een vijver en waarin het licht van de fijn grijze lucht waar de zon onderging weerkaatste. Het was eb en het water zeer laag.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dank voor uw brief van gisteren<c type="kk">/</c> ik vind het zeer aardig dat Willem Valkis in de zaak komt.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Groet hem vooral eens voor mij. Ik zou nog wel eens met U beiden door de boschjes<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> naar Scheveningen willen wandelen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Heb een goeden dag van daag en groet allen die naar mij mochten vragen en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Uw liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Heb het goed vandaag jongen, en begin een gelukkig en gezegend jaar. Het zijn belangrijke jaren waarin wij beiden zijn en waarvan veel reeds afhangt. Moge alles goed uitkomen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik zal blij zijn als Anna wat heeft gevonden maar betrekkingen zoo als zij zoekt zijn nog al schaars. Eene ziekelijke dame hier die iemand noodig had om haar op te passen ontving 300 brieven op hare advertentie.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">In gedachten U hartelijk de hand gedrukt.– à Dieu!</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Ramsgate, 28 April 1876</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Many happy returns; my hearty congratulations on this day,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> may our love for one another only increase as we get older.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m so happy that we have so much in common, not only memories of the past but also that you’re working for the same firm I worked for until now, and therefore know so many people and places that I know too, and that you love nature and art so much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You’ll have received that letter containing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>’s advertisement in good order. There’s also an advertisement in the Daily News;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> now we can only hope that something will come of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs> told me that he intends to move after the holidays – with the whole school, naturally – to a village on the Thames, around 3 hours from London. He would then furnish the school somewhat differently and perhaps expand it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Now let me tell you about a walk we took yesterday. It was to an inlet of the sea, and the road to it led through the fields 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> of young wheat and along hedgerows of hawthorn etc.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> When we got there we had on our left a high, steep wall of sand and stone, as high as a two-storey house, on top of which stood old, gnarled hawthorn bushes. Their black or grey, lichen-covered stems and branches had all been bent to the same side by the wind, also a few elder bushes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">The ground we walked on was completely covered with large grey stones, chalk and shells.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">To the right the sea, as calm as a pond, reflecting the delicate grey sky where the sun was setting. It was ebb tide and the water was very low.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Thanks for your letter of yesterday, I think it very nice that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem Valkis</rs> will be joining the branch.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Give him my particular regards. I’d like to walk with you both sometime through the Bosjes<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> to Scheveningen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Have a pleasant day today, and give my regards to everyone who asks after me, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Your loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I wish you well today, old boy, and begin a happy and blessed year. These are important years for us both, years on which much already depends. May everything turn out well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’ll be glad when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> has found something, but situations like the ones she is looking for are rather scarce. A sickly lady here who needed someone to look after her received 300 replies to her advertisement.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I shake your hand heartily in thought. Adieu!</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Ramsgate 28 April 1876’</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The search for a situation for Anna <ref target="let078.xml">(78)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo was to turn 19 on 1 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>No such advertisement has been found in the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Daily News</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This walk must have taken them to Pegwell Bay. See exhib. cat. Nottingham 1974, p. 13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem Valkis</rs> entered the employ of Goupil &amp; Co. at the end of April. On 29 April 1876, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘I think it nice for Willem that he’s joined the firm as well!’ (FR b2743).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The local name for the Scheveningse Bosjes, a small wooded area joining The Hague and Scheveningen.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    