<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Isleworth, Friday, 18 August 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let088"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b86 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>088</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>73</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>087</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-08-18">Friday, 18 August 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Isleworth</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0086" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0086" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000089_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Isleworth. 18 Aug. 1876</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gisteren ben ik bij Gladwell<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> geweest, die voor eenige dagen thuis is; er gebeurde iets heel treurigs in zijne familie; zijne zuster, een meisje vol leven met donkere oogen en haar, 17 jaar, is gevallen bij het paardrijden, op Blackheath, zij was buiten kennis toen men haar opnam en is 5 uur later, zonder weer tot zich zelven gekomen te zijn, gestorven.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
  
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zoodra ik hoorde wat er gebeurd was en dat Gladwell thuis was ben ik er heen gegaan.─ Gisteren morgen 11 uur vertrok ik van hier en had eene lange wandeling naar Lewisham<c type="kk">/</c> de weg ging van ’t eene eind van Londen naar het andere, om 5 uur was ik bij Gladwell.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik was nog naar hun winkel gegaan<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> maar die was gesloten.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Allen waren juist van de begrafenis terug, het was een waar klaaghuis en het was mij goed daar te zijn.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik voelde een gevoel van verlegenheid en schaamte bij het zien van die groote eerbiedwaardige smart, want deze menschen zijn eerbiedwaardig.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Zalig zijn die treuren,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> zalig zijn zij die “droevig zijn, maar altijd blijde”,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> zalig zijn zij die eenvoudig zijn van hart,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> want God vertroost de eenvoudigen.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Zalig zijn zij die de Liefde vinden op hunnen weg<c type="kk">/</c> die door God innig aan elkaar zijn verbon<c type="shy">-</c>den, want hun werken alle dingen mede ten goede.─<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Ik sprak lang met Harry tot s’avonds toe, over allerlei, over het koninkrijk Gods en over zijn Bijbel en al pratende wandelden wij in het station op en neer en die oogenblikken tot het afscheid zullen wij wel niet vergeten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">wij kennen elkaar zoo, zijn werk was mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> de menschen ginder die hij kent ken ik, zijn leven was mijn leven, en zoo diep was het mij gegeven te zien in de geschiedenis van die familie, omdat ik meen dat ik hen liefheb<c type="kk">/</c> minder omdat ik de bijzonderheden van die geschiedenis ken dan omdat ik den toon en de stemming van hun zijn en leven voel<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Wij wandelden dus op en neer in dat station<c type="kk">/</c> in die alledaagsche wereld maar met een gevoel 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>in ons dat niet alledaagsch was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zij duren niet lang<c type="kk">/</c> die oogenblikken<c type="kk">/</c> en wij moesten spoedig afscheid nemen van elkaar<c type="kp">_</c> Het was een mooi gezigt uit den trein over Londen dat daar lag in den donker, St Paul<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en andere kerken in de verte. Ik spoorde tot Richmond<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> en wandelde langs den Theems naar Isleworth, dat was eene mooie wan<c type="shy">-</c>deling, links de parken met hunne groote populieren, eiken en iepen<c type="kk">/</c> rechts de rivier waarin de groote boomen spiegelden. Het was een mooien bijna plechtigen avond; om kwart over 10 was ik thuis.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dank voor Uw laatsten brief. Gij hadt nog niet geschreven dat Mevrouw Vincent overleden was, wat heb ik Haar dikwijls s’avonds thuis gebragt.─<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Komt Gij nog wel eens bij Borchers aan huis? Wat zou ik graag mede naar de Hoeve zijn gewandeld! Dikwijls doe ik Bijbel<c type="shy">-</c>sche geschiedenis met de jongens en verl. Zondag deed ik bijbellezing met hen. S’morgens en s’avonds lezen wij allen den Bijbel en zingen en bidden en dat is goed.─ Ook te Ramsgate deden wij dat en als die 21 zonen van de Londensche markten en straten baden “Our Father, who art in Heaven<c type="kk">/</c> give us this day our daily bread”<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> heb 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>ik wel eens gedacht aan den roep der jonge raven dien de Heer hoort,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en ’t was mij goed met hen mede te bidden en waarschijnlijk lager dan zij het hoofd te buigen bij de woorden <hi rend="italics">Do not lead us into temptation</hi> <hi rend="italics">but deliver us from evil</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik ben nog vol van gisteren; ’t moet goed zijn den broeder te zijn van dien man dien ik gisteren zoo bedroefd zag, ik bedoel het moet “zalig zijn te treuren”<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> met mannelijke droefheid, wat had ik dien Vader graag getroost, maar ik stond verlegen dáárvoor, tot den zoon kon ik spreken. Er was iets geheiligds in dat huis gisteren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Hebt gij ooit gelezen “A life for a life”<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t Hollandsch meen ik “uit het leven voor het leven”<c type="kk">/</c> door de schrijfster van John Halifax,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> dat zoudt Gij zeer mooi vinden<c type="kp">_</c> Hoe gaat het met Uw Engelsch.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het was een genot om weer eens eene verre wandeling te doen, hier op school wordt maar zeer weinig gewan<c type="shy">-</c>deld. Als ik denk aan mijn leven van strijd te Parijs verl. jaar en nu hier waar ik soms een heelen dag de deur niet uit kan, ten minste niet verder dan den tuin, dan denk ik wel eens<c type="kk">/</c> wanneer zal ik weer terug<c type="shy">-</c>gaan in die wereld? Ga ik er in terug dan zal het echter waarschijnlijk wel weer ander werk zijn dan verl. jaar.─ Maar ik geloof dat ik liever Bijbelsche geschie<c type="shy">-</c>denis met de jongens doe dan wandelen, men gevoelt zich min of meer veilig als men het eerste doet.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En nu<c type="kk">/</c> groeten bij Roos en mocht soms iemand anders naar mij vragen. Hoe maken het de families v.d. Berg<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en v. Stockum op het Buitenhof,<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> hoort Gij ooit iets van hen.─ Een handdruk in gedachten en het beste U toegewenscht door</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En hierbij een brief voor Mauve<c type="kp">_</c> Gij moogt dien lezen, ik geloof het goed is om zijne bekenden van vroeger niet te vergeten<c type="kk">/</c> daarom schrijf ik maar weer eens aan den een en ander, ook te Parijs, aan Soek en anderen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
  
<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als Gij iemand kunt overhalen om Scenes from Clerical Life door Elliott en Felix Holt te lezen dan doet Gij een goed werk. Het eerste is zoo prachtig schoon.─ <ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Recommandeer het eerste eens aan Caroline en bij Mauve en <hi rend="italics">als</hi> <hi rend="italics">’t kan</hi> ook aan de Hr Tersteeg<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Zoudt Gij per ommegaande kunnen opgeven of een <hi rend="italics">Nederlandsch</hi> pond boter 80<hi rend="super">ct</hi> kost en is het een ander pond ─ welk gedeelte van een kilo is dat dan?<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Groet ook de Heer Tersteeg voor mij en Mevrouw en Betsy<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik schrijf U tusschen de schooluren in en nog al in haast zoo als Gij ziet.─<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Isleworth, 18 Aug. 1876</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Yesterday I went to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Gladwell</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> who’s home for a few days. Something very sad happened to his family: his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_395">sister</rs>, a girl full of life, with dark eyes and hair, 17 years old, fell from her horse while riding on Blackheath. She was unconscious when they picked her up, and died 5 hours later without regaining consciousness.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I went there as soon as I heard what had happened and that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Gladwell</rs> was at home. I left here yesterday morning at 11 o’clock, and had a long walk to Lewisham, the road went from one end of London to the other. At 5 o’clock I was at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394 bio.xml#_396">Gladwell</rs>’s.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’d gone to their gallery first,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> but it was closed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">They had all just come back from the funeral, it was a real house of mourning and it did me good to be there.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I had feelings of embarrassment and shame at seeing that deep, estimable grief, for these people are estimable. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Blessed are they that mourn,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> blessed are they that are ‘sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing’,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> blessed are the pure in heart,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> for God comforts the simple.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Blessed are they that find Love on their path, who are bound intimately with one another by God, for to them all things work together for good.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I talked with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry</rs> for a long time, until the evening, about all kinds of things, about the kingdom of God and about his Bible, and we walked up and down on the station, talking, and those moments before parting we’ll probably never forget.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">We know each other so well, his work was my work, the people he knows there I know too, his life was my life, and it was given to me to see so deeply into their family affairs, I think, because I believe that I love them, not so much because I know the particulars of those affairs, but because I feel the tone and feeling of their being and life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">So we walked back and forth on that station, in that everyday world, but with a feeling 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> that was not everyday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">They don’t last long, such moments, and we soon had to take leave of each other. It was a beautiful sight, looking out from the train over London, that lay there in the dark, St Paul’s<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and other churches in the distance. I stayed in the train until Richmond<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> and walked along the Thames to Isleworth, that was a lovely walk, on the left the parks with their tall poplars, oaks and elms, on the right the river, reflecting the tall trees. It was a beautiful, almost solemn, evening; I got home at quarter past 10.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Thanks for your last letter. You hadn’t yet written that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_795">Mrs Vintcent</rs> had died; how often I brought her home in the evenings.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Do you still visit <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_298">Borchers</rs> sometimes? How I’d like to have walked with you to Hoeven! I often teach the boys biblical history, and last Sunday I read the Bible with them. Mornings and evenings we all read the Bible and sing and pray, and that is good. We did that at Ramsgate, too, and when those 21 sons of the London markets and streets prayed ‘Our Father, who art in Heaven, give us this day our daily bread’,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I’ve 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> sometimes thought of the cry of the young ravens that the Lord hears,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and it did me good to pray with them and to bow my head, probably even lower than they did, at the words <hi rend="italics">Do not lead us into temptation but deliver us from evil</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’m still full of yesterday; it must be good to be the brother of the man I saw so sorrowful yesterday, I mean that it must ‘be blessed to mourn’<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> with manly sorrow, how I’d have liked to comfort the Father, but I was embarrassed, though I could talk to the son. There was something hallowed in that house yesterday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Have you ever read ‘A life for a life’, I think in Dutch it’s called ‘Uit het leven voor het leven’, by the woman who wrote John Halifax?<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> You’d find it very beautiful. How’s your English coming along?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">It was a delight to take a long walk again, very little walking is done here at school. When I think of my life of struggle in Paris last year and now here, where sometimes I can’t leave the house for a whole day, or at least no further than the garden, then I sometimes think, when will I return to that world? If I do return to it, though, it will probably be some other kind of work than I did last year. But I think that I prefer doing biblical history with the boys to walking; one feels more or less safe doing the former.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And now, regards to everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’, and if anyone else should ask after me. How are <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_264 bio.xml#_265">the Van den Berghs</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_768 bio.xml#_769">the Van Stockums</rs> on Buitenhof?<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Do you ever hear anything from them? A handshake in thought and best wishes from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">And herewith a letter for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>. You may read it, I believe it’s good not to forget one’s old acquaintances, that’s why I’m writing again to some of them, also those in Paris, to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_758">Soek</rs> and others.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">If you can persuade anyone to read Scenes from clerical life by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs>, and Felix Holt, you’ll be doing a good deed. The former is a wonderful book.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Recommend the former to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_761">Caroline</rs> and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321 bio.xml#_323">the Mauves</rs> and, <hi rend="italics">if possible</hi>, to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> as well.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Could you write by return of post saying whether a <hi rend="italics">Dutch</hi> pound of butter costs 80 cents and – if it’s a different pound – what part of a kilo is it then?<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Also give my regards to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787 bio.xml#_788">Mr and Mrs Tersteeg</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_789">Betsy</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I’m writing to you between school hours and rather in haste, as you can see.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Isleworth. 18 Aug. 1876’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This refers to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry Gladwell</rs>, who apparently had already been to visit Vincent, since <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> told Theo (before 18 August 1876): ‘Vincent’s last letter contained nothing special except that Gladwell had been to see him, which he was so happy about’ (FR b2765).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_395">Susannah Eleanor Gladwell</rs> died on Wednesday, 16 August 1876.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>To get from Isleworth (south-west of London) via the gallery in the City (Gracechurch Street) to Lewisham (south-east of London), Van Gogh had to walk more than 30 km.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_396">Gladwell</rs>’s gallery, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let055.xml#n-1">see letter 55, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Cf. Eccl. 7:2-4; cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-6">n. 6</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Cf. Eccl. 7:3 and Matt. 5:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 6:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 5:8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Cor. 7:6, ‘God, that comforteth those that are cast down’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  Rom. 8:28. The repetition of ‘Blessed are...’ reflects the wording of Matt. 5:3-11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>St Paul’s Cathedral in the City of London.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Richmond station was south-east of Isleworth.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>This most likely refers to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_795">Cornelia Wilhelmina De Lezenne Greve</rs>, the wife of<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_230"> Johannes Bernardus Lodewijk Philippus Vintcent</rs>, a brother of the painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_231">Lodewijk Antonie Vintcent</rs>. When Van Gogh was living in The Hague, Mrs Vintcent-De Lezenne Greve was living at Hofstraat 13, where she had resided since c. 1869/1870. She died on 21 July 1876 in The Hague (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The Lord’s Prayer: Matt. 6:9-11 and Luke 11:2-3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Cf. Ps. 147:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The Lord’s Prayer: Matt. 6:13 and Luke 11:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 5:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>In 1856, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_713">Dinah Maria Mulock Craik</rs> wrote the bestseller <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_74"><hi rend="italics">John Halifax, gentleman</hi></ref>, the story of a tanner’s apprentice who works his way up to the point where he can afford to set up in business for himself. Widely read, but less successful, was Mulock Craick’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_75"><hi rend="italics">A life for a life</hi></ref> (1859), a book which shows that ‘women and men have similar strengths, needs, and emotions. The plot shows that a man who commits murder and a woman who has a child out of wedlock can experience the same pattern of suffering and redemption.’ The principal characters, both lonely people, accept each other as they are, marry, and decide to emigrate to Canada, because there is no place for them in English society. See Mitchell 1983, pp. 56-58 (quotation on p. 56).</p>

<p rend="indent">The Dutch translation of <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_75"><hi rend="italics">A life for a life</hi></ref> was titled <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Leven om leven</hi>, but no copy has been traced. Mention of this edition is made on the title page of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_713">Mulock Craik</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A noble life</hi>, namely <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Een welbesteed leven</hi> (Van Kampen publishers, Amsterdam, 1866. Copy in the Groningen University Library). In those days it was not unusual for a book’s title page or binding to display a phrase such as ‘from the author of John Halifax’, and this could be where Van Gogh had seen it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>The family of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_264">Arie van den Bergh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_265">Johanna Ewaldine Stricker</rs>, a daughter of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_778">Johannes Andries Stricker</rs>. Van den Bergh was a chemist and distiller in The Hague’s prestigious Spuistraat (no. 51). The couple had been living since 1866 in Huis te Hoorn in Rijswijk, where they were photographed, together with their three sons and two daughters, in August 1872 (FR b5348).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>The family of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_768">Wilhelmus Petrus van Stockum</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_769">Maria de Langen</rs>. Van Stockum was a bookseller and publisher in The Hague. The family lived at Buitenhof 36. The couple had four sons and four daughters, though several of them no longer lived at home, one being <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_760">Willem Jacob</rs>, the husband of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_761">Caroline Haanebeek</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            
    
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_65"><hi rend="italics">Scenes of clerical life</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let70.xml#n-4">see letter 70, n. 4</ref> and for <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_57"><hi rend="italics">Felix Holt, the radical</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let066.xml#n-1">see letter 66, n. 1</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Jones</rs> had previously asked Van Gogh to inquire about the price of Dutch butter; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let087.xml">see letter 87</ref>. Between May and October 1876, the price of one Dutch pound (which was actually 1 kg) of butter fluctuated between 1.50 and 1.80 guilders on the Delft market. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Uitkomsten van het onderzoek naar den toestand van den landbouw in Nederland</hi>. The Hague 1890, vol. 2, section 58, p. 20. Van Gogh asked expressly about a ‘Dutch pound’ because in those days weights and measures had not yet been standardized. See J.M. Verhoeff, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De oude Nederlandse maten en gewichten</hi>. Amsterdam 1982.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>The marginal comments were obviously written in haste.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    