<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus and Theo van Gogh. Isleworth, Friday, 13 October 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let094"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b91 V/1962 (sheet 1), and inv. no. b1470 V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>094</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>77</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>093</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-10-13">Friday, 13 October 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Isleworth</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anna van Gogh-Carbentus and Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0091" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0091" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000095_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1470" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001358_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001358_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1470" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001358_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001358_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Isleworth 13 October 1876</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Lieve Moeder en Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Morgen gaan de jongens naar huis en dan ontvang ik mijn geld<c type="kp">_</c> Ik vroeg aan Mr Jones om mij naar U toe te laten gaan in die drie dagen, mijn hart is zoo bij u.– Het hangt nu van U beiden af – als U zegt – “gij moogt komen” dan wil Mr Jones mij laten gaan. Behalve dat ik zoo graag eens aan het bed van Theo zou zitten, zou ik zoo heel graag ook eens met mijne Moeder spreken, en zoo mogelijk ook nog eens naar Etten gaan om mijn Vader weer eens te zien en te spreken. ’t Zou maar voor kort zijn<c type="kk">/</c> een of twee dagen zou ik bij U kun<c type="shy">-</c>nen zijn.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Verleden Maandag was ik weer te Richmond en nam de woorden<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Hij heeft mij gezonden om den armen het evangelie te verkondigen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Maar zoo wie het evangelie wil verkondigen die moet het eerst zelf in het hart hebben, och dat ik het vinden mocht, want het is alleen het woord gesproken in eenvoudigheid en uit den overvloed des harten<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> dat vrucht kan voortbrengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Misschien ga ik dezer dagen weer eens naar Londen of Lewisham.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Daarjuist heb ik Duitsche les gegeven aan de Meisjes van Mr Jones<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en hen na de les de Sneeuwkonin<c type="shy">-</c>gin van Andersen<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> verteld.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Als het kan schrijf dan per ommegaande of ik komen mag; ik was blij met Moe’s laatsten brief.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dezer dagen hoop ik eens een bezoek te gaan brengen aan de school van Mr Stokes.– En dan hoop ik een paar nieuwe schoenen te koopen om mij weer op te maken. Het gezicht uit het raam van Uw kamertje zal nu mooi zijn, gij weet ik ken dat van ouds.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wij hebben veel regen hier tegenwoordig<c type="kk">/</c> dat zal bij U ook wel zoo zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Met Kersmis zal ik 14 dagen of 3 weeken hebben om naar Holland te gaan, mocht Anna dan ook kunnen komen dan zouden wij misschien zamen kunnen gaan.– En nu gaan wij dus zoo langzamer<c type="shy">-</c>hand den winter weer te gemoet, wordt gij maar weer geheel beter tegen dien tijd. Het is toch heerlijk het kersmis is in den winter. O Jongen ik verheug er mij zoo op om als het koud zal zijn hier en daar rond te gaan te Turnham green.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Als ik zoo aan U denk, als aan “een dien zijne Moeder vertroost en die waardig is om door zijne Moeder vertroost te worden”,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ’t is om te benijden. Maar word maar spoedig beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Gisteren vroeg ik aan Mr Jones om mij te laten gaan maar Hij wilde niet toestemmen en zeide ten laatste<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf aan je Moeder<c type="kk">/</c> als die het goed<c type="shy">-</c>vind dan vind ik het ook goed.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het is toch een mooi vers dat van de Genestet:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Op de bergen van het Lijden</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Steile weg naar ’t heilig Land</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Steile weg naar hooger streven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Steile weg naar beter leven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Op die bergen van het Lijden</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Voerde mij Gods liefde hand.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Van hun toppen – ’t scheen wel nader</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Bij der starren heilge sfeer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">En de woning van den Vader –</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Op de wereld zag ik neer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Maar toch dacht ik aan den morgen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Aan een morgen van weleer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Toen ik lachend zonder zorgen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Blikte in Uw wereld Heer.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">En nu schrijf ik nog wat over voor mijn broer:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik heb lief want de Heer hoort mijne stem, mijne smeekingen; want Hij neigt Zijn oor naar mij<c type="kk">/</c> dies zal ik Hem al mijne dagen aanroepen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">De banden des doods hadden mij omvangen, en de angsten der hel hadden mij getroffen<c type="kk">/</c> ik vond benaauwdheid en droefenis<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik riep den naam des Heeren aan, zeggende: Och Heer bevrijd mijne ziel<c type="kp">_</c> De Heer is genadig en regtvaardig en onze God is ontfermende. De Heer bewaart de eenvoudigen; ik was uitgeteerd doch Hij verlost mij. Mijne ziel<c type="kk">/</c> keer weder tot Uwe rust want de Heer doet aan U wel. Want Gij o Heer hebt mijne ziel gered van den dood, mijne oogen van tranen<c type="kk">/</c> mijnen voet van aanstoot. Ik zal wandelen voor het aangezicht des Heeren, in de landen der levenden. Ik heb geloofd<c type="kk">/</c> daarom sprak ik; ik ben zeer bedrukt geweest. Ik zeide in mijn haasten: Alle menschen zijn leugenaars. Wat zal ik den Heer vergelden voor al Zijne weldaden aan mij bewezen? Ik zal den beker der verlossingen opnemen, en den naam des Heeren aanroepen. Mijne geloften zal ik den Heer betalen. Och Heer zekerlijk ben ik Uw knecht, een zoon Uwer dienstmaagd. Gij hebt mijne banden losgemaakt<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zal U offeren eene offerande van dankzegging en den naam des Heeren aan<c type="shy">-</c>roepen. Ik zal mijne geloften den Heer betalen<c type="kk">/</c> nu in de tegenwoordigheid van al Zijn volk; in de voorhoven van het huis des Heeren.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Uit de benaauwdheid heb ik den Heer aangeroepen<c type="kk">/</c> de Heer heeft mij verhoord<c type="kk">/</c> mij stellende in de ruimte<c type="kp">_</c> De Heer is bij mij, ik zal niet vreezen; wat zal een mensch mij doen? De Heer is bij mij onder degenen die mij helpen. Het is beter tot den Heer toe<c type="shy">-</c>vlugt te nemen dan op den mensch te vertrouwen.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">“Hij weet niet wat er geschieden zal.”<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Onze kortzichtigheid verlange niet meer te weten dan de Alwijze ons wilde bekend maken, en onze afhankelijkheid geve zich kalm over aan den Almachtige.– Dat is de dagtekst van heden.–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Toen ik een knaap was<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Toen ik een knaap was in ’t zorglooze leven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Gordde ik mij zelven en liep naar mijn lust</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Vrij in mijn wandlen mijn zoeken en streven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Vrij in mijn reizen mijn droomen mijn rust</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Straks ook voor mij is een ure gekomen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Ure van roeping van ernst van gena</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">Dat in mijn boezem de stem werd vernomen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Hebt gij mij lief? – en mijn ziele sprak “ja.”</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">Sinds mij dat uur uit mijn droomen kwam wekken</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.42" n="42">Leidt mij een ander, ook waar ik niet wil</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.43" n="43">Leert mij de handen steeds williger strekken</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.44" n="44">Volgen en dragen, ach, vrolijk en stil.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.45" n="45">Toch nu de Meerdre gebiedt in mijn leven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.46" n="46">Vinde ik trots banden en zielstrijd en smart</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.47" n="47">Wat ik eens vruchteloos zocht in mijn leven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.48" n="48">Meer rust en meer vrede voor ’t rusteloos hart.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.49" n="49">En nu een handdruk aan U beiden en aan de Hr en Jufvr. Roos en aan Willem<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en als gij anderen ziet die ik ken. En laat spoedig weer eens hooren hoe het gaat en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.50" n="50">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.51" n="51">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.52" n="52">Wat wilt Gij Heer dat ik doen zal<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> is eene vraag die wel dikwijls in het leven op de lippen komt, en wel dikwijls moeten wij vragen<c type="kk">/</c> Och, geef Uw zegen op dat wat ik doen zal. Moge dat gebed voor ons verhoord wor<c type="shy">-</c>den<c type="kk">/</c> Vader ik bid U niet dat Gij hen uit de wereld wegneemt maar dat Gij hen bewaart voor den booze.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Dat zij zoo.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.53" n="53">Het gebeurde dat wij ons alleen bevonden, mijne Moeder en ik<c type="kk">/</c> aan een geopend venster, van waar wij het uitzigt hadden op den tuin van het huis waarin wij ons begeven hadden, aan de haven van Ostia. Daar wachtten wij, verre van de volksmenigte, na de vermoeijenis eener lange reis, het oogenblik van den over<c type="shy">-</c>togt af. Wij waren alleen, te zamen sprekende met een onuit<c type="shy">-</c>sprekelijk genot; en terwijl wij het verleden vergaten en geheel in de toekomst ons verdiepten, bespraken wij hoe voor de heiligen dat eeuwige leven zijn zou wat geen oog gezien, geen oor heeft vernomen en dat in niemands hart is opgekomen. En op de vleugelen der Liefde gevoerd tot Hem die is wandelden wij in den geest naar die hemelstreken, vanwaar de sterren, de maan en de zon hun licht ons toezenden. En nog hooger stijgende in onze gedachten, in onze woorden, in de bewondering Uwer werken, o Heer, traden wij als buiten ons zelven, om de ongeschapen wijsheid te bereiken, die is wat zij geweest is, wat zij altijd zal zijn, of liever in welke nooit het geweest zijn is of het moeten zijn, maar het zijn alleen, omdat zij eeuwig is want het geweest zijn en het moeten zijn sluiten de eeuwigheid uit. En terwijl wij zoo spraken in de vlugt onzer gedachten naar dat leven, kwamen wij er een enkel oogenblik in den geest mede in aanraking, en wij zuchtten en lieten de eerste<c type="shy">-</c>lingen des geestes gevangen, en daalden weer af tot het ge<c type="shy">-</c>luid der stem, tot het woord dat begint en eindigt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.54" n="54">Wij spraken aldus: Als er eene ziel is, in wie de stem des vleesches tot stilzwijgen komt, die zich zelve het stilzwijgen oplegt, en zich zelven vergetende, den drempel van het binnenste overschrijdt; als de laatste stem in het stilzwijgen verloren gaat, nadat onze ziel zich verheven heeft tot den oorsprong aller dingen, en Hij alleen spreekt, niet door Zijne schepselen maar door zich zelven, als Hij tot ons spreekt, Hij alleen wien wij in alles beminnen; als Hij tot ons spreekt terwijl alles ons ontvlugt en terwijl alle beschouwing eener lagere orde ophoudt den beschouwer in zijne stille vreugde verrukt gevangen houdt en medesleept; als het eeuwige leven eindelijk gelijk is aan deze vlug<c type="shy">-</c>tige verrukking die ons nog zuchten doet; is dat niet de be<c type="shy">-</c>lofte van dit woord “Ga binnen in de vreugde Uws Heeren”? Zoo waren de gedachten van dit onderhoud.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.55" n="55"><hi rend="italics">Augustinus</hi><ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.56" n="56">zoo waar twee of drie vergaderd zijn in Mijnen naam daar ben Ik in het midden van hen.–<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.57" n="57">Daarjuist ontvang ik Pa’s brief. Goddank. God make ons broeders.–<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.58" n="58">Al ware het dat ik de talen der menschen en der Engelen sprak en de Liefde niet had, zoo ware ik een klinkend me<c type="shy">-</c>taal of luidende schel geworden. En al ware het dat ik de gave der profetie had en wist al de verborgenheden en al de weten<c type="shy">-</c>schap, en al ware het dat ik al het geloof had zoodat ik bergen verzette, en de Liefde niet had<c type="kk">/</c> zoo ware ik niets<c type="kp">_</c> En al ware het dat ik al mijne goederen tot onderhoud der armen uitdeelde; en al ware het dat ik mijn ligchaam overgaf, opdat ik ver<c type="shy">-</c>brand zoude worden, en had de Liefde niet<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zoude het mij geene nuttigheid geven<c type="kp">_</c> De liefde is lang moedig<c type="kk">/</c> zij is goedertieren; de Liefde is niet afgunstig; de Liefde handelt niet ligtvaardig, zij is niet opgeblazen. Zij han<c type="shy">-</c>delt niet ongeschikt, Zij zoekt zichzelve niet<c type="kk">/</c> Zij wordt niet verbitterd, Zij denkt geen kwaad. Zij verblijdt zich niet 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>in de ongeregtigheid, maar zij verblijdt zich in de waarheid; zij bedekt alle dingen, Zij gelooft alle dingen<c type="kk">/</c> zij hoopt alle dingen, zij verdraagt alle dingen. De Liefde vergaat nimmermeer, maar hetzij profetiën<c type="kk">/</c> zij zullen te niet gedaan worden; hetzij talen zij zullen ophouden; hetzij kennis<c type="kk">/</c> zij zal te niet gedaan worden. Want wij kennen ten deele en wij profeteeren ten deele. Doch wanneer het volmaakte zal gekomen zijn, dan zal hetgeen ten deele was te niet gedaan worden. Toen ik een kind was, sprak ik als een kind, overleide ik als een kind, maar wanneer ik een man geworden ben, zoo heb ik te niet gedaan hetgeen eens kinds was. Want wij zien nu door eenen spiegel in eene duistere rede, maar alsdan zullen wij zien aangezigt tot aangezigt, nu ken ik ten deele, maar alsdan zal ik kennen, gelijk ook ik gekend ben. Nu dan blijft geloof<c type="kk">/</c> hoop en Liefde, doch de meeste van deze is de Liefde.–<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.59" n="59"><hi rend="italics">Als droevig zijnde maar altijd blijde, als getuchtigd</hi> <hi rend="italics">maar niet gedood</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.60" n="60"><hi rend="italics">Als een dien zijne Moeder vertroost</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.61" n="61">Je vois d’ici une dame. je la vois marcher pensive dans un jardin peu étendu, et defleuri de bonne heure, mais abrité comme on en voit derrière nos falaises de France ou les dunes de la Hollande<c type="kp">_</c> Les arbustes exotiques sont déjà rentrés dans la serre. Les feuilles tombées dévoilent quelques statues qu’on regarde plus volon<c type="shy">-</c>tiers maintenant que manquent les fleurs. Luxe d’art qui con<c type="shy">-</c>traste un peu avec la très-simple toilette de la dame, modeste<c type="kk">/</c> grave, où la soie noire ou grise s’égaie à peine d’un simple ruban lilas. Parée de rien<c type="kk">/</c> on peut le dire<c type="kk">/</c> elle n’en est pas moins élégante. Elégante pour son mari et simple au profit des pauvres. Elle atteint le bout de l’allée, se retourne. Nous pouvons la voir. Mais ne l’ai-je pas vue déjà aux musées d’Amsterdam ou de La Haye. Elle me rappelle une dame de Philippe de Champagne qui m’était entrée dans le coeur, si candide, si honnête suffisamment intelligente, simple pourtant sans finesse pour se demêler des ruses de ce monde. Cette femme m’est restée trente ans, me revenant obstinément, m’inquiétant<c type="kk">/</c> me faisant dire: Mais comment se nommait-</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.62" n="62">elle? Que lui est-il arrivé<c type="kp">_</c> A-t-elle eu un peu de bonheur? Et comment s’est-elle tirée de la vie. Celle-ci me rappelle un autre portrait<c type="kk">/</c> un van Dyck, une pauvre femme<c type="kk">/</c> fort blanche<c type="kk">/</c> maladive. Le pâle satin de la peau d’incomparable finesse, </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.63" n="63">orne un corps souffrant qui mollit. Dans ses beaux yeux flotte une grande melancolie, celle de l’âge? des chagrins de coeur, du climat aussi peut-être. C’est le regard vague<c type="kk">/</c> lointain, d’une personne qui a eu habituellement sous les yeux le vaste Ocean du Nord, la grande mer grise<c type="kk">/</c> déserte<c type="kk">/</c> sauf le vol du goeland.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.64" n="64">Michelet<c type="kk">/</c> Les aspirations de l’automne.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.65" n="65">Haar man is bekend in de poorten, als Hij zit met de oudsten des lands.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Het hart Haars’ Heeren vertrouwt op Haar zoodat Hem geen goed zal ontbreken<c type="kp">_</c> Zij doet Hem goed en geen kwaad<c type="kk">/</c> al de dagen Haars levens. Zij staat op als het nog nacht is en geeft haar huis spijze, en Harer dienstmaagden haar bescheiden deel. Hare lamp gaat des nachts niet uit. Zij breidt Hare handpalmen uit tot den ellendige, en zij steekt Hare handen uit tot den nooddruf<c type="shy">-</c>tige<c type="kp">_</c> Zij vreest voor Haar huis niet vanwege de sneeuw; want Haar gansche huis is met dubbele kleederen gekleed. Sterkte en heerlijkheid zijn Hare kleeding; en zij lacht over den toekomenden dag – Zij doet Haren mond open met wijsheid; en op Hare tong is de leer der goeddadigheid. Zij beschouwt de gangen van Haar huis, en het brood der luiheid eet zij niet<c type="kp">_</c> Hare kinderen staan op en noemen Haar welgelukzalig; ook Haar man; en Hij prijst Haar zeggende<c type="kk">/</c> Vele dochters hebben deugdelijk gehandeld, maar Gij gaat die allen te boven. De bevalligheid is bedrog, en de schoonheid is ijdelheid maar eene vrouw die den Heer vreest zal geprezen worden. Geef Haar van de vrucht Harer handen, en laat Hare werken Haar prijzen in de poorten<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> Twee dingen heb ik van den Heer begeerd, onthoud ze mij niet, voor ik sterf: Doe ijdelheid en leugentaal verre van mij; geef mij armoede noch rijkdom; voed mij met het brood mijns bescheiden deels.–<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> Het is beter te zijn in het klaaghuis dan in het huis der maaltijden. Te treuren is beter dan te lagchen, want door de droefheid des aange<c type="shy">-</c>zigts wordt het hart verbeterd.–<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> Verbind Gij o Heer ons innig aan elkaar en laat de Liefde tot U dien band meer en meer versterken<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> en laat onze latere dagen zijn digter bij U en daarom beter dan deze<c type="kp">_</c> Eens aan den avond van mijn leven, breng ik van zorg en strijden moe<c type="kk">/</c> voor elken dag mij hier gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> U hooger<c type="kk">/</c> reiner loflied toe.<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> Dwing mij niet Heer dat ik U zoude verlaten, om van achter U weder te keeren. Uw volk zij mijn volk, en Uw God mijn God.–<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Isleworth, 13 October 1876</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dearest <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The boys will be going home tomorrow and then I’ll get my money. I asked <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs> to let me go and see you in these three days, my heart is so much with you. It now depends on you two, if you say, ‘you may come’, then Mr Jones will let me go. Besides wanting so much to sit at Theo’s bedside, I should also like so very much to talk to my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>, and if possible to go to Etten once more to see and speak to my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs> again. It would be but a short visit, I could stay with you one or two days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Last Monday I was in Richmond again and took as my text<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> ‘He hath sent me to preach the gospel to the poor’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> But he who wants to preach the gospel must first have it in his own heart, oh, that I might find it, for it is only the words spoken in singleness and from the abundance of the heart<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> that can bear fruit.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">One of these days, perhaps, I’ll go to London or Lewisham again.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I just gave <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>’s girls<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> a German lesson, and after the lesson I told them <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">Andersen</rs>’s story The snow queen.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">If you can, write and tell me by return of post if I may come. I was glad to have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s last letter. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I hope to visit <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s school one of these days. And then I hope to buy a new pair of shoes to prepare myself. The view from the window in your room is no doubt beautiful now, I know it from days past, you know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">We’re having a lot of rain here; it’s probably the same where you are.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’ll have two or three weeks around Christmas to go to Holland, should <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> be able to come as well we could perhaps travel together. And now we’re gradually heading towards winter again, make sure you’re completely better when it arrives. It is indeed wonderful that Christmas falls in the winter. Oh how I’m looking forward to it, old boy, to make my rounds here and there at Turnham Green when it’s cold.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> When I think of you like this, as of ‘one whom his Mother comforteth and who is worthy of being comforted by his Mother’,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> it is with envy. Do get well soon, in any case.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Yesterday I asked <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs> to let me go, but he didn’t want to give his consent and said at last, write to your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>, if she thinks it’s all right then so do I.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It is indeed a beautiful poem, that one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">De Génestet:</rs></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">On the lofty heights of suffering,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Steep the path to the Holy Land,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Steep the path one upward strives,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Steep the path to better lives.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">On these lofty heights of suffering,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Led by God’s own loving hand.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">From their peaks – it did seem nearer</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">To the starry, holy sphere,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And the dwelling of the Father –</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Down upon the world I peered.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">And yet I thought of that one morning,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Of a morning long ago,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">When I, laughing without caring,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Glimpsed, O Lord, Thy world below.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And now I’ll copy out something for my brother:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I love the Lord, because He hath heard my voice and my supplications. Because He hath inclined His ear unto me, therefore will I call upon Him as long as I live.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">The sorrows of death compassed me, and the pains of hell gat hold upon me: I found trouble and sorrow. Then called I upon the name of the Lord; O Lord, I beseech thee, deliver my soul. Gracious is the Lord, and righteous; yea, our Lord is merciful. The Lord preserveth the simple: I was brought low, and He helped me. Return unto thy rest, O my soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee. For Thou hast delivered my soul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling. I will walk before the Lord in the land of the living. I believed, therefore have I spoken: I was greatly afflicted: I said in my haste, all men are liars. What shall I render unto the Lord for all His benefits toward me? I will take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows unto the Lord. O Lord, truly I am Thy servant; a son of Thine handmaid: Thou hast loosed my bonds. I will offer to Thee the sacrifice of thanksgiving, and will call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all His people, in the courts of the Lord’s house.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">I called upon the Lord in distress: the Lord answered me, and set me in a large place. The Lord is on my side; I will not fear: what can man do unto me? The Lord taketh my part with them that help me. It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in man.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">‘For he knoweth not that which shall be.’<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> May our shortsightedness ask to know no more than the Omniscient wanted to make known to us, and may our dependence slowly yield to the Almighty. That is the lesson for the day.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">When I was a lad<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">When I was a lad, my life carefree as ever,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">I girt myself up, did whatever I chose,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Free to go wand’ring, to seek, to endeavour,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Free in my travels, my dreams, my repose.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Even for me, though, the hour was nearing</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">Of calling, of mercy, of seriousness,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">When in my bosom the voice I’d been hearing</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">Enquired ‘Do you love me?’ – my soul answered ‘Yes’.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">Since that hour of waking my dreams are no longer,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Another now leads me, at times ’gainst my will,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Teaches my hands to reach eagerly further,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.45" n="45">To follow and carry, oh, happy and still.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.46" n="46">Yet now that life’s governed by the Supreme Being,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.47" n="47">Despite pain and fetters, my soul torn apart –</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.48" n="48">I find what in life I’d once vainly been seeking:</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.49" n="49">More rest and more peace for my uneasy heart.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.50" n="50">And now a handshake to you both and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">Mr and Mrs Roos</rs> and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/><hi rend="super"> </hi>and to anyone else you might see whom I know. And let me know soon how you are and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.51" n="51">Your most loving brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.52" n="52">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.53" n="53">Lord, what wilt Thou have me to do?<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> is a question that often springs to one’s lips, and often we must ask, Oh, bless that which I shall do. May that prayer of ours be heard: Father, I pray not that Thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that Thou shouldest keep them from the evil.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> So be it.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.54" n="54">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.55" n="55">It happened that we found ourselves alone, my mother and I, at an open window, where we had a view of the garden of the house to which we had betaken ourselves at the harbour of Ostia. There, far from the crowd, we were awaiting the time of the crossing after the fatigue of a long journey. We were alone, conversing with inexpressible pleasure; and, forgetting the past and dwelling completely on the future, we talked about what that eternal life of the saints would be like, which no eye hath seen, nor ear heard, nor any heart conceived. And, transported on the wings of Love to Him who is, we wandered in spirit to those heavenly spheres, whence the stars, the moon and the sun send us their light. And rising ever higher in our thoughts, in our words, in the admiration of Thy works, O Lord, it was as though we left our bodies, in order to attain uncreated wisdom, which is what it was, what it ever will be, or rather, in which there is no ‘having been’ or ‘what must still be’ but only ‘being’, because it is eternal, because ‘having been’ and ‘what must still be’ exclude eternity. And as we were speaking thus, in the flight of our thoughts towards that life, we touched it for an instant in spirit, and we groaned and allowed to be caught the first-fruits of the spirit, and descended again to the sound of voices, to words that begin and end.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.56" n="56">Thus we spoke: If there is a soul in which the voice of the flesh falls silent, which imposes silence on itself, and, forgetting itself, oversteps its innermost bounds; if the last voice is lost in silence, after our soul has raised itself to the origin of all things, and He alone speaks, not through His creatures but through himself, if He speaks to us, He alone whom we hold dear above all else; if He speaks to us while everything drains out of us and while all beholding of a lower order stops, holding the viewer in thrall, enraptured, in his quiet joy and carrying him away; if eternal life is ultimately the same as this brief bliss that makes us go on groaning; is that not the promise held by the words ‘Enter thou into the joy of Thy Lord’? Such were our thoughts as we spoke.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.57" n="57"><hi rend="italics">Augustine</hi><ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.58" n="58">For where two or three are gathered together in My name, there am I in the midst of them.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.59" n="59">I just received <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s letter. Thank God. May God make us brothers.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.60" n="60">Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not Charity, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal. And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not Charity, I am nothing. And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing. Charity suffereth long, and is kind; Charity envieth not; Charity vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up, doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not her own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil; rejoiceth not 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth; beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things. Charity never faileth: but whether there be prophecies, they shall fail; whether there be tongues, they shall cease; whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away. For we know in part, and we prophesy in part. But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part shall be done away. When I was a child, I spake as a child, I thought as a child: but when I became a man, I put away childish things. For now we see through a glass, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know even as also I am known. And now abideth faith, hope, Charity; but the greatest of these is Charity.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.61" n="61"><hi rend="italics">As sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing; as chastened, but not killed.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.62" n="62"><hi rend="italics">As one whom his mother comforteth.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.63" n="63">From here I see a lady, I see her walking, pensive, in a garden that is not very big and has lost its flowers quite early, but is sheltered, like the ones one sees behind our cliffs in France or the dunes of Holland. The exotic shrubs have already gone back into the greenhouse. The fallen leaves reveal some statues which one is all the more eager to look at now that the flowers have gone. A sumptuousness of art, which contrasts slightly with the very simple attire of the lady — modest, grave — the black or grey silk of which is barely brightened by a plain lilac ribbon. Unadorned, this we can say, she is no less elegant. Elegant for her husband and simple for the benefit of the poor. She reaches the end of the avenue, turns. We can see her. But have I not seen her before in the museums of Amsterdam or The Hague? She reminds me of a lady by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_937">Philippe de Champaigne</rs>, who had found her way into my heart, so ingenuous, so honest, sufficiently intelligent, yet simple, without the subtlety to extricate herself from the snares of this world. This woman has remained with me for thirty years, obstinately returning to me, worrying me, making me say, But what was she called? What became of her? Did she have a little happiness? And how did she manage to get through life? She reminds me of another portrait, a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1008">Van Dyck</rs>, a poor woman, very pale, unhealthy. The pale satin of the incomparably delicate skin clothes a sickly body, which is beginning to slacken. A great melancholy fills her lovely eyes, the melancholy of old age? Of heartbreaks, of the climate too, perhaps. It is the vague, distant look of someone who has lived within sight of the vast North Sea, the great grey sea, deserted but for the flight of the seagull.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.64" n="64"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>, Les aspirations de l’automne.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.65" n="65">Her husband is known in the gates, when he sitteth among the elders of the land.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> The heart of her husband doth safely trust in her, so that he shall have no need of spoil. She will do him good and not evil all the days of her life. She riseth while it is yet night, and giveth meat to her household, and a portion to her maidens. Her candle goeth not out by night. She stretcheth out her hand to the poor; yea, she reacheth forth her hands to the needy. She is not afraid of the snow for her household: for all her household are clothed with scarlet. Strength and honour are her clothing; and she shall rejoice in time to come. She openeth her mouth with wisdom; and in her tongue is the law of kindness. She looketh well to the ways of her household, and eateth not the bread of idleness. Her children arise up, and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth her, saying: Many daughters have done virtuously, but thou excellest them all. Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain: but a woman that feareth the Lord, she shall be praised. Give her of the fruit of her hands; and let her own works praise her in the gates.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> Two things have I required of the Lord; deny me them not before I die: Remove far from me vanity and lies: give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with food convenient for me.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> It is better to be in the house of mourning than in the house of feasting. Sorrow is better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> O Lord, join us intimately to one another and let our Love for Thee make that bond ever stronger,<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> and let our latter days be closer to Thee and therefore better than these. When once life’s evening overcomes me, worn down by ills and strife always, for every day Thou hast allowed me, I’ll bring Thee higher, purer praise.<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> Intreat me not to leave Thee, Lord, or to return from following after Thee. Thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Isleworth 13 October 1876’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The phrase ‘Daarjuist ontvang ik Pa’s brief. Goddank. God make ons broeders’ (I just received Pa’s letter. Thank God. May God make us brothers) <ref target="#l-180">(ll. 180-181)</ref> indicates that the sheet on which these words were written (which begins with the quotation from Augustine (<ref target="#l-141">ll. 141</ref> ff.)) was once part of a letter. The relief expressed by these words points to the time when Theo was ill and Vincent tended to pepper his letters with edifying quotations, which is why we assume that the sheet was written in October or November 1877 (<ref target="let092.xml#n-2">see letter 92, n. 2</ref>). Moreover, Van Gogh used the expression ‘Thank God’ a number of times in the same context during this period (<ref target="let093.xml">see letters 93</ref> and <ref target="let096.xml">96</ref>; cf. also <ref target="#n-20">n. 20</ref> below).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The sheet could not have been part of <ref target="let092.xml">letter 92</ref>, because in that letter Vincent said that he had just heard – for the first time – that Theo was ill. In <ref target="let093.xml">letter 93</ref> he wrote in the body of the letter <ref target="#l-94">(ll. 94-98)</ref> that he had received good news from home, and it would therefore not make sense to repeat this, as indeed happens in <ref target="#l-180">ll. 180-181</ref>. Finally, when <ref target="let095.xml">letter 95</ref> was written, the most difficult period of Theo’s illness was clearly past. We therefore think that the sheet in question belongs to the present letter.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s illness <ref target="let092.xml">(92)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On Monday evenings Van Gogh attended the prayer meetings at the Wesleyan Methodist Church in Richmond. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let092.xml">letter 92</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  Luke 4:18.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh combines ‘eenvoudigheid des harten’ (singleness of heart; Acts 2:46, Eph. 6:5 and Col. 3:22) with ‘overvloed des harten’ (abundance of the heart; Matt. 12:34 and Luke 6:45).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Slade-Jones</rs> occasionally sent Van Gogh to London and Lewisham on errands, such as collecting money (probably from the parents of the boys at his boarding school). The <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_396 bio.xml#_394">Gladwell family</rs> happened to live in Lewisham.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Slade-Jones</rs>’s daughters.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">H.C. Andersen</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_99">De sneeuwkoningin</ref>’, Andersen 1872, pp. 44-81, also published as ‘The snow queen’ in Andersen 1861, pp. 150-184. In this fairy tale, splinters of glass in people’s hearts and eyes prevent them from seeing anything but ugliness or evil. The boy Kay falls under the spell of the snow queen: he is abducted, and his heart becomes a lump of ice. His friend Gerda goes in search of him, and is strengthened in this endeavour by prayer. The hot tears of love that flow at their reunion thaw the lump of ice and melt the glass, the message being that ‘if you don’t become like children, you will never set eyes on the kingdom of God’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was permitted to work on behalf of the Congregational Church of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Reverend Slade-Jones</rs> in Turnham Green. On 19 November, he was ‘formally accepted as a co-worker’. See exhib. cat. London<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1992, p. 67 and Bailey 1990, p. 94.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Cf. Isa. 66:13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Based on the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_100">Op de bergen</ref>’ (On the lofty heights) by<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615"> P.A. de Génestet</rs> (beginning and end of the second part of the poem):</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">To the lofty heights of suffering,</p>

<p rend="indent">– Steep the path to the Holy Land –</p>

<p rend="indent">On the lofty heights of suffering,</p>

<p rend="indent">I was led there by Love’s hand.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>And the final stanza reads thus:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">And I thought of that one morning,</p>

<p rend="indent">Of that morning long ago,</p>

<p rend="indent">When I laughing, without caring,</p>

<p rend="indent">From lofty Alps looked down below.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">(Op de bergen van het Lijden,</p>

<p rend="indent">– Steile weg naar ’t heilig Land –</p>

<p rend="indent">Op de bergen van het Lijden</p>

<p rend="indent">Voerde mij der Liefde hand.’</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">En ik dacht weer aan dien morgen,</p>

<p rend="indent">Aan dien morgen van weleer,</p>

<p rend="indent">Toen ik lachend, zonder zorgen,</p>

<p rend="indent">Blikte hoog van de Alpen neer.)</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>Van Gogh’s version (or the version his father had once sent him – <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let104.xml">see letter 104</ref>) has been Christianized. It is however possible that Vincent was following yet another version; indeed, the rhyming lines</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">Steep the path one upward strives</p>

<p rend="indent">steep the path to better lives</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">(Steile weg naar hooger streven</p>

<p rend="indent">Steile weg naar beter leven)</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>which do not occur in the 1869 edition, seem to suggest this possibility. See De Génestet 1869, vol. 2, pp. 115-117.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 116:1-19. Van Gogh evidently thought it suitable, in the light of Theo’s illness, to skip verse 15: ‘Kostelijk is in de oogen des Heeren de dood zijner gunstgenooten’ (Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 118:5-8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
  Eccl. 8:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>A ‘lesson for the day’ is an edifying text printed on calenders and in booklets for the pious to reflect upon.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Based on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">P.A. de Génestet</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_101">Toen ik een knaap was</ref>’ (When I was a lad). See De Génestet<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1869, vol. 2, pp. 13-14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_802">Willem Valkis</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Acts 9:6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>
  John 17:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Taken from Augustine, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_102"><hi rend="italics">Belijdenissen</hi></ref> (Confessions), book 9, chapter 10 (conversation with his mother about the kingdom of heaven). No nineteenth-century Dutch edition has been traced, so it is not known which text Van Gogh transcribed. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let104.xml">letter 104</ref> of 28 February 1877, Van Gogh also quotes a line from the <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_102"><hi rend="italics">Confessions</hi></ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 18:20. We have placed this biblical passage outside the quotation marks because it does not occur in the passage quoted from Augustine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Like the exclamation ‘Goddank’ (Thank God) (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arrangement</hi>), this prayer for brotherly fellowship is often uttered by Vincent during this period; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let087.xml">see letters 87</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let092.xml">92</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let111.xml">111</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
  1 Cor. 13:1-13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 6:9-10 (in reverse order).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>Cf. Isa. 66:13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Taken from the chapter ‘Les aspirations de l’automne’ in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> (part 5, chapter 5). See <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, pp. 387-396; see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let014.xml">letter 14</ref>. Van Gogh introduced a few small changes.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 31:23.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 31:11-31. Van Gogh skipped several verses.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 30:7-8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>Cf. Eccl. 7:2-3. Van Gogh left out the second half of verse 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>A prayer written and often recited in the family circle by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let113.xml">see letter 113</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 180:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>Cf. Ruth 1:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    