<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Isleworth, between Monday, 23 and on or about Wednesday, 25 October 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let095"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b93 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>095</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>78</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>094</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-10-23">between Monday, 23 and on or about Wednesday, 25 October 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Isleworth</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0093" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0093" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000097_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Zoo dankbaar was ik voor Uw briefje en voor het schrijven van Moe,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> dus wachten wij tot Kersmis en dan geve God ons het elkander wederzien in vrede.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">“Mijn ziekzijn is niet kwaad”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Neen, want Sorrow is better than laughter.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Neen, ziek zijn gesteund door Gods arm,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en in die dagen van ziek zijn andere denkbeelden en nieuwe voornemens krijgen, die niet in ons konden opkomen toen wij niet ziek waren, en in die dagen helderder geloof en vaster vertrouwen krijgen, dat is niet kwaad.─ Wij aanbidden, zwijgen stil.─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Het leven in de wereld moet worden een der wereld geven wat der wereld is, terwijl de Godsdienst<c type="kk">/</c> het zoeken te doen van Gods wil de hoofdzaak moet worden.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Godsdienst ─ Gods wil doen, een Christen zijn, wat is dat? Laat ons daarnaar zoeken en God spare ons het leven, en de droefheid naar God<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> zal niet zonder vruchten blijven<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Werkt onzichtbaar, maar met kracht.─<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">“Dit is het verbond, dat Ik na die dagen met hen maken zal, spreekt de Heer: Ik zal Mijne wet in hun binnenste geven, en zal die in hun hart schrijven; en Ik zal hun tot eenen God zijn, en zij zullen Mij tot een volk zijn.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En zij zullen niet meer, een iegelijk zijnen naaste, en een iegelijk zijnen broeder, leeren, zeggende: Kent den Heer, want zij zullen Mij allen kennen van hunnen kleinste af tot hunnen grootste toe<c type="kk">/</c> spreekt de Heer: want Ik zal hunne ongeregtigheid vergeven, en hunner zonden niet meer gedenken. Zoo zegt de Heer, die de zon ten licht geeft des daags<c type="kk">/</c> de ordeningen der maan en der sterren ten licht des nachts, die de zee klieft, dat hare golven bruisen, Heer der heirscharen is Zijn naam”.─<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het leven in de wereld moet worden een der wereld geven wat der wereld is? Ja, maar dat leven in de wereld wordt “getuchtigd, maar niet gedood”,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> o, wat kunnen er schoone rijke dagen zijn in alle tijdperken van het leven, als de liefde tot Christus ons dringt.─<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Wat kan Elliott<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> die beschrijven.─ Het leven in de wereld wordt getuch<c type="shy">-</c>tigd maar niet gedood, ga er in terug als een kind.─ ’t Is een schoon woord “<hi rend="italics">wees oprecht als</hi> <hi rend="italics">de duiven</hi> en voorzichtig als de slangen”.─<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ziet alle dingen zijn nieuw geworden.─<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dat hoorde ik Ds Bersier<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> zeggen toen Hij stond voor een tijd van lijden en moeijelijkheden waarin men zegt: “Al deze dingen zijn tegen ons”.─<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">“Toutes choses sont devenues nouvelles”<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> zeide Hij met ontroering als zag Hij door alles heen.─ Het is een mooi woord<c type="kk">/</c> Niets behaagt mij dan in Jezus Christus, en in Hem behagen mij alle dingen<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> “though even in mirth the heart be sad”.─<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">“Mijn ziek zijn is niet kwaad”, neen, want man’s extremity is Gods opportunity.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Als wij zwak zijn dan zijn wij krachtig.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Het ziek zijn heiligt het gezond zijn en leert gezond zijn.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vader wij bidden U dat Gij ons niet uit de wereld wegneemt maar dat Gij ons bewaart voor den booze.─<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Wordt toch maar gaauw beter, kerel, o ik verlang zoo naar kersmis.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Hierbij den laatsten brief van Anna, zij zal nog wel dikwijls aan Welwyn denken als zij er eenmaal van daan is, het is er alles zoo mooi.─</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Gisteren was ik in Mr Jones’ kerk om te helpen om alles klaar te maken voor dezen avond. Een dominé uit Leicester zal dan eene lezing geven over de Her<c type="shy">-</c>vorming en die verduidelijken door een tooverlantaarn met voorstellingen uit dien tijd. Ik zag reeds enkele van de platen, zij zijn in den trant van Holbein<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/> Gij weet dat veel schilders en teekenaars hier in dien trant werken.─ Er was eene zeer mooie plaat van Luthers huwelijk.─<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Verleden Maandag was er in die kerk eene “tea-meeting”<c type="kk">/</c> het was een jaar geleden sedert de kerk geopend was.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Er werden zeker wel 250 menschen daar onthaald en daarna spraken Mr. Jones en enkele andere predikanten tot s’avonds laat toe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar jongen, nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> wie zou zijn gedachten ook maar eenigzins bij elkaar kunnen houden indien het gevoel van <hi rend="italics">pligt</hi> de dingen niet aaneenschakelde. Wie zou eenigen ernst kunnen behouden zonder het kinderlijk geloof:<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> wij zijn reizigers, vreemdelingen;─ vergeet wat achter is<c type="kk">/</c> strek u uit naar hetgeen voor is!─<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> ’t is ook goed te gelooven dat daar een Engel achter ieder onzer staat<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is goed te voelen in ons hart den roep<c type="kk">/</c> Abba Vader!<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Het is hier mooi tegenwoordig, vooral in de straten s’avonds, als het min of meer mist en de lantaarns worden aangestoken, en ook in dat park waarover ik U reeds schreef,<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> ik zag daar de zon ondergaan een paar dagen geleden achter die iepenboomen waarvan de bladeren nu de kleur van brons hebben. Over het gras lag die waas waarover Anna schrijft<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> en er loopt eene beek door dat park waarin men de zwanen ziet zwemmen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">De accaciaboomen op de speelplaats hebben reeds veel van hunne bladeren verloren, men ziet ze door het raam voor mijn lessenaar, soms teekenen zij zich donker tegen de lucht af, soms ziet men de zon daarachter rood in den mist opkomen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Wat zal het spoedig winter zijn, ’t is toch gelukkig kersmis in den winter is<c type="kk">/</c> daarom is mij den winter liever dan eenig anderen tijd van het jaar<c type="kk">/</c> kersmis en oudejaar is zelfs meer dan den herfst<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Wat zal het heerlijk zijn om dien Theems af te varen en de zee over, en dan die vriendelijke hollandsche duinen en het torentje dat men reeds van zoo heel uit de verte ziet.─ Wat zien wij toch weinig van elkaar jongen en wat zien wij weinig van onze ouders<c type="kk">/</c> en toch<c type="kk">/</c> zoo sterk is het gevoel van onzen oorsprong en van elkander dat het hart zich soms opheft en het oog blikt naar God en smeekt<c type="kk">/</c> Laat mij niet al te ver dwalen van Hen, niet <hi rend="italics">al</hi> te lang o Heer!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Heeft niet de mensch een strijd op aarde?<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> Toen Gij ziek waart zult Gij dat wel gevoeld hebben. Geen overwinning zonder strijd, geen strijd zonder lijden.─</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Daar moet veel strijds gestreden zijn</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Daar moet veel leeds geleden zijn</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">En veel gebeds gebeden zijn</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">En dan zal ’t einde zalig zijn.─<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Laat mij niet al te ver dwalen van Hen! van Uw volk o Heer. Gij die Hun God zijt<c type="kk">/</c> wees ook mijn God<c type="kk">/</c> dan zijn wij vereenigd in U, vorm mijn hart naar het Hunne opdat van daar uitga een leven als het Hunne. En in Uwe handen bevelen wij ons hart<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> al trachten wij ook naar het waken en bidden en strijden.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> Als de Heer het huis niet bouwt dan arbeiden de bouwlieden te vergeefs<c type="kk">/</c> als de Heer de stad niet be<c type="shy">-</c>waakt dan waken de wachters te vergeefs.─<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> à Dieu jongen<c type="kk">/</c> heb het zoo goed mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> groet hen bij Roos en als Gij andere bekenden ziet en geloof mij, na een handdruk in gedachten</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Geef Oom Jan<ptr target="#note-t-35"/> een hand voor mij.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I was so grateful for your short letter and for what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> wrote,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> so we’ll wait until Christmas, and then may God let us see one another again in peace.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">‘My illness is not a bad thing’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> No, for Sorrow is better than laughter.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> No, being ill and supported by God’s arm,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and acquiring new ideas and resolutions during the days of one’s illness, which couldn’t occur to us when we weren’t ill, and acquiring clearer faith and firmer trust during those days, that’s not a bad thing. We worship and are silent.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Living in the world must become a matter of giving to the world that which is of the world, while Religion, striving to do God’s will, must become the main concern.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Religion – doing God’s will, being a Christian – what is that? Let us seek it, and may God spare our lives, and godly sorrow<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> shall not be fruitless. Its work is wrought invisibly, yet powerfully.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">‘This shall be the covenant that I will make with them; After those days, saith the Lord, I will put My law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts; and will be their God, and they shall be My people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And they shall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: for they shall all know Me, from the least of them unto the greatest of them, saith the Lord: for I will forgive their iniquity, and I will remember their sin no more. Thus saith the Lord, which giveth the sun for a light by day, and the ordinances of the moon and of the stars for a light by night, which divideth the sea when the waves thereof roar; The Lord of hosts is His name.’<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Must living in the world become a matter of giving to the world that which is of the world? Yes, but that living in the world means being ‘chastened, but not killed’,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> oh, there may be beautiful, rich days in all phases of one’s life, if the love of Christ constrains us.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> How well <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> can describe them. Life in the world is chastened but not killed, go back into it like a child. These are beautiful words: ‘<hi rend="italics">be ye therefore harmless as doves </hi>and wise as serpents’.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Behold, all things are become new.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I heard the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_266">Rev. Bersier</rs><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> say that when he was faced with a period of suffering and difficulties in which one says: ‘All these things are against us’.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">‘All things are become new’,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> he said with emotion, as though he saw through everything. These are beautiful words: ‘Nothing pleaseth me but in Jesus Christ, and in Him all things please me’,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> ‘though even in mirth the heart be sad’.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">‘My illness is not a bad thing’, no, for man’s extremity is God’s opportunity.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> When we are weak, we are strong.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Being ill sanctifies being well and teaches one to be well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Father, we pray that Thou dost not take us out of the world, but that Thou shouldest keep us from the evil.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"> Just get well soon, old chap, oh, how I long for Christmas.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Herewith <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>’s last letter, she’ll probably think of Welwyn often once she has left it, everything is so beautiful there. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Yesterday I was in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>’s church to help get everything ready for this evening. A vicar from Leicester will be giving a lecture on the Reformation and illustrating it with a magic lantern showing scenes from that period. I’ve already seen some of the plates, they’re in the manner of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1090">Holbein</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> You know that many painters and draughtsmen here work in his manner. There was a very beautiful plate of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_494">Luther</rs>’s marriage.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Last Monday there was a ‘tea-meeting’ at that church, it had been one year since the church was opened.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> There were at least 250 people at the reception, and afterwards Mr Jones and several other preachers spoke until late in the evening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But again, old boy, who would be able to collect his thoughts at all if the feeling of <hi rend="italics">duty</hi> did not join everything together? Who would be able to maintain some earnestness without childlike faith:<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> we are travellers, strangers – forget those things which are behind, and reach forth unto those things which are before!<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> It is also good to believe that an angel stands behind each one of us, it is good to feel in our hearts the cry, Abba, Father!<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">It’s lovely here now, especially in the streets in the evening, when it’s a bit foggy and the street-lamps are lit, and also in that park I wrote to you about,<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> I saw the sun setting there a couple of days ago, behind the elm trees whose leaves are now the colour of bronze. That haze which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> writes about<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> lay over the grass, and a brook runs through that park in which one sees the swans swimming. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The acacias in the playground have already lost many of their leaves, one sees them through the window in front of my reading-desk, sometimes they stand out dark against the sky, sometimes one sees the sun behind them, rising up red in the mist.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">It will surely be winter soon, how fortunate that Christmas is in the winter, that’s why I like winter better than any other season, Christmas and New Year’s Eve are even better than the autumn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">How wonderful it will be to sail down the Thames and across the sea, and then those friendly Dutch dunes and that small tower that one already sees from a great distance. How little we see of each other, old boy, and how little we see of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs>, and yet the feeling of our origins and of one another is so strong that the heart is at times uplifted and our eyes look to God, beseeching, Let me not stray too far from them, not for <hi rend="italics">too</hi> long, O Lord!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Must man not struggle here on earth?<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> You must have felt so when you were ill. No victory without a battle, no battle without suffering.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Many battles must be fought</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Much of life with suffering fraught</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Many prayers must needs be said</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">For a blissful end to lie ahead.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Let me not stray too far from them, from Thy people, O Lord. Thou which art their God, be Thou also mine God, then we will be united in Thee, mould my heart after theirs, that a life may proceed from it as from theirs. And into Thy hands we commend our heart,<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> though we endeavour to watch and pray and fight.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> Except the Lord build the house, they labour in vain that build it: except the Lord keep the city, the watchmen waketh but in vain.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> Adieu, old boy, I wish you the very best, give my regards to those at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’ and to any other acquaintances you might see, and believe me, after a handshake in thought,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Shake <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs>’s<ptr target="#note-t-35"/> hand for me.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Unlike the preceding letter, the present letter is not addressed to both Theo and Mrs van Gogh, which means that Vincent must have known that their mother was no longer with Theo. In fact, she left The Hague on Monday, 23 October (FR b2786), so the letter could not have been written before that day. During this period Van Gogh generally wrote every week. In the following letter, which was written on Friday, 3 November, Van Gogh wrote: ‘It really is time you heard something from me’ <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>. Since the interval between that letter and this one was longer than usual, the present letter was most likely written not long after 23 October. We have therefore dated it to between Monday, 23 and on or about Wednesday, 25 October 1876.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s illness <ref target="let092.xml">(92)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>These letters must have been sent when <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> was still in The Hague nursing Theo back to health.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Evidently a quotation from Theo’s letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  Eccl. 7:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Cf. Rhy. ps. 12:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 21:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Cor. 7:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 43:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Jer. 31:33-35.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 6:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 5:14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">George Eliot</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 10:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 5:17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh quoted <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_266">Bersier</rs>’s text in a previous letter: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let040.xml#n-7">see letter 40, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 42:36.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 5:17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Cf. hymn 62:2, ‘Och! mogt all’ mijn levensdagen, / Wat hem behaagt ook mij behagen’ (Oh, may all my livelong days, / What pleaseth Him please me always).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Cf. Eccl. 7:4, ‘But the heart of fools is in the house of mirth’, and Prov. 14:13, ‘Even in laughter the heart is sorrowful; and the end of that mirth is heaviness’. Cf. also Eccl. 2:2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>Saying derived from: ‘We knew that man’s extremity is God’s opportunity’, to be found in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1789">John Flavel</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A faithful and succinct narrative of some late and wonderful sea-deliverances</hi>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The works of John Flavel</hi>. The Banner of Truth Trust. 2nd ed. Fakenham, Norfolk 1982, vol. 4, p. 507.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Cor. 13:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
  John 17:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1090">Hans Holbein the Younger</rs>. No information about this presentation with the magic lantern has been found. The minister in question was perhaps Mr Hicks, who is mentioned a number of times in the Minutes of Resolutions of the Sunday school at Turnham Green (London, Metropolitan Archives, ref. N/C/35/6/1).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>Various depictions of the marriage of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_494">Martin Luther</rs> are known. Van Gogh could have seen the reproduction of a work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_130">Pierre Antoine Labouchère</rs>, who painted historical subjects in the manner of<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1090"> Holbein the Younger</rs>. A painting by Labouchère of 1856 was reproduced as an engraving by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1576">Jean Denis Nargeot</rs> titled <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The marriage</hi>, which shows the wedding ceremony in Amdorff’s house at Wittemberg on 13 June 1525. The print was published by Dan &amp; Son, Lithographers to the Queen. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1780">Ill. 1780</rs>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Illustrations of the life of Martin Luther: engraved in line after original paintings by P.A. Labouchère with letterpress descriptions by I.H. Merle d’Aubigné</hi>. London 1862.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>The church opened its doors on 21 September 1875, so it was not exactly one year old.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 128:4. ‘Leer mij, o Heer! dien pligt betrachten, / Door kinderlijk geloof geleid’ (Teach me, O Lord, to fulfil that duty, / Led by childlike faith). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>
  Phil. 3:14 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Phil. 3:13).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>Cf. Mark 14:36, Rom. 8:15 and Gal. 4:6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>Syon Park in Isleworth.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> must have described her impressions to Vincent in much the same way as she wrote about them to Theo in a letter of 4 October 1876: ‘I’m sitting here writing in front of my open window and have a view of a magnificent sunset and a large old cedar, which dates from before the days of the poet Young. It’s beautiful here, the leaves on all the trees are beginning to change, and such a grey, fog-like shadow lies over everything’ (FR b2783).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>
  Job 7:1 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> ‘Is there not an appointed time to man upon earth?’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>In 1618, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_556">Dirk Rafaelsz. Camphuysen</rs> wrote:</p>
  <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>‘Daer moet veel strijdts gestreden sijn:</p>

<p>Daer moet veel leets geleden sijn:</p>

<p>En veel gebedts gebeden sijn:</p>

<p>En Christelijcke zeden sijn:</p>

<p>Een nauwen wech betreden sijn;</p>

<p>Soo lang wij hier beneden sijn:</p>

<p>Soo sal ’t hier nae in vreden sijn.’</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>(Many battles must be fought</p>

<p>Much of life with suffering fraught </p>

<p>Many prayers one must needs pray</p>

<p>And Christian morals should hold sway</p>

<p>A straight and narrow way be tread</p>

<p>As long as life on earth is led</p>

<p>Hereafter peace doth lie ahead.) </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>Quoted after H.G. van den Doel, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ik hoor trompetten klinken. De dichters Jacobus Revius en Dirk Camphuysen</hi>. Leiden 1969, p. 23. The verses were included in printed editions of Camphuysen’s poetry, including <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Stichtelijcke rijmen</hi> (Edifying verses), but Van Gogh was likely referring to a later version – whether or not adapted – or else quoting from memory. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_559">Stichtelijcke rijmen</ref></hi>. Rotterdam 1655, part 1, p. 412. It is not clear whether the variant last line, based on hymn 20:9 – ‘Het eind zal zeker zalig zijn’ (The end will certainly be blest) – was Van Gogh’s own invention. Various versions did exist, as evidenced by such books as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Uitgelezen Stichtelijke Rijmen van D.R. Camphuysen</hi>. Ed. J. van Vloten. Schiedam 1861, p. 86. Cf. Pabst 1988, p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>
  Luke 23:46 has ‘in uwe handen beveel ik mijnen geest’ (into thy hands I commend my spirit).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="33" xml:id="note-t-33">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 27:2 and Hymn 50:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="34" xml:id="note-t-34">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 127:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="35" xml:id="note-t-35">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan (Johannes) van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    