<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Isleworth, Friday, 17 and Saturday, 18 November 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let098"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b95 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>098</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>81</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>098</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-12-17">Friday, 17 and Saturday, 18 November 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Isleworth</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0095" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0095" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000099_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Isleworth 17 November 1876</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Beste Vader en Moeder,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Goddank het met Theo goed blijft vooruit gaan en bravo hij reeds met Pa in de sneeuw naar het Heike<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> wandelde, wat was ik graag met U beiden meegegaan.─ Het is reeds laat en morgen ochtend vroeg moet ik voor Mr Jones naar Londen en Lewisham, waar ik bij Gladwell hoop aan te gaan, het zal eerst s’avonds laat zijn dat ik t’huis kom.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Waar krijgen Mr Jones en anderen hun inkomen van daan? Ja, daar heb ik wel dikwijls reeds aan gedacht<c type="kp">_</c>─ Het woord dat men hier dikwijls hoort is: God zorgt voor hen die voor Hem werken<c type="kp">_</c>─ Ik ben zeer verlangend hier over nog met U te spreken en te overleggen. En dan vraagt U nog of ik nog les geef aan de jongens, tot s’middags 1 uur ben ik daar dagelijks mede bezig, en dan na 1 uur moet ik er meestal voor Mr Jones op uit of soms ook les geven aan Mr. Jones’ kinderen of aan een paar jongens in stad. En dan s’avonds en zoo tusschen de droppeltjes door<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> in mijn preeken boek schrijven.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">verl. Zondag was ik reeds vroeg te Turnham Green om les te geven in de Zondagschool<c type="kk">/</c> het was een echten Engelschen regendag, s’morgens preekte Mr Jones over de Samaritaansche vrouw<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en daarop weer zondagschool; ook door de week moet ik daar voor werken<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn heel wat kinderen maar het is een toer ze geregeld bij elkaar te krijgen. Mr Jones en zijn jongen<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en ik gingen 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>s’middags thee drinken bij den koster<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> een schoenmaker die in een van de buiten<c type="shy">-</c>wijken woont. Uit het raam daar was het een gezigt dat veel aan Holland deed denken ─ eene vlakte met gras begroeid die door den plasregen bijna in een moeras veranderd was, daaromheen de rijen roode huisjes met hunne tuinen en de lichten van de lantaarns die werden aange<c type="shy">-</c>stoken.─ s’Avonds preekte Mr Jones over Naäman de Syriër,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> zeer mooi<c type="kk">/</c> en daarna de wandeling naar huis. Verl. Donderdag gaf Mr. Jones mij zijne beurt over en nam ik “ik wenschte wel van God dat<c type="kk">/</c> en bijna en geheelijk<c type="kk">/</c> niet alleen gij, maar allen die mij heden hooren<c type="kk">/</c> zijn mochten als ik, uitge<c type="shy">-</c>nomen deze banden.”─<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Aanst. Zondag moet ik s’avonds naar Petersham naar een Methodiste kerk;<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Petersham is een dorp aan den Theems<c type="kk">/</c> een 20 minuten voorbij Richmond; ik weet nog niet wat ik nemen zal, de verloren zoon<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> of Ps. 42:1.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">s’Morgens en s’middags de zondagschool te Turnham Green.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En zoo gaan de weken voorbij en naderen wij den winter en het vriendelijke kersfeest. Morgen moet ik in twee uithoeken van Londen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> in Whitechapel ─ dat heel arme gedeelte waar U in Dickens wel van heeft gelezen<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en dan met een bootje de Theems 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>over en van daar naar Lewisham.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">De kinderen van Mr Jones zijn weer beter maar nu hebben 3 van de jongens de mazelen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Deze week had ik met een van de jongens een tocht te doen voor Mr Jones naar Acton Green<c type="kk">/</c> dat is die grasvlakte waarop het raam van den koster uitziet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Het was verbazend modderig daar maar het was een mooi gezicht toen het donker begon te worden en de mist opsteeg en men het licht van een klein kerkje in het midden van de vlakte zag.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> En links van ons was de spoor op een vrij hoogen dijk en er kwam juist een trein aan en dat was een mooi gezicht<c type="kk">/</c> den rooden gloed van de locomotief en de rei lichten in de wagons in de schemering. Rechts van ons liepen eenige paarden te grazen in een land met een heg van meidoorn en bramen er om heen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Terwijl ik U zoo zit te schrijven op mijn kamertje en het zoo heel heel stil is en ik rond zie naar Uw portretten en de prenten aan den muur<c type="kk">/</c> Christus Consolator<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> en Le vendredi saint<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en de Vrouwen die naar het graf gaan<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> en Le vieux Huguenot<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en l’Enfant prodigue van Ary Scheffer<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> en het scheepje op de stormachtige zee<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> en eene ets<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>een herfstlandschap, gezicht op de hei<c type="kk">/</c> die ik van Harry Gladwell kreeg op mijn verjaardag<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en als ik aan U allen denk en dan aan allen hier en aan Turnham Green en Richmond en Petersham &amp;c. dan voel ik “Blijf Heer, het gebed van mijne Moeder ver<c type="shy">-</c>hooren dat Zij voor mij bad toen ik het Ouderlijk huis verliet: Vader ik bid U niet dat Gij hen uit de wereld wegneemt maar dat Gij hen bewaart voor den booze,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en<c type="kk">/</c> Heer och of Gij mij toch wildet maken, niet alleen bijna maar ook geheelijk<c type="kk">/</c> als het ware mijns Vaders broeder<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> een Christen en een christen<c type="shy">-</c>werkman<c type="kp">_</c> Voleindig Uw werk in mij dat Gij begonnen zijt.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Ja maak Gij mij, langzaam maar zeker, stap voor stap, en bijna en ook geheelijk mijn’s Vaders broeder.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En verbind Gij o Heer ons innig aan elkaar en laat de liefde tot U dien band meer en meer versterken.”─<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En nu goeden nacht aan U beiden en aan Theo<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> en Willemien en Cor, weer verlang ik naar Uw brief.─ Goeden nacht<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet er morgen vroeg op uit, een hand<c type="shy">-</c>druk in gedachten van</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Uw zoo innig liefh.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">van uit het andere eindje van L.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Dag allen! van morgen 4 uur ging ik er op uit<c type="kk">/</c> nu is het 2 uur<c type="kp">_</c> Daar juist kwam ik door de oude koolvelden<c type="kk">/</c> nu naar Lewisham<c type="kk">/</c> een mensch zegt zoo wel eens<c type="kk">/</c> hoe kom ik er nog<c type="kp">_</c> à Dieu<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Isleworth, 17 November 1876</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Father and Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Thank God Theo continues to get better, and bully for him, already walking in the snow to Het Heike<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, how I’d have liked to walk along with you both. It’s already late, and early tomorrow morning I have to go to London and Lewisham for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>, where I hope to drop by and see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Gladwell</rs>. It will be late at night before I’m home again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Where do <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs> and the others get their income from? Yes, I’ve thought about that many times. Here one often hears it said that God takes care of those who work for Him. I dearly long to talk to you about this and to confer. You then ask, too, whether I still give lessons to the boys: I do so every day until 1 o’clock, and then after 1 o’clock I usually have to go out for Mr Jones, or sometimes also teach Mr Jones’s children or a couple of boys in town. And then in the evening and in my spare moments I write in my sermon book.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Last Sunday I arrived at Turnham Green early to teach at Sunday school; it was a real, English, rainy day. In the morning <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs> delivered a sermon on the woman of Samaria,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and afterwards there was Sunday school. I also have to do this during the week; there are quite a few children, but it’s a job to round them all up regularly. In the afternoon Mr Jones and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1664">his son</rs><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and I went 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> and had tea with the sexton,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> a shoemaker who lives in one of the suburbs. There was a view from the window there that reminded me very much of Holland – a flat, grass-covered area, which the torrential rains had turned almost into a morass, surrounded by rows of little red houses with their gardens and the lights of the street-lamps that were being lit. In the evening Mr Jones delivered a sermon on Naaman the Syrian,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> very beautiful, and afterwards the walk home. Last Thursday Mr Jones let me take his turn, and I took as my text ‘I would to God, that not only thou, but all that hear me this day, were both almost, and altogether such as I am, except these bonds’.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Next Sunday evening I have to go to Petersham to a Methodist church;<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Petersham is a village on the Thames, about 20 minutes beyond Richmond; I don’t know yet what I’ll talk about, the prodigal son<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> or Ps. 42:1.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Mornings and evenings Sunday school at Turnham Green.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And so the weeks pass and we approach winter, and the congenial Christmas festivities. Tomorrow I have to be in two remote parts of London, in Whitechapel – that extremely poor area which you’ll have read about in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_61">Dickens</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – and then cross the Thames in a boat 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> and from there to Lewisham.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>’s children are better again, but now 3 of the boys have the measles.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">This week I had to go on a journey for Mr Jones with one of the boys to Acton Green, which is that grassy area that the sexton’s window looks out on.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">It was surprisingly muddy there, but it was a beautiful sight when it began to grow dark and the mist rose and one saw the light of a small church in the middle of the green.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And to our left were railway tracks on a rather high embankment, and at that moment a train came, and that was a beautiful sight, the red glow of the locomotive and the rows of lights inside the carriages in the twilight. To our right a few horses were grazing in a meadow surrounded by a hedge of hawthorn and blackberry bushes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">As I sit writing to you in my room and it’s so very, very quiet and I look around at your portraits and the prints on the wall, Christus Consolator<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> and Good Friday<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and the Women at the sepulchre<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and The old Huguenot<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and The prodigal son by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> and the little boat on a stormy sea<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> and one etching, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> an autumn landscape, view of the heath, which I got from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry Gladwell</rs> on my birthday,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and when I think of all of you and then of all those here and of Turnham Green and Richmond and Petersham &amp;c., then I feel ‘Stay, Lord, and hear the prayer my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> said for me when I left my parent’s house: Father, I pray not that Thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that Thou shouldest keep them from the evil,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and, Lord, oh if Thou would only make me, not only almost but altogether, as it were, my Father’s brother,<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> a Christian and a Christian worker. Complete Thy work in me which Thou hast begun.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Yea, make me, slowly but surely, step by step, and almost and altogether, my Father’s brother.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And O Lord, join us intimately to one another and let our love for Thee make that bond ever stronger.’<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And now good-night to you both and to Theo<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>, I’m longing again for a letter from you. Good-night, I have to get up early tomorrow, a handshake in thought from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Your most loving and affectionate</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">From the other end of L.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> I bid you all good-day! I left this morning at 4 o’clock, now it’s 2. I just came through the old cabbage fields, now on to Lewisham. A man sometimes says, how shall I manage it? Adieu.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Isleworth 17 November 1876’. Van Gogh writes that on Saturday (18 November) he will go to London, and that is where the postscript was written (<ref target="#l-120">ll. 120-125</ref>, in pencil).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mr van Gogh sent this letter on to Theo: ‘Herewith Vincent’s last letter; I’ll get it back from you at some point’ (FR b2797, 24 November 1876). Probably Theo kept the letter, thereby ensuring its survival.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Het Heike (St. Willibrorddorp) is c. 3 km south-west of Etten.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Saying which means ‘to make the most of opportune moments’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  John 4:1-42.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Slade-Jones</rs> had one son, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1664">Edward C</rs>., who was 10 years old at this time.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This sexton in Acton Green has not been found in the parish records.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  2 Kings 5:20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  Acts 26:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The Methodist chapel at Petersham, a small village one mile south of Richmond. Van Gogh made a small drawing of this church in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let099.xml">letter 99</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Luke 15:11-24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>‘As the hart panteth after the water brooks, so panteth my soul after thee, O God’ (Ps. 42:1).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The poor district of Whitechapel in the East End of London occurs in such works as <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_107"><hi rend="italics">Oliver Twist</hi></ref> (chapter 19) and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_108"><hi rend="italics">The Pickwick papers</hi></ref> (chapters 20, 22 and 43).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must be referring to the parish school (of St Mary’s, Acton), which became the parish hall of St Alban’s but has since been demolished. The little building lay some 250 metres from the railway line.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1771"><hi rend="italics">Christus Consolator</hi></rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let085.xml#n-7">see letter 85, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Paul Delaroche</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1730"><hi rend="italics">Good Friday</hi></rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let041.xml#n-7">see letter 41, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>This is probably a reference to a reproduction after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The entombment of Christ</hi> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Holy Women at the sepulchre</hi>), 1845 (Manchester, Manchester City Art Galleries). Goupil published a photograph of an engraving after the painting (Paris, BNF, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1781">Ill. 1781</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Albert Anker</rs>,<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1720"> <hi rend="italics">The old Huguenot</hi></rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let036.xml#n-3">see letter 36, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1779"><hi rend="italics">The prodigal son</hi></rs>; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let090.xml#n-84">letter 90, n. 84.</ref> Goupil published a reproduction after this work in the series <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Oeuvre de Ary Scheffer reproduit en photographie per Bingham accompagné d’une notice sur la vie et les ouvrages de Ary Scheffer</hi>. By L. Vitet of the Académie Française. Paris 1860, no. 427; it was sold separately in the series ‘Galerie Photographique’ (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1782">Ill. 1782</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>There is a chance that this refers to the etching <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Bateau pêcheur et barques</hi> (Fisherman’s boat and small fishing vessels)<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_77">Léon Gaucherel</rs> after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs>. Since Van Gogh’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> evidently required no more than this brief description, it could refer to the same ‘little boat’ that he had sent his father after a visit to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_359">Durand-Ruel</rs>’s gallery. Unlike the other ‘little boats’ by Dupré sold at this gallery, this etching displays water that is choppy (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Galerie Durand-Ruel</hi> 1873, no. 225). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1763">Ill. 1763</rs>. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let066.xml#n-7">letter 66, n. 7</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let073.xml#n-5">letter 73, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>An etching after a work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_942">Théophile-Narcisse Chauvel</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let074.xml#n-12">see letter 74, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
  John 17:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Besides referring to the hoped-for clerical office, it is possible that this was an expression familiar in the family. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote on 7 March 1877 to Theo: ‘you know that you have a father who also wants to be a brother to you’ (FR b2510). The passage is, moreover, an adaptation of Acts 26:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>See <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let109.xml#n-15">letter 109, n. 15</ref>, and cf. hymn 255:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>The preceding texts were well known and oft-repeated in the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Van Gogh family</rs>, and were therefore frequently quoted in Vincent’s correspondence; for the last prayer (‘join us... stronger’), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let113.xml">see letter 113</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>Evidently Vincent was under the impression that Theo was still at home in Etten, which might explain why <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> sent the letter on to Theo. Cf. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Additional details</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>London.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    