<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Dordrecht, Wednesday, 7 and Thursday, 8 February 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let102"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b102 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>102</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>85</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>102</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-02-07">Wednesday, 7 and Thursday, 8 February 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0102" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0102" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000109_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Adam Bede kost f<c type="kp">_</c> 2.60<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> dus ontvangt Gij hierbij terug f<c type="kp">_</c> 1.40.– Nu hoop ik maar zij er ’t huis genot van zullen hebben, en dat zal wel.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dank voor Uw brief waar ik zoo blij mede was, als wij elkaar nu weer eens ontmoeten zullen wij elkaar maar eens ferm in de oogen kijken<c type="kk">/</c> het is mij soms zulk eene heerlijke gedachte wij weer denzelfden grond onder de voeten hebben en dezelfde taal spreken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Verl. week hebben wij hier eene overstrooming gehad. s’Avonds tusschen 12 en 1 van den winkel komende wandelde ik de Groote kerk<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> nog eens om, het stormde toen in de iepenboomen die daarom heen staan en de maan scheen door de regenwolken en weerkaatste in de grachten die reeds boordevol waren. s’Nachs 3 uur waren wij bij Rijken, een grutter waar ik in huis lig,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> allen in de weer om de dingen uit den winkel naar boven te brengen want het water kwam een el hoog in huis. Er was niet weinig leven en rumoer, en in alle benedenkamers waren de menschen bezig om naar boven te brengen wat zij konden en een bootje kwam de straat opvaren. s’Morgens toen het wat licht begon te worden zag men eene groep mannen aan het eind van het straatje die den een na den ander naar hunne pakhuizen waadden<c type="kp">_</c> Er is veel schade, ook in de plaats waar de Heer Braat zijn papier &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> bewaart is water gekomen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> niet door de overstrooming maar door de groote drukking van onder uit den grond.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">De Heer Braat zegt het hem een bankje van het grootste soort<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> kost. Wij zijn anderhalven dag bezig geweest om alles over te brengen naar een bovenhuis<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo eens een dag met de handen werken is wel eene aangename afwisseling, ’t was maar jammer het om die reden was<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij hadt dien avond de zon moeten zien ondergaan<c type="kk">/</c> de straten schenen van goud, zooals Cuyp<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> dat wel schilderde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Verlang naar mijn koffer die onderweg is,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ook om weer wat prenten op mijne kamer te hebben. Heb er nu hangen Christus consolator die ik van U heb<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en twee Engelsche houtsneden<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. de Emmausgangers:<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> En zij dwongen Hem<c type="kk">/</c> zeggende “blijf bij ons” want de zon was onderge<c type="shy">-</c>gaan en de avond was gevallen<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – en een ander: “Zij die in duisternis zaten en schaduwe des doods<c type="kk">/</c> hebben een groot licht gezien;<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> des avonds vernacht wel het geween, maar des morgens is er gejuich”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Er kan een tijd zijn in het leven waarin men als het ware van alles vermoeid is en een gevoel heeft als of al wat men doet verkeerd is, en daar is ook wel wat van aan – zou dit een gevoel zijn dat men ontwijken en verdringen moet, of wel zou het zijn “de droefheid naar God” die men niet moet vreezen maar waarop men moet letten of zij misschien ons ten goede zou kunnen dringen – zou het misschien zijn “de droefheid naar God die werkt eene onberouwe<c type="shy">-</c>lijke keuze”.–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> En in zulk een tijd, waarin men zich vermoeid gevoelt van zich zelven<c type="kk">/</c> mag men met aandacht<c type="kk">/</c> hoop en liefde denken aan het woord “Komt allen tot Mij, gij die vermoeid en belast zijt en Ik zal u ruste geven. Neemt mijn juk op en leert van Mij dat ik zachtmoedig ben en nederig van hart, en gij zult rust vinden voor uwe ziele<c type="kp">_</c> Want Mijn juk is zacht en mijn last is ligt.–<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Zoo iemand achter 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Mij wil komen die verloochene zich zelven en neme zijn kruis dagelijks op en volge Mij”.–<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> In zulk een tijd mag men wel denken aan “zoo een mensch niet weder geboren wordt<c type="kk">/</c> hij kan het koninkrijk Gods niet zien”.–<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Als wij ons laten leeren door de ervaring des levens en leiden door de droefheid naar God dan kan er nog eene nieuwe levenskracht ontspringen uit het vermoeide hart. Als wij maar eens goed vermoeid zijn dan zullen wij vaster gelooven in God en zullen in Christus, door Zijn woord, vinden een Vriend en een Trooster. En dan kunnen er dagen komen waarin wij zullen voelen “Gij doet mijne ongeregtigheden van mij zoover het Oosten is van het Westen.”<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> waarin wij iets zullen voelen van “den ijver voor Uw huis heeft mij verslonden”,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en “onze God is een verteerend vuur”<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> – waarin wij weder zullen weten wat het zegt vurig te zijn van geest.–<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> “Niet altoos zal de hope kwijnen”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Laat ons maar niet vergeten “de dingen die wij in den beginne gehoord hebben”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">In den beginne was het woord en het woord was bij God en het woord was God.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Alzoo lief heeft God de wereld gehad dat Hij zijn eengeboren Zoon gegeven heeft opdat een iegelijk die in Hem gelooft niet verderve, maar het eeuwige leven hebbe.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Niets zal ons scheiden van de Liefde van Christus<c type="kk">/</c> noch tegenwoordige noch toekomende dingen.–<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Juich Aarde juich tot God omhoog</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dat dankbre tranen uit uw oog</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Voor Hem d’Algoedheid vloeien</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Viert vrolijk dezen blijden dag</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Den schoonsten die de wereld zag</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Aan hare kimmen gloeien.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nog juicht ons toe die zaalge nacht</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Waarin ’t gestarnt met nieuwe pracht</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En ’t Englen heir met nieuwe vreugd</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Zich over Jezus komst verheugt.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik weet aan Wien ik mij vertrouwe</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Al wisselen ook dag en nacht</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik ken de rots waarop ik bouwe</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Hij feilt niet die mijn heil verwacht</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Eens aan den avond van mijn leven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Breng ik van zorg en strijden moe</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">voor elken dag mij hier gegeven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">U hooger reiner loflied toe.–<ptr target="#note-t-29"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">’t Hijgend hert der jagt ontkomen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Schreeuwt niet sterker naar ’t genot</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Van de frissche waterstroomen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Dan mijn ziel verlangt naar God</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ja mijn ziel dorst naar den Heer!</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">God des levens ach wanneer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Zal ik naad’ren voor Uw oogen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">In Uw huis Uw naam verhoogen.<ptr target="#note-t-30"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">O mijn ziel wat buigt ge u neder</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Waarom zijt ge in mij ontrust</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Voed het oud vertrouwen weder</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Zoek in s’Hoogsten lof Uw lust</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">Menigwerf heeft Hij Uw druk</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Doen verandren in geluk</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">Hoop op Hem sla ’t oog naar boven</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.42" n="42">Want ik zal mijn God nog loven.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.43" n="43">Niet altijd zal de hope kwijnen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-32"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.44" n="44">Verl. Zondag morgen was ik in de Fransche kerk hier,<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> die is zeer ernstig en deftig en heeft iets zeer aantrekkelijks, de tekst was: Houdt wat gij hebt, opdat niemand uwe kroon neme.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> Het slot van de preek was “Zoo ik U vergete, o Jeru<c type="shy">-</c>zalem, zoo vergete mijne regterhand zich zelven”.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.45" n="45">Na de kerk deed ik eene mooie wandeling alleen op een dijk langs de molens,<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> het was eene schitterende lucht boven de weilanden die weerkaatste in de sloten. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.46" n="46">Er zijn in andere landen wel eigenaardige dingen. b.v. de Fransche kust die ik zag bij Dieppe – de falaises met het groene gras er op<ptr target="#note-t-37"/> – de zee en lucht – de haven met de oude booten zooals Daubigny ze schildert met bruine netten en zeilen<c type="kk">/</c> de kleine huisjes waaronder een paar restauraties met witte gordijntjes en groene mastentakken in het raam – de karren met witte paarden met blaauwe groote halsters en roode kwasten opgetuigd – de voerlui met hunne blaauwe kielen<c type="kk">/</c> de vischers met hunne baarden en geöliede kleeren en de Fransche vrouwen met bleek gezigt<c type="kk">/</c> donkere dikwijls wat diepliggende oogen<c type="kk">/</c> zwarte japon en witte muts en b.v. de Londensche straten in den regen met de lantaarns en een nacht daar doorgebragt op den stoep van een oud grijs kerkje gelijk het mij dezen zomer na dien togt van Ramsgate<ptr target="#note-t-38"/> overkwam – er zijn in andere landen ook wel eigenaardige dingen – maar toen ik verl. Zondag alleen wandelde op dien dijk<c type="kk">/</c> toen dacht ik zoo hoe goed die hollanschen grond was, en ik voelde iets van “heden is het in mijn hart om een verbond te maken met mijnen God”<ptr target="#note-t-39"/> – want de herinnering aan vroeger kwam bij mij op<c type="kk">/</c> o.a<c type="kp">_</c> hoe dikwijls hebben wij zoo in de laatste dagen van Februarij met Pa gewandeld naar Rijsbergen<ptr target="#note-t-40"/> enz. en de leeuwrik ge<c type="shy">-</c>hoord boven de zwarte akkers met het jonge groene koren<c type="kk">/</c> de tintelende blaauwe lucht met de witte wolken er boven – en dan de steenweg met de beukenboomen<ptr target="#note-t-41"/> – o Jerusalem Jerusalem!<ptr target="#note-t-42"/> of liever o Zundert o Zundert! wie weet of wij van den zomer nog niet eens zamen aan de zee wandelen. Wij moeten toch maar goede vrienden blijven Theo, en maar gelooven in God en vertrouwen met een oud vertrouwen<ptr target="#note-t-43"/> op Hem die kan doen boven bidden en boven denken<ptr target="#note-t-44"/> – wie zal zeggen hoe hoog gena kan stijgen.<ptr target="#note-t-45"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.47" n="47">Van harte gelukgewenscht met den dag van heden, het is reeds half 2 en dus reeds 8 Februarij. God spare onzen Vader nog lang voor ons “en Hij verbinde ons innig aan elkaar, en moge de liefde tot Hem dien band meer en meer versterken”.–<ptr target="#note-t-46"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.48" n="48">Pa schreef Hij al spreeuwen had gezien, weet Gij nog hoe die te Zundert op de kerk konden zitten,<ptr target="#note-t-47"/> hier heb ik er nog geen opgemerkt – maar wel veel kraaijen, s’morgens op de groote kerk<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu wordt het weer haast lente en komen ook de leeuwrikken weer<c type="kp">_</c> “Hij vernieuwt het gelaat des aardrijks”<ptr target="#note-t-48"/> en daar staat: Ziet Ik maak alle dingen nieuw<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-49"/> en zooals Hij het gelaat des aardrijks vernieuwt zoo kan Hij ook s’menschen ziel en hart en geest vernieuwen en versterken – de natuur van ieder waar zoon heeft wel iets van dien van den zoon uit de gelijkenis “die dood was en weer levend werd”.–<ptr target="#note-t-50"/> Laat ons het woord Droevig maar altijd blijde<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-51"/> onbekend maar nogthans bekend<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-52"/> maar niet vergeten en het woord weemoed maar met twee woorden schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">wee</hi> en <hi rend="italics">moed</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-53"/> en gelooven in God die op Zijn tijd ook de eenzaamheid, die wij soms zelfs in het gewoel zoo kunnen voelen, van om onze knieën kan doen wijken<c type="kk">/</c> en van Wien Jozef zeide “Hij heeft mij doen vergeten mijns Vaders huis en al mijn verdriet”<ptr target="#note-t-54"/> – en toch vergat Jozef zijn vader niet – dat weet Gij wel maar Gij weet wel wat hij met zijn woord bedoelde. Houd U maar goed<c type="kk">/</c> groet allen bij Roos en vooral ook de Hr. Tersteeg en Mevrouw en ontvang in gedachten een handdruk en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.49" n="49">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.50" n="50">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.51" n="51">Zeg aan den Hr Tersteeg hij het niet kwalijk moet nemen de teekenvoorbeelden zoo lang weg blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is voor de H.B. school<c type="kk">/</c> er worden er reeds 30 gehouden – maar ook wil men er nog voor de B. Avondschool uitzoeken en moet ze om die reden nog een dag of 8 houden.<ptr target="#note-t-55"/> Zoodra mogelijk ontvangt gij ze terug.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.52" n="52">Jongen stuur mij nog eens die bladzijde uit Michelet,<ptr target="#note-t-56"/> die Gij mij vroeger stuurdet is in mijn lessenaar<ptr target="#note-t-57"/> in mijn koffer en ik heb het weer noodig – schrijf maar weer spoedig.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Adam Bede costs 2.60 guilders,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> so herewith you get back 1.40 guilders. Now I only hope that it will give them some pleasure at home, but no doubt it will.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Thanks for your letter, which made me so happy. When next we meet we’ll look each other straight in the eye. I sometimes think how wonderful it is that we have the same ground beneath our feet and that we speak the same language.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Last week we were flooded here. Coming from the shop between 12 and 1 at night, I took another turn around the Grote Kerk.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> The wind was blowing hard in the elm trees surrounding it, and the moon shone through the rain-clouds and reflected in the canals that were already filled to the brim. At 3 o’clock in the morning we were all rushing around at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_633 bio.xml#_634">Rijken</rs>’s, the grocer in whose house I’m lodging,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> bringing things upstairs from the shop, because the water was an ell high in the house. There was quite a bit of commotion, and in all the downstairs rooms people were busy bringing upstairs what they could, and a small boat came down the street. In the morning, when it was beginning to grow light, one saw a group of men at the end of the street, wading one after another to their warehouses. There’s a lot of damage, the water has also got into the place where <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_306">Mr Braat</rs> keeps his paper &amp;c.,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> not because of the flood but because of the great pressure coming from under the ground.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_306">Mr Braat</rs> says it will cost him a banknote of the largest kind.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> It took us a day and a half to carry everything to an upstairs flat. Working with your hands like that for a day is a welcome change, though it was a pity it was for that reason. You should have seen the sun go down that evening, the streets shone of gold, the way <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_964">Cuyp</rs><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> used to paint them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Longing to have my trunk, which is on the way,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> one reason being to have some prints hanging in my room again. I now have Christus Consolator, which you gave me,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and two English woodcuts, namely the Supper at Emmaus:<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> ‘But they constrained Him, saying, Abide with us: for it is toward evening, and the day is far spent’,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and another: ‘They that sat in darkness and the shadow of death have seen a great light’;<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> ‘Weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning’.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> There can come a time in life when one is tired of everything, as it were, and has the feeling as if everything that one does is wrong, and there’s certainly some truth in that – is this a feeling that one ought to avoid and repress, or it is rather ‘the godly sorrow’ that one must not fear but carefully consider whether it can perhaps compel us to do good – is it perhaps ‘the godly sorrow that worketh a choice not to be repented of’?<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> And at such times, in which one feels tired of oneself, one may think with heedfulness, hope and love of the words ‘Come unto Me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you, and learn of Me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your soul. For My yoke is easy, and my burden is light’.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> ‘If any man will come after Me, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> let him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow Me.’<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> At such times one may well reflect upon: ‘Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God’.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> If we let ourselves be taught by the experience of life and led by godly sorrow, then new vitality may spring from the tired heart. If we are once good and tired, then we shall believe more firmly in God, and shall find in Christ, through His word, a Friend and Comforter. And then there may be times when we feel ‘thou removest my iniquities from me as far as the east is from the west’,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> when we feel something of ‘the zeal for Thine house hath eaten me up’<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and ‘our God is a consuming fire’<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> – when we shall again know what it is to be fervent in spirit.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Hope will not always fade away.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Let us not forget ‘the things which we have heard from the beginning’.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> God so loved the world, that He gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have everlasting life.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Nothing shall separate us from the Love of Christ, neither things present, nor things to come.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Rejoice on earth, praise God on high,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Let thankful tears stream from your eye</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">For Him from whom all blessings flow.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">This joyful day then celebrate,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The greatest the world has seen to date,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">On its horizon all aglow.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Still welcoming us, that blessed night,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">In which the stars with beauteous light</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">And heavenly hosts with one glad voice</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">In Jesus’ coming do rejoice.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I know in Whom my faith is founded,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Though day and night change constantly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I know the rock on which I’m grounded,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">My Saviour waits, unfailingly.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">When once life’s evening overcomes me,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Worn down by ills and strife always,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">For every day Thou hast allowed me,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I’ll bring Thee higher, purer praise.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">The panting hart, the hunt escapèd,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Cries no harder for the pleasure</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Of fresh flowing streams of water</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Than my soul doth long for God.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Yea, my soul thirsts for the Lord,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">God of life, oh when shall I</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Approach Thy sight, and drawing nigh,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Give Thee praise in Thine own house.<ptr target="#note-t-30"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Why art thou cast down, my soul,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Disquieted in me, oh why?</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Foster again the faith of old,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Rejoice in praising Him most high.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">Oft hath he taken your distress</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">And turned it into happiness.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">Hope in Him, eyes heavenward raised,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">For to my God I still give praise.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Hope will not always fade forever.<ptr target="#note-t-32"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Last Sunday morning I was in the French church here,<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> which is very serious and dignified and has something very appealing. The text was Hold that fast which thou hast, that no man take thy crown.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> The end of the sermon was ‘If I forget thee, O Jerusalem, let my right hand forget her cunning’.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.45" n="45">After church I took a lovely walk alone on a dyke running past the mills,<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> there was a brilliant sky above the meadows that was reflected in the ditches. <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> There are curious things in other countries, such as the French coast which I saw at Dieppe – the chalk cliffs with green grass on top<ptr target="#note-t-37"/> – the sea and sky – the harbour with old boats like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs> paints them, with brown nets and sails, the small houses including a couple of restaurants with little white curtains and green pine branches in the window – the carts with white horses with big blue halters decorated with red tassels – the drivers with their blue smocks, the fishermen with their beards and oiled clothing and the French women with pale faces, dark, often somewhat deep-set eyes, black dress and white cap, and such as the streets of London in the rain with the street-lamps, and a night spent there on the steps of an old, small grey church, as happened to me this summer after that journey from Ramsgate<ptr target="#note-t-38"/> – there are certainly curious things in other countries, too – but last Sunday when I was walking alone on that dyke, I thought how good that Dutch soil was, and I felt something akin to ‘today it is in mine heart to make a covenant with my God’<ptr target="#note-t-39"/> – because memories of times past came back to me, including how often we walked with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> to Rijsbergen<ptr target="#note-t-40"/> and so on in the last days of February and heard the lark above the black fields with young green wheat, the shimmering blue sky with white clouds above – and then the paved road with the beech trees<ptr target="#note-t-41"/> – O Jerusalem Jerusalem!<ptr target="#note-t-42"/> or rather O Zundert O Zundert! Who knows but that we may go walking at the seaside together this summer? We really must remain good friends, Theo, and simply believe in God and trust with that faith of old<ptr target="#note-t-43"/> in Him who is able to do above all that we ask or think<ptr target="#note-t-44"/> – who can say to what heights grace can ascend?<ptr target="#note-t-45"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.46" n="46">Hearty congratulations for today, it’s already half past 1 and therefore already 8 February. May God spare our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs> for us for a long time yet ‘and may He join us intimately to one another and let our love of Him make that bond ever stronger’.<ptr target="#note-t-46"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.47" n="47"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> wrote that he had already seen starlings, do you remember how they used to sit on the church at Zundert?<ptr target="#note-t-47"/> I haven’t seen any here yet – though there are a lot of crows on the Grote Kerk in the mornings. Now it’s almost spring again and the larks will return again. ‘He reneweth the face of the earth’<ptr target="#note-t-48"/> and it is written, Behold, I make all things new,<ptr target="#note-t-49"/> and just as He renews the face of the earth, so can He renew and strengthen the human soul and heart and mind – the nature of every true son somewhat resembles that of the son in the parable who ‘was dead, and is alive again’.<ptr target="#note-t-50"/> Let us not forget the words ‘sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing’,<ptr target="#note-t-51"/> ‘unknown, and yet well known’,<ptr target="#note-t-52"/> and write the word woe-spiritedness as two words, <hi rend="italics">woe</hi> and <hi rend="italics">spiritedness</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-53"/> and believe in God who in His own good time can make the loneliness disappear which we sometimes feel so much even in the bustle, of whom Joseph said ‘He hath made me forget my Father’s house and all my sorrow’<ptr target="#note-t-54"/> – and yet Joseph did not forget his father – you know that of course, but you also know what he meant by those words. Do keep well, give my regards to everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’, and especially to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787 bio.xml#_788">Mr Tersteeg and his wife</rs>, and accept in thought a handshake, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.48" n="48">Your most loving brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.49" n="49">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.50" n="50">Tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> that he shouldn’t be upset about the drawing examples being away for so long, it’s for the high school, 30 have already been chosen – but they still want to select some for the secondary school, which is why they have to keep them for another week or so.<ptr target="#note-t-55"/> You’ll get them back as soon as possible.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.51" n="51">Old boy, send me that page from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> again,<ptr target="#note-t-56"/> the one you sent me earlier is in my reading-desk<ptr target="#note-t-57"/> in my trunk and I need it again – do write again soon.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Part of this letter was written on 8 February 1877: ‘congratulations for today, it’s already half past 1 and therefore already 8 February’ <ref target="#l-108">(ll. 108-109)</ref>. The fact that this remark occurs not at the beginning but much later on in the letter suggests that Van Gogh had begun writing on the evening of 7 February.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mr van Gogh’s birthday on 8 February <ref target="let101.xml">(101)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The available translation of <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_20"><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adam Bede</hi></ref> cost 2.90 guilders; presumably Van Gogh received the bookshop discount of 10%. The translation was to be had both as a separate publication (‘3e dr. Sneek, J.F. van Drunten (Rott., D. Bolle.) 1871’) and as vol. 2 of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">George Eliot</rs>’s romantic works: ‘Uit het Engelsch. Nieuwe uitgaaf met inleiding en onder toezicht van <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1670">P. Bruyn</rs> (From the English. New edition with introduction and editorial supervision by P. Bruijn), Sneek, Van Drunten &amp; Bleeker (Rott. D. Bolle) 1870-1873’. Because the <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_570"><hi rend="italics">Novellen</hi></ref> mentioned in the previous letter appeared as vol. 1 in the series (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let101.xml#n-3">see letter 101, n. 3</ref>), this last edition must have been the birthday present in question.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The present was well chosen: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> found <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_20"><hi rend="italics">Adam Bede</hi></ref> a ‘wonderful thing to have’ (FR b2507, 19 February 1877).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The Grote Kerk (also called the Onze Lieve Vrouwekerk) facing Grote Kerksplein. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_633">Pieter Rijken</rs> and his wife, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_634">Maria Aelmans</rs>, kept a lodging-house at Tolbrugstraat (Waterzijde) A 312; on the ground floor they ran a greengrocer’s shop.  Van Gogh was their lodger from January to May 1877. They sometimes had as many as four or five lodgers at a time. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, pp. 110-112 and Molendijk 1990, pp. 5-7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The storehouse of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_291">Blussé &amp; Van Braam</rs> was next to Vincent’s lodging-house. During the flooding, Van Gogh carried heavy cartons of wet paper upstairs. People recollecting the incident commented also on his physical strength as well as his introversion. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, p. 109.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>A bank note of the highest value, namely 1,000 guilders.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_964">Aelbert Cuyp</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Some of Van Gogh’s possessions had to be sent from England. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘It was with great pleasure that I sent Vincent a parcel with several items this week; his clothes are still in England’ (FR b2502, 19 January).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1771"><hi rend="italics">Christus Consolator</hi></rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let085.xml#n-7">see letter 85, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>These English prints of the pilgrims on the road to Emmaus have not been traced.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  Luke 24:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 4:16 and Isa. 9:1 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Isa. 9:2).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 30:6 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 30:5).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Cor. 7:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 11:28-30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Luke 9:23.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>
  John 3:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Cf. Ps. 103:10-12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
  John 2:17; cf. also Ps. 69:10 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 69:9).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>
  Heb. 12:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Cf. Acts 18:25 and Rom. 12:11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 189:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>Cf. 1 John 2:24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>
  John 1:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  John 3:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>Cf. Rom. 8:38-39.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 113:1. Vincent wrote ‘Juich Aarde’ (Rejoice on earth) instead of ‘Juicht Christenen’ (Rejoice, Christians).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 114:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 180:5. Cf. Pabst 1988, p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 42:1. Cf. Pabst 1988, p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 42:7. Cf. Pabst 1988, p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 189:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="33" xml:id="note-t-33">
                            

<p>The French Church on the corner of Visstraat and Voorstraat.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="34" xml:id="note-t-34">
                            

<p>
  Rev. 3:11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="35" xml:id="note-t-35">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 137:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="36" xml:id="note-t-36">
                            

<p>A series of windmills on the Weeskinderendijk.  Van Gogh would make a drawing of these windmills in 1881; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let171.xml">see letter 171</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="37" xml:id="note-t-37">
                            

<p>When travelling from Paris to London and vice versa, Van Gogh no doubt saw the coastal town of Dieppe and the chalk cliffs (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">falaises</hi>) on the north-west coast of France. These trips occurred in May 1873, October 1874 and May 1875.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="38" xml:id="note-t-38">
                            

<p>Vincent’s journey from Ramsgate to London in June 1876; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let084.xml">see letter 84</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="39" xml:id="note-t-39">
                            

<p>
  2 Chron. 29:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="40" xml:id="note-t-40">
                            

<p>Rijsbergen is a village c. 6 km north of Van Gogh’s birthplace, Zundert, and its churchgoers were part of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>’s congregation. The <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_246 bio.xml#_66">Aertsen family</rs>, who are mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let108.xml">letter 108</ref>, were among the Van Goghs’ friends there.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="41" xml:id="note-t-41">
                            

<p>In 1810-1813 the road was paved and planted on either side with oak and beech trees. See Kools 1990, p. 61.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="42" xml:id="note-t-42">
                            

<p>For ‘O Jerusalem’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-35">see n. 35.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="43" xml:id="note-t-43">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 42:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="44" xml:id="note-t-44">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 36:2 and Eph. 3:20. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="45" xml:id="note-t-45">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 118:8, ‘Te zien hoe hoog, als wij gena’ verkrijgen, Gena’ kan stijgen’ (If grace we can obtain, to see the heights that grace may gain).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="46" xml:id="note-t-46">
                            

<p>A prayer written and often recited in the family circle by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let113.xml">see letter 113</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="47" xml:id="note-t-47">
                            

<p>Apparently this was an important image Van Gogh remembered from his youth, because an early drawing (in a sketchbook made for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_789">Betsy Tersteeg</rs>) also shows a small church with birds on the roof (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. d409). Cf. Kools 1990, p. 63.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="48" xml:id="note-t-48">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 104:30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="49" xml:id="note-t-49">
                            

<p>
  Rev. 21:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="50" xml:id="note-t-50">
                            

<p>
  Luke 15:11-32.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="51" xml:id="note-t-51">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 6:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="52" xml:id="note-t-52">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 6:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="53" xml:id="note-t-53">
                            

<p>Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let089.xml">letter 89</ref>: ‘Charity... is meek, it is woe-spirited, it has woe and spirit’. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘I do imagine that he always has the inclination to melancholy. He simply shouldn’t dwell on it too much, and I hope that he receives encouragement through the awareness that he can come up to scratch’ (FR b2502, 19 January 1877).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="54" xml:id="note-t-54">
                            

<p>Cf. Gen. 41:51.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="55" xml:id="note-t-55">
                            

<p>Evidently the Gemeentelijke Hogere Burgerschool (HBS) (municipal high school) and the Burgeravondschool (secondary evening school) had drawing examples published by Goupil on approval from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> (via <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_291">Blussé</rs>). It is possible that the drawings in question belonged to the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs> series (for his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_170">Cours de dessin</ref></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_202">Exercices au fusain</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let136.xml">see letters 136</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml">156</ref>). At the Burgeravondschool, housed in the former Armhuis (poorhouse) on the Stek, pupils above the age of 12 received instruction in arithmetic, mathematics and drawing. See J.L. van Dalen, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Geschiedenis van Dordrecht</hi>. 2 vols. Dordrecht 1931, vol. 2, pp. 926-928.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="56" xml:id="note-t-56">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the passage ‘Je vois d’ici une dame’ from the chapter ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_10">Les aspirations de l’automne</ref>’ in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let014.xml#n-19">see letter 14, n. 19</ref>). He had already asked Theo to send this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let089.xml">letters 89</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let090.xml">90</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="57" xml:id="note-t-57">
                            

<p>A wooden reading-desk preserved in the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Van Gogh family</rs> could be the one mentioned here. It is now to be found in the Van Gogh Museum (inv. no. v44 V/1975). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1816">Ill. 1816</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 1987, p. 500, cat. no. 3.12. That the reading-desk was once Vincent’s is recorded in a ‘Memorandum’ written by V.W. van Gogh dated 8 October 1975, though he later doubted whether it had actually been the one used by Vincent.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    