<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Dordrecht, Thursday, 8 March 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let106"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b110 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>106</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>92</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>106</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-03-08">Thursday, 8 March 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0110" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000119_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000119_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0110" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000119_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000119_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Dieu est fidèle qui ne permettra point que vous soyez tenté au-dessus de vos forces, mais avec la tentation Il donnera aussi l’issue.–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Let none of these things move thee.–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Beste Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dank voor Uw brief, wees sterk en Hij zal Uw hart versterken.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Vandaag ontving ik een langen brief van huis, waarin Pa mij vroeg of wij beiden het zouden kunnen schikken om Zondag aanst. naar Amsterdam naar Oom Cor te gaan.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Vindt Gij het goed dan kom ik dus Zaturdag avond met den trein die 11 uur eenige minuten te s’Hage komt bij U en gaan wij s’morgens met den eersten trein naar Amsterdam tot s’avonds<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wij moesten dat maar doen, Pa schijnt er zeer op gesteld te zijn, dan zijn wij ook aanst<c type="kp">_</c> Zondag weer bij elkaar. Het kan immers wel ik dien nacht bij U blijf – anders ga ik in den Toelast<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Schrijf nu nog een briefkaart of Ge het goed vindt, laat ons maar dicht bij elkaar blijven.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Hierbij nog een woordje voor Oom Cor<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> schrijf er nog iets bij als Gij wilt<c type="kp">_</c> Het is reeds laat, dezen middag deed ik eens eene wan<c type="shy">-</c>deling<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> omdat ik daar zoo behoefte aan gevoelde, eerst de Groote kerk om, toen de Nieuwe kerk en toen den dijk op waar al die molens staan die men als men bij de spoor wandelt ziet in de verte.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Er is zoo veel in dat eigenaardige landschap en omgeving dat spreekt en 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>dat schijnt te zeggen “houd goeden moed, vrees niet”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Er zijn zoo dagen in het leven waarop al de leden mede lijden omdat één van de leden lijdt,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en waar zoo opregte “droefheid naar God”<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> is, daar is God niet verre, Die ons ook houden zal.–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Als wij dat gelooven<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons dan in die dagen vurig wenschen en vragen om dingen die wij zouden willen zien gebeuren, of wij ook mogten verhoord worden.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Zoudt Gij ook voor mij willen vragen of mij een weg mogt worden geopend<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> om mijn leven, meer dan nu het geval is, te wijden aan de dienst van Hem en van het Evangelie.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Ik blijf er om aandringen en ik geloof dat ik verhoord zal worden, ik zeg dit in alle nederigheid en mij nederbuigende als het ware. ’t Is zoo’n groote, maar ook zoo’n zware zaak en toch ik begeer haar<c type="kp">_</c>– Menschelijkerwijs gesproken zou men zeggen, het kan niet gebeuren, maar als ik er ernstiger over nadenk en onder de oppervlakte van wat bij de menschen onmogelijk is<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> doordring dan is mijne ziel stil tot God,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> want het is mogelijk bij Hem die spreekt en het is er<c type="kk">/</c> die gebiedt en het staat er en het staat vast.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> O Theo, Theo, jongen, als het mij eens gebeuren mogt en die overvloed van neergedruktheid over allerlei wat ik ondernam en mij mislukte, die stroom van verwijten die ik heb gehoord en gevoeld, als het eens van mij mogt worden weggenomen en mij mogt worden gegeven en de gelegenheid en de kracht en liefde<c type="kk">/</c> vereischt om tot ontwikkeling te komen en te volharden en staande te blijven in dat waarover mijn Vader en ik den Heer zoo innig zouden danken.– Een handdruk in gedachten en groete bij Roos, vraag gij <hi rend="italics">het</hi> voor mij in dezen Uwen dag,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Uw zoo liefh. broeder</p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Let none of these things move thee.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Thanks for your letter, be of good heart, and He shall strengthen thine heart.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Today I received a long letter from home in which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> asked me if it would suit us both to go to Amsterdam next Sunday to visit <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> If it’s all right with you, then I’ll come to you in The Hague on Saturday evening on the train that arrives a few minutes after 11, and in the morning we’ll take the first train to Amsterdam and stay till evening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">We ought to do it, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> seems very keen on the idea, then we’ll be together again next Sunday. It is possible, isn’t it, for me to stay with you that night? Otherwise I’ll go to the Toelast.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Write a postcard now if you agree, let us stick close together.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Herewith a few words for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> add something to it if you like. It’s already late, this afternoon I took a walk,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> because I felt such a need to, first around the Grote Kerk, then the Nieuwe Kerk, and then up onto the dyke where all those mills<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> are that one sees in the distance if one walks along the railway tracks. There is so much in that singular landscape and vicinity that speaks and 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> seems to say ‘be of good courage, fear not’.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">There are days in one’s life when all members suffer because one member suffers,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and where there is true ‘godly sorrow,’<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> God is not far, He who will hold us.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> If we believe that, let us, in those days, fervently desire and ask for things we should like to see happen, that we might also be heard.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Would you also ask for me that a way be found<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> for me to devote my life, more so than is now the case, to the service of Him and the gospel?<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> I continue to insist and I believe that I’ll be heard, I say this in all humility and bowing myself down, as it were. It is such an import and such a difficult matter, and yet I desire it. One might say it isn’t humanly possible, but if I think about it more seriously and delve beneath the surface of what is humanly impossible,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> then truly my soul waiteth upon God,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> for it is possible for Him who speaks, and it is done, who commands, and it stands, and it stands fast.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> O Theo, Theo, old boy, if only it might happen to me and that deluge of downcastness about everything which I undertook and failed at, that torrent of reproaches I’ve heard and felt, if it might be taken away from me and if I might be given the opportunity and the strength and the love required to develop and to persevere and to stand firm in that for which my Father and I would offer the Lord such heartfelt thanks. A handshake in thought and regards to everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’, ask <hi rend="italics">it</hi> for me in this thy day,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="#l-18">l. 18</ref> Vincent writes that he is sending a letter for Theo to forward to Uncle Cor, along with any message he would care to add. This is <ref target="let107.xml">letter 107</ref>, dated 8 March. That the present letter cannot have been written a day earlier emerges from a letter written by Mr van Gogh to Theo on 7 March, in which he says that he intends to write to Vincent to suggest that he and Theo go that Sunday to visit Uncle Cor (FR b2510). This ‘long letter from home’, which has not survived, is referred to in <ref target="#l-7">l. 7</ref>. Vincent’s letter to Uncle Cor is the result of Mr van Gogh’s proposal, which had meanwhile reached Vincent. Mr van Gogh must therefore have written and sent his letter to Vincent on the same day as his letter to Theo (7 March; cf. also <ref target="let107.xml#l-34">letter 107, l. 34</ref>). His letter to Vincent must have arrived in Dordrecht on 8 March 1877, the day referred to as ‘today’ in <ref target="#l-7">l. 7</ref>. It is highly unlikely that the letter was written after this, because the proposed visit was supposed to take place only three days later.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s infatuation <ref target="let103.xml">(103)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  1 Cor. 10:13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Cf. Acts 20:24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 27:14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The visit was to take place a week later, because <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote on 17 March 1877 to Theo: ‘How wonderfully lucky that you can go straightaway to Uncle Cor and will be there tomorrow together with Vincent’ (FR b2514).</p>
  
<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> had taken the initiative in suggesting that both brothers come and visit him, and had written of his idea to Theo. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo on 27 February: ‘Friendly, too, of Uncle Cor to invite you, and Vincent as well. I had wished that the latter would go some time – but I’m afraid he won’t. Surely it is good if you go and see him, but make an appointment with him beforehand. Otherwise you might miss him. And make the most of a good day’ (FR b2509). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let107.xml">See letter 107</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Hotel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Toelast</hi> at Groenmarkt in The Hague. Evidently family members frequented this hotel: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, for example, stayed there occasionally on visits to The Hague (FR b2498).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let107.xml">letter 107</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had a break between 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, p. 110.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The windmills on the Weeskinderendijk: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let102.xml#n-36">see letter 102, n. 36.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  1 Chron. 22:13 and 1 Chron. 28:20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Vincent’s own variation on 1 Cor. 12:26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 7:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Biblical, cf. Ps. 139:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 21:13 and Matt. 6:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Sam. 22:33.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>This remark and what follows reveal that Van Gogh was already thinking of becoming a clergyman.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 19:26; Luke 18:27.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 62:2 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 62:1).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 33:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
  Luke 19:42.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    