<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Sunday, 8 April 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let110"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b109 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>110</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>91+91a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>111</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-04-08">Sunday, 8 April 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0109" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000118_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000118_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0109" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000118_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000118_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000118_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Etten 8 April 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Beste Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wil zorgen Gij weer spoedig<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> een brief ontvangt, zooals Gij ziet schrijf ik U weder uit Etten.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Gisteren morgen ontving ik een brief van Pa waarin Pa schreef dat Aertsen stervende was en hoe Pa er nog eens geweest was daar hij verlangde om Pa nog eens te zien en te spreken.─<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Toen ik dat hoorde werd mijn hart zoo naar Zundert getrokken dat ik behoefte had er ook eens heen te gaan. Maar hierover later ─ daar juist las ik Uwen laatsten brief en zag daaruit Uwe reis volbragt is en Gij weer te s’Hage zijt, schrijf mij maar weer eens spoedig ook en laat ons maar digt bij elkaar blijven.─ </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Heden een briefkaart van Anna zij goed is aangekomen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> moge het haar goedgaan, is het U ook niet opgevallen er in Haar iets gekomen is dat doet denken aan de vrouwen die Jezus liefhadden waar den Bijbel van spreekt.─<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> En aan haar denkende komen mij ook telkens de woorden van Beranger in gedachten:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dans les palais et sous le chaume,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Dit la vierge, j’ai de mes mains</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Préparé le miel et le baume</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Pour les souffrances des humains.─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Wat is zij lief geweest ook in dat huisgezin te Welwijn en lief en leed met hen gedeeld, en niets achter gehouden van wat in haar was om hun tot hulp en troost te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ook in de dagen toen dat kind daar ziek was en stierf;<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ik heb zoo gezien hoe allen daar van haar hielden.─ Van ’t begin af aan heeft zij zich zoo aangegrepen en is 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>s’winters vroeg opgestaan om met eigen handen het vuur aan te maken<c type="kk">/</c> al waren die eerste dagen niet gemakkelijk en schreef zij hoe zij dacht aan: Zonder U, o Eeuwig Wezen,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> ach! wat was de mensch op aard, Wien heb ik nevens U in den Hemel<c type="kk">/</c> nevens U lust mij ook niets meer op de aarde.─<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> En hoe zij toen zoo verlangde naar het Avondmaal en daar heen ging en er door versterkt werd.─ En wat houden Pa en Moe van haar, en dat doen wij allen ook wel, ja laat ons maar digt bij elkaar blijven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Zaturdag avond vertrok ik met den laatsten trein uit Dordrecht naar den Oudenbosch en wandelde van daar naar Zundert<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Daar in de hei was het zoo mooi<c type="kk">/</c> al was het donker kon men toch onderscheiden hoe die heivlakte en mastboschen en moerassen zich heinde en ver uitstrekten<c type="kk">/</c> het deed mij denken aan die plaat van Bodmer die op Pa’s studeerkamer hangt.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> De lucht was graauw maar de avondster scheen tusschen de wolken door en nu en dan zag men ook andere sterren.─ Het was nog zeer vroeg toen ik te Zundert op het kerkhof kwam waar het zoo stil was<c type="kk">/</c> ik ging nog eens zien naar al de oude plekken<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en paadjes en wachtte het opgaan van de zon af. Gij kent het verhaal van de Opstanding<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> alles herinnerde mij daar dezen morgen aan op dat stille kerkhof.─ Bij Aertsen en Mientje<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> hoorde ik zoodra zij op waren hoe hun Vader dien nacht was gestorven, o, zij 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>waren zoo bedroefd en hun aller gemoed was zoo vol want ook Hein<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> kwam er reeds vroeg. Het was mij goed er te zijn, en ik voelde met hen want ik had den man ook zoo lief.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Gij moet de groete hebben van de Tantes<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> en ook van Jan Doome<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> waar ik ook nog was<c type="kp">_</c>─ Van daar wandelde ik met Hein naar Rijsbergen,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en was ongeveer een uur in het huis en wij lazen te zamen. Woutje Prins<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> had ook 3 nachten bij den gestorvenen<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> gewaakt en tot het laatste toe hem bijgestaan.─ Zijn heengaan was zacht geweest.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het zal mij onvergetelijk zijn, dat edele hoofd dat daar lag op het kussen en waarin men bij de teekenen van het lijden eene uitdrukking van vrede en iets heiligs zag. O, het was zoo schoon, ik zou zeggen het sprak van al het eigenaardige dat dit land heeft en het leven van dit Brabantsche volk. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En zij waren allen zoo vol van Pa en wat Pa altijd voor hen geweest was en hoe die twee van elkaar hielden.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Toen ben ik met Hein Aertsen naar Etten gewandeld en ben nu weer t’huis om morgen vroeg te vertrekken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Dag jongen, het is posttijd, ontvang een handdruk in gedachten en geloof mij na groeten aan Uwe huisgenooten </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Etten, 8 April 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Want to make sure you get a letter quickly,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’m writing to you again from Etten, as you see.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Yesterday morning I got a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> in which Pa wrote that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_246">Aertsen</rs> was dying and how Pa had been there again, as he wished to see and speak to Pa again.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> When I heard that, my heart was drawn to Zundert so strongly that I felt the need to go there again. But more about this later – I just read your last letter and saw that your trip is over and you’re back in The Hague. Do write to me again soon, too, and let’s remain close to one another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Today a postcard from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> to say she arrived safely,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> may things go well for her. Haven’t you also noticed that something has come over her that recalls the women who loved Jesus of whom the Bible tells.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And every time I think of her I am reminded of the words of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">Béranger</rs>:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">In palaces and under thatch,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The Virgin said, with my hands</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I have prepared honey and balm</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">For mankind’s suffering.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And how sweet she was in that family in Welwyn, sharing their joys and sorrows, keeping nothing back of what she had in her to be a help and comfort to them, also during the time that child there was sick and died;<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I saw so clearly how everyone there loved her. She did her very best from the start, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> getting up early in the winter to make the fire with her own hands, even though the first days weren’t easy and she wrote that she was thinking: Without Thee, O Eternal Being,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> oh, what would become of man on earth? Whom have I in heaven but Thee? And there is none upon earth that I desire beside Thee.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> And how she wanted so much to attend the Lord’s Supper, and went there and found strength in it. And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> love her so much, and we all do too, yes, do let’s stay close to one another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">On Saturday evening I left on the last train from Dordrecht to Oudenbosch and walked from there to Zundert.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> It was so beautiful there on the heath, even though it was dark one could make out the heath and the pine-woods and the marshes stretching far and wide, it reminded me of that illustration by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_867">Bodmer</rs> that’s hanging in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s study.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> The sky was grey but the evening star shone through the clouds, and now and then other stars were visible too. It was still very early when I arrived at the cemetery in Zundert, where it was so quiet, I went to have a look at all the old places<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and paths and waited for the sun to rise. You know the story of the Resurrection,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> everything there reminded me of it in that quiet cemetery this morning. I heard from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_242">Aertsen</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_243">Mientje</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> as soon as they were up, that their Father had died that night, oh, they 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> were so sad and their hearts were so full, for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_250">Hein</rs><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> also arrived there early. I was glad to be there; I sympathized with them because I had also been so fond of the man.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_499 bio.xml#_501">aunts</rs><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> send you their regards, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_337">Jan Doome</rs><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> too, whom I also went to see. From there I walked with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_250">Hein</rs> to Rijsbergen,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and was in the house around an hour and we read together. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_599">Woutje Prins</rs><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> had also sat up for 3 nights with the deceased, and had stood by him till the last. His passing was peaceful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’ll never forget that noble head lying there on the pillow; one saw, besides the signs of suffering, an expression of peace and something holy. Oh, it was so beautiful, I’d say that it spoke of all the singularity this land has and the life of these Brabant folk.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And they were all so full of praise for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and what Pa had always been to them, and how fond those two were of each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Then I walked with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_250">Hein Aertsen</rs> to Etten and am now at home, leaving early tomorrow morning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Goodbye, old boy, it’s time for the post, accept a handshake in thought and believe me, after giving my regards to all your housemates,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Your most loving brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Etten 8 April 1877’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
  <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mr van Gogh wrote a short note to Theo on the back of the letter (p. [1r:4]);  <ref target="documentation.xml#id8April1877"><hi rend="italics">see Documentation</hi>, 8 April 1877</ref>.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s sales trip <ref target="let107.xml">(107)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The friendship between the Aertsen and Van Gogh families <ref target="let108.xml">(108)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The two brothers had seen each other in Etten on Easter (1 April) (FR b2519).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>On Monday, 2 April <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had been to see <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_246">Jan Aertsen</rs> on his deathbed (FR b2519).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>After some delay, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> entered the service of the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Van Houten family</rs> in Hengelo as a governess (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let107.xml">letter 107</ref>). She left Etten on 6 April (FR b2519).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Mary (the mother of James), Mary Magdalene and the mother of Zebedee’s children (Matt. 27:55).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">Pierre Jean de Béranger</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_126">Les deux soeurs de charité</ref>’ (The two sisters of charity). All of the editions consulted differ from Van Gogh’s transcription in the same two places:</p>

<p><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-21">l. 21</ref> Dit la vierge [ Moi, dit la soeur</p>

<p><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-22">l. 22</ref> Préparé ... Pour [ Distillé ... Sur</p>

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">P.-J. de Béranger</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Chansons. Anciennes et posthumes</hi>. Paris 1866 (Songs. Old and posthumous), pp. 121-122. Van Gogh alludes to this poem again in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let388.xml">letter 388</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In Welwyn, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> had lived with Mrs <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1674">Catherine Stothard</rs>, her employer’s sister; Catherine’s son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_207">Ernest</rs> died of diphtheria on 9 April 1875. See Bailey 1990, pp. 54, 82 (cf. also FR b2331 and b2333).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Compare, among others, rhy. ps. 28:1 and rhy. ps. 35:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 73:25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>It is c. 16 km from Oudenbosch to Zundert. Van Gogh borrowed the railway fare from his roommate <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 4, pp. 331-332.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This could be the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_867">Bodmer</rs> print that Van Gogh may have sent to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> in January 1876 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let066.xml">see letter 66</ref>). Its description suggests that it was the lithograph after Bodmer's painting <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1753"><hi rend="italics">Fontainebleau in the autumn</hi></rs> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Interior of the forest in winter</hi>); see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let055.xml#n-11">letter 55, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>One of these ‘old places’ was the grave of Van Gogh’s deceased brother Vincent: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let124.xml">see letter 124</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The resurrection of Christ; see Matt. 28, Mark 16, Luke 24 and John 20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The farmer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_242">Serfaas Aertsen</rs>, third son of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_246">Jan Aertsen</rs>, and his wife <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_243">Jacomijna (Mientje) Honcoop</rs>. Mientje was formerly a servant in the Van Gogh household. As sextoness she lived near the Zundert church and cemetery (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RAW</hi> and Kools 1990, pp. 18, 28-29, 139).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_250">Hendrik (Hein) Aertsen</rs>, likewise a son of the late Jan Aertsen. Cf. Kools 1990, pp. 139-140.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">P.C. Görlitz</rs> recalled the words Van Gogh had used to describe that evening: ‘I did not go in vain, I sat and prayed with the members of the old man’s household. I’ll tell you what I tried to impress upon them: Jesus and his teachings must be for you a light unto your path and a lamp unto your feet, then you will learn to resign yourself’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 4, p. 332. The first part of the text quoted was taken from Ps. 119:105.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>This was how the members of the Van Gogh family referred to the unmarried daughters of Zundert’s former minister: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_501">Elisabeth Petronella</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_499">Louisa Christina van der Burg</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The farmer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_337">Johannes (Jan) Doomen</rs> lived with a working-woman, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_338">Johanna Belet</rs>, who was seven years his junior, at Katerstraat A 186 (later 190) in Zundert. Their son, Cornelis Maria, was born on 20 September 1866. In the past Doomen had taken care of the Van Gogh family’s garden and had also tended the vegetable garden of the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_499 bio.xml#_501">Van der Burg sisters</rs> (FR b2506; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RAW</hi> and Kools 1990, p. 21).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_246">Johannes Aertsen</rs>’s farm was in Rijsbergen. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_599">Wouterina (Woutje) Prins</rs> had been a maidservant in the Van Gogh family when they were living in Zundert.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘den gestorvene’ (the deceased).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    