<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Dordrecht, Sunday, 15 April 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let111"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b108 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>111</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>90</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>110</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-04-15">Sunday, 15 April 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0108" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000117_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000117_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0108" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000117_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000117_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw brief van gisteren, die ik een uurtje tijd hebbende heden beantwoord.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Heb mij herinnerd wij op ’t museum van der Hoop zijnde<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> spraken over het boekje van Burger,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> hierbij ontvangt Gij het per post, Gij zult er in vinden nog eene houtsnee naar G. Doré<c type="kk">/</c> Judith &amp; Holophernes en een naar Brion &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> voor Uw plakboek<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ga daar maar mede door want dat zult Gij wel mooi krijgen door den tijd.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Neem mijne kleine bijdrage maar aan, het is mij zoozeer behoefte om door kleinigheden in gemeenschap met U te blijven, als ik op mijn kamertje kom word ik telkens aan U herinnerd door de platen aan den muur.–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">De liefde tusschen broeders is een krachtigen steun in het leven, dat is eene van ouds erkende waarheid, laat ons zoeken naar dien steun, het liefdevuur tusschen ons worde niet verdoofd<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> maar veeleer laat levenservaring den band tusschen ons versterken,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> laat ons oprecht<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en openhartig blijven met elkaar, laten er geene geheimen zijn – zooals dat heden is.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dank voor Uw laatsten brief<c type="kp">_</c> “het is nog niet voorbij” zegt Gij – neen dat kan het nog niet zijn.– Uw hart zal behoefte hebben zich te vertrouwen en zich uit te storten – daar zal tweestrijd zijn in U – haar of mijn Vader<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – ik geloof dat onzen Vader U meer 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>liefheeft dan zij – dat Zijne liefde van grooter waarde is – het is fijn goud<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> die woorden:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het kind vertrouwt zich aan zijn Vader</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dat is die Vader waard</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Uw Vader toch Wien hebt ge nader</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">In Hemel of op aard.–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ga er nog maar eens heen<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> als het U te moeielijk wordt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Deze week kreeg ik een brief van Oom Vincent die schrijft Hij het niet noodig oordeelt de correspondentie verder voort te zetten, dat Hij in dit geval mij niet kan behulp<c type="shy">-</c>zaam zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Ook kwam tegelijk een brief van den Heer Gladwell waarin hij schrijft over Harry – die heel wat zielsangst moet hebben uitgestaan en wien het vuur na aan de scheenen moet zijn gelegd om hem te doen handelen zooals hij gehandeld heeft<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Heden is de Hr Gorlitz te Etten om Pa te spreken over de vacante onderwijzersbetrekking aan de Leur<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Van harte hoop ik Hij die zal krijgen.– Heden was het hier voor het eerst vroegpreek<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> waar ik ben geweest<c type="kk">/</c> de preek was zeer mooi over de verschijning van Jezus aan de discipelen aan de zee van Tiberias<c type="kk">/</c> Joh. 21<c type="kp">_</c></p>
  
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Hierbij eenige gedichten van Uhland die mij troffen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Schrijft Gij weer spoedig, jongen, groet Uwe huis<c type="shy">-</c>genooten hartelijk voor mij en ontvang in gedachten een handdruk van</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Uw liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">bloemen uit Etten door Gorlitz meegebragt</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter of yesterday, which I answer today, having an hour of time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Remembered that when we were at the Van der Hoop Museum<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> we talked about the book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">Bürger</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> which you’ll be receiving in the post, in it you’ll also find a woodcut after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">G. Doré</rs>, Judith and Holofernes, and one after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs> &amp;c. for your scrapbook.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Do go on with it, because you’ll turn it into something beautiful in time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Do accept my small contribution, I need so much to commune with you by way of such trifles; when I come back to my room I’m reminded of you again and again by the illustrations on the wall.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The love between brothers is a great support in life, that is an age-old truth, let us seek that support, let the fire of love between us not be extinguished,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> but let instead the experience of life make that bond ever stronger,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> let us remain upright<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and candid with each other, let there be no secrets – as things stand today.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Thanks for your last letter. ‘It’s not over yet’, you say – no, it cannot be over yet. Your heart will need to trust itself and to pour forth – you’ll be torn between the two – her and my Father<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – I think that our Father loves you more 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> than she does – that his love is worth more – these words are ‘fine gold’:<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The child puts great faith in his Father</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">As befits the father’s worth.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">For who is closer than thy Father, is he nearer</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In Heaven or on earth?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">By all means go there again<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> if things get to be too much for you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">This week I got a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs>, who wrote that he thought it unnecessary to continue the correspondence, that he cannot help me in this matter.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> A letter came at the same time from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_396">Mr Gladwell</rs>, in which he wrote about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry</rs> – who must have endured much anguish, being very hard pressed to make him act as he did.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Mr Görlitz</rs> is in Etten today to talk to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> about the vacancy for a teaching post at Leur.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I sincerely hope he’ll get it. Today was the first early sermon,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> which I attended, the sermon was very beautiful, about Jesus showing himself to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias, John 21.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Herewith a few poems by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_841">Uhland</rs> which I found moving.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Do write soon, old boy, give my warm regards to your housemates, and accept a handshake in thought from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Your loving brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">Flowers from Etten, brought by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs></hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On the day he wrote this letter, Van Gogh’s roommate P.C. Görlitz visited Rev. Van Gogh in Etten, and there was an early sermon in Dordrecht. Lack of documented evidence makes it impossible to date these events, however. It is certain that this letter was written on a Sunday, because of the sermon <ref target="#l-44">(l. 44)</ref>. This must have been <hi rend="italics">after</hi> Sunday, 18 March, since Van Gogh mentions having visited Amsterdam on that day (the museum, <ref target="#l-4">l. 4</ref>). There is also a reference, however, to a letter from Uncle Vincent van Gogh, in which he must have said that he was unable to lend any further support to Vincent’s new plans and intended to break off the correspondence <ref target="#l-33">(l. 33)</ref>. Mrs van Gogh talks about this in a letter to Theo dated Wednesday, 18 April: ‘Dearest Theo, we haven’t read the letter from Uncle to Vincent yet; Vincent is to bring it with him some time when he comes. Uncle wrote to tell us that he had written to him, but could not endorse his plans’ (FR b2521; see also <ref target="#n-11">n. 11</ref>). Theo must therefore have written to his mother about the letter from Uncle Vincent, having been prompted to do so by what Vincent told him in the present letter. Considering the importance of this matter and the frequent contact among family members in this period – the whole family were together in Etten at Easter, on 1 April – it is unlikely that the contents of Uncle Vincent’s letter were not yet known to the parents three weeks later. Because Van Gogh had already written <ref target="let110.xml">letter 110</ref> by Sunday, 8 April, it is likely that the present letter was written on Sunday, 15 April. A dating to later in April is unlikely, because around that time plans for Vincent to study in Amsterdam were already taking shape.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">Placing this letter between the letter of 8 April (<ref target="let110.xml">letter 110</ref>) and that of 22 and 23 April (<ref target="let112.xml">letter 112</ref>) helps to clarify a number of things: for example, the remark about the books by Thoré (<ref target="let112.xml#l-66">letter 112, l. 66</ref>) can now be explained as a reaction to the letter Theo wrote after receiving the book by Thoré that was sent with the present letter; and more light is shed on the letters that had meanwhile reached Van Gogh from Harry Gladwell’s father and Harry (see the present letter, <ref target="#l-37">l. 37</ref> and <ref target="let112.xml#l-57">letter 112, l. 57</ref>), telling of Harry’s difficulties. Finally, it would be strange if Van Gogh were to wait until three weeks after the fact to ask if he had already told them that Görlitz had applied for a teaching post in Etten (<ref target="let112.xml#l-50">see letter 112, l. 50</ref>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s infatuation <ref target="let103.xml">(103)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s plans to become a clergyman <ref target="let106.xml">(106)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>From 1854 to 1885, the Museum Van der Hoop in Amsterdam was housed in the former Oude Mannen- en Vrouwenhuis (Old Men’s and Old Women’s House) in the Oudemanhuispoort, which the brothers visited on 18 March (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let109.xml">see letter 109</ref>). In 1885 the collection was moved to the newly built Rijksmuseum. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 2004-2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">E.J.T. Thoré</rs> (under the pseudonym of W. Bürger), <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_14"><hi rend="italics">Musées de la Hollande, <hi>ii</hi>. Musée Van der Hoop, à Amsterdam et Musée de Rotterdam</hi></ref>. Paris 1860.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p>In the Van Gogh family estate there are two scrapbooks containing several dozen prints (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. nos. t*1487 and t*1488). The woodcut in question after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Gustave Doré</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Judith with the head of Holophernes</hi> (Swansea, Glynn Vivian Art Gallery), <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1801">Ill. 1801</rs>, is not to be found in either scrapbook, nor is a print after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs> (unless it is one of the unidentified prints in the scrapbooks).</p>

<p rend="indent">It was previously assumed, on the basis of a remark written later on the endpaper, that the prints in the first album (on yellow paper, 30 x 24 cm) had been collected by Vincent when he was living in Paris (May 1875-March 1876), but this seems unlikely. It seems more probable that both albums, the second one as well (on blue paper, 50 x 30 cm), belonged to Theo. Exactly how these scrapbooks took shape is difficult to ascertain, however. On this subject, see exhib. cat. Amsterdam 2003, p. 102.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo had given Vincent a number of prints. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let109.xml">See letter 109</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 133:1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>A prayer written and often recited in the family circle by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let113.xml">see letter 113</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Biblical.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This remark suggests that it was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> in particular who disapproved of Theo’s infatuation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Biblical; see, for example, Ps. 19:11 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 19:10) and Isa. 13:12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 56:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>By ‘there’ Van Gogh must have meant their parental home.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs> had been consulted about Vincent’s plans to study in Amsterdam. On 18 April 1877, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘Uncle wrote that he had written to him [Vincent], but could not endorse his plans. You say that Uncle doesn’t know Vincent, that he means well, but that isn’t the point. Though Uncle doesn’t sympathize with his ideas, he knows very well that Vincent is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">a good person</hi>, but Uncle sees no future prospects in the plans, and knows that this is necessary, and that’s why he cannot accept them and certainly told Vincent this plainly. You and we are not yet reconciled to it either, but we would risk putting it to the test if possible, though we’ve heard nothing more from Amsterdam from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>, whom we long to hear from. This morning a kind letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs>, saying that Vincent’s room was being made ready, meaning that he can come if he wants to – otherwise Uncle isn’t getting involved in it, but provides the opportunity. Who knows whether this will do Vincent good, and civilize him, that is certainly a redeeming feature of this affair, that there is this good opportunity, because if he wants to become a clergyman, Vincent must really be able to associate just as easily with the upper classes as with simple folk’ (FR b2521).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let112.xml">letter 112</ref> it emerges that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry Gladwell</rs> had fallen into (unspecified) difficulties.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Leur was a village due west of Etten; now the two places form the municipality of Etten-Leur.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The early sermon is a sermon delivered in the early-morning service held at 7.00 am. No details have been found about the ‘first’ early sermon. Van Gogh presumably meant that the first early service of that year had been held (the cold weather usually being over by mid-April).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            
<p>It is not known which poems by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_841">Uhland</rs> were enclosed with the letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>This choice of words suggests that the letter to Theo contained one or more of the flowers that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs> had brought back from Etten.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    