<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Dordrecht, Sunday, 22 and Monday, 23 April 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let112"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b111 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>112</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>93</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>112</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-04-22">Sunday, 22 and Monday, 23 April 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0111" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0111" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000120_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Dordrecht 23 April 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Uw brief van 21 April ontving ik, dank voor Uw spoedig schrijven ─ en die brief heeft mij een gevoel van vreugde gegeven zooals de vrouw moet gehad hebben die haar penning terugvond<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> n.l. Gij schrijft dat het lessenaartje van Tante Koos<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> met de brieven van Pa en Moe, bij gelegen<c type="shy">-</c>heid van het schoonmaken, bij Roos is gevonden.─<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wat heb ik er met angst en zorg verl. jaar naar gezocht in de ver<c type="shy">-</c>beelding zijnde ik het mede had genomen naar Engeland en dat het was blijven staan in één van de huizen waar ik te Londen geweest ben.─ Het is heerlijk dat het is teregtgekomen, ik ben er zoo dankbaar voor, bewaar het voorloopig nog maar, te Amsterdam als ik “op weg”<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> ben zal ik het noodig hebben.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu herinner ik mij zeer goed het bij Roos te hebben achtergelaten bij mijn vertrek naar Engeland, omdat er niet veel ruimte in mijn koffer was en ook omdat ik meende het ginder veiliger zou zijn dan wanneer het mee ging trekken in den vreemde.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Het is mij als het ware een nieuw bewijs, en een wenk zooals ik er meer in den laatsten tijd meende op te 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>merken<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik zal zegen hebben op mijne pogingen<c type="kk">/</c> dat het mij goed zal gaan en de zaak die ik zoo vurig begeer mij zal gegeven worden ─ er wordt iets van het oud ver<c type="shy">-</c>trouwen<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> in mij levendig dat mijne gedachten zullen bevestigd worden<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en een vasten geest vernieuwd<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en de ziel hersteld in het oud Geloof. Alleen ik doe eene keuze voor mijn leven<c type="kp">_</c> Zet ook Gij Uw hart en zin vast op iets goeds, op eene goede zaak, en begeer ze van den Heer.─<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Oom Jan is te Etten geweest en heeft gezegd dat mijn kamertje reeds gereed was<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> ─ de Heer Braat is met iemand in besprek dus in Mei zal ik waarschijnlijk de hand aan den ploeg slaan.─<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Op dat kamertje zullen de prenten die ik van U heb<c type="kk">/</c> hangen en zal ik daardoor dagelijks aan U herinnerd worden ─ onder dat naar Rosenthal<c type="kk">/</c> dien monnik<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> heb ik geschreven “Neem mijn juk op u en leer van Mij dat ik zachtmoedig ben en nederig van hart en gij zult rust vinden voor Uwe ziele, want mijn juk is zacht en mijn last is ligt.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Zoo wie achter Mij wil komen die verloochene Zich zelven en neme zijn kruis op en volge Mij<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> ─ in het koninkrijk der Hemelen<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> trouwen zij niet en worden niet ten huwelijk gegeven”.─<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Onder de pendant: l’imitation de Jesus Christ (naar Ruyperez)<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> schreef ik wat wij Pa hoorden zeggen: “Heer ik zou zoo graag ernstig zijn”.─<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dezen morgen hoorde ik eene zeer mooie preek van D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Keller van Hoorn over “En dat gij van jongsaf de schriften geweten hebt”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> dezen middag waren Gorlitz<c type="kk">/</c> Mager<c type="kk">/</c> ten Broek<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en ik op het museum om de Scheffers te zien ─ die zijn toch schoon. Schreef ik U reeds Gorlitz naar Etten is geweest om te solliciteeren naar de onderwijzersbetrekking die daar aan de Leur vacant is.─<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Hij kwam terug vervuld met alles wat hij daar had gezien<c type="kp">_</c> Pa had gepreekt over Jakob die in het veld sliep te Bethel,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> en het had hem alles zoo getroffen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik zou hem gunnen dat hij die plaats kreeg, dan zou hij denkelijk wel spoedig trouwen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Verl. week had ik een brief van Harry Gladwell zelf.─ Hem is iets overkomen, ja wel eenigzins anders maar toch van den zelfden aard van wat U overkwam, en hij is daar in gevaarlijke omgeving ─ de vogelvangers<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> zijn er velen en slim.─ Hoop spoedig iets naders te vernemen en wij spreken er nog wel eens over.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Van Taines leven weet ik weinig<c type="kk">/</c> ik veronderstel hij veel heeft gereisd in Frankrijk<c type="kk">/</c> Italie<c type="kk">/</c> Engeland en Holland ook, dat zou men uit zijne schriften opmaken<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Hij is wel een artist.─ Het 1<hi rend="super">o</hi> boek van Burger<c type="kk">/</c> Musées<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik zelf nog.─<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Nu Theo, heb een goeden Zondag van daag. Als ik naar Amsterdam ga hoop ik U nog te zien<c type="kp">_</c>─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Voor een “zaaijer des woords”<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> zoo als ik hoop te worden zal ook wel<c type="kk">/</c> even als voor den zaaijer van het koren op het veld<c type="kk">/</c> wel iederen dag genoeg blijven hebben aan zijn eigen kwaad<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> ─ en de aarde velerlei doornen en distelen voortbrengen<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> ─ laat ons elkander maar tot steun blijven en naar broederliefde zoeken.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">à Dieu, groet uwe huisgenooten en ontvang een hand<c type="shy">-</c>druk in gedachten en geloof mij steeds </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Uw liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Het regent hier vandaag en men zou zich kunnen verbeelden te Londen te zijn. Maar wat wordt het alles groen buiten<c type="kk">/</c> dezen morgen gingen Gorlitz, ten Broek en ik reeds vroeg wandelen. Is het in de Scheveningsche boschjes<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> ook niet mooi<c type="kp">_</c> Zouden wij daar nog eens zamen wandelen en aan het strand.─ ik hoop het!─ Als ik dezen op de post breng hoop ik dat paadje achter het station nog eens te gaan waar wij zamen wandelden.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dordrecht, 23 April 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I received your letter of 21 April, thanks for writing so quickly – and that letter gave me a feeling of joy such as the woman must have had who found the piece of silver she had lost,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> namely, you wrote that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_37">Aunt Koos</rs>’s little reading-desk<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> containing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>’s letters was found at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’ when the house was being cleaned.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">What fear and worry I felt last year, looking for it and imagining that I’d taken it to England and that it got left behind at one of the houses I stayed at in London. It’s wonderful that it has turned up, I’m so grateful, keep it for the time being, I’ll be needing it in Amsterdam when I’m ‘on the way’.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I now remember very clearly having left it behind at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’ when I left for England, because there wasn’t much room in my trunk and also because I thought it would be safer there than travelling with me in foreign parts.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It seems to me to be new proof, as it were, and a sign like others that I think I’ve been noticing recently, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> that my efforts will be blessed, that things will go well for me, and the thing I desire so fervently will be granted me – something of the faith of old<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> has come alive in me that my thoughts shall be established<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and a right spirit renewed<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and the soul restored to the old faith. I alone am making a choice for my life. Set your heart and mind, you too, on something good, on a good cause, and desire it of the Lord.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs> was in Etten and said that my room was already ready.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_306">Mr Braat</rs> is negotiating with someone, so in May I’ll probably put my hand to the plough.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Hanging in that little room will be the prints I got from you, and so I’ll be reminded of you daily – beneath that one after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_191">Rosenthal</rs>, that monk,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I have written ‘Take my yoke upon you, and learn of Me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Whosoever will come after Me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow Me<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> – in the kingdom of heaven<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> they do not marry, and are not given in marriage’.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Beneath its pendant, The imitation of Jesus Christ (after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1335">Ruipérez</rs>),<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I wrote what we used to hear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> say: ‘Lord, I should so much like to be earnest’.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">This morning I heard a very beautiful sermon by the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_474">Rev. Keller van Hoorn</rs> on ‘and that from a child thou hast known the scriptures’.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> This afternoon <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_507">Mager</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_316">Ten Broek</rs><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and I went to the museum to see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Scheffer</rs>s – they’re really beautiful. Have I already told you that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs> went to Etten to apply for the teaching position that has fallen vacant in Leur?<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">He came back filled with everything he had seen there. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> had given a sermon on Jacob who slept in the field at Bethel,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> and he had found it all so moving.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’d be happy for him if he got the position; then he would probably marry very soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Last week I got a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry Gladwell</rs> himself. Something has happened to him, a little different, admittedly, and yet essentially the same as what happened to you, and he is in dangerous surroundings there – the fowlers<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> are many and clever. I hope to hear more soon, and we’ll talk about it sometime.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I know little of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_833">Taine</rs>’s life, I assume that he travelled a lot in France, Italy, England and also Holland, one could deduce as much from his writings.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> He is certainly an artist. I still have the first book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">Bürger</rs>, Musées.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Now, Theo, have a nice Sunday today. I hope to see you if I go to Amsterdam.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">For a ‘sower of the word’<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> as I hope to become, sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof, just like for a sower of corn in the field<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> – and the earth shall bring forth all manner of thorns and thistles<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> – do let’s continue to support each other and to seek brotherly love.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Adieu, give my regards to your housemates, and accept a handshake in thought, and believe me ever</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Your loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">It’s raining here today and one could imagine oneself in London. But how green everything outside is becoming. This morning <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_316">Ten Broek</rs> and I went for a walk while it was still early. Isn’t it beautiful in the Scheveningen Bosjes as well?<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> Shall we walk there together again, and on the beach? I hope so! When I go to post this I hope to take that small path behind the station again where we walked together.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Dordrecht 23 April 1877’. Van Gogh’s remark to ‘have a nice Sunday today’ suggests that the letter was written as far as the signature on Sunday, 22 April. This is confirmed by the visit to the museum with acquaintances <ref target="#l-48">(l. 48)</ref>, which is unlikely to have taken place on Monday. The handwriting of the closing sentence of the postscript looks slightly different. It might have been added, along with the date, on Monday, 23 April.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s plans to train to be a clergyman <ref target="let106.xml">(106)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See Luke 15:8-9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>‘Aunt Koos’ could refer to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_37">Jacoba Wilhelmina van der Burg</rs>. Regarding Van Gogh’s reading-desk in England, cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let102.xml#n-57">letter 102, n. 57.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Before leaving for England, Van Gogh boarded with the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">Roos family</rs> in The Hague; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let001.xml">see letter 1</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>‘On the way’ means ‘on my way to becoming a clergyman’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 42:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  Prov. 16:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 51:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Cf. rhy. ps. 37:2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
  
<p>Van Gogh was planning to live in Amsterdam with his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs>, who lived at Grote Kattenburgerstraat 3 on the Marinewerf (naval dockyard) on the island of Kattenburg, not far from the centre. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>An expression based on Luke 9:62. As also emerges from the family correspondence, Van Gogh’s employer did not want to let him go until he had found a replacement (FR b2520).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            


<p>This most likely refers to the print <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Humility</hi>, which was published in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_679">Thomas a Kempis</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_35"><hi rend="italics">L’Imitation de Jésus-Christ</hi></ref>. With reflections by F. de Lammennais at the end of every chapter. Inscribed below it, in addition to ‘Rosenthal pinxit’ and ‘Girardet &amp; Pelé sc.’, is ‘Furne, Pagnerre, Perrotin, Éditeurs’. See 12th edition. Paris 1844, between pp. 148-149. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1802">Ill. 1802</rs>. Vincent had received the print from Theo, to whom he had recommended the book in November 1876 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let197.xml">see letter 197</ref>). The engraving is part of a series, the others being by Auguste Blanchard (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">père</hi>), Johannes de Mare and Tony Goutière. The painting was most probably made by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_191">Constantin David Rosenthal</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            


<p>
  Matt. 11:29-30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  Mark 8:34; cf. also Matt. 16:24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>‘The kingdom of heaven’ is alluded to many times in the Gospel according to Matthew.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Mark 12:25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>For Ruipérez, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let040.xml#n-16">see letter 40, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Cf. hymn 73:10, ‘Dus past de waakzaamheid den Christen, En daaglijks ernstig onderzoek’ (Thus watchfulness becomes the Christian, And serious probing every day).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>
  2 Tim. 3:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>This perhaps refers to the clerk <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_316">Christiaan van de(n) Broek</rs>, who lived at Groenmarkt A 209 and is recorded in the 1873 <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboek</hi>. The civil registration records of the municipality of Dordrecht for the years 1860-1890 contain no <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ten</hi> Broek.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let111.xml">See letter 111</ref> concerning <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_397">Görlitz</rs>’s application for this position.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 28:10-22.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Used in the Bible as a name for the godless and for the evil threatening humankind; cf. such passages as Ps. 91:3 and rhy. ps. 124:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_833">Hippolyte Adolphe Taine</rs> was probably mentioned by Theo in his letter of 21 April. From <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let133.xml">letter 133</ref> of 30 October 1877, it emerges that Vincent had read Taine’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_128"><hi rend="italics">Histoire de la littérature anglaise</hi></ref>. He could have inferred that Taine had visited the countries mentioned from the list of Taine’s other publications appearing in the front of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Histoire de la littérature anglaise</hi> of 1874, a list which includes <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Voyage aux Pyrénées</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Notes sur l’Angleterre</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Notes sur Paris</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Voyage en Italie</hi>. It is not known which of these works Van Gogh read, but he certainly knew <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_129"><hi rend="italics">Voyage aux Pyrénées</hi></ref>. See Pabst 1988, p. 27.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">E.J.T. Thoré</rs> (writing under the pseudonym W. Bürger), <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_13"><hi rend="italics">Musées de la Hollande, <hi>i</hi>. Amsterdam et La Haye</hi></ref>; Vincent had sent part 2 to Theo (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let111.xml">letter 111</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>Cf. Mark 4:14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>An allusion to the parable of the sower in the four Gospels, including Matt. 13:3-8. See for ‘sufficient ... thereof’: Matt. 6:34.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 3:18.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let079.xml#n-5">See letter 79, n. 5.</ref>
</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>Regarding this walk, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let103.xml">see letter 103</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    