<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Monday, 9 July 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let121"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b120 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>121</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>101a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>121</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-07-09">Monday, 9 July 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0120" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000129_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000129_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0120" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000129_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000129_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amsterdam 9 Julij 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat zegt gij wel van Anna, mij heeft het verrast, en het schijnt ernst te zijn ook en zal, zou men zoo zeggen, zeker wel doorgaan.─<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Het kan goed zijn. De moeielijkheden verbonden aan het bekleeden van eene ondergeschikte betrekking, vooral wanneer men gedurende langeren tijd daarin volhardt, zooals zij dat toch gedurende jaren in alle eer en deugd heeft gedaan, zijn zeer groot en worden soms een zwaren strijd<c type="kk">/</c> en het schijnbaar gemakkelijke uiterst moeielijk.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het heeft veel poezie toch en zulke jaren zijn een schat die niet ligt ontvalt, en wanneer men, voor het eerst vooral, zich zelven verloochent en vernedert<c type="kk">/</c> heeft men een heer<c type="shy">-</c>lijk gevoel van vrede van binnen, maar ik zou het mij zeer goed kunnen begrijpen als het zoo was dat de toekomst ook voor haar soms duister werd ─ het kan verstandig van haar zijn dat zij, wat Haar aangaat reeds tot dezen stap besloten is.─ En ook houd ik het er voor Zij opregte liefde voor hem gevoelt, dat geloof en vertrouw ik zeker en vast, anders zou het zoo ver niet zijn gekomen.─ En daarom hoop ik van harte Zij niet zal worden teleurgesteld maar dat dit onder Gods leiding den weg tot haar blijvend geluk zal zijn. De Heer geve Haar dat zij ruste vinde, die beste zuster, en zegene Haar, en geve haar goede dingen in Haar leven.─ Ook U wensch ik met deze zaak geluk<c type="kk">/</c> gelijk ik het ook Anna en Pa en Moe deed.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Hoe gaat het U kerel, reeds vroeger had ik U willen schrijven en Uw laatsten brief beantwoorden, ik heb veel te doen en ’t is geen gemakkelijk werk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dan ga ik veel naar de kerk, er zijn mooie oude kerken hier en uitmuntende predikers, Oom Stricker hoor ik dikwijls en wat Hij zegt is zeer goed en Hij spreekt met veel warmte en gevoel.─ D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Laurillard hoorde ik driemaal, die zou U ook bevallen, want Hij schildert als het ware, en zijn werk is te gelijk hooge en edele kunst, Hij heeft het gevoel van een kunstenaar in den waren zin van het woord, zoo als een Anderssen dat had als hij b.v. zegt:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Elke avond kwam de maan, en fluistrend sprak ze mij</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Van wat ze in den stillen stillen nacht</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Gezien heeft van heur hooge hemelwacht;</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Zij wie eeuwen heugt ─ zij wandelde daarheen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Hoog boven ’t schuim des zondvloeds, en bescheen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">De vlottende ark met zachten zilvergloed,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Gelijk zij nu mijn eenzaam venster doet</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En ook, toen Israel met vochtig oog</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Bij Babylon’s rivieren nederboog</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Bestraalde zij met droeve tinteling</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De ontsnaarde harp, die aan de wilgen hing.─<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">De maan schijnt ook nu nog en de zon en de Avondster, dat is gelukkig, en die spreken nog dikwijls van de Liefde Gods en doen denken aan het woord<c type="kk">/</c> Ziet Ik ben met U alle dagen tot aan de voleinding der wereld.─<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ben bezig een uittreksel te maken van de geschiedenis van de kerkhervorming,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> er is veel opwekkends en aantrekkelijks in de geschiedenis van die dagen.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">De zaal in het Trippenhuis waar de Staalmeesters van Rembrandt hangen is weer open, gisteren, uit de kerk komende liep ik er even heen, vlak naast de Rembrandt hangt dat bewuste portret door van der Helst.─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">à Dieu Theo, een hartelijken handdruk in gedachten, heb het zoo goed mogelijk en geloof dikwijls aan U denkt</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Hierbij nog eene kleine bijdrage voor Uw plakboek<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> gaat dat vooruit? Groet Uwe huisgenooten en als den een of ander soms naar mij mocht vragen.─</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Amsterdam, 9 July 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Well, what do you say about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>? It surprised me, and it seems to be serious too, and will certainly take place, one would venture to say.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It could be good. The difficulties of holding a subordinate position, especially when one perseveres in it for a longer period, as she has in fact done for years in all honour and virtue, are very great and sometimes become a hard struggle, and the seemingly easy becomes extremely difficult.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">There’s nevertheless much poetry in it, and such years are a treasure not easily lost, and when one denies and humbles oneself, especially the first time, one has a wonderful feeling of inner peace, but I would understand very well if the future was sometimes dark for her too – it might be sensible of her, for her part, to have already decided to take this step. And I also maintain that she truly loves him, I believe that and trust in it absolutely, otherwise things wouldn’t have gone this far. And so I sincerely hope that she won’t be disappointed but that this, with God’s guidance, will be the path to her lasting happiness. May the Lord grant that she find peace, that dear sister, and bless her, and give her good things in life. On this occasion I congratulate you, too, as I have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">How are you, old chap? I had wanted to write to you earlier and answer your last letter. I have a lot to do and the work isn’t easy.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Then again, I go to church a lot, there are beautiful old churches here, and outstanding preachers, I often hear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>, and what he says is very good, and he speaks with much warmth and feeling. I’ve heard the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_53">Rev. Laurillard</rs> three times, you would like him too, because he paints, as it were, and his work is at once lofty and noble art. He has the feeling of an artist in the true sense of the word, as someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">Andersen</rs> had when he says, for example:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Every evening came the moon and whispered in my ear,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Telling of the quiet night and what its eye</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Had lit on from its watch-post in the sky.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It who knows centuries – through ages did it roam,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Casting, high above the Flood and crest of foam,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">On the floating ark a soft silver glow,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Just as it now lights my lonely window</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Then, too, when the folk of Israel knelt down</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">To weep by the waters of Babylon</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">It illumined with sad twinkling down below</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The unstrung harp, hanging on the willow.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The moon still shines now, and the sun and the evening star, which is fortunate, and they often speak of God’s Love and call to mind the words, lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Am busy making a summary of the history of the Reformation,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> there’s much that is stimulating and appealing in the history of those days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">The room in the Trippenhuis where <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s Syndics are hanging is open again; coming from church yesterday I walked over there for a while, hanging right next to the Rembrandt is that portrait by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1086">Van der Helst</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Adieu, Theo, a hearty handshake in thought, I wish you the very best, and believe that often thinking of you is</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Herewith a small contribution for your scrapbook,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> is it coming along? Give my regards to your housemates and if someone or other should ask after me.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 9 Julij 1877’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent’s sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> had received a proposal of marriage from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Joan Marius van Houten</rs>, the son of the family in Hengelo for whom she worked as a lady companion. Van Houten, a ‘calmly cordial, reliable boy’, according to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, was a manufacturer of shell lime and a member of the firm of Van Houten &amp; Ledeboer, lime-burners at Leiderdorp (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Nederland’s patriciaat</hi> 44 (1958), p. 138 and FR b2538, 1 July 1877, Mr van Gogh to Theo (quotation)). Joan had been courting Anna since 20 May, and their courtship surprised not only Vincent but also <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs>: ‘They’ve known each other since Whitsun, and he’s been here a lot. You can imagine how it surprised us’ (FR b2539, to Theo, 2 July 1877). Their engagement was announced on 9 July, and Mr van Gogh wrote to Theo that Vincent was also pleased about it (FR b2540). Vincent’s prediction came true: the marriage was solemnized on 22 August 1878.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">Hans Christian Andersen</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_63"><hi rend="italics">Vertellingen van de maan</hi></ref> (What the moon saw). Van Gogh owned the edition <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_63"><hi rend="italics">Andersen’s prentenboek zonder prenten: Vertellingen van de maan</hi></ref>. Translated by<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_681"> J.J.L. ten Kate</rs>. 4th ed. Leiden 1870; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let068.xml">see letter 68</ref>. The passage quoted, which was taken from the introduction, varies somewhat from the original (pp. 3-4). In the poetry album made for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Matthijs Maris</rs> – probably compiled between May 1875 and March 1876 – Van Gogh copied a number of pages from Ten Kate’s translation. See Pabst 1988, pp. 55-58.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 28:20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Various books and textbooks on the history of the Reformation were in circulation, among them several whose titles included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De geschiedenis van de kerkhervorming</hi> (The history of the Reformation), such as those by Bernhard ter Haar, Henricus Jacobus Hofstede, Evert Jan Diest, Jacob Gijsbert de Hoop Scheffer and F. Naef (translated from the French by J.W.Ph. Feith), so that it is possible that Van Gogh was speaking here of a specific book.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Syndics of the the Amsterdam Drapers’ Guild </hi>(Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1835">Ill 1835</rs>. As emerges from a drawing made of the Syndics Room by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_902">Henri de Braekeleer</rs> in 1883, the painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Aert van Nes</hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1086">Bartholomeus van der Helst</rs> hung to the left of Rembrandt’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Syndics</hi>, to the right of which hung its pendant, the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Geertruida den Dubbelde</hi>, Van Nes’s wife; both portraits date from 1668 (Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1836">Ill 1836</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1837">Ill. 1837</rs>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Honderd jaar Rijksmuseum</hi> 1985, p. 13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Regarding Theo’s scrapbooks, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let111.xml#n-3">see letter 111, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    