<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Hermanus Gijsbertus Tersteeg. Amsterdam, Friday, 3 August 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let124"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement/>
                                        <institution/>
                                        
                                        <idno/>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>124</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-08-03">Friday, 3 August 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Hermanus Tersteeg</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amsterdam 3 Augustus 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Heer Tersteeg,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Uit het laatste schrijven van Theo hoorde ik van Uw verlies<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en het is mij behoefte U een woordje te schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">“Zoo wie niet heeft liefgehad die heeft God niet gekend want God is Liefde”,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> over die woorden hoorde ik D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Keller van Hoorn te Dordrecht, een oud vriend van mijn Vader<c type="kk">/</c> preeken op een Zondag<c type="shy">-</c>avond, eenige dagen na het overlijden van zijne dochter.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Hij zeide: wat mij bij dezen slag, den gevoeligsten die mij ooit heeft getroffen versterkte en staande hield, was het geloof in mijn God, zonder dat kan ik niet leven, – mijn troost vond ik ook nu weer in den rijken schat van Zijn woord. Onwillekeurig sloeg hij den Bijbel die vòòr Hem lag op en wel, als doorleefde hij dat oogenblik van zielssmart opnieuw, op dezelfde plaatsen als toen. n.l.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En David zocht God voor dat jongsken, toen zijn kind zeer krank was, en ging in en lag den nacht over op de aarde. Toen maakten de oudsten van zijn huis zich op tot hem, om hem te doen opstaan van de aarde, maar hij wilde niet en at geen brood met hen.– En het geschiedde op den zevenden dag dat het kind stierf en Davids knechten vreesden hem aan te zeggen dat het kind dood was want zij zeiden: Zie als het kind levend was spraken wij tot hem maar hij hoorde naar onze stem niet, hoe zullen wij dan tot hem zeggen: het kind is dood, want het mogt kwaad doen. Maar David hoorde dat zijne knechten mompelden, zoo merkte David dat het kind dood was, en hij zeide tot zijne knechten: is het kind dood? En zij zeiden: het is dood. Toen stond David op van de aarde en wiesch en zalfde zich en veranderde zijne kleeding en ging in het huis des Heeren en bad aan, daarna kwam hij in zijn huis en eischte brood en zij zetteden hem brood voor en hij at<c type="kp">_</c> Toen zeiden zijne knechten: wat is dit voor een ding dat gij gedaan hebt. om des levenden kinds wil hebt gij gevast en geweend maar nadat het kind gestorven is zijt gij opgestaan en hebt brood gegeten<c type="kp">_</c> En hij zeide<c type="kk">/</c> Als het kind nog leefde heb ik gevast en geweend want ik zeide: wie weet de Heer zoude mij mogen genadig zijn, dat het kind levend bleve. Maar nu is het dood<c type="kk">/</c> waarom zoude ik nu vasten, zal ik hem nog kunnen wederhalen? ik zal wel tot hem gaan maar hij zal tot mij niet wederkomen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En verder 1 Kon XIX:3-15 Toen Elia dat zag maakte hij zich op, en ging henen, om zijns levens wil, en kwam te Berseba dat in Juda is, en liet zijnen jongen aldaar. Maar hijzelf ging in de woestijn eene dagreis, en kwam en zat onder eenen jeneverboom, en bad, dat zijne ziel stierve, en zeide: Het is genoeg, neem nu Heer mijne ziel<c type="kp">_</c> Want ik ben niet beter dan mijne vaderen. En hij leide zich neder, en sliep onder den jeneverboom, en zie toen roerde een Engel hem aan, en zeide tot hem<c type="kk">/</c> sta op, eet! En hij zag om, en zie, aan zijn hoofdeneinde was een koek op kolen gebakken, en eene flesch met water, alzoo at hij, en dronk, en leide zich wederom neder. En de Engel des Heeren kwam ten anderen male weder en roerde hem aan en zeide: Sta op, eet! want de weg zoude voor u te veel zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo stond hij op, en at, en dronk en hij ging door de kracht dezer spijs, veertig dagen en veertig nachten, tot aan den berg Gods, Horeb.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En hij kwam aldaar in eene spelonk, en vernachtte aldaar, en zie, het woord des Heeren geschiedde tot hem: Wat maakt gij hier Elia? En hij zeide: ik heb zeer geijverd voor den Heer, den God der heirscharen, want de kinderen Israëls hebben uw verbond verlaten<c type="kk">/</c> Uwe altaren afgebroken en Uwe profeten met het zwaard gedood, en ik alleen ben overgebleven, en zij zoeken mijne ziel om die weg te nemen. En Hij zeide: Ga uit, en sta op dezen berg voor het aangezigt des Heeren. En zie de Heer ging voorbij, en een groote en sterke wind, scheurende de bergen en brekende de steenrotsen ging voor den Heer henen, doch de Heer was in den wind niet: en na dezen wind eene aardbeving: de Heer was ook in de aardbeving niet: en na de aardbeving een vuur, de Heer was ook in het vuur niet; en na het vuur het suizen van eene zachte stilte. En het geschiedde als Elia dat hoorde, dat Hij zijn aangezigt bewond met zijnen mantel, en uitging en stond in den ingang der spelonk. En zie eene stem kwam tot hem die zeide: Wat maakt gij hier Elia? En hij zeide: ik heb zeer geijverd voor den Heer<c type="kk">/</c> den God der Heirscharen, want de kinderen Israels hebben Uw verbond verlaten<c type="kk">/</c> Uwe altaren afgebroken en Uwe profeten met het zwaard gedood en ik alleen ben overgebleven, en zij zoeken mijne ziel om die weg te nemen. En de Heer zeide tot hem: Ga<c type="kk">/</c> keer weder op uwen weg.–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Toen deed hij den Bijbel weer digt en sprak lang en met onbeschrijfelijk veel gevoel hoe onze dagen en levensomstandigheden wel anders zijn dan die van David en Elia maar hoe toch hun God niet verre is van een iegelijk onzer en er ook voor ons versterking is van Boven, als wij zwak zijn dan zijn wij krachtig,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> uit den overvloed zijns harten<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> sprak zijn mond, de woorden vielen van Zijne lippen als de sneeuw of den regen van den hemel valt,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> het een volgde op het ander, dat was <hi rend="italics">het</hi>, het geloof.– Zij hebben een eigenaardigen klank die woorden op zulk een uur uit zulk een mond: Ik ben de opstanding en het leven, die in Mij gelooft zal leven al ware hij ook gestorven, en een iegelijk die leeft en in Mij gelooft zal niet sterven in eeuwigheid<c type="kp">_</c> Gelooft gij dat?<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> En ook dat andere woord: Het is niet gestorven maar het slaapt.–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Mijn Vader heeft ook gevoeld wat dezer dagen in U zal zijn omgegaan, onlangs stond ik nog des morgens vroeg bij het grafje op het kerkhof te Zundert<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> waarop staat: Laat de kinderkens tot Mij komen want derzulken is het koningrijk Gods<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Het is nu ruim 25 jaar geleden sedert Hij Zijn eerste jongsken daar begroef<c type="kk">/</c> in die dagen trof Hem een boek van Bungener<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> dat ik U gisteren zond<c type="kk">/</c> denkende het een boek ook naar Uw hart zou zijn. Alle dingen zullen medewerken ten goede dengenen die God liefhebben,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> dat heeft Hij (mijn Vader n.l.) wel ondervonden, en bij alles wat Hem zelven en zijnen kinderen wedervoer is Hij steeds gaandeweg sterker geworden tot nu toe<c type="kk">/</c> en heeft zijn geloof zich vaster geworteld, dat er een band is die ons nooit loslaat zelfs dan wanneer wij het meeste lijden<c type="kk">/</c> de band van Gods liefde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Toen Cromwell bij het lijkje van zijn jongske stond en als het ware een zwaard hem door de ziel ging, versterkte hem het woord: for I have learned<c type="kk">/</c> in what<c type="shy">-</c>soever state I am<c type="kk">/</c> therewith to be content. I know both how to be abased and know how to abound, every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry<c type="kk">/</c> both to abound and to suffer need<c type="kp">_</c> I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me. (Philip IV:11-13)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ben nu ongeveer 3 maanden aan de studie van Latijn en Grieksch en mijn meester Mendes da Costa, zeide dezer dagen toen ik hem er naar vroeg dat wij zoover gekomen waren als hij gemeend had wij komen zouden in dien tijd indien ik voor studie geschikt was, dus ben ik niet zonder hoop en ga met goed vertrouwen, met iets van <hi rend="italics">het oud vertrouwen</hi><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> van dag tot dag voort.– Vandaag komt mijne zuster Anna met den aanstaanden zwager te Amsterdam en ben niet weinig verlangend naar hen.– Duid het mij ten goede ik U zoo schrijf als ik doe<c type="kk">/</c> het was mij behoefte<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">mijne hartelijke groete aan Mevrouw en aan Betsy en geloof mij met een handdruk in gedachten aan U allen</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Yours truly</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Wilt U zoo goed zijn het ingesloten briefje aan Theo te geven.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Amsterdam, 3 August 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Theo told me of your loss in his last letter,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and I feel the need to write a few words to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">‘He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is Love’,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I heard <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_474">Rev. Keller van Hoorn</rs>, an old friend of my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs>, deliver a sermon on this text in Dordrecht one Sunday evening, a few days after the death of his daughter. He said: what has given me strength and kept me going after this, the most crushing blow I have ever been dealt, was faith in my God, without which I cannot live – I found comfort yet again in the great riches of His words. He couldn’t help opening the Bible that lay before him and, as though reliving that moment of heartbreak, hit upon the same passage as then, namely:</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">David therefore besought God for the child, when his child was very sick, and went in,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and lay all night upon the earth. And the elders of his house arose, and went to him, to raise him up from the earth: but he would not, neither did he eat bread with them. And it came to pass on the seventh day, that the child died. And the servants of David feared to tell him that the child was dead: for they said, Behold, while the child was yet alive, we spake unto him, and he would not hearken unto our voice: how will he then vex himself, if we tell him that the child is dead? But when David saw that his servants whispered, David perceived that the child was dead: therefore David said unto his servants, Is the child dead? And they said, He is dead. Then David arose from the earth, and washed, and anointed himself, and changed his apparel, and came into the house of the Lord, and worshipped: then he came to his own house; and when he required, they set bread before him, and he did eat. Then said his servants unto him, What thing is this that thou hast done? thou didst fast and weep for the child, while it was alive; but when the child was dead, thou didst rise and eat bread. And he said, While the child was yet alive, I fasted and wept: for I said, Who can tell whether God will be gracious to me, that the child may live? But now he is dead, wherefore should I fast? can I bring him back again? I shall go to him, but he shall not return to me.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And also 1 Kings XIX:3-15: And when Elijah saw that, he arose, and went for his life, and came to Beer-sheba, which belongeth to Judah, and left his servant there. But he himself went a day’s journey into the wilderness, and came and sat down under a juniper tree: and he requested for himself that he might die; and said, It is enough; now, O Lord, take away my life; for I am not better than my fathers. And as he lay and slept under a juniper tree, behold, then an angel touched him, and said unto him, Arise and eat. And he looked, and, behold, there was a cake baken on the coals, and a cruse of water at his head. And he did eat and drink, and laid him down again. And the Angel of the Lord came again the second time, and touched him, and said, Arise and eat; because the journey is too great for thee. And he arose, and did eat and drink, and went in the strength of that meat forty days and forty nights unto Horeb the mount of God.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And he came thither unto a cave, and lodged there; and, behold, the word of the Lord came to him, and he said unto him, What doest thou here, Elijah? And he said, I have been very jealous for the Lord God of hosts: for the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword; and I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away. And he said, Go forth, and stand upon the mount before the Lord. And, behold, the Lord passed by, and a great and strong wind rent the mountains, and brake in pieces the rocks before the Lord; but the Lord was not in the wind: and after the wind an earthquake; but the Lord was not in the earthquake: and after the earthquake a fire; but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the fire a still small voice. And it was so, when Elijah heard it, that he wrapped his face in his mantle, and went out, and stood in the entering in of the cave. And, behold, there came a voice unto him, and said, What doest thou here, Elijah? And he said, I have been very jealous for the Lord God of hosts: because the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thy altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword; and I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away. And the Lord said unto him, Go, return on thy way.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Then he closed the Bible and spoke at length and with incredible feeling about how our days and circumstances are different from those of David and Elijah, yet their God is not far from each and every one of us, and for us, too, there comes strength from Above, for when we are weak, then are we strong,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> his mouth spoke from the abundance of the heart,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> the words fell from his lips as the snow or the rain cometh down from heaven,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> one thing followed another, this was <hi rend="italics">it</hi>, faith. Those words have a special sound coming at such moments from such lips: I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth in Me, though he were dead, yet shall he live: and whosoever liveth and believeth in Me shall never die. Believest thou this?<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> And those other words too: She is not dead, but sleepeth.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">My <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs> has also felt what you will have been feeling these past days. I recently stood early one morning in the cemetery at Zundert<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> next to the little grave on which is written: Suffer the little children to come unto Me, for of such is the kingdom of God.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> More than 25 years have passed since he buried his first little boy there, in those days he was moved by a book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_550">Bungener</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> which I sent to you yesterday, thinking it would be a book after your own heart. All things will work together for good to them that love God,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> this has been his (namely my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs>’s) experience at least, and in everything that has befallen him and his children he has until now grown gradually stronger, and his faith has taken root more firmly, so that there is a bond that never lets go of us, not even when we suffer the most, the bond of God’s love.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">When <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_339">Cromwell</rs> was standing by his little boy’s body and a sword pierced his soul, as it were, these words gave him strength: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therewith to be content. I know both how to be abased and know how to abound, every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need. I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me (Philip IV:11-13).<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Have now been studying Latin and Greek for about 3 months and my tutor, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_520">Mendes da Costa</rs>, said a few days ago when I asked him about it that we had progressed as far as he thought we would in this amount of time if I were suited for study, so I am not without hope and I go on from day to day with good hope, with something of <hi rend="italics">the faith of old</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> My sister <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> is coming to Amsterdam today with my future <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">brother-in-law</rs> and I am looking forward not a little to seeing them. Do not think ill of me for writing to you as I have done, I felt the need to do it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">My warm regards to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_788">Mrs Tersteeg</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_789">Betsy</rs> and believe me, with a handshake in thought to all of you</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Would you be so good as to give the enclosed note to Theo?</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 3 Augustus 1877’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent enclosed a letter to Theo (<ref target="let125.xml">letter 125</ref>; see <ref target="#l-44">l. 44</ref>) with this letter of condolence. He traced over many of the letters to make them more readable.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jansen <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi> 2003-1</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Anna van Gogh and Joan van Houten’s visit to Amsterdam <ref target="let123.xml">(123)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On 24 July 1877, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1682">Marie Tersteeg</rs>, the third child of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787 bio.xml#_788">Mr and Mrs Tersteeg</rs>, died in The Hague; she was born on 2 May 1877 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi> and FR b2547-b2548, 1 and 2 August). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> also wrote a letter of condolence (FR b2549, 6 August 1877).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  1 John 4:8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Vincent had written to Theo on 21 January 1877 about this sermon preached by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_474">P.M. Keller van Hoorn</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let101.xml#n-29">see letter 101, nn. 29-31.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  2 Sam. 12:16-23. Van Gogh added the phrase ‘when his child was very sick’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-13">(l. 13)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  1 Kings 19:3-15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 12:10. The Statenvertaling has ‘machtig’ (powerful) instead of ‘krachtig’ (strong).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 12:34 and Luke 6:45.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Isa. 55:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  John 11:25-26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  Mark 5:39; cf. Luke 8:53.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>This visit to the cemetery at Zundert took place in the early morning of Sunday, 8 April 1877; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let110.xml">see letter 110</ref>. On 30 March 1852, exactly one year before Van Gogh was born, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> gave birth to a still-born child, whom they named Vincent. Cf. Hulsker 1985, pp. 21-22.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
  Mark 10:14 and Luke 18:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Although Van Gogh says that his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> had found consolation in the work of the French writer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_550">Laurence Louis Félix Bungener</rs> at the time of the first Vincent’s death, in 1852, in fact the book he refers to – <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Bij het lijkje van mijn kind: drie dagen uit het leven van een vader</hi> (Keeping vigil over the body of my child: three days in the life of a father) – was not published until 1863. Translated by W.G. Brill. Amsterdam 1863. The original version is <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_142"><hi rend="italics">Trois jours de la vie d’un père: quelques pages intimes</hi></ref>. Paris and Geneva 1863. This consolatory volume is the only work in Bungener’s oeuvre that would have been appropriate to the occasion.</p>

<p rend="indent">
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Bij het lijkje van mijn kind</hi> was written in the form of a diary covering the time from the death of Madeleine, the writer’s daughter, until her burial three days later. Bungener describes his life with his daughter, how he coped with his grief, and how he found support in his religious faith.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
  Rom. 8:28.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Van Gogh took this episode from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_685">Lamartine</rs>’s book <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_139"><hi rend="italics">Cromwell</hi></ref>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cromwell</hi>. Paris 1864, pp. 247-248 and cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let119.xml#n-4">letter 119, n. 4.</ref> The phrase ‘het zwaard dat door de ziel gaat’ (a sword pierced his soul) <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-75">(ll. 75-76)</ref> was derived from Jer. 4:10 and Luke 2:35. Lamartine also refers to this passage from Paul’s epistle to the Philippians, but he quotes it in French.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 42:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    