<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Monday, 27 August 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let128"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b126 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>128</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>107</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>127</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-08-27">Monday, 27 August 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0126" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000135_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000135_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0126" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000135_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000135_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amsterdam 27 Aug. 1877.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het gaat tegen Moe’s verjaardag,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> daarom stuur ik U hierbij een couponnetje van f<c type="kp">_</c> 1.23 1/2, want ik zou wel gaarne met U zamen iets geven. Het is niet veel maar alles wat ik heb, als Gij er evenveel bijlegt dan kunnen wij er echter eene goede Photographie voor hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Gij zult er zelf wel eene uitkiezen. Le Christ marchant sur la mer van Jalabert is weer duurder,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> daar had ik anders aan gedacht en weer heel veel duurder zijn de Emmausgangers van Rembrandt.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Enfin Gij weet het ook wel en zult wel eene goede keus doen, maar schrijf, des noods op een briefkaart, den titel van wat gij zult gekozen hebben. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dank voor Uw brief waar ik zeer<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> blij mede was, even als met een opgewekten brief van huis die gisteren kwam.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Gisteren was het een regenachtigen morgen zoodat ik mijn overjas reeds aantrok om naar de vroegpreek in de Noorderkerk te gaan. Daar preekte D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Posth. Meyes (de jonge d<hi rend="super">s</hi> nl.) over Hand<c type="kp">_</c> 4:12 &amp; 12<hi rend="super">a</hi> <c type="kk">/</c> Deze is de steen die van de bouwlieden veracht is, welke tot een hoofd des hoeks geworden is<c type="kp">_</c> En de zaligheid is in geenen anderen want er is ook onder den Hemel geen andere naam die onder de menschen gegeven is, door welken wij moeten zalig worden.─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Die D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Meyes preekt zeer goed<c type="kk">/</c> ook is het een lust om Zijne zoons<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> aan te zien, zoo als zij bij Hem in de kerk zitten. Hij heeft eene zeer schoone maar bijna al te krachtige stem, in eene zeer groote kerk klinkt dat echter wel goed en zijn uiterlijk is zeer eigen<c type="shy">-</c>aardig, schreef U reeds hoe dat mij getroffen had, toen ik hem eens van den preekstoel zag afkomen. Mij dunkt Hij moet goed kunnen preeken over “Wilde vijgeboomen”<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en den olijfberg<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en b.v. over een tekst als “vruchten voortbrengen des berouws en der bekeering waardig”<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> of “de droefheid naar God werkt eene onberouwelijke keuze tot zaligheid”<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> of over Zaccheus<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Gij begrijpt wel wat ik meen<c type="kk">/</c> men kan het hem aanzien waar zijn hart en gedachten altijd zijn en van welken geest Hij is; als men Hem aanziet denkt men dadelijk aan een priester en een heilige.─ Zijn zoon kwam gisteren hier en was eenigen tijd op het studeerkamertje, kwam n.l. vragen of ik dezen avond daar aan huis<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> wilde komen, wat ik gaarne heb aangenomen. Was ook nog eens bij den ouden D<hi rend="super">s</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zijn vader<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> verl. week.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Was gisteren morgen ook in de Eilands kerk bij Oom Stricker<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Die sprak over Luk<c type="kp">_</c> XI:28. Maar Hij zeide: Ja zalig zijn degenen die het woord Gods hooren en het bewaren, bragt daarbij te pas Maria de Moeder van Jezus die al deze dingen bewaarde<c type="kk">/</c> ze overleggende in Haar hart<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en over Maria van Bethanie die aan de voeten van Jezus zat en het goede deel had uitgekozen dat van haar niet zou worden weggenomen.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Des middags en een gedeelte van den avond ben ik bij Oom Stricker geweest en had dus een goeden Zondag, heb dikwijls gedacht hoe Gij het zoudt hebben. Er was t’huis een goeden brief van Anna geweest schreef Pa, zij had het druk doordien er zooveel logés waren, maar scheen zeer gelukkig te zijn en Moe is reeds aan haar uitzet bezig.─<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zoudt Gij in het najaar de reis<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> doen en dan ook naar Amsterdam komen? Van harte hoop ik dat, schrijf het eens zoodra Gij iets dienaangaande hoort<c type="kp">_</c> En wij moeten het zoo zien te schikken Gij hier kwaamt logeeren<c type="kk">/</c> er is in huis plaats genoeg en het hoeft maar een woord aan Oom te kosten, wij moeten maar woekeren met den tijd en gelegenheid om zamen te zijn. Heb vandaag nog heel wat te werken, hebt Gij het druk in de zaak?</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Verl. week is er op de Werf een schip (monitor de Draak) te water geloopen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> dat was interessant om te zien en eene groote vreugde voor het werk<c type="shy">-</c>volk. Op Bickerseiland zijn ook veel scheepstimmerwerven maar voor kleinere vaartuigen, als ik er kom zie ik ze altijd maar eens goed aan, als men zelf wil leeren werken moet men op de werklieden letten, en als men een studeerkamertje heeft op de werkplaatsen<c type="kk">/</c> want even als op een scheepstimmerwerf in aanbouw zijnde grootere en kleinere schepen liggen die geleidelijk klaar komen en ook van stapel loopen zoo moeten ook op een studeerkamer grootere en kleinere werken worden ontworpen en “by patient continuance in well doing”<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> voortgezet en ook met Gods zegen voleindigd.─<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> En er staat ook “Laat niet varen het werk uwer handen,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> zijt dan lang moedig<c type="kk">/</c> zie<c type="kk">/</c> de landman verwacht de kostelijke vrucht des lands, lang moedig zijnde over dezelve totdat het den vroegen en spaden regen zal hebben ontvangen; Weest ook gij lang moedig en versterkt uwe harten”.─<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">There is something good in all labour.─<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Dit is ook een mooien tekst: Acht het voor groote vreugde, mijne broeders<c type="kk">/</c> als gij in velerlei verzoekingen valt. Wetende dat de beproeving uws geloofs lijdzaamheid werkt<c type="kp">_</c> Doch de lijdzaamheid hebbe een volmaakt werk opdat gij moogt volmaakt zijn en geheel opregt “in geen ding achterlijk”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">En indien iemand van u Wijsheid ontbreekt, dat hij ze van God begeere, Die een iegelijk</hi> <hi rend="italics">mildelijk geeft en niet verwijt en zij zal hem gegeven worden</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Maar dat hij ze begeere in geloof, niet twijfelende, want die twijfelt, is eene baar der zee gelijk die van den wind gedreven en op en neer geworpen wordt.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Laat ons daarom ons hart<c type="kk">/</c> ons verlangen en onzen geest vastzetten op de eene of andere goede zaak, voor ons leven, en die begeeren van den Heer.─<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> ik voor mij begeer ze zoo zeer<c type="kk">/</c> die wijsheid die wij in onzen Vader en Moeder zien<c type="kk">/</c> bij hen in meerdere mate dan ergens anders, er is geen huis als het onze en mij dunkt onder edelen en goeden, onder “les hommes de bonne volonté” zooals velen der schilders en schrijvers<c type="kk">/</c> geen die meer is dan onze Vader.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Laat ons maar blijven zoeken of wij er ook iets van vinden mogten, “faites bien ce que vous faites”<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> en alle werk is Gods werk,<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> door oefening wordt de kunst verkregen<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> en “polissez le sans cesse et le repolissez”,<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> creusez<c type="kk">/</c> fouillez, bêchez, ne laissez nulle place, où la main ne passe et repasse,<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> deze woorden in gedachten houdende en er naar doende zal er wel iets van teregt komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Jongen, ik verlang zoo naar U, kom maar spoedig met de nouveautés en zie het zoo te schikken wij eenigen tijd kunnen zamen zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Zouden wij misschien nog een Zondag hier zamen kunnen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> zoo gaarne zou ik wenschen Gij de Oude zijds kapel eens zaagt en er den een of ander als D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Laurillard of Oom Stricker eens hoordet. Toe zie het te schikken. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Dat boek van Daudet waarover Gij schrijft ken ik niet maar hebt Gij ooit gelezen “A life for a life” door de schrijfster van John Halifax,<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> kunt Gij dat eens krijgen lees het dan, het is vol van het geloof en ook van de natuur, van de hei en van steden als Liverpool en iedere bladzijde is geest en leven.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet aan de Grieksche themas<c type="kk">/</c> groet Uwe huisgenooten en ook Mauve &amp; Jet<ptr target="#note-t-35"/> als Gij er komt<c type="kp">_</c> Heb het geschrift van de gelijkenissen en wonderen in het Fransch af gekregen en in het Engelsch moet van avond af. à Dieu<c type="kk">/</c> beste broer, een hartelijken handdruk in gedachten<c type="kk">/</c> gaarne stuurde ik U meer voor Moe’s verjaardag maar ’t kan niet<c type="kk">/</c> heb het zoo goed mogelijk, het is wel goed Gij die dagen bij den Hr Tersteeg<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> in huis zijt geweest dunkt mij. Geloof mij steeds</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Uw zoo liefh<c type="kp">_</c> broer </p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>


<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Oom Jan heeft plan voor 8 dagen naar Helvoirt te gaan met 1 Sept<c type="kp">_</c>, dan hoop ik daarvan te profiteeren door s’avonds lang beneden in de kamer te zitten schrijven, dat kan ik anders ook wel maar Ooms slaapkamer is vlak bij en ik moet dus voorzigtig zijn. Kan wel op mijn slaapkamer gaan zitten maar daar is de verzoeking om te gaan rusten te sterk als het laat is en op mijn studeerkamertje is geen gas.─</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Gij weet dat de oude Vader Lips is gestorven.<ptr target="#note-t-37"/> Bij de begrafenis sprak Pa over de begrafenis in het koren van v.d. Maaten<ptr target="#note-t-38"/> en ook over I Thess. IV:13-18, V:1-10<c type="kk">/</c> dat is <hi rend="italics">het</hi><ptr target="#note-t-39"/> wel even als Mark<c type="kp">_</c> IV:26-29 en Joh<c type="kp">_</c> XII:24 en I Kor<c type="kp">_</c> XV:35-38, 40-58<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Daar net een goede brief van Anna. Haar brieven zijn nog al zeldzaam dus stuur ik U dezen om te lezen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Amsterdam, 27 Aug. 1877.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It’s nearing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s birthday,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> so I’m sending you herewith a money order for 1.23  1/2  guilders, because I’d very much like to give something together with you. It isn’t much, but it’s all I have; if you add the same amount to it then we can nonetheless get a good photograph.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You may certainly choose one yourself. Christ walking on the sea by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1114">Jalabert</rs> is more expensive still,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> otherwise I’d have suggested it, and even much more expensive is Supper at Emmaus by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Enfin, you know it too and will surely make a good choice, but write the title of what you’ve chosen, on a postcard if necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Thanks for your letter, which I was very<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> happy to get, as also with a cheerful letter from home that arrived yesterday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Yesterday morning was rainy, so I put on my overcoat to go to the early sermon in the Noorderkerk. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_575">The Rev. Posthumus Meijjes</rs> (that is, the young minister) was preaching there on Acts 4:12 and 12a,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> This is the stone which was set at nought of the builders, which is become the head of the corner. Neither is there salvation in any other: for there is none other name under Heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_575">Rev. Meijjes</rs> preaches very well, it’s also a treat to see his sons<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> sitting with him in church. He has a very beautiful voice, though it’s almost too powerful, it sounds good, however, in a very large church, and his appearance is very striking, already wrote to you about how it moved me to see him come down from the pulpit once. It seems to me that he must be able to speak well on the ‘sycamore trees’<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and the Mount of Olives<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and, for example, on a text like ‘bring forth therefore fruits worthy of repentance and reform’,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> or ‘godly sorrow worketh a choice of salvation not to be repented of’,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> or on Zacchaeus.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> You surely understand what I mean, one can tell where his heart and thoughts always are and of what mind he is; when one looks at him one immediately thinks of a priest and a saint. His son came here yesterday and spent a while in the little study, he came in fact to ask if I would visit them at home this evening,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> which I gladly agreed to. Went again last week to see the old minister, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_571">his father</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Also went yesterday morning to the Eilandskerk to hear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> who spoke on Luke XI:28. But He said, Yea rather, blessed are they that hear the word of God, and keep it, mentioning the example of Mary the mother of Jesus who kept all these things, pondering them in her heart,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and on Mary of Bethany who sat at Jesus’ feet and had chosen that good part, which would not be taken away from her.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I spent the afternoon and part of the evening at Uncle Stricker’s and so had a good Sunday, often thinking of what you were doing. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> wrote that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> had written a good letter home, she was busy because there were so many people staying, but seemed to be very happy, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> is already busy putting together her trousseau.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Will you be making the trip<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> in the autumn and come to Amsterdam then as well? I sincerely hope so, write as soon as you hear anything about it. And we must arrange for you to come and stay here, there is room enough in the house and you only have to let <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle</rs> know, we must make the most of the time and opportunity to be together. Still have a lot of work to do today, are you busy in the gallery?
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Last week at the dockyard a ship (monitor the Draak) was launched;<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> that was interesting to see and a great joy for the workers. There are also a lot of shipyards on Bickerseiland, but for smaller craft; whenever I go there I take a good look at them, if one wants to learn how to work oneself one must pay attention to the workers, and to the workshops if one has a little study, for just as in a shipyard there are smaller and larger ships that are eventually finished and launched, in a study there are larger and smaller works planned and carried on ‘by patient continuance in well doing’<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> and completed with God’s blessing.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> And it is also written ‘Forsake not the works of thine own hands,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> be patient, behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, until he receive the early and latter rain. Be ye also patient; stablish your hearts’.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">There is something good in all labour.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">This is also a beautiful text: My brethren, count it all joy when ye fall into divers temptations; knowing this, that the trying of your faith worketh patience. But let patience have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, ‘wanting nothing’.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">If any of you lack Wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.</hi> But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea driven with the wind and tossed.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> Let us therefore fix our hearts, our desires and our minds on one good thing or another, for life, and ask that of the Lord.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> For my part I desire so much to have the wisdom we see in our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Father and Mother</rs>, in them to a greater extent than anywhere else, there is no family like ours, even, it seems to me, among good and noble people, among ‘the men of good will’, like many painters and writers, none better than our Father.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Let us but continue to seek and see whether we may also find something of it, ‘do well what you do’<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> and all work is the work of God,<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> practice makes perfect,<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> and ‘polish it and repolish it unceasingly’,<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> work, take pains, dig, burrow, turn over, let there be no place your hand has not touched and retouched,<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> keeping these words in mind and acting on them will make some of it turn out right.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Old boy, I long for you so, do come soon with the <hi rend="italics">nouveautés</hi>, and make sure to arrange it so that we can spend some time together.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Will we perhaps be able to have another Sunday here together? I’d be so happy if you could see the Oudezijdskapel sometime and hear one of the ministers like the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_53">Rev. Laurillard</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>. Do try to arrange it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I don’t know that book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs> you wrote about, but have you ever read ‘A life for a life’ by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_713">the woman</rs> who wrote John Halifax?<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> If you can get it sometime, do read it, it’s full of faith and also of nature, of the heath and of cities like Liverpool, and each page is spirit and life.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> Now I must work on the Greek themes, give my regards to your housemates, and also to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321">Jet</rs><ptr target="#note-t-35"/> if you go there. Have finished the text with the parables and miracles in French, and must finish it in English this evening. Adieu, dear brother, a hearty handshake in thought, I’d gladly send you more for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s birthday but can’t, I wish you the very best, it seems very good to me that you spent those days at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787 bio.xml#_788">Mr Tersteeg’s</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> Believe me ever</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs> is planning to go to Helvoirt for a week on 1 Sept., I hope to profit by it by sitting downstairs for a long time in the evening in the living room and writing, I could do it anyway, but Uncle’s bedroom is nearby, so I have to be quiet. Can go and sit in my bedroom, but there the temptation to rest is too great when it’s late, and there’s no gas in my little study.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">You know that old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_488">Father Lips</rs> died.<ptr target="#note-t-37"/> At the funeral <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> spoke about The burial in the cornfield by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1191">Van der Maaten</rs><ptr target="#note-t-38"/> and also about I Thess. IV:13-18, V:1-10, that is surely <hi rend="italics">it</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-39"/> as is Mark IV:26-29 and John XII:24 and I Cor. XV:35-38, 40-58.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Just had a good letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>. Her letters are quite rare, so I’m sending you this one to read.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 27 Aug.1877.’</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is working on his <hi rend="italics">loci communis</hi> notebook <ref target="let127.xml">(127)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Mrs van Gogh turned 58 on 10 September.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1114">Charles François Jalabert</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Christ walking on the waves</hi>. The price mentioned means that Vincent must be referring to the reproduction <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Christ marchant sur la mer</hi> in the series ‘Album de Photographies’ (17 x 25 cm.), which cost 6 francs (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1845">Ill. 1845</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1735"><hi rend="italics">Pilgrims at Emmaus</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let042.xml#n-9">see letter 42, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>It is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘weer’ instead of ‘zeer’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The intended passage is Acts 4:11-12; the mistake could have been caused by mistaking the Bible’s place reference (the letter ‘a’) for a verse reference.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In 1877, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_575">Jeremias Posthumus Meijjes</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_219">his wife</rs> had seven children (five sons and two daughters): <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_162">Christiaan Bernard</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_163">Reinier</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_164">Willem</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_165">Leonard</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_166">Guliana Cornelia</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_167">Egbert Johannes Wernhardt</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_168">Catharina</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Biblical; see, for example, 1 Kings 10:27, 1 Chron. 27:28, 2 Chron. 1:15, 2 Chron. 9:27, Ps. 78:47 and Isa. 9:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The Mount of Olives, as told of in the four Gospels.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 3:8 and Luke 3:8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  2 Cor. 7:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Zaccheus was the ‘chief among the publicans’; see Luke 19:2-8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_575">Jeremias Posthumus Meijjes</rs> lived with his family at Prinsengracht 851.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_571">Reinier Posthumus Meijjes</rs> lived at Prinsengracht 1003.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>On 26 August, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">J.P. Stricker</rs> preached at 10 a.m. in the Eilandskerk.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Luke 2:19.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Luke 10:42.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> would marry one year later, on 22 August 1878.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Theo undertook the sales trips for Goupil, to present the new editions (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">nouveautés</hi>) to potential customers <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-78">(see l. 78).</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>The ‘ram monitor’ <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Draak</hi> (Dragon) first class – an ironclad vessel with very low freeboard, used in naval warfare – was laid down on 15 November 1875 at the Rijkswerf and launched on 22 August 1877 at 13.30 (The Hague, Collectie Instiuut voor Maritieme Historie, Marinestaf). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1846">Ill. 1846</rs>. The launch was reported in the ‘Stadsnieuws’ in the evening edition of the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Amsterdamsche Courant</hi> of Wednesday, 22 August.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>
  Rom. 2:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Cf. Ps. 138:8 and Rev. 17:17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 138:8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>
  Jas. 5:7-8.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>For this expression, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let108.xml#n-24">see letter 108, n. 24.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  Jas. 1:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>
  Jas. 1:2-6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>Cf. John 11:22.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>Cf. the French saying ‘Fais ce que tu fais’ and the Latin ‘Age quod agis’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>Cf. John 6:28-29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>Cf. the Dutch expression ‘Oefening baart kunst’ (practice creates art).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_21">Boileau</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let127.xml#n-19">see letter 127, n. 19.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_602">La Fontaine</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let127.xml#n-20">see letter 127, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="33" xml:id="note-t-33">
                            
  
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_713">Dinah Mulock Craik</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_75"><hi rend="italics">A life for a life</hi></ref> and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_74"><hi rend="italics">John Halifax, gentleman</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let088.xml#n-18">see letter 88, n. 18.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="34" xml:id="note-t-34">
                            

<p>Cf. John 6:63.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="35" xml:id="note-t-35">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321">Jet Mauve-Carbentus</rs>, Anton Mauve’s wife.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="36" xml:id="note-t-36">
                            

<p>Theo presumably stood by the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787 bio.xml#_788">Tersteeg family</rs> during the period of mourning following the death of their daughter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1682">Marie</rs> on 24 July 1877. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let125.xml">See letter 125</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="37" xml:id="note-t-37">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_488">Jacobus Lips</rs> died on Tuesday, 14 August and was buried on Thursday, 16 August (FR b2551).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="38" xml:id="note-t-38">
                            
  
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1191">Van der Maaten</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1719">The funeral in the cornfield</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let036.xml#n-2">see letter 36, n. 2.</ref> Van Gogh gave an impression of the lithograph to his teacher <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_520">M.B. Mendes da Costa</rs> in 1877 or 1878. He copied out biblical texts, some of them in Latin, and quotations from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">Longfellow</rs> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="RM03.xml#n-3">(cf. RM3, n.1)</ref> in the margins. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1912">Ill. 1912</rs> (Amsterdam, Universiteitsbibliotheek, Ms. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">XIII C</hi> 13 a). See Kōdera in exhib. cat. Osaka 1986, pp. 87-88.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="39" xml:id="note-t-39">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs>’s motto.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    