<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Wasmes, Thursday, 26 December 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let149"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b147 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>149</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>127</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>148</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1878-12-26">Thursday, 26 December 1878</date>
                            <placeName>Wasmes</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0147" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000155_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000155_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0147" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000155_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000155_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000155_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Petites Wasmes 26 Dec<c type="kp">_</c> 1878</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Borinage Hainaut<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het is tijd dat ik U weer eens schrijf<c type="kk">/</c> vooreerst ook om U geluk te wenschen bij het begin van een nieuw jaar. Moge veel goeds Uw deel zijn en Gods zegen rusten op Uw werk in dit jaar dat wij beginnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Zeer verlangend ben ik naar een brief van U om weer eens te hooren hoe Gij het hebt en hoe het U gaat<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> ook om misschien eens te hooren of Gij in den laatsten tijd iets moois en merk<c type="shy">-</c>waardigs hebt gezien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wat mij aangaat, gij begrijpt wel dat er hier in de Borinage geen schilderijen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> dat men zelfs over ’t algemeen ganschelijk niet<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> weet wat een Schilderij is<c type="kk">/</c> zoodan spreekt het van zelf dat ik op ’t gebied van kunst ten eenemale niets heb gezien sedert mijn vertrek uit Brussel.─ Maar dit neemt niet weg dat het hier een zeer eigenaardig en zeer schilderachtig land is, alles spreekt als het ware en is vol karakter. Dezer dagen<c type="kk">/</c> de donkere dagen voor Kerstmis<c type="kk">/</c> lag er sneeuw. Alles herinnerde toen aan die middeneeuwsche Sch<hi rend="super">ijen</hi> van Boeren Breugel o.a. en van zooveel anderen die het eigenaardig effekt van rood &amp; groen<c type="kk">/</c> zwart &amp; wit zoo treffend hebben weten uit te drukken. Telkens weer doet hetgeen men hier ziet denken aan het werk b.v. van Thijs Maris of van Albert Durer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Er zijn hier holle wegen begroeid met dorenstruiken en met oude verwrongen boomen met hunne grillige wortels die volmaakt gelijken op dien weg op de ets van Durer<c type="kk">/</c> Le chevalier et la mort.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Zoo b.v. dezer dagen was het een eigenaardig gezigt met de witte sneeuw s’avonds tegen het uur der schemering de arbeiders uit de mijnen huiswaarts te zien keeren. Deze lieden zijn geheel zwart als zij uit de donkere mijnen weer in het daglicht komen<c type="kk">/</c> gelijkerwijs de schoorsteenvegers zien zij er uit<c type="kp">_</c> Hunne woningen zijn meestal klein en veeleer hutten te noemen<c type="kk">/</c> verspreid ook langs die holle wegen en in het bosch en tegen de helling der heuvels<c type="kp">_</c> Hier en daar ziet men nog bemoste daken en vriendelijk schijnt het licht s’avonds door de vensters met kleine ruiten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Gelijk bij ons in Brabant het hakhout &amp; de eikenstruiken en in Holland de knotwilgen zoo ziet men hier om de tuinen<c type="kk">/</c> velden en akkers die zwarte dorenheggen. Met de sneeuw dezer dagen maakte dat een effekt als van een letterschrift op wit papier zooals de bladzijden van het Evangelie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Reeds onderscheidene malen heb ik hier gesproken zoowel in een vrij groot<c type="kk">/</c> voor godsdienstige zamenkomsten opzettelijk ingerigt vertrek<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> als in de bijeenkomsten die men gewoon is s’avonds in de arbeiderswoningen te houden<c type="kk">/</c> die men het best Bijbellezingen noemen kan. Sprak o.a<c type="kp">_</c> over: de gelijkenis v.h. mostaardzaad,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> den onvruchtbaren vijgeboom,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> de blindgeborene.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Op Kerstmis natuurlijk over de stal v<c type="kp">_</c> Bethlehem<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en Vrede op aarde.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Mogt het onder Gods zegen zoo geschieden dat ik hier ieverans<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> voor vast werd geplaatst<c type="kk">/</c> dat zou ik van harte gaarne wenschen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Overal ziet men hier in het rond de groote schoorsteenen &amp; de ontzettende bergen steenkolen aan den ingang der mijnen, de zoogenaamde charbonnages. Gij kent die groote teekening v<c type="kp">_</c> Bosboom<c type="kk">/</c> Chaudfontaine<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> die geeft goed het karakter van het land hier weer, alleen hier is alles steenkolen<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t noorden v<c type="kp">_</c> Henegouwen steengroeven en Chaudfontaine meer ijzer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Zoo dikwijls denk ik nog aan den dag toen Gij te Brussel zijt geweest en aan ons bezoek aan ’t Museum.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> En dikwijls zou ik wenschen dat Gij wat digter in de buurt waart en wij wat meer konden zamenzijn<c type="kp">_</c> Schrijf maar weer eens spoedig. Telkens weer bezie ik die ets van Un jeune citoyen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> De taal van de mijnwerkers is zoo heel gemakkelijk niet te verstaan maar men begrijpt het gewone Fransch goed mits men het maar vlug en grif spreken kan<c type="kk">/</c> dan heeft het vanzelf overeenkomst met hun patois<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> dat verbazend snel wordt gesproken. Op eene bijeenkomst deze week sprak ik over den tekst 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Actes XVI:9 “Et Paul eut de nuit une vision d’un homme Macédonien qui se présenta devant lui et le pria disant<c type="kk">/</c> Passe en Macédoine et nous aide”.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en daar luisterde men met aandacht naar toen ik beproefde om te beschrijven hoedanig die Macedonier was die behoefte had en verlangen naar den troost van het Evangelie en naar de kennis van den Eenigen Waarachtigen God. Hoe wij ons hem moeten voorstellen als een arbeider met trekken van smart en lijden en vermoeienis op het gelaat zonder gedaante of heerlijkheid maar met eene onsterfelijke ziel die behoefte heeft aan de Spijze die niet vergaat<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> n.l. het Woord Gods<c type="kk">/</c> omdat de mensch niet leven kan bij brood alleen maar bij alle woord dat door den mond Gods uitgaat.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Hoe Jezus X<hi rend="super">tus</hi> de Meester<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> is die een zoodanig man als die Macedonier, een werkman en arbeider die een moeielijk leven heeft<c type="kk">/</c> kan sterken<c type="kk">/</c> troosten en verlichten<c type="kp">_</c> Omdat Hij zelf is de groote Man van Smarten<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> en die onze krankheden kent<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> die zelf genaamd werd de Zoon des timmermans<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> hoewel Hij de Zone Gods was en de groote Medicijnmeester der kranke zielen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Die 30 jaren lang arbeidde in eene nederige timmermanswerkplaats om den wil Gods te volbrengen; en God wil dat in navolging van X<hi rend="super">tus</hi> de mensch nederig zal leven en wandelen op aarde<c type="kk">/</c> niet trachtende naar hooge dingen maar zich voegende naar de nederige<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-21"/> door het Evangelie leerende zachtmoedig te zijn &amp; nederig van hart.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Reeds had ik gelegenheid om eenige zieken te bezoeken omdat hier veel kranken zijn. Schreef heden aan de President van het comité d’Evangelisation<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> om hem te vragen dat mijn zaak op de eerstkomende vergadering van het comité zou mogen behandeld worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het heeft van nacht gedooid<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan U niet zeggen hoe schilderachtig het heuvelachtige land nu is met het dooiweer, nu de sneeuw aan het smelten is en de zwarte akkers met het groen van het winterkoren weer zigtbaar worden. Voor een vreemdeling zijn de dorpen hier waarlijk een doolhof met de ontelbare naauwe straten en steegen van kleine arbeiderswoningen, zoowel beneden aan den voet als tegen de helling en op den top van de heuvels. Het is nog het best te vergelijken bij een dorp als Scheveningen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral de achterbuurten<c type="kk">/</c> of bij die dorpen in Bretagne die wij uit de Schilderijen kennen. Trouwens gij zijt zelf hier door deze streek heen gespoord op Uwe reis naar en van Parijs, en zult het U mogelijk eenigermate herinneren. De Kerkjes der Protestanten zijn klein<c type="kk">/</c> gelijken op die te Hoeve<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> maar iets grooter<c type="kk">/</c> maar waar ik gesproken heb dat is maar een eenvoudig groot vertrek dat een 100tal personen desnoods kan bevatten. Ook woonde ik eene godsdienstoefening bij in een stal of schuur dus is het eenvoudig en oorspronkelijk genoeg.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Schrijf eens spoedig als gij tijd hebt en weet dat Gij telkens weer<c type="kk">/</c> ja voortdurend in mijne gedachten zijt<c type="kp">_</c> U nogmaals toewenschende dat Gods besten zegen in het nieuwe jaar Uw deel moge zijn en U in gedachten de hand drukkende<c type="kk">/</c> geloof mij steeds</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Uw zoo liefh<c type="kp">_</c> broer</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Groet allen bij Roos en wensch hun allen veel heil en zegen in ’t nieuwe jaar als ook aan een iegelijk die mogelijk naar mij mogt vragen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Als gij schrijft adresseer s.v.p. uw brief adres M. van der Haegen<c type="kk">/</c> Colporteur à <hi rend="italics">Pâturages</hi> près de Mons (Borinage Haînaut)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Zooeven bezocht ik een oud moedertje in een kolenbrandersgezin<c type="kp">_</c> Zij is bitter krank maar geloovig en geduldig<c type="kp">_</c> Ik las een hoofdstuk met haar en bad met hen allen<c type="kp">_</c> Het volk hier heeft wel iets eigenaardigs en aantrekkelijks vanwege zijne eenvoudigheid en goedhartigheid gelijkerwijs ook het Brabantsche volk te Zundert &amp; Etten.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Petit-Wasmes, 26 Dec. 1878</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Borinage Hainaut<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">It’s time I write to you again, first of all to wish you happiness at the beginning of a new year. May much good be your share, and God’s blessing be on your work in this year that we’re beginning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’m eagerly longing for a letter from you, to hear again how things are going and how you are,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> also perhaps to hear if you have recently seen anything beautiful or remarkable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">As far as I’m concerned, you surely understand that there are no paintings here in the Borinage, that in general they haven’t the slightest idea of what a painting is, so it goes without saying that I’ve seen absolutely nothing in the way of art since my departure from Brussels. But this doesn’t mean that this isn’t a very special and very picturesque country, everything speaks, as it were, and is full of character. There was snow these last few days, the dark days before Christmas. Then everything was reminiscent of the medieval paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_909">Peasant Bruegel</rs>, among others, and by so many others who were so good at expressing the singular effect of red and green, black and white. Time and again, what one sees here reminds one of the work of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Albrecht Dürer</rs>, for example.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">There are sunken roads here, overgrown with thorn-bushes and with old, twisted trees with their gnarled roots, which look exactly like that road in the etching by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Dürer</rs>, The knight and Death.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">These last few days, for instance, it was an extraordinary sight, with the white snow in the evening around the twilight hour, seeing the workers returning home from the mines. These people are completely black when they come out of the dark mines into the daylight again, they look just like chimney-sweeps. Their houses are usually small and could better be called huts, scattered along the sunken roads and in the wood and against the slopes of the hills. One sees moss-covered roofs here and there, and the light shines kindly in the evening through the small-paned windows.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Just as in Brabant we have the copse and the oak wood, and in Holland the pollard willows, so here one sees those black thorn-bushes around the gardens, fields and land. The recent snow gave it the effect of letters written on white paper, like the pages of the gospel.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’ve already spoken here at various times, both in a fairly large room, specially furnished for religious meetings,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and in the gatherings that are customarily held in the workers’ houses in the evenings, which one can best call Bible-reading. Spoke, among other things, on: the parable of the mustard seed,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> the barren fig tree,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> the man who was blind from his birth.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> On Christmas, of course, on the stable of Bethlehem,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and Peace on earth.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">May it come to pass with God’s blessing that I be placed here permanently somewhere; I should sincerely wish it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Everywhere around here one sees the big chimneys and the huge mountains of coal at the entrance to the mines, the so-called coal-pits. You know that large drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_884">Bosboom</rs>, Chaudfontaine,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> it conveys the character of the land here well, only here everything is coal, in the north of Hainaut stone-quarries, and Chaudfontaine more iron ore.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I still think so often of that day when you were in Brussels and of our visit to the Museum.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And I often wish that you were a bit closer and we could be together more often. Do write again soon. Again and again I look at that etching of A young citizen.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> The mine-workers’ language is not all that easy to understand, but they understand normal French well if one can speak it rapidly and fluently, then it naturally resembles their dialect, which is spoken amazingly fast. At a gathering this week I spoke on the text 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Acts XVI:9 ‘And a vision appeared to Paul in the night; There stood a man of Macedonia, and prayed him, saying, Come over into Macedonia, and help us.’<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> And they listened attentively when I tried to describe what that Macedonian was like who needed and longed for the comfort of the gospel and the knowledge of the Only True God. How we should imagine him as a worker with signs of sorrow and suffering and fatigue on his face, without form or glory but with an immortal soul that has need of the meat which endureth unto everlasting life,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> namely the Word of God, for man cannot live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">How Jesus Christ is the Master<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> who can strengthen, comfort and enlighten a man like the Macedonian, a workman and labourer who has a hard life. Because He himself is the great Man of Sorrows,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> who knows our diseases,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> who himself is called the carpenter’s son,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> even though He was the Son of God and the great physician of sick souls.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Who worked for 30 years in a humble carpenter’s workshop to carry out God’s will; and God wants man to live and walk humbly upon the earth, in imitation of Christ, minding not high things, but condescending to men of low estate,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> learning from the gospel to be meek and lowly in heart.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ve already had the opportunity to visit a few sick people, for many people here are ill. Wrote today to the president of the Comité d’Evangelisation<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> to request that my case be brought before the next meeting of the committee.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">It thawed last night, I cannot tell you how picturesque the hilly countryside looks in the thaw, now that the snow is melting and the black fields with the green of the winter wheat are again becoming visible. For foreigners the villages here are truly a maze, with countless narrow streets and alleyways with the small houses of the workers, at the foot of the hills as well as on their slopes and at the top. It can best be compared to a village like Scheveningen, especially the poor quarters, or to those villages in Brittany that we know from paintings. For that matter, you rode through this region yourself on the railway journey to and from Paris, and maybe remember it a little. The Protestant churches are small, similar to the one in Hoeven,<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> but slightly larger, but where I spoke was only a simple, large room that can hold a hundred people if necessary. I also attended a service in a stable or barn, so it’s quite simple and novel.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Write soon when you have the time, and remember that you are repeatedly, even constantly, in my thoughts. Wishing again that God’s best blessings may be your share in the new year, and shaking your hand in thought, believe me ever</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Your most loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Give my regards to everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’ and wish them all, and anyone who should happen to ask after me, a happy New Year.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> If you write, please address your letter care of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_801">M. Vanderhaegen</rs>, Colporteur à <hi rend="italics">Pâturages</hi> près de Mons (Borinage Haînaut).<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I just visited an old mother in a charcoal-burner’s family. She’s seriously ill, but pious and patient. I read a chapter to her and prayed with all of them. The people here have something special and appealing because of their simplicity and kind-heartedness, just like the Brabanters in Zundert and Etten.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Petit-Wasmes 26 Dec 1878 / Borinage Hainaut’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Since a longer stay at the Flemish training college at Brussels had become impossible (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let148.xml">see letter 148</ref>), Van Gogh left for the Borinage to seek a position as an evangelist. Around the beginning of December 1878 he went to live in Petit-Wasmes, a village in the south of Belgium. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had meanwhile written to Theo about this on 15 December: ‘A week ago we received a rather good letter from Vincent. Good inasmuch as he has found good lodgings with a Protestant farming family at Pâturages. For 30 francs a month – so little because he instructs their children in the evenings. He has been received there with kindness by many people, and associating with those people appears to fulfil his expectations. Moreover, the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_176">Rev. Péron</rs> at Dour has promised his assistance. In mid-January there will be another meeting of the Committee, of which the Rev. Péron is secretary, and he will try to further Vincent’s interests. Meanwhile he spends his free time drawing large maps of Palestine which could be of use to schools and confirmation classes – and which he hopes to dispose of for money. I received one from him and ordered 4 more copies, for which I will give him 10 francs each.</p>

<p rend="indent">So now we are relieved inasmuch as he has good accommodation for the present – and otherwise we’ll wait and see. Especially now that it’s so wintry, we’re glad that he has initially ended up there, and in that colliery country there will certainly be no lack of opportunity to warm oneself. Accordingly, he writes that in his room, too, he has a fire in the grate, and clothing, and simple but healthy fare’ (FR b2448). The above-mentioned ‘Rev. Péron’ is Pierre Péron, who worked for the Eglise protestante unie de Belgique from 1869 to 1882.</p>
  
<p rend="indent">A new situation for Vincent had thus been arranged fairly quickly. On 5 December, Mr van Gogh had sent a frank letter of recommendation to Péron at Dour, in which he said that Vincent had refused to take money from him, not wanting him to bear the expense. (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="documentation.xml#5December1878">See <hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, 5 December 1878</ref>).  Evidently two more letters followed, addressed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_460">Nicolaas de Jonge</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_605">Abraham van der Waeyen Pieterszen</rs>, because on 8 January 1879 Mr van Gogh confided to Theo: ‘I wrote again in his behalf to Brussels and Mechelen’ (FR b2455).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>On the last day of the year <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo, making sure he had Vincent’s exact address and asking him to write soon to Vincent in Belgium (FR b2452).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Absolutely nothing, none whatsoever. Van Gogh uses this adverb ‘ganschelijk’ here for the first time (probably under the influence of Flemish).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The description suggests that Van Gogh has <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Dürer</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1882"><hi rend="italics">Ritter, Tod und Teufel</hi></rs> (Knight, Death and the Devil) in mind, of which he stressed the same aspect in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let148.xml">letter 148</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This room, known in popular parlance as the ‘Salon du Bébé’ and ‘Le temple du Bébé’, was located at what is now rue du Bois 257-259 in Petit-Wasmes. See Eeckaut 1990, p. 173 and ‘Annexes’, pp. 23, 47.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 13:31-35, Mark 4:31-32 and Luke 13:18-19.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 21:19-22, Mark 11:12-26 and Luke 13:6-9. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>John 9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Matt. 2 and Luke 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  Luke 2:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘iewers’, which means ‘somewhere’. Otherwise used only in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let152.xml">letter 152</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_884">Johannes Bosboom</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Lime-kiln by the quarry of Chaudfontaine</hi> (private collection) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_607">Ill. 607</rs>. The watercolour, whose measurements – 32 x 52 cm – entitle it to be called ‘large’, was in the possession of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M. van Gogh</rs>; Vincent and Theo doubtless saw the drawing at his house.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let148.xml">See letter 148</ref> with regard to the brothers’ visit to the Brussels museum. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Although Van Gogh calls it an etching, he must be referring to the wood engraving of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1050">Goupil</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_887"><hi rend="italics">A young citizen of the year <hi>v</hi></hi></rs>; see <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let145.xml#n-14">letter 145, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>The ‘patois’ means the dialect of the region.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The text conforms to the translation in David Martin, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_191"><hi rend="italics">La Sainte Bible</hi></ref>. Brussels 1860.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
  John 6:27.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Deut. 8:3 and Matt. 4:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 23:8 and Matt. 23:10. ‘Xtus’ is the abbreviation of the name Christ, beginning with the first letter of the Greek word for Christ ( ).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Cf. Isa. 53:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Cf. Ps. 103:3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 13:55.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>
  Luke 4:23 and Ezek. 34:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
  Rom. 12:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 11:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>The president of the Belgische Evangelisatie-Comité van de Bond van Kerken (Belgian Evangelization Committee of the Association of Churches) was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_187">Emile Rochedieu</rs>. This letter is no longer to be found in the archives of the Eglise protestante unie de Belgique.</p>

<p rend="indent">On 1 February 1879, the Committee appointed Vincent to a position for a period of six months, as evidenced by the document ‘Signatures des Agentes nouveaux depuis 1870’. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1913">Ill. 1913</rs>. From the minutes of the meeting of 14 January 1879, it emerges that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_605">Abraham van der Waeyen Pieterszen</rs> had reported that he ‘introduces the subject of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, who would like to be employed in the Borinage’ (fait connaître M. Van Gogh, qui voudrait être occupé dans le Borinage) [p. 173]. The minutes go on to say: ‘The Chairman introduces the application for employment from Mr van Gogh, son of a minister from Holland, who has come to the Borinage with the aim of working there. From what Mr Pieterszen and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_176">Mr Péron</rs> say, it emerges that this devout young man, completely devoted to work, would make a good Bible reader and would do useful work in that capacity, in Wasmes and Warpignies. Mr Péron suggests employing him in this way, at the modest salary of 600 francs. There will be a trial period of 6 months’ (M. le Président fait connaître la demande d’emploi de Mr van Gogh, fils d’un pasteur de Hollande et venu dans le Borinage dans le but d’y travailler. Il résulte de ce que disent M.M. Pieterszen et Péron que ce jeune homme pieux, dévoué dur au travail, ferait un bon lecteur de la Bible et travaillerait utilement à ce titre, à Wasmes et à Warpignies. M. Péron propose de l’employer ainsi avec le sobre traitement de 600 francs. On fera un essai de 6 mois’) (Brussels, Eglise protestante unie de Belgique, Bureau du Synode).</p>

<p rend="indent">The minutes of 15 April 1879 report the situation to date: ‘Attention is drawn to Mr Vincent and his work. The details, both regrettable and encouraging, that have been given persuade the committee to authorise the Hainaut sub-committee to extend Mr Vincent van Gogh’s trial period for three [months], if it sees fit .’ (L’attention est attirée sur M. Vincent et sur son oeuvre. Les détails à la fois regrettables et encourageants qui sont donnés déterminent le comité à autoriser le sous-comité du Hainaut à prolonger l’essai de M. Vincent van Gogh pendant trois [mois], s’il le juge bon’) [p. 177]. (Brussels, Archives of the Eglise protestante unie de Belgique). Cf. also Lutjeharms 1978, p. 105.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was also responsible for the Protestant community in the nearby hamlet of  Hoeven.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was ‘warmly received the first week’ by the evangelist-colporteur <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_801">Benjamin Vanderhaegen</rs>, who found him lodgings in the house of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_346">Jean Baptiste Denis</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let150.xml">see letter 150</ref>). According to archival records, he lived at rue de la place St Pierre 12 in Pâturages; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, who corresponded with Vanderhaegen, gave Theo the address as rue de l’église 39. Cf. FR b2452, 31 December 1878 and FR b2463, 27 February 1879 (quotation).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    