<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Brussels, Saturday, 2 April 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let164"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b162 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>164</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>142</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>163</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-04-02">Saturday, 2 April 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Brussels</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0162 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0162 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000172_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0162 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000173_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000173_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0162 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000173_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000173_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000173_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">2/4-81</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">72 B<hi rend="super">d</hi> du Midi Bruxelles</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">In antwoord op Uwe twee goede brieven &amp; naar aanleiding van een bezoek van Pa<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> waarnaar ik reeds sedert eenigen tijd verlangde heb ik U ’t een &amp; ander te zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En wel vooreerst dit. Van Pa hoorde ik dat zonder dat ik hiervan wist gij mij reeds geld gezonden hebt en zoodoende mij krachtdadig helpt om vooruit te scharrelen. Ontvang mijn hartelijken dank daarvoor. Ik heb het vast vertrouwen dat gij geen spijt hiervan zult hebben; zoodoende leer ik een handwerk en hoewel ik er zeker niet rijk door worden zal<c type="kk">/</c> althans zal ik er mijn 100 francs per maand die men voor levensonderhoud minstens noodig heeft wel uithalen zoodra ik wat vaster in mijn schoenen sta als teekenaar en vast werk krijg.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Zeer heeft het geen gij ons met betrekking tot den schilder Heyerdahl<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> hebt doen weten de belangstelling gewekt<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel van Rappard als van mij zelven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Daar de eerstgenoemde zonder twijfel U zelf wel</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">dienaangaande zal schrijven spreek ik bij dezen alleen over deze kwestie in zoover als zij mij persoonlijk min of meer aangaat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Uwe opmerkingen aangaande de Hollandsche artisten<c type="kk">/</c> als zijnde het twijfelachtig of men van hun heldere teregtwijzing zou kunnen verkrijgen betreffende de moeielijkheden van perspectief &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> waar ik mee worstel<c type="kk">/</c> vind ik in zekeren zin vrij juist en waar. Althans ik geef het U van ganscher harte toe dat iemand als Heyerdahl verreweg zou te prefereeren zijn<c type="kk">/</c> daar hij een zoo veelzijdig ontwikkeld mensch schijnt te wezen<c type="kk">/</c> boven zekere anderen die de gaaf niet mogten bezitten om hunne wijze van doen ook aan een ander te verklaren en iemand de zoo noodige leiding &amp; teregtwijzing eenigermate te kunnen geven. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Gij spreekt van Heyerdahl als van iemand die zich veel moeite geeft om “verhoudingen voor teekening” te zoeken<c type="kk">/</c> dat is juist wat ik noodig heb. Menig goed schilder heeft niet het minste begrip of bijna niet wat “verhoudingen voor teekening” zijn of schoone lijnen of karakteristieke compositie en gedachte en poesie. Toch zijn dit belangrijke kwesties die Feyen Perrin en Ulysse Butin en Alphonse Legros<c type="kk">/</c> om niet te spreken van Breton &amp; Millet en Israels<c type="kk">/</c> wel zeer ter harte nemen en nooit uit het oog verliezen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Menig Hollandsch schilder zou niets en ten eenemale niets begrijpen van het zoo schoone werk van Boughton<c type="kk">/</c> Marks<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Millais<c type="kk">/</c> Pinwell<c type="kk">/</c> Du Mauriez<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Herkomer, Walker, om maar enkele artisten te noemen die als “teekenaars” waarachtige Meesters zijn<c type="kk">/</c> buiten &amp; behalve hunne kwaliteiten in andere richting<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Menigeen<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> haalt voor dergelijk werk de schouders op gelijkerwijs velen<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs onder de schilders hier in Belgie, die toch beter behoorden te weten<c type="kk">/</c> dat doen voor ’t werk van de Groux. Van de Groux zag ik deze week 2 dingen die ik nog niet kende<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. eene schilderij Départ du conscrit<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en eene teekening in de hoogte<c type="kk">/</c> L’ivrogne<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> twee composities die zoo zeer geleken op Boughton dat ik getroffen werd door die gelijkenis als van twee broeders die elkaar nooit zouden hebben ontmoet en niettemin eensgezind zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Alzoo gij ziet dat ik Uwe zienswijze deel betreffende Heyerdahl<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik mij gelukkig zal rekenen wanneer Gij mij later in relatie met dien man zoudt kunnen brengen<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik verder niet bepaald wil doordrijven op ’t punt van het naar Holland gaan, althans dan wanneer ik ’t vooruitzigt heb op Parijs later en daar min of meer op rekenen mag.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">In den tusschentijd evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> wat moet ik doen; wat zoudt gij het beste vinden. Voor een week of wat kan ik bij Rappard blijven werken maar dan zal deze waarschijnlijk vertrekken. Mijn slaapkamertje is al te klein en ’t licht is er niet goed en de lui zouden er op tegen hebben dat ik t’licht van ’t raam gedeeltelijk afsloot, ik mag zelfs mijn etsen niet aan den muur hangen of mijn teekeningen. Als Rappard dus van hier gaat in Mei dan moet ik verhuizen en zou alsdan zeer graag een tijd buiten gaan werken<c type="kk">/</c> Heyst<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Calmpthout<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Etten<c type="kk">/</c> Schevening<c type="kk">/</c> Katwijk of waar dan ook. of zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen digter bij is<c type="kk">/</c> Schaerbeek<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Haeren<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Groenendael.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Evenwel bij preferentie eene plaats waar kans is om in aanraking te komen met andere schilders &amp; zoo mogelijk zamen te wonen &amp; te werken omdat dat goedkooper &amp; beter is. De kosten van verblijf waar dan ook zijn eigentlijk minstens 100 francs per maand<c type="kk">/</c> wat men minder heeft daarvoor lijdt men gebrek<c type="kk">/</c> hetzij ligchamelijk hetzij aan ’t onontbeerlijke materiaal &amp; gereedschap.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Dezen winter heb ik ± 100 fr. per maand verteerd wil ik rekenen<c type="kk">/</c> hoewel in waarheid het maar naauwelijks zooveel geweest is. En daarvan heb ik een aanmerkelijk deel besteed aan teekenbehoeften en mij ook kleeren aangeschaft<c type="kp">_</c> Heb n.l. twee werkmanspakken gekocht van grof zwart fluweel<c type="kk">/</c> van die stof die men meen ik veloutine<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> noemt<c type="kp">_</c> Dat staat knap en men kan er zich mee vertoonen en bovendien doen ze mij later dienst omdat ik heel wat werkmanskleeren later en zelfs nu reeds noodig heb voor mijn modellen die ik natuurlijk als ieder ander noodig heb. Gaandeweg<c type="kk">/</c> desnoods uit de tweede hand moet ik mij allerlei kleedingstukken aanschaffen<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel mannen- als vrouwenkleeren tot dat doeleinde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar dat hoeft natuurlijk niet alles op eens<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel reeds heb ik een begin gemaakt &amp; ga voort.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Finantie kwesties zegt ge, en te regt, hebben in de wereld al heel wat mee &amp; tegen gewerkt. Que soit; en ’t woord van Bernard Palizzi blijft waar: “Pauvreté em<c type="shy">-</c>pêche les bons esprits de parvenir”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Maar als ik nadenk dan zeg ik toch<c type="kk">/</c> Zou het wel zijn dat in eene familie als de onze waar 2 heeren van Gogh zeer rijk zijn<c type="kk">/</c> en dat in ’t vak van kunst<c type="kk">/</c> C.M. en onzen oom te Prinsenhage<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> en waar ook gij en ik in ’t tegenwoordige geslacht ons ’t zelfde vak hoewel in verschillenden kring hebben gekozen<c type="kk">/</c> zou het, zeg ik, wel zijn als bij deze gegevens ik op de een of andere wijze niet<c type="kk">/</c> voor den tijd die noodwendig verloopen moet voor ik vast werk als teekenaar krijg<c type="kk">/</c> op die 100 francs per maand kon blijven rekenen. Nu 3 jaar geleden heb ik over eene heel andere kwestie woorden gehad met Oom Cor<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> maar hoeft dat een reden te zijn waarom voor altijd en eeuwig C.M<c type="kp">_</c> mij zou vijandig blijven. Veel liever neem ik aan dat hij mij nooit vijandig geweest is en beschouw ’t als een misverstand waar ik met pleizier de gansche schuld van op mij neem<c type="kk">/</c> liever dan er over te vitten in hoever dit al dan niet mijn schuld is want voor dergelijke redenaties heb ik geen tijd disponibel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Oom Cor nu doet zoo dikwijls iets voor andere teekenaars en zou ’t nu zoo heel onnatuurlijk zijn als hij ook mij als ’t geval zich voordeed ook met der daad zijne belangstelling toonde. Ik zeg dit een en ander evenwel niet eens zoo zeer om geldelijke hulp van ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> te krijgen dan veeleer omdat ik meen dat het niet wel zou zijn als hij zich gansch ongenegen zou toonen dat<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> althans goede verstandhouding tusschen ons zich krachtig vernieuwde. Nog op heel andere wijze dan door bepaald mij geld te geven zou ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> mij veel kunnen helpen<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>b.v. als dat mogelijk ware door mij nu of later met zulke personen in kennis te brengen van wie ik nog veel zou kunnen leeren. En ware het mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> mogt door ZEd. intermediair ’t een of ander tot stand komen voor den tijd die nog verloopen moet voor &amp; aleer ik te Parijs b.v. vast werk voor een of andere illustratie<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> zou krijgen. In dezen geest heb ik ook met Pa gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> of het eenig resultaat zal geven weet ik niet maar ik merkte dat er over het vreemde en onverklaarbare gesproken werd van ’t verschijnsel dat ik zoo tobben moest terwijl ik toch tot die &amp; die familie behoorde. Ik heb ook nu weer daarop gezegd dat ik meende dit maar van voorbijgaanden aard zou zijn &amp; later teregt zou komen<c type="kp">_</c> Toch kwam het mij raadzaam voor er eens met Pa en U over te spreken en ik schreef er met een woord over aan den Heer Tersteeg maar ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> schijnt mijne bedoeling niet te hebben begrepen daar hij het opvatte als was ik van plan om op den zak van C.M. te gaan leven en dit zijne opvatting zijnde schreef hij mij een vrij ontmoedigenden brief en zei ik had geen regt op iets dergelijks. Regt beweer ik niet te hebben maar wensch te voorkomen dat nu of later op de ateliers over deze kwestie zou gesproken worden en daarom moet mijns inziens<c type="kk">/</c> althans provisoir en voor ’t oog van de wereld, in afwachting van dat men tot andere gedachten mij aangaande komen kan<c type="kk">/</c> de goede verstandhouding tusschen mij en de familie zich herstellen. Wil men dat niet, que soit, maar dan kan ik niet verhoeden dat er hier en daar over zal worden gesproken. Schreef ik nu onmiddelijk aan C.M. of ging naar ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> toe dan was er kans dat hij mijn brief niet las of mij wat al te stroef ontving<c type="kk">/</c> ik spreek er dus eens over met Pa en met U omdat gij alligt terloops er eens een woordje over zoudt kunnen zeggen en hij mijne bedoeling niet zal misverstaan. ’t Is mijne bedoeling niet om geld van ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> gelijk de Hr Tersteeg verstond<c type="kk">/</c> dan alleen in ’t geval hij na met mij gesproken te hebben fidutie &amp; vertrouwen in mijne toekomst krijgt en mij met een heel ander oog mogt gaan beschouwen<c type="kp">_</c> En komt hij tot die overtuiging dan zou ik zeer zeker zijne hulp niet versmaden, dat spreekt van zelf en dan zou hij nog op heel andere wijze dan door mij geld te geven mij den weg wat makkelijker kunnen maken, b.v. in den tusschentijd<c type="kk">/</c> tusschen nu en ’t naar Parijs gaan. Ik schreef aan den Hr. Tersteeg dat het mij niet ten eenemale verwonderde dat hij mijn brief zoo had opgevat daar ook gijzelf in der tijd van “rentenieren”<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> had gesproken. En gelijkerwijs ik nu meen uit den toon van Uw brief te verstaan dat gij mijne moeielijke positie niet langer in dat ellendig licht ziet en dat ervaar ook door 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>Uwe krachtige medewerking<c type="kk">/</c> zoo hoop ik dat ook de Heer Tersteeg zijne opinie gaandeweg zal veranderen<c type="kp">_</c> Te meer daar ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> de eerste was om mij te helpen met die Bargues<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> waarvoor ik altijd dankbaar zal blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Nu schrijft gij over een mannequin.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Daar is geen bepaalden haast mee maar ’t zou mij van veel dienst zijn bij ’t composeeren en ’t vinden van standen<c type="kk">/</c> dat voelt ge wel. Liever echter wacht ik wat langer en heb een beter<c type="kk">/</c> dan spoedig een al te gebrekkig werktuig.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Maar vooral houdt een open oog voor alle mogelijke platen of boeken over proportie en informeer daar zoo goed naar als ge maar kunt<c type="kk">/</c> dat is onuitsprekelijk veel waard<c type="kk">/</c> zonder dat kan men niet vlug eene compositie van figuren daarstellen. Verder<c type="kk">/</c> ’t een of ander over de anatomie van ’t paard &amp; schaap<c type="kk">/</c> koe<c type="kk">/</c> maar niet met het oog op de veeartsenij maar veeleer met betrekking tot het teekenen van voornoemde dieren<c type="kk">/</c> is voor mij zeer wenschelijk. Als ik U zoo om al die dingen vraag dan is het omdat gij alligt eens in de gelegenheid zijt zeer goedkoop betrekkelijk zulke bladen te vinden gelijk ik zelf er ook al eenigen heb gevonden<c type="kk">/</c> en gij er mogelijk minder op zoudt letten als ik U niet had gezegd dat die voor mij zoo bij uitstek nuttig zijn. Als ge ooit in de gelegenheid waart om b.v. Bargue of Violet le Duc eens te vragen naar die proportiebladen<c type="kk">/</c> alligt was dat het beste kantoor voor een dergelijk renseignement.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Later met U zamenwonen zou ik natuurlijk heerlijk vinden maar zoo ver zijn we nu nog niet. Was het dat C.M. zich liet vinden om mij voorlopig nog ergens in te werken<c type="kk">/</c> waarlijk ik zou ’t niet versmaden. Zelfs van betrekkelijk slechte artisten kan men soms veel indirect leeren zooals b.v. Mauve veel van Verschuur<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> leerde met betrekking tot het in perspectief brengen van een stal en een wagen en de anatomie van een paard<c type="kk">/</c> en toch hoezeer staat Mauve ver boven Verschuur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Als ge soms op de Salon ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van Madiol kunt recom<c type="shy">-</c>mandeeren doe het dan want er is veel moois in en de man zit in de penarie met veel kleine kinderen. Hij schildert aan een smidse die ook goed wordt en onlangs vond hij een oud vrouwtje dat superbe is van teekening en kleur vooral.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Maar hij is erg ongelijk. Zijn krijtteekeningen zijn dikwijls uitmuntend.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Deze brief is wel wat lang maar ik kan hem niet korter maken. Als ik er over spreek dat het wenschelijk ware dat althans ’t publiek maar veel liever inderdaad C.M<c type="kp">_</c> en anderen van gedachte veranderen mij aangaande<c type="kk">/</c> dan is het omdat b.v. iemand als Roelofs niet weet wat van zoo’n scheeve positie te denken<c type="kk">/</c> of er moet iets aan mij haperen of aan den anderen kant<c type="kk">/</c> maar hij ziet there is something wrong somewhere anyhow.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Zoo iemand is dus wat al te voorzigtig en laat zich voorlopig niet met mij in juist op ’t moment dat het mij het meest noodzakelijk is raad of teregtwijzing te hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">En dergelijke ervaringen zijn althans niet aangenaam<c type="kk">/</c> resteert of ik met geduldige energie voortwerkende al dan niet gaandeweg vorder notwithstanding. Ik meen van ja. Where there is a will there is a way.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">En zou ’t mij later kwalijk te nemen zijn als ik dan mijn revanche nam.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Een teekenaar teekent evenwel niet ter wille van revanche maar ter wille van de liefde tot het teekenen en die dringt sterker dan eenige andere beweegreden<c type="kp">_</c> Aldus welligt dat later nog sommige dingen teregt komen die nu nog niet in den haak zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Dezen winter heb ik veel houtsneden verzameld<c type="kp">_</c> Uwe Millets zijn vermeerderd met verscheidene anderen en ge zult zien dat uw kapitaal houtsneden &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> niet renteloos bij mij gelogeerd heeft. Van of naar Millet heb ik nu 24 houtsneden<c type="kk">/</c> de Travaux des champs<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> er bij rekenende. Maar zelf teekenen dat is de hoofdzaak en daar moet alles op toe werken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">’t Goedkoopst was al ligt dat ik dezen zomer te Etten doorbragt<c type="kk">/</c> er is daar stof genoeg. Komt U dit wenschelijk voor kunt ge er Pa over schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben bereid mij te schikken in kleeding of iets anders zoo als zij dat maar willen en alligt liep ik C.M. dezen zomer aldaar eens tegen ’t lijf als hij eens naar daar of Prinsenhage mogt gaan. Werkelijk bezwaar bestaat daartegen niet zoover ik weet<c type="kp">_</c> Er zal altijd hetzij in of buiten de familie verschillend over mij geoordeeld of gesproken worden en men zal steeds de meest uiteenloopende meeningen hooren opperen.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">En dat neem ik niemand kwalijk daar betrekkelijk slechts zeer weinige menschen weten waarom of een teekenaar zoo of zoo doet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Maar boeren en burgers verdenken in ’t algemeen iemand die om schilderachtige plekken of figuren te vinden in allerlei plekken<c type="kk">/</c> hoeken en gaten zich begeeft die een ander niet bij voorkeur opzoekt<c type="kk">/</c> van zeer veel snoodheid en booze oogmerken waaraan geen haar op zijn hoofd denkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Een boer die mij een ouden boomstronk ziet teekenen en mij een uur lang daar voor ziet blijven zitten denkt dat ik gek ben en lacht mij uit natuurlijk. Eene jonge dame die haar neus optrekt voor een werkman in zijn gelapt en bestoven en doorzweet werkpak kan zich natuurlijk niet begrijpen waarom iemand de Borinage of Heyst bezoekt en tot in de maintenages van een kolenmijn afdaalt en ook die komt tot de conclusie dat ik gek ben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Maar dat alles kan mij natuurlijk volstrekt niet schelen als maar gij en de Hr Tersteeg en C.M. en Pa en anderen met wie ik te maken heb dat beter weten en<c type="kk">/</c> wel verre van daar aanmerking op te maken<c type="kk">/</c> zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> je vak brengt dat mee en wij begrijpen waarom dat zoo is. Zoodat ik herhaal<c type="kk">/</c> in de gegevenen is er toch eigentlijk geen bepaalde reden waarom ik b.v. niet als dat zoo uitkomt b.v. naar Etten of naar den Haag zou kunnen gaan<c type="kk">/</c> ook al wordt er wat over geredekaveld door heertjes en dametjes<c type="kp">_</c> Aangezien dus Pa bij gelegenheid van zijn bezoek mij zeide<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf maar eens aan Theo en bedistel<ptr target="#note-t-f"/> met dezen wat het beste ware en ’t goedkoopst uitkwam<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zult gij mij Uwe zienswijze in dezen wel binnen kort willen doen weten. Heyst (bij Blankenberg dus aan zee) of Calmpthout zijn zeer schilderachtig<c type="kk">/</c> te Etten is ook stof<c type="kk">/</c> desnoods hier ook hoewel ik dan toch verhuizen zou naar Schaerbeek. Schevening of Katwijk werd alligt mogelijk als C.M<c type="kp">_</c> jegens mij van gedachte veranderde en dan kon ik nog profiteeren direct of indirect van de Hollandsche artisten. Wat betreft de kosten<c type="kk">/</c> ik reken ze te bedragen op zijn allerminst ± 100 francs per maand<c type="kk">/</c> minder is niet mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> “den dorschenden os zult ge niet muilbanden”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Aldus wacht ik Uw nader schrijven betreffende dit een en ander en werk intusschen bij Rappard. Rappard heeft wel sommige flinke studies geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> o.a. een paar naar de modellen van de akademie die flink zijn aangepakt.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> Wat meer passie of hartstogt zou hem niet schaden<c type="kk">/</c> wat meer zelfvertrouwen en wat meer durven. Iemand zei mij eens <hi rend="italics">Nous devons faire</hi> <hi rend="italics">des efforts de perdus</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> de désespérés<c type="kp">_</c> Voilà ce qu’il</hi> <hi rend="italics">ne fait pas encore</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> Zijn teekeningen met de pen<c type="kk">/</c> landschap<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-28"/> vindt ik zeer geestig en bevallig<c type="kk">/</c> ook daarin nog wat meer passie evenwel gaandeweg s.v.p. En nu neem ik afscheid met een handdruk in gedachten en blijf</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">t.t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Ik zend U drie krabbelingen die nog onhandig zijn maar waaruit ge hoop ik toch zien zult dat het gaandeweg beter wordt<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-29"/> ge moet in aanmerking nemen dat het nog niet lang is dat ik teeken<c type="kk">/</c> al heb ik als jongen wel eens kleine schetsjes gemaakt. En dat bovendien dezen winter het bij mij hoofdzaak was strenge anatomische studies te maken en niet eigen composities<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">2/4-81</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">72 blvd du Midi Bruxelles</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">In answer to your two good letters and prompted by a visit from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which I’d been looking forward to for some time, I have a few things to tell you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And this, first of all. I heard from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> that you’ve already been sending me money without my knowing it, and in doing so are effectively helping me to get along. For this accept my heartfelt thanks. I have every confidence that you won’t regret it; in this way I’m learning a handicraft, and although I’ll certainly not grow rich by it, at least I’ll earn the 100 francs a month necessary to support myself once I’m surer of myself as a draughtsman and find steady work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">What you told us about the painter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> has greatly aroused the interest of both <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> and myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Because the former will no doubt write to you about it himself, I address this question only because it concerns me personally, to some extent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Your remarks about the Dutch artists, that it’s doubtful whether they’d be able to give clear advice on the difficulties of perspective &amp;c. with which I’m wrestling, I find in a certain sense quite correct and true. At any rate, I whole-heartedly agree with you that someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs>, because he seems to be such a highly cultivated man, would be far preferable to some others who might not have the ability to explain their way of doing things to anyone else, or to give one the guidance and advice that’s so necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">You speak of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs> as one who takes great pains to seek ‘proportions for the purpose of design’, that’s precisely what I need. Many good painters have no idea, or almost no idea, what ‘proportions for the purpose of design’ are, or beautiful lines or distinctive compositions, and ideas and poetry. Yet these are important questions which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1022">Feyen-Perrin</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_915">Ulysse Butin</rs><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1157">Alphonse Legros</rs>, not to mention <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Breton</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, take very much to heart and never lose sight of. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Many Dutch painters would understand nothing, absolutely nothing, of the beautiful work of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1200">Marks</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1269">Pinwell</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1197">Du Maurier</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1428">Walker</rs>, to name but a few artists who are true masters as ‘draughtsmen’, over and above their qualities in other directions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Many, I say, shrug their shoulders at such work, just as many — even among the painters here in Belgium, who should know better — do at the work of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs>. I saw 2 things by Degroux this week that I didn’t know yet, namely a painting, The conscript’s departure,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and a drawing in vertical format, The drunkard,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> two compositions that so much resemble <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs> that I was struck by the resemblance, as of two brothers who had never met each other but were nevertheless kindred spirits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">So you see that I share your view of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs>, that I’ll consider myself fortunate if you can put me in touch with that man later on, that I certainly won’t insist on having my way about going to Holland, not, at least, if I have the prospect of going to Paris later on and can more or less count on it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">In the meantime, though, what should I do? What would you think best? I can carry on working at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s for a week or so, but then he’ll probably be leaving. My bedroom is all too small and the light isn’t good, and the people would object to my shutting out some of the light coming in through the window, I’m not even allowed to hang my etchings on the wall or my drawings. So when Rappard leaves here in May I’ll have to move, and in that case I’d very much like to work in the country for a while, Heist,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Kalmthout,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Etten, Scheveningen, Katwijk or wherever. Or even, which is closer, Schaarbeek,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Haren,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Groenendaal.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> But preferably a place where there’s a chance of coming into contact with other painters, and if possible of living and working together, because that’s cheaper and better. The cost of accommodation, no matter where, is at least 100 francs a month, anything less means suffering deprivation, either bodily or through a lack of indispensable materials and tools. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">This winter I spent around 100 francs a month, I reckon, although in truth it was scarcely that much. And of that I spent a considerable amount on drawing materials and also bought some clothes. Namely bought two workmen’s suits of coarse black velvet, of the material I think one calls velveteen.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> They look smart and one looks presentable in them; moreover, they’ll come in handy later on, for I’ll need a great many workman’s clothes later, and even now already, for my models, whom I naturally need like anyone else. Gradually I’ll have to acquire articles of clothing of all kinds, second-hand if necessary, both men’s and women’s clothing, for that purpose.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Naturally this doesn’t have to happen all at once, though I’ve already made a start and shall continue.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">You say, and rightly so, that financial matters have done a lot both to assist and to thwart people in the world. So be it, and the words of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1258">Bernard Palissy</rs> remain true: ‘Poverty prevents good minds succeeding’.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> But when I think about it, I nonetheless say, Could it be that in a family like ours, in which 2 Messrs van Gogh are very rich, and that in the art business, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> and our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">uncle</rs> at Princenhage,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and in which you and I in the present generation have also chosen that line of work, albeit in different spheres, I say, notwithstanding these facts, could it be that I can’t continue to count in one way or another on those 100 francs a month for the time that must necessarily elapse before I obtain regular employment as a draughtsman? 3 years ago I had words with Uncle Cor<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> on an entirely different matter, but is that any reason for C.M. to bear me ill will for ever and ever? I much prefer to assume that he never bore me any ill will, and view it as a misunderstanding for which I gladly take the entire blame, rather than bickering about whether and to what extent I’m to blame, because I have no time for such arguments.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> so often does things to help other draughtsmen, and would it now be so very unnatural for him to take an active interest in me as well, should the occasion arise? I say these things, however, not so much to obtain financial help from His Hon. but rather because I think it wouldn’t be good if he were to show himself completely unwilling for there to be a vigorous renewal of harmony, at least, between us. His Hon. could help me a great deal in a wholly different way than by giving me money, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> for example by putting me in touch, if possible, now or later, with people from whom I could learn a great deal. And, if possible, by His Hon.’s mediating to bring about one thing or another during the time that must still elapse before I obtain regular employment — in Paris, for example — at some illustrated magazine or other. I also spoke to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> in this vein, I don’t know whether it will be of any use, but I noticed that they were talking about how strange and inexplicable it was that I had to struggle so hard even though I belonged to such and such a family. In reply to this I said that I thought that this was a passing thing and would be set to rights later. Nonetheless, it seemed to me advisable to speak to Pa and to you about it, and I wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> and mentioned it briefly, but His Hon. seems not to have understood my meaning, because he took it to mean that I was planning to live out of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>’s pocket and, this being his interpretation, he wrote me a rather discouraging letter and said that I had no right to such a thing. I don’t claim to have the right, but I wish to prevent the matter being talked about sooner or later in the studios, and so, in my opinion, harmony must be restored between me and the family, at least temporarily and in the eyes of the world, in expectation of their changing their minds about me. If they refuse, so be it, but then I can’t prevent it being talked about here and there. If I were to write immediately to C.M., or to go and see His Hon., there would be a chance that he wouldn’t read my letter or would receive me all too brusquely, so I’m speaking about it to Pa and to you, because you’ll probably be able to say a word or two about it in passing, and then he won’t misconstrue my meaning. It isn’t my intention to obtain money from His Hon., as Mr Tersteeg thought, unless it be the case that after talking to me he acquires faith and confidence in my future and starts to see me in an entirely different light. And if he were to be convinced of it, then I’d certainly not spurn his help, that goes without saying, and then he would be able to smooth my way a little in an entirely different way than by giving me money, for instance, in the interval of time between now and going to Paris. I wrote to Mr Tersteeg that it didn’t surprise me in the least that he had interpreted my letter in that way, since you had also spoken at one time of ‘idling’.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> And just as I now understand from the tone of your letter that you no longer see my difficult position in that dismal light, and experience it as well through 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> your effective assistance, so I hope that Mr Tersteeg, too, will gradually change his opinion. The more so because His Hon. was the first to help me with those <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs>s,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> for which I’ll always be grateful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Now you write about a manikin.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> There’s no particular hurry, but it would be of great use to me in composing and finding poses, you’re sensible of that. However, I’d rather wait a bit longer and have a better one than have a tool sooner that was far too inadequate.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Be sure and keep an eye out, though, for all manner of prints or books about proportion, and find out as much as you can about them, that’s of inestimable value, without it one can’t make a figure drawing quickly. Moreover, it would be very beneficial for me to have a thing or two about the anatomy of the horse and sheep, cow, not with an eye to veterinary medicine but rather with a view to drawing the aforementioned animals. If I’m asking you for all these things like this, it’s because you’ll most likely have an opportunity to find such prints very cheaply, relatively speaking, just as I’ve already found a few myself, and you’d perhaps pay them less heed if I hadn’t said that they’re of such great use to me. If you ever have an opportunity to ask <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1412">Viollet-le-Duc</rs>, for example, about those prints about proportion, that’s most probably the best place for such information.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I should, of course, find it wonderful to live with you later on, but we haven’t reached that point yet. If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> could be persuaded to give me a chance to learn the ropes somewhere on a temporary basis, I’d certainly not scorn it. One can sometimes learn much indirectly even from relatively bad artists, just as, for example, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> learned a great deal from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1417">Verschuur</rs><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> about bringing a stable and a wagon into perspective, and the anatomy of a horse, and yet how Mauve towers above Verschuur.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">If by any chance you can recommend the painting of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1187">Madiol</rs> at the Salon, do so, for there’s much that’s beautiful in it, and the man is in a fix and has lots of small children. He’s painting a smithy that will also be good, and he recently made a little old woman that is superb in its drawing and especially colour.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> But he’s very inconsistent. His chalk drawings are often outstanding.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">This letter is really rather long, but I can’t make it any shorter. If I mention that it would be desirable for at least the general public, but in fact even more so for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> and others, to change their minds about me, it’s because people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1318">Roelofs</rs>, for example, don’t know what to think of such an untoward position, whether there is something wrong with me or with the other side, but he sees that there is something wrong somewhere anyhow.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Such a person is therefore too circumspect and will have nothing to do with me at present, just when it’s most necessary for me to receive advice and help.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And such experiences are unpleasant, to say the least, it remains to be seen whether, working on with patient energy, I gradually make progress notwithstanding.<ptr target="#note-t-d"/> I mean to. Where there is a will there is a way.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> <ptr target="#note-t-e"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">And would I be to blame later on if I were to take revenge?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Nonetheless, a draughtsman doesn’t draw for the sake of revenge but for the love of drawing, and that’s more compelling than any other reason. And so it’s likely that later on some things will be set to rights that aren’t quite right yet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I’ve collected a lot of woodcuts this winter. Your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>s have been augmented with various others, and you’ll see that your wealth of woodcuts &amp;c. haven’t had an unproductive stay with me. I now have 24 woodcuts by or after Millet, counting the Labours of the fields.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> But my own drawing is the main thing, and everything has to work towards that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">The cheapest thing, of course, would be for me to spend this summer in Etten, there’s subject matter enough there. If you think this desirable, you can write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> about it, I’m willing to conform to what they want as regards clothing or anything else, and I’d most likely run into <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> there this summer, if he were to go there or to Princenhage. There’s no real objection to it, as far as I know. I’ll always be judged or talked about in differing ways, whether within or outside the family, and one will always hear the most wide-ranging opinions being put forward. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">And I don’t blame anyone for it, for relatively very few people know why a draughtsman does this or that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Peasants and townsfolk, however, generally impute very great wickedness and evil intentions never dreamt of by one who betakes himself to all manner of places, corners and holes that others prefer not to visit, in order to find picturesque places or figures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">A peasant who sees me drawing an old tree-trunk and sees me sitting there in front of it for an hour thinks I’m mad, and naturally laughs at me. A young lady who turns up her nose at a workman in his patched and dusty and sweaty work-clothes can’t understand, of course, why anyone visits the Borinage or Heist and goes down a coal-mine all the way to the <hi rend="italics">maintenages</hi>, and she, too, comes to the conclusion that I’m mad.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">All that, though, doesn’t matter to me in the slightest, of course, if only you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and others I’m concerned with know better and, far from criticizing it, say instead, your line of work involves that, and we understand why it is so. So that I repeat, in the circumstances there’s actually no particular reason why I shouldn’t be able to go to Etten, for example, or to The Hague, if it should work out that way, even if little gentlemen and ladies chop logic on the subject. So, since Pa said to me during his visit, do write to Theo and arrange with him what would be best and least expensive, be so good as to let me know your views on this matter before long. Heist (near Blankenberge, thus on the sea) or Kalmthout are very picturesque, there’s subject matter in Etten as well, here too if necessary, although I’d move to Schaarbeek all the same. Scheveningen or Katwijk would of course be possible if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> were to change his opinion of me, and then I could profit directly or indirectly from the artists in Holland. As far as expenses go, I reckon them to be at least around 100 francs a month, less isn’t possible, ‘thou shalt not muzzle the ox that treadeth out the corn’.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">And so I’ll wait until you write more concerning one thing and another, and will work at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s in the meantime. Rappard has really painted some spirited studies, including a few from the models at the academy which are vigorously conceived.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> A bit more passion or emotion would do him no harm, a little more self-confidence and a little more daring. Someone once said to me, <hi rend="italics">We must make an effort like the lost, like the desperate. But he isn’t doing it yet.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-27"/> I find his landscape drawings in pen<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> very witty and pleasing, in those too, though, gradually a bit more passion please! And now I take my leave with a handshake in thought, and remain</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">I’m sending you three scratches that are still awkward, but from which I hope you’ll nonetheless see that there’s gradual improvement.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> You must remember that I haven’t been drawing for long, even if I did sometimes make little sketches as a boy. And also that this winter the most important thing for me was to make strict anatomical studies and not my own compositions.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘2/4-81 / 72 B du Midi Bruxelles’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo sends money for Vincent <ref target="let163.xml">(163)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s wants to become an illustrator <ref target="let162.xml">(162)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>’s visit had probably taken place a short while before. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Hans Olaf Heyerdahl</rs> worked in Paris. Theo knew this painter through Goupil. See exhib. cat. Åmot 1981, and Trond E. Aslaksby, ‘Hans Heyerdahl <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">i</hi> Paris’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Kunst og kommentar</hi>. Ed. Svein Olav Hoff. Asker 1992, pp. 48-67.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The ‘draughtsman’ by the name of Marks to whom Van Gogh refers cannot be identified with certainty, but <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1200">Henry Stacy Marks</rs>, a draughtsman on wood and etcher and painter of animals seems the most likely candidate. His work appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> (1876-1879) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi>; and he illustrated <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_169"><hi rend="italics">Child’s history of England</hi></ref>, which Van Gogh knew. The Dalziel Brothers made engravings after his designs. See Engen 1985, pp. 174-175.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1197">George Louis Palmella Busson du Maurier</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The conscript’s departure</hi>, c. 1869-1870 (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_138">Ill. 138</rs>. Van Gogh refers to this work again in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let260.xml">letter 260</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The drunkard</hi> (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_139">Ill. 139</rs>. This watercolour ‘in portrait format’ measures 42.1 x 26.1 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Heist is some 8 km north of Blankenberge on the north-west coast of Belgium, as clarified by Van Gogh further on in the letter: ‘near Blankenberge, so [it is] on the sea’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Kalmthout is about 18 km north of Antwerp, near the Dutch border.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Schaarbeek is north-east of Brussels.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Haren is about 7 km from Brussels, in the direction of Antwerp.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Groenendaal is south-east of Brussels, in the Soignes Forest.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Veloutine is cotton or silk velvet.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>For this <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">dictum</hi>, falsely attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1258">Palissy</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let158.xml#n-20">see letter 158, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The ‘matter’ in question is not known, though Van Gogh is probably referring to his discussion with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_131"><hi rend="italics">Phrynée</hi></rs>, about which he wrote in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let139.xml">letter 139</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Conjunction referring back to ‘ongenegen’ (‘unwilling’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Illustrated magazine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Regarding Vincent’s supposed ‘idling’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let154.xml">see letter 154</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Van Gogh thanked <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> for sending <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_202"><hi rend="italics">Exercices au fusain</hi></ref> and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_170"><hi rend="italics">Cours de dessin</hi></ref> in late August or early September 1880 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let157.xml">see letter 157</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>A lay figure (with movable limbs) used in drawing.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Derived from the French ‘composer’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1417">Wouterus Verschuur</rs>, who mainly painted horses, had taught <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1187">Madiol</rs> did not display any work at the 1881 Salon; the painting mentioned has not been traced.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘He found a little old woman to pose for him and the painting was superb in its drawing and especially colour’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            
  
<p>‘There... anyhow’ was written by Vincent in English. Cf. the title of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Charles Dickens</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_199"><hi rend="italics">Little Dorrit</hi></ref>, book 2, chapter 5: ‘Something wrong somewhere’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="d" xml:id="note-t-d">
                            
<p>‘notwithstanding’ is written in English.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            
      
<p>A saying; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let527.xml">letter 527</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="e" xml:id="note-t-e">
                            
<p>‘Where ... way’ is written in English.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s series <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1887"><hi rend="italics">The labours of the fields</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml#n-1">see letter 156, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="f" xml:id="note-t-f">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘bedissel’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  1 Tim. 5:18 and 1 Cor. 9:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>There are no known examples of work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> made during the time he spent at the Brussels Academy (autumn 1880 to May 1881). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 68-69.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>‘Voila... encore’ must refer to the above-mentioned <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>One surviving example is a pen drawing made slightly earlier, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Valley of Jehoshaphat</hi> (Rotterdam, Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1900">Ill. 1900</rs>. The drawing is dated 17 March 1881. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 69, cat. no. 52.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>These three scratches are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    