<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, between Wednesday, 12 and Saturday, 15 October 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let175"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b172 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>175</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>152</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>174</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-10-12">between Wednesday, 12 and Saturday, 15 October 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0172" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0172" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000184_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Regt veel genoegen deed het mij zoo even Uw brief te ontvangen en vanwege ik toch reeds dezer dagen voornemens was om U te schrijven doe ik het nu onmiddelijk naar aanleiding van uw schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dat gij het Papier-Ingres hebt afgezonden vind ik heerlijk<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb nog wel wat maar niet meer van de bewuste kleur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dat de Hr Tersteeg U omtrent mijn teekeningen heeft gezegd wat hij gezegd heeft<c type="kk">/</c> verheugt mij<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en zeer zeker niet minder dat gijzelf uit de gezondene schetsjes<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> vindt er vooruitgang is<c type="kp">_</c> indien die aanvangt te komen<c type="kk">/</c> zeer zeker hoop ik terdeeg te werken zoodat noch gij noch de Hr T<c type="kp">_</c> die meer gunstige opinie behoeven terug te nemen, ik zal mijn best doen U in dezen niet te bedriegen. De natuur begint altijd met den teekenaar te weerstaan maar zoo wie het waarachtig ernstig opneemt laat zich door dien tegenstand niet van streek brengen<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel ’t is prikkel te meer om te overwinnen<c type="kk">/</c> en in den grond zijn de natuur en een opregt teekenaar het eens<c type="kp">_</c> Maar de natuur is zeer zeker “intangible”<c type="kk">/</c> toch moet men haar aanpakken en dat met vaste hand.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En na nu eenigen tijd met de natuur geworsteld en gestreden te hebben begint die wat meer meegevend en gedweeër te worden<c type="kk">/</c> niet dat ik er al ben<c type="kk">/</c> niemand is er verder vandaan dan ik zelf dat te meenen maar ’t begint beter te vlotten. De strijd met de natuur heeft somwijlen wel iets van wat Shakespeare noemt “Taming the shrew”<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> (d.i<c type="kp">_</c> de wederstrevende overwinnen door volharding<c type="kk">/</c> bongré &amp; malgré)<c type="kp">_</c> In veel dingen maar bepaaldelijk in ’t teekenen meen ik dat Serrer de près vaut mieux que lâcher.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Hoe langer hoe meer gevoel ik dat bepaaldelijk het figuurteekenen goed is, ook indirekt ten goede werkt op ’t landschapteekenen<c type="kp">_</c> Als men een knotwilg teekent als ware die een levend wezen<c type="kk">/</c> en dat is toch eigentlijk zoo<c type="kk">/</c> dan volgt de omgeving vanzelf betrekkelijk als men maar al zijn aandacht geconcentreerd heeft op dien bewusten boom en niet gerust heeft voor dat er iets van het leven in kwam.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Hierbij een paar schetsjes<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben nog al dikwijls op den Leurschen weg bezig tegenwoordig.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Werk ook nu &amp; dan met waterverf &amp; sepia maar dat lukt zoo in eens niet<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Mauve is naar Drenthe<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> heb afspraak met hem ik naar hem toe zal komen zoodra hij mij schrijft maar misschien komt hij nog eens een dag te Prinsenhage.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> De Fabritius te Rotterd. ging ik nog zien op mijn laatste reis<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en ’t doet mij pleizier dat o.a. die teek. Mesdag<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> onder je oogen is gekomen<c type="kp">_</c> Als de teekening van Mevr. Mesdag waarover je schrijft is geele rozen op een mosgrond<c type="kk">/</c> dan heb ik die op de tentoonstelling gezien<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en waarlijk dat is zeer mooi en zeer artistiek<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Wat gij over de Bock zegt vind ik in allen deele waar<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is ook mijn gedacht omtrent hem maar ’t was mij nog niet gelukt het zoo in woorden te brengen als gij ’t in uw brief doet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Indien hij zich kon en wilde concentreeren<c type="kk">/</c> voorzeker hij ware een beter artist dan nu. Ik heb hem ronduit gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> de Bock als gij en ik een jaar lang ons toeleggen op ’t figuur teekenen dan zijn we beiden na verloop van dien tijd heel andere lui dan nu op ’t moment<c type="kk">/</c> indien we ons niet aangrijpen en maar blijven voortgaan zonder iets nieuws er bij te leeren dan blijven we niet eens wat we zijn maar stilstaande gaan we achteruit. Als we geen figuur teekenen of anders boomen als waren ’t figuren dan zijn we als menschen zonder ruggegraat of met een te zwakke. Millet &amp; Corot van wie we beiden zoo veel houden<c type="kk">/</c> konden die een figuur teekenen ja of neen. Ik meen die Meesters stonden voor niets. En hij gaf mij daarin ook wel gedeeltelijk of geheel gelijk<c type="kp">_</c> Trouwens hij heeft geloof ik terdeeg serieus gewerkt aan dat Panorama en ook dat zal in ’t algemeen<c type="kk">/</c> al wil hij ’t zelf niet erkennen<c type="kk">/</c> een gunstigen invloed op hem hebben. Hij zei mij met betrekking tot dat Panorama een alleraardigst woord dat oorzaak was ik veel sympathie voor hem voelde. Ge kent wel den schilder Destrée<c type="kp">_</c> Deze was met een zeer pedant air naar de Bock toe gekomen en had hem gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> natuurlijk zeer uit de hoogte maar toch zoetsappig en ondragelijk protegeerenderwijs: de Bock ze hebben mij ook gevraagd om dat panorama te schilderen maar ik heb gemeend aangezien het iets onartistieks was het te moeten weigeren. En toen de Bock daarop: Mijnheer Destree wat is gemakkelijker<c type="kk">/</c> een panorama te schilderen of te weigeren een panorama te schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> wat is artistieker<c type="kk">/</c> het te doen of het niet te doen.─ Of dit precies dezelfde woorden waren weet ik niet maar zeer zeker was de repliek in dezen zin en dat vond ik zeer raak. En heb er evenveel respect voor als voor Uwe handelwijs betreffende de oudere en wijzere leden in Uwe vereeniging<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> die ge op hun eigen ouderdom en wijsheid hebt laten teeren terwijl gij zelf wat jonger en energieker de zaak hebt doorgezet. Dat is ware philosophie die ons aldus doet handelen als de Bock &amp; gij bij die respectieve gelegenheden<c type="kk">/</c> van zulke philosophie kan men zeggen dat zij ook praktijk is<c type="kk">/</c> net als Mauve zegt<c type="kk">/</c> “kleur is ook teekenen”. Mijn papier is vol dus eindig ik en ga er eens op uit<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang mijn besten dank voor uwe krachtdadige medewerking en een handdruk in gedachten en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">It gave me a great deal of pleasure to receive your letter just now, and because I was intending to write to you anyway one of these days, I’m doing it now straightaway, in response to your letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I think it’s wonderful that you’ve sent the Ingres paper, I still have some, but no more of that particular colour.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> said what he said to you about my drawings pleases me,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> as does, certainly no less so, your finding progress in the sketches I sent.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> If it’s beginning to manifest itself, I most certainly hope to work to the utmost, so that neither you nor Mr Tersteeg will have to retract that rather favourable opinion. I’ll do my best not to betray you in this. Nature always begins by resisting the draughtsman, but he who truly takes it seriously doesn’t let himself be deterred by that resistance, on the contrary, it’s one more stimulus to go on fighting, and at bottom nature and an honest draughtsman see eye to eye. Nature is most certainly ‘intangible’ though, yet one must seize it, and with a firm hand.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And now, after spending some time wrestling and struggling with nature, it’s starting to become a bit more yielding and submissive, not that I’m there yet, no one is less inclined to think so than I, but things are beginning to go more smoothly. The struggle with nature sometimes resembles what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs> calls ‘Taming the shrew’<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> (i.e. to conquer the opposition through perseverance, willy-nilly). In many things, but more particularly in drawing, I think that delving deeply into something is better than letting it go.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I feel more and more as time goes on that figure drawing in particular is good, that it also works indirectly to the good of landscape drawing. If one draws a pollard willow as though it were a living being, which it actually is, then the surroundings follow more or less naturally, if only one has focused all one’s attention on that one tree and hasn’t rested until there was some life in it.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Herewith a couple of sketches, I’m rather busy in Leurseweg these days.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Also work now and then with watercolour and sepia, but that isn’t immediately successful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> has gone to Drenthe,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> have agreed that I’ll go to him as soon as he writes to me, but perhaps he’ll be coming to Princenhage again for a day.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I went to see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1012">Fabritius</rs> in Rotterdam on my last journey,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and I’m glad that you’ve seen that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1218">Mesdag</rs> drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> among other things. If the drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1217">Mrs Mesdag</rs> which you wrote about is yellow roses on moss-covered ground, then I saw it at the exhibition<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and indeed, it’s very beautiful and very artistic. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">What you say about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> I find true in every respect, it’s also what I think about him, but I had never succeeded in expressing it as you did in your letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">If he were willing and able to concentrate, he’d be a better artist than he is now, to be sure. I told him frankly: <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs>, if you and I were to concentrate on figure drawing for a whole year, afterwards we’d both be completely different people from what we are now; if we fail to get a grip on ourselves and simply go on without learning anything new, we won’t even remain what we are but, standing still, we’ll go backwards. If we don’t draw figures, or else trees as though they were figures, then we’re like people who have no spine, or at least one that’s too weak. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>, whom we both like so much, could they paint a figure or couldn’t they? I mean, those Masters balked at nothing. And he admitted that I was largely right. For that matter, I believe he has worked very seriously on that Panorama and that, too, will generally have a good influence on him, even if he doesn’t want to admit it himself. He told me the nicest thing about that Panorama, which caused me to feel a great deal of sympathy for him. Surely you know the painter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_987">Destrée</rs>. He had gone up to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> with a very pedantic air and had said to him, very superciliously, of course, and yet in a mealy-mouthed and unbearably patronizing way: De Bock, they also asked me to paint that panorama but I thought, since it was so unartistic, that I had to refuse. To which De Bock replied: My dear Mr Destrée, what is easier, painting a panorama or refusing to paint a panorama? What is more artistic, doing it or not doing it? I don’t know whether those were his exact words, but the reply was most certainly in this vein, and I found it very much to the point. And I have just as much respect for it as I do for your behaviour towards the older and wiser members of your club,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> whom you’ve left to the devices of their own seniority and wisdom while you pressed ahead with matters in a somewhat more youthful and energetic way. That is true philosophy, which makes us act like De Bock and you did on those respective occasions. One can say of such philosophy that it’s also practical, just as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> says, ‘colour is also drawing’. My paper is full, so I’ll finish and go out, accept my hearty thanks for your energetic support, and a handshake in thought, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent wrote this letter <hi rend="italics">immediately</hi> after receiving one from Theo, which is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> mentioned in <ref target="let174.xml">letter 174</ref> of 12 October to Van Rappard but <hi rend="italics">is</hi> mentioned in a subsequent letter to him <ref target="let176.xml">(176)</ref> of 15 October. This makes 12 October (after writing to Van Rappard) the earliest possible date. Furthermore, in <ref target="let176.xml">letter 176</ref> Van Gogh says he is replying ‘at once’ to Van Rappard’s letter. The fact that he also conveys Theo’s regards in that letter <ref target="let176.xml#l-133">(l. 133)</ref> means that he must already have written the present letter, at the latest on 15 October.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Request for Theo to send ‘Ingres paper’ <ref target="let171.xml">(171)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh has seen the <hi rend="italics">Panorama Mesdag</hi> <ref target="let171.xml">(171)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent had shown <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> some of his drawings during a visit to The Hague in August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let171.xml">see letter 171</ref>). It is not known how Tersteeg conveyed his opinion of them to Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
      
<p>This probably refers to the sketches in letters <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let172.xml">172</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let173.xml">173</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>A similar remark about the intractability of nature also occurs in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_833">Taine</rs>. See Sund 1992, pp. 54, 277 (n. 11).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_225"><hi rend="italics">The taming of the shrew</hi></ref> (1594-1595, first edition 1623) is the title of a comedy by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">William Shakespeare</rs> and the phrase occurs as a line in the play itself (act 4, scene 2). See ed. Brian Morris. London and New York 1981, pp. 254-255.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh, who wrote in June 1881 that he was studying <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_922">Armand Cassagne</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_212"><hi rend="italics">Traité d’aquarelle</hi></ref>, could have had the following passage in mind when attributing these human characteristics to nature: ‘The painter who is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">strong in tones </hi>is the one who approaches nature with the greatest strength of coloration, and who, through skilful, powerful contrasts, succeeds in giving an idea of the solidity specific to each object. This tree, for example, has boughs that are vigorous, healthy, strong, juicy with sap; and you understand at first glance its strength and weightiness. Some other tree is enormous; but it is old, its wood lacks sap, it is hollow; you sense weakness under its apparent strength. The true painter must make it possible to guess all that in his work; his painting must have that <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi> that characterizes the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">moral </hi>diversity of these types’ (Le peintre <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">puissant de ton</hi> est celui qui aborde la nature avec le plus force de coloration, et qui, par d’habiles et puissantes oppositions, arrive à donner une idée de la solidité propre à chaque objet. Cet arbre, par exemple, a des ramures vigoureuses, saines, fortes, humides de sève; on en comprend au premier coup d’oeil la force et la pesanteur. Tel autre arbre est gigantesque; mais il est vieux, son bois manque de sève, il est creux; sous sa force apparante on sent la faiblesse. Le vrai peintre doit faire deviner tout cela dans son oeuvre; sa peinture doit avoir ce je ne sais quoi qui caractérise la diversité <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">morale</hi> de ces types.) Cassagne 1875, p. 102.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>There are two sketches, at the end of the letter. No. 1 is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Road with a man and pollard willows</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_322">F - / JH 58</rs>), of which no corresponding drawing is known, and the same applies to no. 2, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man putting potatoes in a sack</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_323">F - / JH 60</rs>). For the location depicted in the first sketch (with Leursestraat and the Roman Catholic Lambertuskerk at the end of it), see Kerstens 1990, pp. 24, 26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Drenthe is a province in the north-east of the Netherlands. In Van Gogh’s day it was a relatively undeveloped region and therefore popular among landscape painters.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>To visit <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to his short trip to The Hague at the end of August, at which time he must also have visited Rotterdam (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let171.xml">see letter 171</ref>), where he saw the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1885"><hi rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi></rs> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1012">Carel Fabritius</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let155.xml#n-18">see letter 155, n. 18</ref>, first paragraph).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This is perhaps <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1218">Mesdag</rs>’s drawing <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1140"><hi rend="italics">Fishing boat and horseman</hi></rs>, which Van Gogh had seen in Brussels (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let166.xml#n-17">see letter 166, n. 17</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Fours works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1217">Sientje Mesdag-van Houten</rs> were on display at the Sixth exhibition of drawings (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let171.xml">see letter 171</ref>). Van Gogh must be referring to the drawing <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_243"><hi rend="italics">Rozen</hi></rs> (Roses); see exhib. cat. The Hague 1881-2, p. 11, cat. no. 72.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Theo was a member of the Hollandsche Club (Dutch Club) in Paris, a society where young Dutchmen met (FR b1673). He must have written to Vincent about something that happened there.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    