<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, on or about Monday, 17 October 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let177"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b185 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>177</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>165</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>192</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-10-17">on or about Monday, 17 October 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0185" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000210_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000210_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0185" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000210_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000210_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Daar Pa &amp; Moe schrijven voeg ik er een woordje bij doch hoop U binnenkort meer uitvoerig te schrijven, namelijk dan wanneer Mauve die dezer dagen te Prinsenhage &amp; ook naar hier komt<c type="kk">/</c> er zal geweest zijn. Gij moet weten Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dat M. mij heeft gestuurd een schilderkist met verf<c type="kk">/</c> penseelen<c type="kk">/</c> palet<c type="kk">/</c> tempermes<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> olie<c type="kk">/</c> terpentijn<c type="kk">/</c> enfin met al het noodige.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Zoodat het er dus nu door is dat ik ook aan ’t schilderen zal tijgen &amp; ik ben er maar blij om dat het daartoe gekomen is.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wel, dezen laatsten tijd heb ik heel wat geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> vooral van figuurstudies. Als gij die nu zaagt zoudt ge wel merken welken weg ik uitga<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Natuurlijk ben ik zeer verlangend om te hooren wat M. mij nu verder zeggen zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Heb dezer dagen ook eens kinderen geteekend<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en dat is mij erg goed bevallen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het is dezer dagen buiten prachtig van kleur &amp; toon<c type="kk">/</c> juist als ik wat licht krijg in ’t schilderen zal ik er eenmaal toe komen om iets daarvan uit te drukken doch wij moeten voet bij stek houden &amp; nu ik aan ’t figuurteekenen ben zet ik dat door totdat ik een eind verder ben &amp; als ik buiten werk dan is ’t om boomstudies te maken doch eigentlijk de boomen beschouwende alsof ’t figuren waren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> ze vooral beschouwende met het oog op den contour<c type="kk">/</c> de proportie &amp; hoe ze in elkaar zitten. Dat is het eerste waar men mede te maken heeft. Daarna komt het modeleeren &amp; de kleur en de omgeving en juist over die kwestie moet ik ’t eens met M. hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar Theo, ik ben toch zoo blij met mijn schilderkist &amp; ’t is beter dunkt mij dat ik die nu pas in handen krijg<c type="kk">/</c> na reeds minstens een jaar geteekend te hebben uitsluitend<c type="kk">/</c> dan dat ik er onmiddelijk mee begonnen was. Mij dunkt dat zult ge wel met mij eens zijn.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10"><supplied>N</supplied>u heb ik in mijn vorigen brief nog vergeten U te zeggen dat ik het toch zoo best vind dat gij eens naar Londen zult gaan<c type="kp">_</c> Minder gaarne zou ik er U voorgoed zien heentrekken doch het is nu erg best gij er eens mede zult kennis maken. Maar op den duur zoudt ge er geloof ik niet aarden<c type="kk">/</c> althans ’t wordt mij hoe langs hoe duidelijker dat mij aangaande ik er toch eigentlijk niet in mijn element was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Hier in Holland voel ik mij toch veel meer t’huis ja, ik geloof dat ik weer door &amp; door een Hollander zal worden &amp; vindt ge niet dat dat eigentlijk het meest raisonable is. Ik denk dat ik weer geheel &amp; al hollander zal worden zoowel in karakter als ook in manier van doen wat teekenen &amp; schilderen betreft. Evenwel geloof ik dat het mij nog wel te stade zal komen dat ik ook een tijd buitenslands ben geweest &amp; daar een &amp; ander heb gezien wat niet overbodig is te kennen. Als gij te Londen komt zou ik wel graag hebben gij mijn oude kameraads George Read &amp; Richardson eens hartelijk voor mij wildet groeten<c type="kp">_</c> Den Hr Obach ontmoette ik dezen zomer te s’Hage.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">George Read is als ge wilt een erg gewoon mensch in zoover dat hij misschien niet zich ’t zij in zaken ’t zij in kennis <hi rend="italics">bijzonder</hi> onderscheidt doch als mensch &amp; <hi rend="italics">karakter</hi><c type="kk">/</c> als men hem wat intiem kent is er geen trouwer<c type="kk">/</c> geen hartelijker<c type="kk">/</c> geen fijngevoeliger kerel dan hij. Hij is zoo leuk &amp; zoo geestig &amp; zoo bij de hand in het huiselijk leven dat in dat opzigt hij veel waard is als vriend. Als ik kiezen mogt wie ik ’t liefst weer eens terug zou zien van degenen die ik in Engeland heb leeren kennen dan zou het geloof ik bepaald George Read zijn. Daarom moet ge als ge mij pleizier wilt doen eens een praatje met hem maken<c type="kk">/</c> ge weet ik bedoel de oudste van de twee<c type="kk">/</c> en hem eens zeggen dat ik hoop wij onze kennis van vroeger eens zullen vernieuwen &amp; dat ik hem eens schrijven zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dit denk ik echter eerst te doen nadat gij hem zult gesproken hebben en nadat ik aan ’t schilderen ben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Want Theo<c type="kk">/</c> met dat schilderen begint mijn eigentlijke carrière<c type="kk">/</c> vind ge ’t ook niet goed ’t maar zoo te beschouwen. En nu gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang een handdruk in gedachten &amp; geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Since <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> are writing, I’ll enclose a few words, but hope to write to you soon in more detail, namely after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s visit, who’s going to Princenhage soon and will also come here. I must tell you, Theo, that M. sent me a painting box with paint, brushes, palette, palette knife,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> oil, turpentine, in short, with all the necessaries.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">So now it’s settled that I’ll also set about painting, and I’m really glad it’s come to this.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Well, recently I’ve done a great deal of drawing, especially figure studies. If you saw them now, you’d surely see what direction I’m taking.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Naturally I’m extremely eager to hear what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M</rs>. will have to say to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Have also drawn some children recently,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and I liked that very much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">These days it’s beautiful outdoors in colour and tone, when I’ve gained some understanding of painting I’ll get around to expressing some of it, but we have to persevere, and now that I’m drawing figures I’ll go on with that until I’ve made a good deal more progress, and if I work outdoors it will be to do studies of trees, though actually viewing the trees as if they were figures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I mean, viewing them particularly with an eye to outline, proportion and how they’re constructed. That’s the first thing one has to consider. After that comes the modelling and the colour and the surroundings, and it’s precisely this problem that I must discuss with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But Theo, I’m really so happy with my painting box, and it’s better, it seems to me, that I’ve got it only now, after having drawn exclusively for at least a year, than if I’d started with it immediately. I think you’ll agree with me there. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now then, in my previous letter I forgot to tell you that I really think it very good that you’ll be going to London. I’d like it less if you were to move there for good, but it’s excellent that you’ll now become acquainted with it. But in the long run I don’t think you’d feel at home there, at least it’s becoming increasingly clear to me that, speaking for myself, I wasn’t really in my element there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I really do feel much more at home here in Holland, yes, I think that I’ll again become a Dutchman through and through, and don’t you think that’s actually the most sensible thing? I think that I’ll again become thoroughly Dutch both in character and in my manner of doing things as regards drawing and painting. Though I do think it will help me to have been abroad for a while and to have seen one thing and another there which is not unuseful to know. When you go to London, I’d like it very much if you would give my kind regards to my old mates <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_621">George Read</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_636">Richardson</rs>. I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_547">Mr Obach</rs> this summer in The Hague.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_621">George Read</rs> is, if you will, a very ordinary person inasmuch as he perhaps doesn’t <hi rend="italics">particularly </hi>distinguish himself, whether in business or in knowledge, but as a person and <hi rend="italics">character</hi>, if one knows him rather intimately, there is no more faithful, more kind, more sensitive chap than he. He’s so nice and so witty and so capable in domestic life that in that respect he’s worth a lot as a friend. If I were allowed to choose whom I should most like to see again from those I became acquainted with in England, it would definitely be George Read, I think. Which is why, if you want to do me a favour, you must chat with him sometime – you realize I mean the elder of the two – and tell him that I hope some day to renew our earlier acquaintance and that I’ll write to him sometime.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I mean to do it, though, only after you’ve spoken to him and after I’ve started to paint.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Because, Theo, my actual career begins with painting, don’t you think it’s all right to see it that way? And now regards, accept a handshake in thought, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
      <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 dates this letter to 22-24 December 1881, but on the basis of its contents it is more likely to have been written shortly after <ref target="let176.xml">letter 176</ref> of 15 October. An expected visit from Mauve is described in both letters in nearly the same words (<ref target="let177.xml#l-3">letter 177, ll. 3-4</ref> as well as <ref target="let176.xml#l-43">letter 176, ll. 43-44</ref>). The fact that Van Gogh talks about drawing figures (‘children’) and landscapes (‘studies of trees’) also concurs with his activities in mid-October (<ref target="#l-16">ll. 16-25</ref> and <ref target="#l-74">ll. 74-75</ref>, respectively). The letter was probably written after <ref target="let175.xml">175</ref>, since that letter does not mention Mauve’s visit as anything more than a possibility. Because <ref target="let175.xml">letter 175</ref> is dated between 12 and 15 October and <ref target="let176.xml">letter 176</ref> 15 October, the present letter must have been written after the 15th. In view of the parallel phrasing in <ref target="let176.xml">letter 176</ref> we have dated this letter to shortly thereafter: on or about 17 October 1881. Cf. exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 63 (n. 1), which suggests (but gives no arguments for) a dating in October 1881.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>A palette knife is a flat knife used to mix small amounts of paint and to scrape paint off a rubbing stone (also called a muller).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>These drawings of children from the Etten period are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl with a black cap sitting on the ground</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_324">F 873 / JH 79</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl kneeling in front of a bucket</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_325">F 880 / JH 76</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl kneeling</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_326">F 881 / JH 77</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl raking</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_327">F 884 / JH 57</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl standing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_328">F 896 / JH 78</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    