<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Thursday, 3 November 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let179"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b173 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>179</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>153</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>177</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-03">Thursday, 3 November 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0173" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0173" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000185_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Etten 3/9 1881</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Er ligt me iets op ’t hart dat ik U vertellen wil. Misschien weet ge er reeds iets van &amp; vertel ik U geen nieuws.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik wilde U zeggen dat ik dezen zomer zooveel ben gaan houden van Kee Vos dat ik er geen andere woorden voor kon vinden dan “’t is net of Kee Vos mijn naaste is en ik de naaste van Kee Vos”. en ─ die woorden heb ik tot haar gezegd. Doch toen ik haar dit zeide antwoordde zij mij dat haar verleden en haar toekomst voor haar een bleven en zij dus nooit mijne gevoelens kon beantwoorden.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Toen was ik in een geduchten tweestrijd wat te doen, mij te resigneeren tot dat nooit neen nimmer of ─ nog niet de zaak voor beslist &amp; geeindigd te houden en nog wat goeden moed te houden en ’t nog niet op te geven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">’t Laatste koos ik.─ En tot heden heb ik geen berouw van die opvatting hoewel ik nog altijd sta voor dat nooit neen nimmer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Natuurlijk heb ik sedert heel wat “petites misères de la vie humaine”<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> ondervonden, die, als ze in een boek geschreven waren, mogelijk zouden kunnen dienen om den een of ander te amuseeren doch als men ze zelf beleeft zeker geen aangename gewaarwordingen kunnen geacht worden te wezen. Evenwel tot op heden ben ik blij dat ik ’t resignatie- of “how <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to do it” systeem<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> maar overliet voor wie er trek in hebben &amp; mij aangaande nog wat moed vatte. Ge begrijpt dat ’t in een geval als dit ’t verbazend moeielijk is te weten wat men doen kan<c type="kk">/</c> doen mag &amp; doen moet. Doch “al dwalende vinden we ’t spoor”<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> &amp; niet al stilzittende.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Een der redenen waarom ik U tot heden er niet over schreef is dat de positie waarin ik mij bevond zoo vaag &amp; ongedecideerd was dat ik die U niet kon uitleggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu evenwel zijn we zoo ver dat ik er over heb gesproken ─ behalve tot haar zelve ─ tot Pa en Moe<c type="kk">/</c> tot Oom &amp; Tante Stricker<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp; tot Oom &amp; tante te Prinsenhage.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> De eenige die<c type="kk">/</c> doch dat zeer officieus en in ’t apart<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/> mij gezegd heeft dat er werkelijk indien ik hard werkte &amp; voorspoed had kans voor mij was<c type="kk">/</c> is iemand van wien ik ’t volstrekt niet wachtte,<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> Oom Cent. Deze had schik in de manier waarop ik ’t nooit neen nimmer van Kee opvatte<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk het niet zwaar tillende maar dat ik er zoowat gekheid mee maakte<c type="kk">/</c> b.v<c type="kp">_</c>: geef toch geen koren op den molen van nooit neen nimmer die Kee Vos er op na houdt, ik wensch haar alles goeds toe behalve alleen dat ik hoop dat voornoemde korenmolen failliet zal gaan. Evenzoo trok ik ’t mij niet erg aan toen Oom Stricker er van sprak dat er gevaar was ik “vriendschappelijke verhoudingen &amp; oude banden zoude verbreken”<c type="kk">/</c> ik zei daarop dat mijns inziens ’t onderhavige geval wel verre van oude banden te verbreken de oude banden waar ze reparatie noodig hadden kon vernieuwen. Enfin en zoo hoop ik te blijven doen en zwaarmoedigheid &amp; zwaartillendheid verre van mij te doen. Intusschen hard werkende en sedert ik haar ontmoet heb vlot mijn werk veel beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik zeide dat nu de positie zich zoo wat decideerd.<ptr target="#note-t-c"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">1<hi rend="super">o</hi> Kee zegt nooit neen nimmer en verder geloof ik dat ik enorm veel moeite zal hebben met de oudere personen die de zaak reeds nu voor beslist &amp; geeindigd houden en mij zullen trachten te dwingen er van af te zien. Vooralsnog evenwel geloof ik zij zeer zacht te werk 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>zullen gaan<c type="kk">/</c> mij aan ’t lijntje houden en met een kluitje in ’t riet sturen totdat het groote feest van Oom &amp; Tante Stricker (in December)<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> voorbij zal zijn. Want men wil opspraak vermijden. Daarna echter vrees ik er maatregelen genomen zullen worden om mij er uit te knikkeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vergeef me deze wat harde termen die ik gebruik om U de positie duidelijk te maken; ik geef toe dat de kleuren wat hard zijn &amp; de lijnen wat sterk getrokken maar ’t zal U toch een duidelijker inzigt in de zaak geven dan wanneer ik er om heen praatte. Verdenk mij dus niet van gebrek aan achting jegens die Oudere personen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Alleen geloof ik dat zij er bepaald <hi rend="italics">tegen</hi> zijn &amp; wil U dit doen zien. Zij zullen trachten te zorgen dat Kee &amp; ik elkaar noch zullen kunnen zien noch spreken noch schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat zij zeer wel begrijpen dat indien we elkaar zagen<c type="kk">/</c> spraken of schreven er kans was op gedachten verandering van Kee. Kee zelf meent nooit van gedachten te veranderen &amp; de oudere personen trachten mij te overtuigen zij niet veranderen kan doch hebben toch vrees voor die verandering.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">De oudere personen toch zullen omtrent deze zaak van gedachten veranderen niet dan wanneer Kee van gezindheid veranderd doch dan wanneer ik iemand zal geworden zijn die op zijn minst f 1000 per jaar verdien.─ Nog eens, vergeef de harde contours waarmee ik de dingen afteeken. Indien ik weinig sympathie vinde bij de ouderen zoo geloof ik dat sommige jongeren zich mijne houding zullen kunnen begrijpen. Misschien gij Theo ─ Gij zult misschien wel van mij hooren zeggen dat ik forceeren wil &amp; dergelijke uitdrukkingen. Doch wie begrijpt niet hoe onzinnig forceeren is bij liefde! Neen dat is verre verre van mij. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Doch ’t is geen onbillijk of onredelijk verlangen dat ik wensch dat Kee &amp; ik inplaats van geen omgang met elkaar te mogen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> elkaar zullen zien<c type="kk">/</c> spreken of schrijven om<c type="kk">/</c> elkaar beter leerende kennen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">zelf</hi> beter te kunnen inzien of wij voor elkaar geschikt zijn al dan niet. Een jaar van omgang met elkaar zou heilzaam wezen voor haar &amp; voor mij doch de ouderen zijn werkelijk verstokt op dat punt. Ware ik rijk zij zouden heel anders spreken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Doch nu begrijpt ge wel dat ik niets hoop ongedaan te laten wat mij nader moge brengen tot haar en ’t is mijn voornemen</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Zoo lang zal ik haar beminnen</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Tot ze in ’t eind mij ook bemint.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Plus elle disparaît plus elle apparaît.─<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Theo, zijt gij soms ook verliefd, ik wenschte wel dat gij het waart want geloof me dat ook de “petites misères” er van hun waarde hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Men is soms in desolatie<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn momenten waarin men als ’t ware in de hel is<c type="kk">/</c> doch ─ er is ook iets anders &amp; beters aan verbonden<c type="kp">_</c> Er zijn 3 trappen<c type="kk">/</c> 1<hi rend="super">0</hi> niet beminnen &amp; niet bemind worden<c type="kk">/</c> 2<hi rend="super">0</hi> beminnen &amp; niet bemind worden (’t onderhavige geval)<c type="kk">/</c> 3<hi rend="super">0</hi> beminnen &amp; bemind worden.─</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Nu zeg ik dat de tweede trap beter is dan de eerste, maar de derde! dat is <hi rend="italics">datte</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Nu, old boy, word nu ook maar verliefd, en vertel me dat dan ook eens. Houd U leuk<ptr target="#note-t-d"/> in ’t onderhavige geval en heb wat sympathie voor me. Ik had natuurlijk veel liever een ja en amen doch ik ben toch vast al blij met mijn “<hi rend="italics">nooit neen nimmer</hi>”. Ik houd dat voor <hi rend="italics">iets</hi> doch oudere &amp; wijzere menschen zeggen het is <hi rend="italics">niets</hi>. Rappard is hier geweest<c type="kk">/</c> bragt aquarellen mee die goed worden<c type="kp">_</c> Mauve komt hoop ik spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> anders ga ik naar hem. Ik teeken veel en geloof ’t beter wordt<c type="kk">/</c> ik werk veel meer met ’t penseel dan vroeger. Nu is ’t zoo koud dat ik haast uitsluitend figuur teeken binnenshuis, naaister<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> mandemaker &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Een handdruk in gedachten &amp; schrijf spoedig &amp; geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Men heeft mij willen laten beloven dat ik volstrekt niet meer over deze zaak zal spreken of schrijven doch ik heb dit niet willen beloven, geen mensch ter wereld kan mijns inziens billijkerwijs zooiets van mij (of wie dan ook in t’zelfde geval) vergen. Alleen heb ik aan Oom Cent de verzekering gegeven dat ik voorloopig wel wilde staken aan Oom Stricker te schrijven tot onvoorziene omstandigheden ’t noodig maken mogten. Een leeuwrik kan in de lente ’t zingen niet laten.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Als gij ooit verliefd wordt en een nooit neen nimmer mogt krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> resigneer U vooral niet! doch gij zijt zoo’n gelukskind dat iets dergelijks U wel niet overkomen zal<c type="kk">/</c> hoop ik.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Etten, 3/9 1881</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">There’s something on my mind that I want to tell you. Perhaps you already know something about it, and what I’m telling you isn’t news.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I wanted to tell you that this summer I’ve come to love <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs> so much that I could find no other words for it than ‘it’s just as if Kee Vos were the closest person to me and I the closest person to Kee Vos’. And — I said these words to her. But when I told her this, she replied that her past and her future were all one to her and so she could never return my feelings.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Then I was in an awful dilemma about what to do, to resign myself to that no, nay, never, or — not yet to regard the matter as over and done with, and to take courage and not give up yet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I chose the latter. And until now I haven’t regretted that decision, even though I’m still confronted with that no, nay, never.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Since then, of course, I’ve suffered a great many ‘petty miseries of human life’,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> which, if they were written down in a book, could perhaps serve to amuse some people, though they can hardly be considered pleasant if one experiences them oneself. Nonetheless, up to now I’ve been glad that I left the resignation or ‘how-<hi rend="italics">not-</hi>to-do-it’ method<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> to those who prefer it and, as for myself, plucked up a little courage. You understand that in cases like this it’s surprisingly difficult to know what one can, may and must do. But ‘wandering we find our way’,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and not by sitting still. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">One of the reasons I haven’t written to you about it before now is that the position in which I found myself was so vague and undecided that I couldn’t explain it to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Now, though, we’ve progressed to the point where I’ve spoken about it — in addition to her — to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>, to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317 bio.xml#_318">Uncle and Aunt Stricker</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423 bio.xml#_853">Uncle and Aunt</rs> at Princenhage.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> The only one who said to me, though very informally and in private, that I did indeed have a chance if I worked hard and prospered, is one from whom I didn’t expect it at all, Uncle Cent. He was amused at the way I took <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs>’s no, nay, never, i.e. by making light of it and sort of joking about it, bring no grist to Kee Vos’s mill of no, nay, never, for example, I wish her all good things, apart from hoping that the aforementioned flour-mill will go bankrupt. Likewise I didn’t much mind when Uncle Stricker said there was a danger I ‘would sever friendly relations and break old ties’, to which I replied that in my opinion the case in question, far from breaking old ties, could renew the old ties where they were in need of repair. At any rate, I hope to go on like this and to keep well away from melancholy and pessimism. Meanwhile working hard, and since meeting her my work is going much better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I said that now the situation is becoming somewhat clearer. First, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs> says no, nay, never, and furthermore I believe that I’ll have tremendous difficulty with the elders who already regard the matter as over and done with and will try and force me to give up. For the time being, though, I believe they’ll proceed with caution, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> keeping me dangling and fobbing me off until <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317 bio.xml#_318">Uncle and Aunt Stricker</rs>’s big celebration (in December)<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> is over. Because they want to avoid scandal. After that, though, I fear that steps will be taken to get rid of me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Forgive the rather harsh terms I’m using to make my position clear to you. I admit that the colours are a little harsh and the lines drawn a bit too hard, but it will nevertheless give you a clearer picture of the situation than if I were to beat about the bush. So don’t suspect me of lack of respect for those Elder persons.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Only I believe that they’re decidedly <hi rend="italics">against</hi> it, and I want to make you see this. They’ll try and see to it that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs> and I can neither see nor speak nor write to one another, just because they understand very well that if we were to see, speak or write to one another there would be a chance of a change of heart in Kee. Kee herself thinks she‘ll never change her mind and, though the elder persons are trying to convince me that she can’t change, they fear that change nonetheless.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The elder persons will change their minds about this matter not when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs> changes her mind but when I become someone who earns at least 1,000 guilders a year. Again, forgive the hard contours with which I outline things. While I find little sympathy from the elders, I think that some of the younger ones will be able to understand my attitude. Perhaps you, Theo. Perhaps you’ve heard it said of me that I want to force the issue and suchlike expressions. But who doesn’t understand how senseless it is to try and force love! No, that’s far, far from my thoughts. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> But it’s not unfair or unreasonable to wish that Kee and I, instead of not being allowed to see one another, will see, speak and write to one another so that, getting to know each other better, we’ll be able to see for <hi rend="italics">ourselves</hi> whether or not we’re suited to each other. A year of contact with one another would be beneficial for her and for me, yet the elders won’t budge on this point. If I were rich they’d talk altogether differently.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Yet by now you understand that I mean to leave no stone unturned in my endeavours to bring me closer to her, and I declare that</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I shall love her so long</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">That in the end she’ll love me too.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The more she disappears, the more she appears.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Theo, aren’t you in love too, at times? I wish you were, for believe me, the ‘petty miseries’ of it are also of some value. Sometimes one is desolate, there are moments when one is in hell, as it were, but — it also brings with it other and better things. There are three stages, first not loving and not being loved, second loving and not being loved (the case in question), third loving and being loved.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’d say that the second stage is better than the first, but the third! That’s <hi rend="italics">it</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Now, old boy, go and fall in love and tell me about it sometime. Keep quiet about the case in question and sympathize with me. I’d much rather have a yea and amen, of course, but meanwhile I’m really rather happy with my ‘<hi rend="italics">no, nay, never</hi>’. I consider that <hi rend="italics">something</hi>, but older and wiser people say it’s <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi>. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> was here, brought along watercolours that are becoming good. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is coming soon, I hope, otherwise I’ll go to him. I’m drawing a great deal and think it’s getting better, I’m working much more with the brush than I used to. Now it’s so cold that practically all I do is draw figures inside, seamstress,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> basket-maker &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">A handshake in thought, and write soon, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">They wanted me to promise not to say or write anything more on this subject, but I wouldn’t promise that; no one in the world, in my opinion, can reasonably demand such a thing of me (or of anyone else in the same situation). I’ve only given assurances to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Cent</rs> that I would stop writing to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs> for the time being, until unforeseen circumstances should make it necessary. A lark can’t help singing in the spring.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">If you should ever fall in love and receive a no, nay, never, by no means resign yourself to it! But you’re such a lucky dog that something like this will probably never happen to you, I hope.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Etten 3/9 1881’. Van Gogh used the Latin word for nine to indicate the month: ‘novem’; cf. <ref target="let157.xml">letter 157</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s visit to Etten <ref target="let178.xml">(178)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_806">Christoffel Vos</rs>, the husband of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs>, had died on 27 October 1878. In the summer of 1881 Kee came to Etten for a lengthy stay, and she and Vincent spent a great deal of time together (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let183.xml">letter 183</ref>). Probably thinking that she was just as fond of him as he was of her, he made her a proposal of marriage (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let180.xml">180</ref>). He did not tell Theo about it, however.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
    
<p>A reference to <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_222"><hi rend="italics">Petites misères de la vie humaine</hi></ref>, a book by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_748">Old Nick</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_745">Grandville</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let178.xml#n-6">see letter 178, n. 6</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh frequently used this expression, which he borrowed from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Charles Dickens</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_199"><hi rend="italics">Little Dorrit</hi></ref>: ‘How to do it must obviously be regarded as the natural and mortal enemy of How not to do it.’ See Dickens 1979, p. 500. The expression recurs in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let212.xml">letters 212</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let214.xml">214</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let220.xml">220</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let244.xml">244</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let289.xml">289</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let291.xml">291</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let306.xml">306</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let401.xml">401</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>Taken from the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_227">Onvermoeid</ref>’ (Tireless) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">P.A. de Génestet</rs>. See De Génestet 1869, vol. 2, p. 90. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let193.xml#n-25">letter 193, n. 25</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs> was the daughter of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">J.P. Stricker</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317">Willemina Catharina Gerardina Carbentus</rs>, a sister of Mrs van Gogh, which made her Vincent’s first cousin.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423 bio.xml#_853">Uncle Vincent and Aunt Cornelie van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘onder vier ogen’ (in private).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘verwachtte’ (expected).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘duidelijk wordt welke standpunten men inneemt’ (it’s becoming clear what the situation is, i.e. what the various standpoints are).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The celebration held to mark the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317 bio.xml#_318">Strickers</rs>’ 40th anniversary on 7 December 1881.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The closing lines of the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_228">De edelmoedige wedervergelding</ref>’ (The noble retaliation) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1">Hieronymus van Alphen</rs>. See Van Alphen 1857, vol. 1, pp. 405-406. Also quoted in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let180.xml">letter 180</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Possibly a quotation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="d" xml:id="note-t-d">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘houd u stil’, ‘doe alsof u van niets weet’ (keep quiet about it, pretend to know nothing).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>During this period Van Gogh made a number of drawings of women sewing in which he used watercolour: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_331">F 867 / JH 67</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_331">F 885 / JH 71</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_251">F 886 / JH 69</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_250">F 887 / JH 73</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman mending stockings</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_332">F 888 / JH 68</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_331">F 1221 / JH 70</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Drawings of basket-makers are not known, but there are various drawings of models engaged in other indoor activities. It is impossible to say which drawings Van Gogh is referring to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    