<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. Etten, Saturday, 12 November 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let184"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8338 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>184</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R4</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>182</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-12">Saturday, 12 November 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8338 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8338 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001582_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8338 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8338 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001583_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Etten 12/9-1881</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Van wege ik tot heden geen brief van U ontving zoo dacht ik: Waarschijnlijk is Rappard mijn laatste schrijven volstrekt niet bevallen<c type="kk">/</c> er schijnt iets in geweest te zijn dat hem wat wrevelig gemaakt heeft. Qu’y faire<c type="kp">_</c>– Gesteld dat ware zoo<c type="kk">/</c> is dat dan waarachtig goed van U. Ik weet het zelf niet altijd regt te beoordeelen in hoe ver mijne redeneering juist of onjuist<c type="kk">/</c> gepast of ongepast is. Doch dit weet ik wel<c type="kk">/</c> dat ook als ik nu en dan mij mogelijk ruw en hard uitdruk jegens U ik toch eene zoo warme sympathie voor U heb dat ge toch wel bij bedaarde lezing of herlezing van mijn schrijven zien zult en voelen – die persoon die zoo tot mij spreekt is mijn vijand niet.– En dit eenmaal wetende<c type="kk">/</c> is het dan zoo ten eenemale ondragelijk voor U zelfs wat ruwe en harde uitdrukkingen te slikken die misschien later blijken zullen minder hard &amp; ruw te zijn dan ge aanvankelijk wel meendet.– Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> waarom denkt ge dat het is dat ik tot U spreek zoo als ik spreek of schrijf. Zou dat wezen omdat ik U een strik wil spannen en een soort verleider ben die U in een put wil laten vallen of zou ’t misschien zijn kunnen dat ik werkelijk reden had om te denken “Rappard waagt zich op glad ijs!”– Ik weet nu wel dat er menschen zijn die ook op glad ijs niet alleen staande blijven en er zelfs tours de force op weten te verrigten – maar zelfs al stond ge zóó vast in Uw schoenen (ik zeg niet dat ge er niet zoo vast in staat) dan toch nog zie ik zelfs de zoodanigen liever op een voetpad of straatweg marcheeren.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Word nu niet boos – lees door – tot het eind toe – als ge boos word verscheur dezen brief niet ongelezen – tel eerst tot tien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">een – twee – drie &amp;c.......</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dat calmeert.. er komt echter iets heel ergs – hoor! ’t Geen ik zeggen wil is dit:</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof dat gij ook dan wanneer ge op de akademie werkt ge meer en meer een echt realist zoekt te worden en ook op de akademie U houdt aan ’t reele. Evenwel zonder U zelven daarvan bewust te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> sans le savoir<c type="kk">/</c> is die akademie eene maitresse die verhindert dat er eene meer serieuse<c type="kk">/</c> meer warme<c type="kk">/</c> meer vruchtbare liefde in U wakker wordt.– Laat die maitresse loopen en wordt tot over de ooren verliefd op Uwe eigentlijke beminde<c type="kk">/</c> dame nature of réalité<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik ben aldus ook verliefd geraakt en dat wel tot over de ooren op een dame nature of realité, en voel me sedert zoo gelukkig ofschoon zij mij nog erg wederstaat en zij mij nog niet hebben wil en mij dikwijls op de vingers tikt als ik haar reeds voorbarig als de mijne zou durven beschouwen. Ik ben er dus verre van daan om te zeggen dat ik haar reeds verkregen heb<c type="kk">/</c> doch wel dat ik naar haar ding en den sleutel van haar hart zoek ondanks gevoelige tikken op de vingers.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu behoeft ge niet te denken dat er slechts één vrouw Dame nature of realité is<c type="kk">/</c> neen dat is maar de geslachsnaam van verscheidene zusters, die verschillende voornamen hebben. Wij hoeven dus geen rivaux te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> As-tu compris mon cher. C’est purement artistique<c type="kk">/</c> bien entendu, n’est ce pas?</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu zijn er mijns inziens twee soorten van maitressen. De eene soort is die bij welke men liefde kan nemen en geven<c type="kk">/</c> intusschen zich bewust zijnde van een kant of van weerskanten dat het niet voor altijd is noch ook men zich zonder slag om den arm &amp; sans arriere pensee overgeeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ces maitresses-là elles énervent, elles flattent, elles gâtent<c type="kk">/</c> puis – puis – elles vous brûlent pas mal d’hommes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">De tweede soort maitressen zijn van heel ander kaliber. Collet montées – pharisiennes – jésuites!!! ’t Zijn zoodanige femmes de marbre – sphinx – vipères glacées<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – welke mannen aan zich zouden willen verbinden<c type="kk">/</c> geheel en al<c type="kk">/</c> eens en voor altijd<c type="kk">/</c> zonder van haar kant zich ooit geheel en al zonder slag om den arm<c type="kk">/</c> sans arrière pensee over te geven. Elles sucent le sang<c type="kp">_</c> Ces maîtresses-là elles <hi rend="italics">glacent</hi> les hommes, et les <hi rend="italics">pétrifient</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Doch ik zeide ’t was purement artistique, mon cher – en dus vergelijk ik de eerste soort maîtressen, celles qui brûlent, bij die rigting der kunst die in ’t gemeene vervalt. en dan vergelijk ik die andere soort maitressen (collet montées)<c type="kk">/</c> celles qui glacent et pétrifient<c type="kk">/</c> bij de akademische realiteit of – of – wilt ge dat ik de pil vergulden zal<c type="kk">/</c> bij de niet onakademische realiteit – meer verguldsel wil er op de pil niet blijven vastplakken<c type="kk">/</c> ik vrees ge zult er door heen kijken. De pil is bitter, doch ze is gezond; ’t is een quinine pil.–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">As-tu compris, mon cher!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu zijn er – God dank – behalve deze twee soorten van vrouwen nog anderen – dat is die familie dames Nature en Réalité maar ’t kost veel zielstrijd om er zoo een te winnen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Zij eischen niets meer of niets minder dan geheele overgave van hart<c type="kk">/</c> ziel<c type="kk">/</c> verstand in een bepaalde rigting<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">al</hi> de liefde die in ons is en dan – dan – geven ze ook zich zelven. Deze echte dames natures zijn echter hoewel opregt als de duiven tegelijk voorzigtig als de slangen<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en weten zeer wel te onderscheiden wie opregt is en wie onopregt.– 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Elle renouvelle<c type="kk">/</c> elle retrempe<c type="kk">/</c> elle donne la vie! cette dame Nature<c type="kk">/</c> cette dame Realité<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn menschen<c type="kk">/</c> en misschien zijn gij en ik zoodanigen<c type="kk">/</c> die eerst pas als ze werkelijk lief hebben in zien dat zij vóór dien tijd<c type="kk">/</c> soit le sachant<c type="kk">/</c> soit sans le savoir, maitressen van ’t een of ander dezer kalibers gehad hebben of misschien niet onbekend zijn met beide rassen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Tu as donc selon moi, une maîtresse qui te glace<c type="kk">/</c> te pétrifie et te suce le sang<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Dus vriend ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ge moet U uit de armen van die femme de marbre (of is ’t maar pleister??? quelle horreur!) los maken anders vriest ge dood!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Geloof intusschen dat indien ik een verleider ben, die U in een diepen put wil trekken<c type="kk">/</c> dit wel eens de “puits de la vérité” kon zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin – prijs me nu geen niet onakademische maitresse (in ’t artistieke) meer aan hoor! Mijns inziens is ’t een helleveeg. Mon cher<c type="kk">/</c> je suis d’avis qu’elle te trompera si tu te laisses prendre<c type="kp">_</c>– Envoie la à tous les diables.– Faites la décamper plus vite que ça<c type="kp">_</c>– C’est purement artistique cependant, n’est ce pas – mon cher?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Eh quoi! Si en dehors et en outre de ça c’était encore autre chose – tant mieux – je ne m’en dédis pas. quand bien même tu voudrais prendre mes paroles en sens non figuré. As tu compris, mon cher, et – et – dites moi – m’écriras tu maintenant plus vite que ça, hein! Crois moi toujours<c type="kk">/</c> avec une poignee de main</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik heb dezer dagen een teekening gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> Schofttijd<c type="kk">/</c> een arbeider die koffij zit te drinken en een snee brood snijdt. Op den grond een schop waar hij mee van ’t veld is gekomen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Elle est un peu froide pourtant, mon cher, celle que tu dis aimer<c type="kk">/</c> celle qui provisoirement est ton ideal. Elle est bien telle que je me l’etais figurée – marbre<c type="kk">/</c> plâtre<c type="kk">/</c> que sais je – tout ou plus sonnambule. Vivante<c type="kk">/</c> non.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Tu dis donc:</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">d’où elle vient?... du ciel</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">où elle reste?..... au monde entier</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ses intentions?.... le beau et le sublime<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Mais, ma foi, tu es sincère du moins, et sans le savoir tu es bien d’accord avec moi en ceci que tu conviens donc avoir une maîtresse. de parmi celles que j’ai designées sous le nom de collet montées &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c.</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">C’est bien ça, justement, tu la décris fort bien. Mais, qu’elle est pharisienne, cette belle-là, et toi<c type="kk">/</c> comme tu en es amoureux, quel dommage!</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Madame<c type="kk">/</c> qui êtes vous? Je suis “la belle<c type="kk">/</c> la sublime”<c type="kp">_</c> Dites moi, cependant, ma belle et sublime<c type="kk">/</c> celle qui se sent telle<c type="kk">/</c> l’est elle effectivement. J’admets bien que dans certains crises de la vie<c type="kk">/</c> dans la grande douleur<c type="kk">/</c> dans l’exaltation de joie l’on puisse se sentir et belle et sublime<c type="kk">/</c> et certes j’espère bien être de ceux qui savent apprécier ces choses-là. Toutefois est-il que Vous, Madame, me laissez froid et sans émotion aucune<c type="kp">_</c> comment ça se fait-il<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Je n’ai pourtant pas le cuir trop épais<c type="kk">/</c> j’espère bien<c type="kk">/</c> des personnes pas même jolies<c type="kk">/</c> pas précisement sublimes m’ont souvent charmées mais vous, Madame, vous ne me charmez pas le moins du monde. Du beau et du sublime<c type="kk">/</c> on n’en fait pas profession!</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Madame<c type="kk">/</c> je ne vous aime point et puis je ne crois pas que vous-même sachiez aimer à moins que ce ne soit dans certains ciels académiques<c type="kk">/</c> va encore – mais soit sur la bruyère soit au coin du feu dans l’intimité<c type="kk">/</c> non<c type="kk">/</c> point<c type="kp">_</c>– Ne me chantez pas ça<c type="kk">/</c> Madame la belle<c type="kk">/</c> la sublime<c type="kk">/</c> vous n’en savez rien du tout.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Voyez vous Madame, moi je ne suis qu’un homme à passions humaines, et tant que je me promène “ici bas” sur la bruyère<c type="kk">/</c> je n’ai pas le temps de m’occuper d’un amour céleste et mystique<c type="kk">/</c> tant que j’en sens un autre<c type="kk">/</c> de nature plus terrestre et plus franc. Du beau et du sublime il m’en faut bien<c type="kk">/</c> je l’admets<c type="kk">/</c> mais il me faut avant tout encore autre chose que ça – pour commencer – de la bonté<c type="kk">/</c> de la bonne volonté<c type="kk">/</c> de la tendresse<c type="kk">/</c> en avez vous beaucoup<c type="kk">/</c> Madame la pharisienne? Je suis porté à en douter. Et puis – Madame, dites moi, avez vous effectivement corps et âme<c type="kk">/</c> je suis porté à en douter, ma foi tant du corps que de l’âme<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Ecoute, ma belle, de quelque part que tu prétendes venir, toi qui dis avoir pour intentions fondamentales “le beau et le sublime” (qui ne sauraient être que des <hi rend="italics">résultats</hi><c type="kk">/</c> nullement des <hi rend="italics">intentions</hi>)<c type="kk">/</c> de quelque part que tu viennes, dis je, certes ce n’est point du Sein du Dieu vivant et puis ce n’est pas non plus du sein d’une femme. Va t’en Sphinx<c type="kk">/</c> décampe plus vite que ça – te dis je – tu n’es qu’une blague. tu n’existes point. (Le tiaple n’egzisde boind<c type="kk">/</c> dirait Nucingen)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Si tu existes cependant<c type="kk">/</c> si effectivement tu viens de quelque part, es tu bien sure et certaine que ton origine n’est pas Satan lui-même<c type="kk">/</c> père du mensonge<c type="kk">/</c> es tu moins vipère et moins serpent que lui<c type="kk">/</c> Madame, la belle<c type="kk">/</c> la sublime.</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Dire qu’en tant que quant à moi ta maîtresse<c type="kk">/</c> “la belle<c type="kk">/</c> la sublime qui dit venir du ciel et demeurer sur toute la terre”<c type="kk">/</c> est une personne plus que suspecte<c type="kk">/</c> ce ne serait pas exprimer la chose fortement assez.</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">Demandez lui si elle est bonne et utile<c type="kk">/</c> si elle aime et a besoin d’amour<c type="kp">_</c> Elle se troublera et si elle dit oui, c’est un mensonge.–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Elle – c’est à dire <hi rend="italics">l’autre</hi><c type="kk">/</c> non pas celle aux “intentions” ci dessus mentionnées<c type="kk">/</c> d’où elle vient?</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">– je suis loin de nier sa divinité<c type="kk">/</c> son immortalité<c type="kk">/</c> j’y crois très certainement et même en premier lieu<c type="kk">/</c> toutefois elle est bien terrestre aussi et bien <hi rend="italics">femme</hi> et née d’une femme.</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.42" n="42">Elle? – Où elle reste<c type="kk">/</c> je sais bien où &amp; c’est pas bien loin d’un chacun de nous.</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.43" n="43">Elle – Ses intentions? qu’en sais je moi, comment le dire – je voudrais me taire – cependant<c type="kk">/</c> puisqu’il faut donc parler – eh bien – il me semble: aimer et être aimable – vivre<c type="kk">/</c> donner la vie, la renouveler, la guérir<c type="kk">/</c> l’entretenir, travailler, rendre étincelle pour étincelle<c type="kk">/</c> être bonne surtout, être utile – servir à quelque chose<c type="kk">/</c> à allumer le feu par exemple<c type="kk">/</c> à donner une tartine à un enfant<c type="kk">/</c> un verre d’eau à un malade.</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.44" n="44">Ah! mais tout ça est très beau<c type="kk">/</c> très sublime. Oui mais elle ne savait pas que ça s’appelait ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> elle croyait que c’etait tout simple<c type="kk">/</c> elle ne le fait pas exprès<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">ce n’etait pas son</hi> <hi rend="italics">intention</hi> de faire tant de bruit que ça<c type="kk">/</c> elle croyait que personne n’y prit garde.</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.45" n="45">Ses “raisonnements” à elle, vois tu<c type="kk">/</c> sont peu brillants<c type="kk">/</c> peu cherchés<c type="kp">_</c> Son sentiment est toujours juste.</p>
  
<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.46" n="46">To know what’s her duty she does not go to her head<c type="kk">/</c> she goes to her heart.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.47" n="47">Mais ça ce n’est point du tout une <hi rend="italics">maîtresse</hi><c type="kk">/</c> celle là<c type="kp">_</c> Puisqu’une <hi rend="italics">dame</hi> est une <hi rend="italics">dame</hi><c type="kk">/</c> comme dit Michelet.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p xml:lang="fr" xml:id="p.nl.48" n="48">Intusschen, Rappard, die affaire van het concours vind ik wel aardig<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.49" n="49">N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 11 is primo ’t gekkennommer en verder<c type="kk">/</c> “laatst” is ook een goed teeken somwijlen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> dus feliciteer ik U van harte er mede want mijns inziens is een &amp; ander een goed voorteeken voor U. Ça promet.–</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.50" n="50">Nu zou ik nog heel wat tegen hebben op verscheiden leerstellingen van U ook<c type="kk">/</c> doch omdat nu mijn <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> in de gegevenen bepaaldelijk die bewuste maitresse is<c type="kk">/</c> laat ik de leerstellingen met rust. Kondt ge die M<hi rend="super">me</hi> la belle<c type="kk">/</c> la sublime haar congé geven en verliefd worden op “l’autre”<c type="kk">/</c> mij dunkt dat zou heel andere leerstellingen U in ’t hoofd en in ’t hart geven. En aan sommige verschijnselen meen ik te zien dat<c type="kk">/</c> hoezeer ge ook nu nog aan M<hi rend="super">me</hi> la belle &amp; la sublime zijt gehecht<c type="kk">/</c> ge toch het niet lang meer bij haar zult uithouden. A moins qu’elle ne te pétrifie et te glace et te fixe de cette manière mais ça me parait peu probable<c type="kk">/</c> tu as trop de bon sens pour ça. Sois sur tes gardes – chauffes toi bien – tu sais – (petite précaution à prendre contre son influence glaçante)<c type="kk">/</c> puis promènes toi souvent – (surtout lorsque tu sentirais un petit commencement de pétrification)<c type="kp">_</c> Un homme avisé en vaut deux<c type="kk">/</c> donc te voilà averti.</p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.51" n="51">Ne m’en veux pas<c type="kk">/</c> si ce n’était une phrase académique<c type="kk">/</c> je dirais “c’est pour ton bien”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:lang="fr" rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.52" n="52">Enfin, bien te fasse, j’ai encore une autre <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi> à traquer<c type="kk">/</c> mais je ne te dirai pas maintenant laquelle. Ecoute cependant, je te le dirai tout de même<c type="kp">_</c> Cette autre <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi> c’est “<hi rend="italics">la résignation dans</hi> <hi rend="italics">les désappointements</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c> Encore une invention pharisienne d’un jésuitisme incroyable. Mais ça c’est theologique<c type="kk">/</c> très théologique. Mon cher<c type="kk">/</c> ne te résigne jamais et ne sois jamais désappointé<c type="kk">/</c> voila le meilleur conseil que je puisse te donner<c type="kk">/</c> il vaut même mieux que celui d’envoyer à tous les diables ta froide maîtresse<c type="kk">/</c> à plus forte raison puisque ces deux conseils n’en font qu’un. Je te serre la main<c type="kk">/</c> crois moi toujours</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.53" n="53">t. à t.</p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.54" n="54"> Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Etten, 12/9-1881</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Rappard,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Because I’ve not yet had a letter from you I thought: perhaps <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> didn’t like my last letter at all, there seems to have been something in it that has made him a little peevish. What to do? Supposing that were so, is it truly good of you? I myself am not always able to judge to what extent my reasoning is right or wrong, appropriate or inappropriate. But I do know this, that even if I occasionally address you in what are possibly coarse and harsh terms, I nevertheless feel such warm sympathy for you that you will surely see and feel when calmly reading or re-reading my letter – the person who speaks to me thus is not my enemy. And knowing this, is it then so utterly unbearable for you to swallow somewhat coarse and harsh expressions even if they later appear to be less coarse and harsh than you at first thought? <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, why do you think it is that I speak or write to you as I do? Could it be because I want to lay a trap for you or am a kind of tempter who wants to make you fall into a pit, or could it possibly be that I really had a reason to think ‘Rappard is venturing onto thin ice!’ I now know that there are people who not only maintain their footing on thin ice but even manage to perform tours de force on it – but even if you stood so firmly in your shoes (I’m not saying that you don’t stand so firmly in them), even then I’d prefer to see such a one walking on a footpath or street. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Don’t get angry now – read on – until the end – if you get angry, don’t tear up this letter without reading it – first count to ten.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">One – two – three &amp;c.......</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">That’s calming.. something <hi rend="italics">really</hi> bad is coming, though! What I want to say is this:</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, I believe that even when you’re working at the academy you’re striving to become more and more of a true realist, and at the academy, too, you stick to reality. However, without being aware of it yourself, without knowing it, that academy is a mistress who prevents a more serious, a warmer, a more fertile love from awakening in you. Let the mistress go and fall madly in love with your true love, Dame Nature or Reality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I’ve also fallen in love like that, madly in love with a Dame Nature or Reality, and have felt so happy ever since, even though she’s still resisting me strenuously and doesn’t want me yet, and often raps my knuckles if I dare over-hastily to think of her as mine. So I’m far from saying that I’ve already got her, but I’m courting her and seeking the key to her heart despite the painful knuckle-rapping.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Now you don’t have to think that there is but one Dame Nature or Reality, no, that’s only the surname of various sisters, who have a variety of Christian names. So we don’t have to be rivals. Do you understand, my dear chap? Of course it’s purely artistic, is it not? 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now in my opinion there are two kinds of mistress. One is the kind with whom one can give and take love, one or both of you being aware, meanwhile, that it isn’t forever, neither does one surrender to it whole-heartedly and unreservedly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Such mistresses get on one’s nerves, they coax, they spoil one, then – then — ... they burn up a good many men.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">The second kind of mistress is of an entirely different disposition. The strait-laced – Pharisees – Jesuits!!! They are the kind of women of marble – sphinx – cold vipers<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — who would like to bind men to themselves, entirely, for ever and ever, without her ever surrendering whole-heartedly, entirely, unreservedly. They suck your blood. Such mistresses <hi rend="italics">freeze</hi> men, and <hi rend="italics">petrify</hi> them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But I said it was purely artistic, my dear chap – and so I compare the first kind of mistress, those who burn, with that school of art that lapses into generalities. And then I compare the other kind of mistress (the strait-laced), those who freeze and petrify, with academic reality or – or – if you want me to gild the pill, with not unacademic reality – more gilding won’t stick to the pill, I’m afraid you’ll see through it. The pill is bitter, but salutary; it’s a quinine pill.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Do you understand, my dear chap!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Now there are – thank God – other women besides these two kinds – that is the family of Dames Nature and Reality, but it costs a great deal of inner struggle to win one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">They demand nothing more nor less than complete surrender of the heart, soul, mind in one certain direction, <hi rend="italics">all</hi> the love that’s in us, and then – then – they also give themselves. However, these true Dames Nature, though harmless as doves, are also wise as serpents,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and know very well how to distinguish between who is sincere and who is insincere. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> She renews, she reinvigorates, she gives life! This Dame Nature, this Dame Reality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, there are people, and perhaps you and I are such, who don’t understand, until they really love, that before that time, consciously or unconsciously, they’ve had mistresses of one or other of these dispositions, or perhaps aren’t unacquainted with both varieties.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">You have, in my opinion, a mistress who freezes you, petrifies you and sucks your blood.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">So, friend, I say you must tear yourself from the arms of that woman of marble (or is it but plaster??? how horrible!), otherwise you’ll freeze to death!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Believe, meanwhile, that if I’m a tempter who wants to pull you down into a deep pit, this pit could be the ‘well of truth’. In short – no longer sing the praises of not unacademic mistress (artistically)! In my opinion she’s a shrew. My dear chap, it’s my opinion that she’ll deceive you if you allow yourself to be taken in. The devil with her! Send her packing, and the sooner the better! But it’s purely artistic, is it not — my dear chap?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Indeed it is! If, apart from and in addition to that, it was something else altogether — so much the better — I’m not eating my words. As long, that is, as you’d take my words in a non-figurative sense. Do you understand, my dear chap, and — and — tell me — will you write to me now, the sooner the better, eh? Believe me always, with a handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I recently made a drawing, Mealtime, a worker drinking a cup of coffee and cutting a slice of bread. On the ground a spade he’s brought in from the field.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">She’s a little cold, though, my dear chap, the one that you say you love, the one who is your ideal for the time being. She is indeed as I had pictured her — marble, plaster, what can I say — a sleep-walker, at most. Alive — no.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">So you say:</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28"> where does she come from?... From heaven.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29"> Where does she live?..... All over the world. </p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Her intentions?.... The beautiful and the sublime.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">But, look, you’re sincere at least, and without knowing it you’re fully in agreement with me in that you admit to having a mistress. One of those whom I’ve dubbed strait-laced prudes &amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32"> That’s just it, you describe her very well. But what a Pharisee she is, that beauty, and you, you’re so in love with her, what a pity!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Madame, who are you? I am ‘the beautiful, the sublime’. Tell me, though, my beautiful and sublime, the one who feels herself such, is she so in fact?</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">I certainly agree that in some of life’s crises, in great pain, in transports of joy, one may feel oneself beautiful and sublime, and of course I hope to be among those who know how to appreciate those things. But the fact remains that You, Madame, leave me cold and without any emotion whatsoever. How does that come about?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35"> I don’t, after all, have too thick a skin, I do hope; people who weren’t even pretty, not exactly sublime, have often charmed me, but you, Madame, do not charm me in the very least. One doesn’t make a profession of the beautiful and the sublime!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36"> Madame, I do not love you, and what’s more, I do not believe that you yourself could love unless in certain academic heavens, of course — but on the heath or in private, by the fireside, no, not at all. Don’t sing me that tune, Madame the beautiful, the sublime, you don’t know the first thing about it.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Do you see, Madame, I’m just a man of human passions, and for as long as I walk ‘down here’ on the heath, I don’t have time to worry about a celestial, mystical love, as long as I feel another, of a more frank and earthly nature. I do need the beautiful and the sublime, I admit it, but first of all I also need something other than that — to start with — kindness and good will, tenderness; do you have much of those, Madame Pharisee? I’m inclined to doubt it. And, Madame, tell me, do you actually have a body and soul? I’m inclined to doubt it; as much, indeed, for the body as for the soul.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38"> Listen, my lovely one, from wherever you may claim to come, you who say your fundamental intentions are ‘the beautiful and the sublime’ (which could only be <hi rend="italics">results</hi>, never <hi rend="italics">intentions</hi>), from wherever you may come, I say, it’s surely not from the Bosom of the living God, and it’s not from the bosom of a woman, either. Away with you, Sphinx, clear off, and the sooner the better — I tell you — you’re nothing but a joke. You don’t exist. (De debil ton’t exeest, Nucingen would say.)<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">However, if you do exist, if in fact you come from somewhere, are you quite sure and certain that your origin isn’t Satan himself, father of lies? Are you any less a viper and a serpent than he, Madame, the beautiful, the sublime? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">To say that as far as I’m concerned your mistress, ‘the beautiful, the sublime, who says she comes from heaven and lives over all the earth’, is a more than suspect person, that wouldn’t be putting things strongly enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41"> Ask her if she’s good and useful, if she loves, and needs love. She’ll become flustered, and if she says yes, it’s a lie. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">She — the <hi rend="italics">other one</hi>, that is, not the one with the above-mentioned ‘intentions’, where does she come from?</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">— I’m far from denying her divinity, her immortality; I believe in it very firmly, and in the first place, even; however, she’s definitely earthly, too, and definitely a <hi rend="italics">woman</hi>,<hi rend="italics"> </hi>and born of a woman.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">She? — Where she lives, I know well where, and it’s not very far from each one of us.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.45" n="45">She — Her intentions? What do I know of them, how to say it — I’d like to keep silent — however, since we must speak — ah, well — it seems to me: to love and to be lovable — to live, to give life, to renew it, to heal it, to preserve it, to work, to give back spark for spark; above all, to be good, to be useful — to be of some use, to light the fire, for example, to give a child a piece of bread and butter, a sick man a glass of water.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.46" n="46">Ah, but all that is very beautiful, very sublime. Yes, but she didn’t know that it was called that, she believed that it was quite simple, she doesn’t do it on purpose, <hi rend="italics">it wasn’t her intention </hi>to make as much noise as that, she believed nobody paid attention.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.47" n="47">Her own ‘arguments’, you see, aren’t very brilliant, not very well thought out. Her sentiment is always right.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.48" n="48">To know what her duty is she doesn’t go to her head, she goes to her heart.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.49" n="49">But she’s in no way a <hi rend="italics">mistress</hi>, that one. Since a <hi rend="italics">lady </hi>is a <hi rend="italics">lady</hi>, as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> says.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.50" n="50">
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.51" n="51">Meanwhile, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, that business of the competition I find rather amusing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.52" n="52">No. 11 is first of all the fool’s number and, moreover, ‘last’ is also a good sign sometimes,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> so I offer you my sincere congratulations, for in my opinion one thing and another are good omens for you. It’s promising.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.53" n="53">Now, I still have quite a lot against various principles of yours too, but because my <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> in the circumstances is that particular mistress, I’ll leave the principles alone. If you could sack Mme the beautiful, the sublime, and fall in love with ‘the other’, it seems to me that that would put entirely different principles in your head and in your heart. And I perceive from certain signs that, no matter how much you’re still attached to Mme the beautiful and sublime, you won’t be able to stand her much longer. Unless she petrifies you and turns you to ice and transfixes you in that way, but that seems unlikely to me, you have too much good sense for that. Be on your guard — keep warm — you know — (a little precaution to take against her chilling influence), and take lots of walks — (especially when you feel a little petrification coming on). Forewarned is forearmed, so you’re forewarned, then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.54" n="54">Don’t be annoyed with me; if it wasn’t an academic expression, I would say, ‘it’s for your own good’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.55" n="55">  Finally, much good may it do you, I have another <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi> to hunt down, but I shan’t tell you which, now. But listen, and I’ll tell you anyway. This other <hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi> is ‘<hi rend="italics">resignation in disappointments</hi>’. Another incredibly Jesuitical, Pharisaical invention. But that’s theological, very theological. My dear chap, never resign yourself and never be disappointed, that’s the best advice I could give you, it’s even better than my advice to send your cold mistress to the devil, all the more so since these two pieces of advice amount to only one. I shake your hand, believe me always</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.56" n="56">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.57" n="57">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Etten 12/9-1881’. Van Gogh used the Latin word for nine to indicate the month: ‘novem’; cf. <ref target="let157.xml">letter 157</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s love for Kee Vos <ref target="let179.xml">(179)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs> speaks of ‘women of marble’ (filles de marbre) as ‘women of sadness’ (filles de tristesse). See Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, p. 438.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Quinine is a febrifuge, i.e. a substance used to dispel or reduce fever.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 10:16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The motif of this unknown drawing could correspond to the lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Workman sitting on a basket, cutting bread</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2418">F 1663 / JH 272</rs>), which Van Gogh would make a year later.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Baron Frédéric de Nucingen appears in several of the novels in the cycle <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_219"><hi rend="italics">La comédie humaine</hi></ref> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>. He is an English banker of Jewish descent and therefore speaks with a heavy accent. In <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_329"><hi rend="italics">Splendeurs et misères des courtisanes</hi></ref>, he says: ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le tiaple n’egssisde boinde</hi>’ (le diable n’existe point – the devil doesn’t exist). See Balzac, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La comédie humaine</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><hi>vi</hi></hi>. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Etudes de moeurs. Scènes de la vie parisienne</hi>. Ed. Pierre Citron. Paris 1977, p. 494. Van Gogh made a note of this short sentence in his Antwerp sketchbook, but it is difficult to determine exactly when he wrote it down. See Van der Wolk 1987, p. 122.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Possibly a quotation; see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let183.xml">letter 183</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>In the chapter ‘Il n’y a point de vieille femme’, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> writes: ‘For the rest, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">a lady </hi>is a lady’ (Du reste, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">une dame</hi> est une dame). (Michelet, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref>, p. 385).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Evidently <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had finished in 11th (and last) place at a competition, probably having submitted one of his works that was shown at the ‘Levende Meesters’ (Living Masters) exhibition at <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arti</hi>; the archives of Arti give no further information (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let176.xml#n-10">letter 176, n. 10</ref>). The number eleven has to do with ‘Carnaval’, or Shrovetide, the pre-lenten festivities beginning as early as St Martin’s Day (11-11).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh used <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">bête noir</hi> again in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let188.xml">letters 188</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let190.xml">190</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let474.xml">474</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    