<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Friday, 18 November 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let185"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b178 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>185</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>158</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>183</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-18">Friday, 18 November 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0178" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0178" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000195_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Vrijdag 18/9-1881</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Beste Broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Als ik niet zoo nu en dan eens mijn hart lucht gaf dan zou de stoomketel springen geloof ik. Ik moet U eens eene zaak vertellen die als ik ze maar in mij opsloot misschien me van streek zou maken doch die als ik ze maar eens rondweg uitspreek misschien zoo heel zwaar niet behoeft te wegen. Zooals ge weet zijn Pa en Moe van den eenen kant en ik aan den anderen kant ’t onderling niet eens over ’t geen gedaan of niet gedaan moet worden met betrekking tot zeker “neen nooit nimmer”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wel, nadat een geruimen tijd ik gehoord had de nog al krasse uitdrukkingen “onkiesch en ontijdig”<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> (verbeeld U eens dat ge lief hadt en men noemde die liefde “onkiesch”<c type="kk">/</c> zoudt ge daar niet met een zekere fierheid tegenop komen en zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> Basta!) doch dit opgehouden had op mijn nadrukkelijk verzoek die uitdrukkingen niet meer te bezigen<c type="kk">/</c> kwam er iets anders aan de orde van den dag.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu heette het “dat ik banden zou verbreken”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wel<c type="kk">/</c> menigmaal heb ik met ernst<c type="kk">/</c> met geduld<c type="kk">/</c> met gevoel gesproken er over dat zulks toch geenszins ’t geval was. Doch dit hielp voor een tijd en dan begon ’t weer op nieuw.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">’t Geen ik eigentlijk deed was “brieven schrijven”<c type="kk">/</c> ziedaar de eigentlijke grief.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Doch toen (mijns inziens zoo voorbarig en zoo ligtzinnig) die ellendige uitdrukking “banden verbreken” bleef doorgaan<c type="kk">/</c> deed ik het volgende.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Voor een paar dagen sprak ik geen woord en nam geen de minste notitie van Pa noch Moe. A contre coeur doch ik wilde hen toch eens laten voelen hoe het zijn zou indien er werkelijk banden verbroken waren.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Natuurlijk verwonderde mijn gedrag hen en toen zij ’t mij zeiden antwoordde ik<c type="kk">/</c> Zie<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">zoo zou</hi> <hi rend="italics">’t nu zijn</hi> als er geen band van genegenheid tusschen ons was doch gelukkig bestaat die wel degelijk en zal die zoo ligt vooreerst niet breken<c type="kk">/</c> maar zie nu, bid ik U, toch zelf in hoe miserabel zoo’n woord “banden verbreken” is en zeg dat niet meer.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">’t Resultaat nu was evenwel dat Pa zeer driftig werd<c type="kk">/</c> mij van de kamer stuurde en – en – mij vloekte, althans ’t klonk precies zoo hoor!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu doet mij dat veel verdriet en leed doch <hi rend="italics">’t wil er bij mij niet in</hi> dat een vader die zijn zoon vloekt en (gedenk aan verleden jaar) naar een gekkenhuis wil sturen (waartegen ik mij natuurlijk met al mijn kracht verzette)<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en de liefde van zijn zoon “ontijdig en onkiesch”!!! noemt<c type="kk">/</c> ’t bij ’t regte eind zou hebben.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wanneer Pa zich <hi rend="italics">driftig</hi> maakt is hij, ook van mij, gewoon dat men hem gelijk geeft. Nu evenwel had ik mij vastelijk voorgenomen die drift in Gods naam maar eens te laten uitbarsten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">Ook</hi> IN DRIFT zei pa iets van dat ik maar ergens anders moest heen trekken doch omdat het IN DRIFT gezegd werd hecht ik daar niet veel aan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Hier heb ik mijn modellen en atelier,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> elders zou het leven duurder zijn en ’t werk moeielijker en de modellen kostbaarder. Doch indien Pa en Moe in bedaardheid mij zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> ga heen<c type="kk">/</c> natuurlijk zou ik heengaan.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Er zijn dingen die een man niet over zijn kant <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> laten gaan<c type="kp">_</c> Als men zich liet zeggen “ge zijt een gek” of “ge zijt iemand die familiebanden verbreekt” of ge zijt “onkiesch” dan zou ieder die een hart in ’t lijf heeft daar tegen protesteeren met al zijn energie. Ik heb ook wel wat gezegd tegen Pa en Moe<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat op ’t punt van deze liefde van mij zij zeer dwaalden en hun hart zeer verhard was en zij ten eenemale onvatbaar schenen voor zachtere en meer humane zienswijze<c type="kp">_</c> Dat in een woord hun zienswijs mij bekrompen en niet breed en mild genoeg scheen<c type="kk">/</c> ook dat ’t mij voorkwam dat “God” maar een ijdele klank wezen zou als men liefde moest verbergen en niet de inspraak des harten mogt volgen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu wil ik regt gaarne gelooven dat ik soms mijn verontwaardiging niet heb kunnen bedwingen als ik “onkiesch” of “banden verbreken” hoorde doch wie zou daar kalm onder blijven als dat niet ophield.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Quoi qu’il en soit<c type="kk">/</c> Pa mompelde in zijn drift niets meer of niets minder dan een vloek<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar ook reeds verleden jaar hoorde ik iets dergelijks en God dank wel verre van werkelijk verdoemd te zijn ontwikkelde zich nieuw leven en nieuwe energie in mij<c type="kp">_</c> Dus vertrouw ik vast dat dit nu ook zoo zijn zal<c type="kk">/</c> alleen meer en krachtiger dan verleden jaar.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Theo ik heb haar lief, haar en geen ander,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> haar voor altijd. En – En – En – Theo hoewel het neen nooit nimmer nog in volle werking “Sch<supplied>ijnt</supplied>” te zijn zoo is er een gevoel als van verlossing in mij en is ’t me als of zij en ik hadden opgehouden twee te zijn en vereenigd waren voor eeuwig.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">ZIJN MIJN TEEKENINGEN GEARRIVEERD;<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ik heb er gisteren weer een gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> een boerenjongen die s’morgens ’t vuur van den haard waar de ketel over hangt aansteekt,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en nog een ander<c type="kk">/</c> een oud man die dorre rijzen op den haard legt.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Er blijft tot mijn leedwezen iets hards en strengs in mijn teekeningen en ik denk dat <hi rend="italics">zij</hi><c type="kk">/</c> n.l. <hi rend="italics">haar</hi> invloed er bij zal moeten komen om dat te verzachten. Nu kerel, me dunkt er is geen reden om “den vloek” zoo vreesselijk zwaar op te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> <supplied>miss</supplied>chien nam ik een te hard middel te baat om Pa en Moe iets te laten voelen ’t geen zij niet hooren wilden<c type="kk">/</c> doch is “een vadervloek” niet nog heel wat krasser en harder<c type="kk">/</c> wel wat al te bar! Enfin je te serre la main et crois moi</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Friday, 18/9-1881</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dear Brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I think that if I didn’t give vent to my feelings once in a while the boiler would burst. I must tell you something that would perhaps drive me mad if I kept it to myself but perhaps doesn’t have to weigh so heavily on my mind if only I speak openly about it. As you know, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526 bio.xml#_524">Pa and Ma</rs> on the one hand and I on the other don’t agree about what should or should not be done about that certain ‘no, nay, never’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Well, after hearing for a long time the rather crass expressions ‘indelicate and untimely’<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> (imagine that you loved someone and that love was called ‘indelicate’, wouldn’t you stand up to that with a certain measure of pride and say, Enough!), and this had stopped at my express request not to use those expressions any longer, something else became the order of the day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now it was said ‘that I would break ties’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Well, I’ve said many times with seriousness, with patience, with feeling, that this wasn’t the case at all. This helped for a time, but then it started all over again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">What I did, in fact, was ‘write letters’, behold the actual offence.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But when (so overhastily and stupidly, in my opinion) that awful expression ‘breaking ties’ went on and on, I did the following. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For a couple of days I spoke not a word and took not the slightest notice of either <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa or Ma</rs>. Reluctantly, but still, I wanted to make them feel what it would be like if ties really were broken.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Naturally my behaviour surprised them, and when they told me so I answered, You see, <hi rend="italics">this is how it would be</hi> if there were no bond of affection between us, but fortunately it does exist and won’t be so easily broken for the present, but now see for yourself, I beg you, how wretched words like ‘breaking ties’ really are, and don’t say them any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">The result, though, was that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> became very angry, sent me out of the room and – and – cursed me, at least that’s what it sounded like!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">It causes me much sorrow and grief but <hi rend="italics">I refuse to accept</hi> that a father is right who curses his son and (think of last year) wants to send him to a madhouse (which I naturally opposed with all my might)<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and calls his son’s love ‘untimely and indelicate’!!! 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">When <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> gets <hi rend="italics">angry</hi> he’s used to having people, me included, admit that he’s right. Now, though, I’d firmly resolved to let his anger burst forth, for God’s sake.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">Also</hi> IN ANGER, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> said something about my having to move somewhere else, but because it was said IN ANGER I don’t attach much importance to it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Here I have my models and my studio,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> life would be more expensive elsewhere, and working more difficult and models costlier. But if Pa and Ma said to me calmly, leave, of course I would leave.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">There are things that a man <hi rend="italics">cannot</hi> take lying down. If one were to let himself be told ‘you’re a madman’ or ‘you’re someone who breaks family ties’ or you’re ‘indelicate’, then anyone with a heart in his body would protest with all his might. I also said something to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>, namely that in the matter of this love of mine they were very wrong and their heart was very hardened and they seemed entirely insensible to a milder and more humane view. That, in a word, their view seemed to me to be bigoted and not broad-minded and generous enough, also that it seemed to me that the word ‘God’ would have only a hollow ring to it if one had to conceal love and wasn’t allowed to follow one’s heart’s promptings. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Well, I’ll gladly believe that at times I couldn’t hide my indignation upon hearing ‘indelicate’ or ‘breaking ties’, but who would remain calm if it didn’t stop?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">In any event, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, in his anger, muttered neither more nor less than a curse.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But I already heard something similar last year, and thank God, far from being damned in reality, new life and new energy developed in me. So I have every confidence that it will be like that now as well, only more and stronger than last year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Theo, I love <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">her</rs>, her and no other,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> her for ever. And – And – And – Theo, even though the ‘no, nay, never’ still ‘appears’ to be in full force, there’s a feeling of deliverance in me, and it’s as though she and I had ceased to be two people and had been united for eternity.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">HAVE MY DRAWINGS ARRIVED?<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I made another one yesterday, a peasant lad, in the morning, lighting the fire in the hearth where the kettle hangs,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and another one, an old man laying dry twigs on the fire.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I’m sorry to say that there’s still something stiff and severe in my drawings, and I think that <hi rend="italics">she</hi>, namely <hi rend="italics">her</hi> influence will be needed to soften that. Now, old chap, I don’t see any reason to take ‘the curse’ so very seriously, perhaps I availed myself of too harsh a means to make <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> feel something they didn’t want to hear, but isn’t ‘a father’s curse’ much more crass and harsh, really too bad! Anyway, I shake your hand, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Vrijdag 18/9-1881’. Van Gogh used the Latin word for nine to indicate the month: ‘novem’; cf. <ref target="let157.xml">letter 157</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>. Later the same day he wrote <ref target="let186.xml">letter 186</ref>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s love for Kee Vos <ref target="let179.xml">(179)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For ‘onkiesch’ (indelicate) and ‘ontijdig’ (untimely), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let181.xml">see letter 181</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Regarding ‘banden verbreken’ (‘break old ties’), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let179.xml">see letter 179</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>As also emerges from later letters (e.g. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let186.xml">186</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let227.xml">227</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let228.xml">228</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let234.xml">234</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">235</ref>), in 1880 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was thinking about having Vincent committed to a lunatic asylum in Geel. This Belgian village was a psychiatric colony, where most of the patients lived in a kind of supervised freedom. With regard to this place and what was known at that time about the patient care at the institution, see H.A. Banning, ‘Een uitstapje naar Gheel’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Katholieke Illustratie</hi> 10 (1876-1877), NS, nos. 35, 41-43, 45, 50; pp. 275-278, 323-324, 335-336, 339-342, 355, 398-399. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let155.xml#n-1">letter 155, n. 1.</ref> In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914 this passage was censured.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>According to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Elisabeth van Gogh</rs>, her brother had his studio in an annexe by the parsonage, which had earlier served as an evangelization classroom. Many years later Elisabeth was prompted by the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Church and parsonage in Etten </hi>(from 1876), in which the annexe is depicted (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_684">F Juv. XXI / JH Juv. 6</rs>), to write the following to Anna de Jong-van Houten: ‘that annex was first a place where confirmation classes were held and later – when V. returned from Antwerp [she means Brussels] – his studio’ (FR b4538, 11 June 1933). See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 57-59, cat. no. 7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh borrowed ‘her and no other’ from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let180.xml#n-5">see letter 180, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>These are the otherwise unspecified drawings Van Gogh refers to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let182.xml">letter 182</ref>, saying he has sent them.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This drawing of a ‘peasant lad’ is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man sitting by the fireplace </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2349">F 868 / JH 80</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    