<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. Etten, Monday, 21 November 1881. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let188"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8339 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>188</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R5</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>186</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-21">Monday, 21 November 1881</date>
                            <placeName>Etten</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8339" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8339" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001584_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Etten. <hi rend="italics">21 Nov 1881</hi>.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Rappard.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Om eens minder abstract te spreken wil ik ’t eens met U hebben ditmaal over enkele daadzaken. Gij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ten Cate<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> sprak tot U over dergelijke dingen als ik<c type="kp">_</c> Que soit, doch indien de Heer ten Cate is een persoon die ik op zekeren dag eens heel even op Uw atelier gezien heb dan betwijfel ik ten zeerste of hij en ik in den grond precies dezelfde gedachten hebben. Is hij iemand klein van persoon en met zwart althans donker haar en vrij bleeke gelaatskleur<c type="kk">/</c> bij de gelegenheid dat ’k hem zag althans zeer netjes geheel in ’t zwart laken gekleed? Ge moet weten dat ik gewoon ben erg op ’t physiek der personen te letten als ik na wil gaan hoe hun denkwijs eigentlijk is. Maar nu is de Heer ten C. iemand die ik maar ééns en zeer ter loops gezien heb<c type="kk">/</c> als ik hem nl. gezien heb<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/> en dus kan ik geen peil op hem trekken. Evenwel ’t moge zoo zijn dat in sommige opzigten hij tot U gesproken heeft als ik<c type="kk">/</c> daar heb ik niets op tegen, tant mieux.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Uw antwoord op mijn schrijven is eigentlijk maar een half antwoord<c type="kk">/</c> toch dank er voor. ge zult me de andere helft ook nog wel eens vertellen maar vooreerst nog niet. die andere nog te komen helft is langer dan de eerste reeds ontvangene and much more satisfactory<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Gesteld eens dat gij vroeger of later voorgoed van de akademie zult afgaan dan houd ik het er voor dat gij met eene zeer eigenaardige moeielijkheid zult te worstelen krijgen die ook nu reeds U lang niet onbekend is. Iemand die zoo als gij geregeld werkt aan de akademie moet zich meer of minder uit zijn element gevoelen wanneer hij in plaats van vooruit te weten<c type="kk">/</c> dit of dat moet ik van daag doen<c type="kk">/</c> van dag tot dag zich een werkkring moet <hi rend="italics">improviseeren</hi> of liever <hi rend="italics">scheppen</hi>. Vooral op den duur is dat werk zoeken en vinden zoo makkelijk nog niet. Althans ’t zou me niet verwonderen als ge zoo nu en dan eens een gevoel kreegt, wanneer ge eenmaal voorgoed van de akademie los zijt, als was de grond onder uw voeten weggezonken. Maar gij zijt er de man niet naar, geloof ik, om U door dit natuurverschijnsel in consternatie te laten brengen, en spoedig zult ge Uw evenwigt terug krijgen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dan echter wanneer gij eens en voor altijd (want als gij eens U er inwerpt zult ge er niet van terug keeren) U hals over kop zonder slag om den arm in de werkelijkheid stort<c type="kk">/</c> dan zult gij zelf net precies spreken als ten Cate en net precies als ik tot anderen die zich nog aan de akademie vastklemmen. Want naar aanleiding van een &amp; ander dat ge mij verteld hebt van den Hr ten Cate geloof ik dat zijne redenatie tot U gereduceerd kan worden tot deze woorden: Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> houd geen slag om den arm maar werp U hals over kop in de werkelijkheid.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Die volle zee is Uw eigentlijk element en zelfs op de akademie verloochent ge Uw eigentlijk karakter en natuur niet en daarom willen de Heeren aldaar U eigentlijk niet erkennen en sturen U met een kluitje in ’t riet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">De Heer ten Cate en nog meer ik kunnen daarom de zee nog niet baas en kunnen ons nog niet zóó bewegen &amp; manoevreeren als we zouden willen doch dat neemt niet weg dat als we niet verzuipen of tegen de rotsen worden verbrijzeld in de branding<c type="kk">/</c> we echte zeelui zullen worden. En er is geen genade voor, een tijd van tobberij en scharrelen moet een iegelijk door die afsteekt naar de diepte.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wij beginnen met weinig of geen visch te vangen maar we leeren ’t vaarwater kennen en ons bootje sturen en dat is al vast iets onmisbaars<c type="kp">_</c> En over een poosje dan vangen we veel visschen en grooten ook hoor! De Hr ten Cate maakt evenwel denk ik waarschijnlijk bij voorkeur jagt op ander soort visch dan ik omdat onze temperamenten geloof ik uiteen loopen<c type="kk">/</c> want ’t is ieder visscher gepermiteerd zijn fort te maken van wat hij wil maar onwillekeurig loopt een visch van ’t eene soort in ’t andere net en een van ’t andere soort in t’eene en zoo kan er soms overeenkomst zijn tusschen zijn vangst en de mijne<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu hebt gij van tijd tot tijd het land aan zaaiers en naaisters en spitters<c type="kp">_</c> Que soit – ik ook<c type="kp">_</c> Maar dat “soms het land hebben” wordt bij mij verre overtroffen door een zeker enthousiasme en bij U schijnen ze allebei even zwaar te wegen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Hebt ge nu mijn epistels nog bewaard? Als ge eens een momentje hebt &amp; ze zijn nog niet in de vlammen omgekomen<c type="kk">/</c> herlees ze nog eens zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ’t misschien pretentieus is zoo iets van U te vragen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik heb ze niet zonder ernst geschreven hoewel ik niet schroomde door te slaan en mijn fantaisie den vrijen teugel gaf. Nu zegt ge dat ik eigentlijk toch wel een drijver ben en wel degelijk eene leer verkondig.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> als ge ’t zoo wilt opnemen dan zij het zoo<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er desnoods niet op tegen<c type="kk">/</c> ik schaam mij mijn gevoelens niet<c type="kk">/</c> je ne rougis point d’être homme<c type="kk">/</c> d’avoir des principes et une foi. Maar waarheen wil ik dan de menschen drijven<c type="kk">/</c> vooral me zelf? Naar de volle zee<c type="kp">_</c> en welke leer verkondig ik? Menschen laat ons onze ziel overgeven in onze zaak en laat ons met het hart werken en liefhebben wat we liefhebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11"><hi rend="italics">Liefhebben wat we liefhebben</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wat schijnt dat eene overbodige waarschuwing en toch<c type="kk">/</c> wat heeft ze enorm veel raison d’être. Immers toch<c type="kk">/</c> hoe menigeen spendeert zijn beste krachten aan iets dat zijn beste krachten niet waard is en behandelt ’t geen hij lief heeft “stiefmoederlijk” in plaats van zich rondborstig over te geven aan den onweerstaanbaren aandrang des harten. En dan meenen we nog dat zulke handelwijs als bovenstaande “vastheid van karakter” is en “geestkracht”<c type="kk">/</c> en we spendeeren onze kracht aan eene onwaardige en ons eigentlijk meisje negligeeren we. en dat alles met “de heiligste bedoelingen” en “meenende ’t te moeten doen” uit “gewetensovertuiging” en “pligtgevoel”. Zoo hebben we “den balk in eigen oog”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> verwarrende een quasi of would be geweten met onze  eigentlijke conscientie.– De persoon die op dit moment aan zijn waarden vriend Rappard schrijft heeft lang gemarcheerd in de wereld met één<c type="kk">/</c> ja misschien meer dan één dergelijk voorwerp<c type="kk">/</c> doch van monstrueuse groote<c type="kk">/</c> in zijn oog.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Is dien balk er nu uit? vraagt ge. Ja wat zal de onderhavige schrijver U daarop antwoorden<c type="kp">_</c> Een ding weet hij<c type="kk">/</c> dat er één erge groote balk provisoir uit is<c type="kk">/</c> doch juist omdat hij dien niet merkte toen 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>hij er aan laboreerde acht hij ’t niet onmogelijk dat er nog meer aanwezig zouden zijn wier al dan niet bestaan hem nog niet volkomen duidelijk zijn mogt. Evenwel de onderhavige persoon heeft geleerd op zijn quivive te zijn tegen oogkwalen, oogbalken. De onderhavige buitengewoon grooten balk was van min of meer onartistieken aard. Ik zeg U nu bij deze gelegenheid niet van welken aard hij was. Want er zijn allerlei “oogbalken”, artistieke, theologische, moreele oogbalken (zeer menigvuldig)<c type="kk">/</c> praktijk oogbalken en theorie oogbalken (soms de twee gecombineerd<c type="kk">/</c> erg fataal!) en enfin nog veel meer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het moet ons dus niet al te zeer in consternatie brengen als we niet zonder zijn<c type="kk">/</c> mits we dat “niet in consternatie zijn” maar zóó ver niet drijven dat het zorgeloosheid of onverschilligheid wordt of verstoktheid op dat chapiter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb dezer dagen een aardigen brief van mijn broer Theo gehad die ook naar U informeerde<c type="kk">/</c> ik had hem eenige teekeningen gestuurd en hij raadde mij zeer om met die brabantsche typen door te gaan. Wat hij zegt over kunst is altijd pittig en hij geeft dikwijls wenken die praktisch en uitvoerbaar zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik heb van daag weer jagt gemaakt op zeker “bête noire” van mij<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk het resignatie systeem<c type="kk">/</c> dat “bête noire” is geloof ik van ’t ras der hydra<c type="kk">/</c> dat wil zeggen hoe meer slangenkoppen men er afhakt hoe meer nieuwe er uitspruiten<c type="kp">_</c> Toch zijn er mannen geweest die er in geslaagd zijn zoo’n “bête noire” te laten crêpeeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Dat is altijd mijn meest geliefkoosde occupatie als ik er een half uurtje voor vinden kan<c type="kk">/</c> dat oude “bête noire” weer eens te gaan bevechten. Doch gij weet misschien niet  eens dat er in de theologie een resignatie systeem bestaat met zijtak mortificatie<c type="kp">_</c> En was het dat dit slechts eene zaak was die slechts in de verbeelding en schriften of preeken der theologen bestond<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou er me niet mee bemoeien doch helaas<c type="kk">/</c> het is een van die ondragelijke lasten die zekere theologen leggen op den nek van de menschen en zelve met den vinger niet aanraken<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> dus behoort helaas die resignatie tot het gebied der werkelijkheid en veroorzaakt veel groote en kleine petites misères de la vie humaine.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Maar toen ze mij dat juk wilden aantrekken toen heb ik gezegd: donder op! En dat vonden zij erg oneerbiedig. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> que soit. Wat er ook zij van de raison d’être der resignatie, zij, nl. de resignatie<c type="kk">/</c> is voor wie zich resigneeren <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> en ’t geloof voor wie gelooven <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> En wat wil ik als ik niet voor t’eerste<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. ’t resigneeren<c type="kk">/</c> maar wel voor ’t tweede<c type="kk">/</c> nl. ’t gelooven en wat daar uit voortvloeit<c type="kk">/</c> ben in de wieg gelegd.– Nu, als ge eens een momentje hebt schrijf dan weer eens<c type="kk">/</c> geloof me intusschen met een handdruk,</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Etten, <hi rend="italics">21 Nov. 1881.</hi></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">To speak less abstractly for once, I’d like to discuss several matters with you this time. You say <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_918">Ten Cate</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> spoke to you about the same things I did. Be that as it may, but if Mr Ten Cate is the person I saw very briefly in your studio one day, then I most seriously doubt whether he and I have at bottom exactly the same thoughts. Is he small of stature, with black or at least dark hair and a rather pale complexion, and very smartly dressed completely in black worsted, at least on the occasion that I saw him?  I should tell you that I’m used to paying very close attention to the outward appearance of people if I want to work out how they actually think. But Mr Ten C. is someone I saw but once and only very briefly, if indeed he was the one I saw, and so I can’t really take the measure of him. Still, it may be that he spoke to you in some respects as I did. I have nothing against that, all the better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Your answer to my letter is actually only half an answer, but I thank you for it anyway. You’ll no doubt tell me the other half sometime, but not just yet. The other, still-to-come half is longer than the first, already-received half and much more satisfactory.<ptr target="#note-t-b"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Assuming that sooner or later you’ll leave the academy for good, I imagine that you’ll have to wrestle with a very singular problem which is far from unfamiliar to you, even now. Someone who works regularly at the academy as you do must feel rather out of his element when, instead of knowing in advance, today I have to do this or that, he must daily <hi rend="italics">improvise</hi> or rather <hi rend="italics">create</hi> his working environment. Looking for and finding work isn’t at all easy, especially in the long run. At any rate, it wouldn’t surprise me if, when you’ve finally left the academy for good, you occasionally felt as though the ground were being cut from under your feet. But you’re not the kind of man, I think, to let yourself be dismayed by this natural phenomenon, and you’ll soon recover your equilibrium. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Then, however, when you plunge once and for all (for once you’ve taken the plunge, you’ll never go back), head over heels and whole-heartedly into reality, you’ll talk exactly as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_918">Ten Cate</rs> does and exactly as I do to others who still stick to the academy. Because from what you’ve told me about Mr Ten Cate I think that the arguments he presented to you can be reduced to these words: <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, don’t hold back, plunge head over heels into reality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">That open sea is your native element, and even at the academy you can’t deny your true character and nature, and that’s why the gentlemen there don’t really recognize you and fob you off.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">This doesn’t mean that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_918">Mr Ten Cate</rs>, and this applies even more to me, can handle the sea and can yet move and manoeuvre as we’d like, but if we don’t drown or get battered against the rocks by the breakers, we’ll become able seamen all the same. And there’s no mercy, everyone who launches out into the deep<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> has to go through a time of drudgery and toil. We start out catching few or no fish, but we get to know the waters and how to steer our boat, and that’s already something vital. And after a while we catch a lot of fish, and big ones too! I think, though, that Mr Ten Cate probably fishes for a different kind of fish than I do, because our temperaments are different, I believe, for each fisherman is permitted to make his forte what he likes, but fish of one sort can’t help going into the other net and the other sort into the first one, and so his catch and mine may sometimes overlap. From time to time you might dislike sowers and seamstresses and diggers. That may well be. So do I. But ‘sometimes disliking’ is in my case far outweighed by a certain enthusiasm, whereas in your case they seem to carry equal weight. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Have you saved my epistles? If you have a moment and they haven’t yet perished in the flames, read them again, I say, though perhaps it’s pretentious to ask such a thing of you. Still, I wrote them in earnest, though I didn’t hesitate to speak plainly and to give free rein to my imagination. Now you’ll say that I’m actually a headstrong person and that I’m in fact preaching a doctrine.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Well, if you want to take it that way, so be it, I don’t necessarily have anything against it, I’m not ashamed of my feelings, I’m not ashamed of being a man, of having principles and faith. But where do I want to drive people, especially myself? To the open sea. And which doctrine do I preach? People, let us surrender our souls to our cause and let us work with our heart and love what we love.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><hi rend="italics">Love what we love</hi>, what an unnecessary warning that seems, and yet how great a <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi>. After all, how many people expend their best efforts on something that isn’t worthy of their best efforts, and treat what they love in a ‘stepmotherly’ fashion instead of giving themselves openly to the irresistible urging of their heart. And we even think that behaviour such as the above shows ‘firmness of character’ and ‘strength of mind’, and we expend our efforts on an unworthy one and neglect our true lass. And all of that with ‘the most sacred of intentions’ and ‘thinking we must do it’ from a ‘moral conviction’ and ‘sense of duty’. Thus we have ‘the beam in our own eye’,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> confusing a seeming or would-be conscience with our real conscience. The person who is now writing to his dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> has long gone through the world with one – perhaps even more than one – such object, though of monstrous size, in his eye.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Is that beam now gone? you ask. Well, how should the present writer answer you? He knows one thing, that one very large beam is temporarily gone, but precisely because he didn’t notice it when 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> he was labouring under it, he considers it not impossible that there might be more whose existence or otherwise might not be completely clear to him as yet. However, the present person has learned to be on the <hi rend="italics">qui vive</hi> for eye complaints, eye beams. The exceptionally large beam in question was of a rather unartistic nature. I won’t tell you on this occasion what kind it was. For there are all manner of ‘eye beams’, artistic, theological, moral eye beams (very frequent), practical eye beams and theoretical eye beams (sometimes in combination, very fatal!) and, well, many, many more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">So we needn’t be too dismayed if we aren’t without them, provided we don’t take ‘not being too dismayed’ so far that it becomes carelessness or indifference or obduracy on that score.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I recently received a nice letter from my brother Theo, who also asked after you. I had sent him a few drawings and he strongly advised me to go on with those Brabant types. What he says about art is always powerful, and he often has tips that are both practical and workable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Today I again pursued a certain ‘<hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi>’ of mine, namely the resignation method. That ‘<hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi>’ is of the hydra variety, I believe, which is to say the more serpent heads one chops off the more new ones sprout. Yet there are men who have succeeded in killing such a ‘<hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi>’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">That’s always my favourite occupation whenever I can find half an hour for it, to fight that old ‘<hi rend="italics">bête noire</hi>’ again. But perhaps you didn’t even know that theology has a resignation system with a side branch of mortification. And if this were but a matter that existed only in the imagination and in the writings and sermons of theologians, then I wouldn’t bother about it, but sadly it’s one of those burdens grievous to be borne which certain theologians place around people’s necks and do not touch with one of their fingers,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> so unfortunately such resignation belongs to the sphere of reality and causes many large and petty miseries of human life.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> But when they wanted to strap that yoke to me I said: go to hell! And they found that very disrespectful. Well then, so be it. No matter what the <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi> of resignation, it, namely resignation, is for those who <hi rend="italics">can</hi> resign themselves and faith for those who <hi rend="italics">can </hi>believe. And what else can I do if I wasn’t born for the first, namely resignation, but for the second, namely faith and all it entails? Well, write again when you have a moment, believe me meanwhile, with a handshake,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Etten. <hi rend="italics">21 Nov 1881</hi>’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_918">Siebe Johannes ten Cate</rs> was a friend of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>. Despite Ten Cate’s reservations about the academy – expressed later in the letter – he was probably the one who had persuaded Van Rappard to attend a winter semester at the Brusselse Académie Royale in 1880. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 11, 16, 61; De Bodt 1995, pp. 241, 249.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            
  
<p>Read: ‘als hij inderdaad degene was die ik heb gezien’ (if indeed he was the one I saw).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
<p>Van Gogh wrote the words ‘much more satisfactory’ in English.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
      
<p>
        Luke 5:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The metaphors of ‘catching fish’ and ‘eye beams’ refer to Matt. 7:10 and Matt. 7:4-5; catching fish could also be an allusion to John 21:1-14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Cf. Luke 11:46.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
  
<p>For the source of this phrase, which was taken from <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_222"><hi rend="italics">Petites misères de la vie humaine</hi></ref> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_748">Old Nick</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_745">Grandville</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let178.xml#n-6">see letter 178, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    