<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 29 December 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let194"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b187 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>194</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>166</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>194</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-29">Thursday, 29 December 1881</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0187" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0187" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000212_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">den Haag Donderdag avond</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ontvang mijn dank voor Uw brief &amp; het ingeslotene<c type="kp">_</c> Ik was te Etten terug toen ik Uw brief ontving<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ik U schreef volgens overleg met Mauve. Maar nu ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik toch weer te s’Hage terug.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Op kerstmis had ik nog al een heftige scène met Pa en het liep zoo hoog dat Pa zei ’t beter was ik t’huis maar zou verlaten. Nu, het werd zoo gedecideerd gezegd dat ik nog denzelfden dag werkelijk vertrok.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het kwam eigentlijk aan door dat ik niet naar de kerk ging en ook zeide dat als het naar de kerk gaan iets gedwongens was &amp; ik naar de kerk <hi rend="italics">moest</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik er zeer zeker zelfs nooit meer uit beleefdheid zou heengaan zooals ik dezen heelen tijd dat ik te Etten was vrij geregeld deed. Maar ach, eigentlijk zit er veel meer achter, o.a. de heele geschiedenis van ’tgeen dezen zomer voorviel tusschen mij en K.V.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik was zoo driftig als ik me niet herinner ooit in mijn leven geweest te zijn, en ik heb ronduit tegen Pa gezegd dat ik het heele systeem van die godsdienst afschuwelijk vond en juist omdat gedurende een miserabelen tijd van mijn leven ik mij te veel in die dingen verdiept<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> heb er niets meer mee wil te maken hebben en mij er voor wachten moet als voor iets fataals.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ben ik <hi rend="italics">te</hi> driftig<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">te</hi> heftig geweest – het zij zoo<c type="kk">/</c> maar al ware dat eens het geval dan is ’t nu meteen voor goed uit ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik ging naar M. terug en zei<c type="kk">/</c> hoor eens M.<c type="kk">/</c> te Etten kan ’t niet gaan en ik moet ergens anders<c type="kk">/</c> liefst hier gaan wonen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> M. zei<c type="kk">/</c> dan maar hier. En dus ik heb hier een atelier gehuurd<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. een kamer en alkoof die er voor geschikt te maken zijn. goedkoop genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> even buiten de stad op den Schenkweg, een minuut of 10 achter M.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Pa zei me, als ik geld noodig had wilde hij desnoods ’t mij voorschieten maar dat kan nu niet meer<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet geheel &amp; al onafhankelijk blijven van Pa. Hoe? ik weet het nog niet maar M. wil me wat helpen desnoods en ik hoop &amp; vertrouw gij<c type="kk">/</c> en natuurlijk ik zal werken &amp; mij moeite geven zooveel ik kan om wat te verdienen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik zit er nu en we zijn eenmaal in het schuitje<c type="kp">_</c>– Op een ongemakkelijk moment, maar qu’y faire.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik moet wat eenvoudige meubels hebben, en bovendien al mijn uitgaven voor teeken- &amp; schilder<c type="shy">-</c>behoeften worden er niet minder op.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ook moet ik probeeren me wat beter te kleeden. ’t Is gewaagd en eene kwestie van erop of er onder. Maar ’t moest er toch ééns toe komen dat ik me installeerde<c type="kk">/</c> dus wat wil ik<c type="kk">/</c> het is nu sneller gegaan dan ik verwacht had.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Wat betreft de verhouding tusschen Pa en Moe en mij<c type="kk">/</c> dat zal zich zoo heel spoedig niet redresseeren. Het verschil van denk- en zienswijs is al te groot.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">En ofschoon ik in drift gesproken heb zoo heb ik toch de dingen gezegd zooals ik ze ook in bedaarder stemming opvat. Ik neem het dus ook niet terug wat ik gezegd heb en enfin<c type="kk">/</c> Pa heeft dat nu eens ronduit gehoord. Ware ik bedaarder geweest<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou het in andere<c type="kk">/</c> minder hoog opgevoerde kleuren gezegd hebben maar in den grond zou ik toch hetzelfde hebben gedacht.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">En ik hoop dat het toch in elk geval tot iets goeds zal leiden. Ik moet een kwaden tijd door en het water komt hoog<c type="kk">/</c> misschien tot aan de lippen en misschien nog hooger<c type="kk">/</c> wat weet ik daar vooruit van. Maar ik zal mijn strijd strijden &amp; mijn leven duur verkoopen &amp; probeeren ’t te winnen en er boven op te komen.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Tegen 1 Januarij betrek ik het atelier. Ik zal wat betreft meubels het aller eenvoudigste nemen<c type="kk">/</c> een houten tafel<c type="kk">/</c> een paar stoelen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Voor bed zou ik tevreden zijn met een wollen deken en den grond. Maar M. wil dat ik toch een bed zal nemen &amp; wil ’t me desnoods voorschieten. Bij ’t opmaken van de rekening over de frs 100 kwam ’t uit dat er nog geld over was ofschoon ik dus toch tweemaal op reis geweest ben dezen zomer er van<c type="kk">/</c> en eens<c type="kk">/</c> nu de laatste keer<c type="kk">/</c> voor zoo’n langen tijd. Het is waar dat ik t’huis heb medegegeten &amp; ge<c type="shy">-</c>logeerd maar Pa heeft dat zelf gezegd in der tijd dat hij er dat voor over had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gij begrijpt ik zit nu verbazend in de zorg en voorzie veel tobberij. Maar ’t is me toch een rust dat ik zòò ver gegaan ben dat ik niet meer terug <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> en dat ofschoon de weg moeielijk te bewandelen is<c type="kk">/</c> mijn weg nu duidelijk genoeg zich afteekent<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Het spreekt van zelf dat ik U vraag<c type="kk">/</c> Theo als gij het kunt doen stuur mij dan nu en dan wat gij kunt zonder U zelven in de penarie te helpen. En – in de gegevenen<c type="kk">/</c> stuur ’t liever aan mij dan dat ge ’t aan anderen zoudt geven. Want als het mogelijk is moeten we Mauve er niet in mengen wat ’t finantieele aangaat. Het is al onwaardeerbaar veel waard dat hij mij op artistiek gebied met zijn raad &amp; daad bijstaat. Hij staat er echter op ik moet b.v. een bed &amp; een paar meubels nemen &amp; zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal ’t je voorschieten des noods. Want volgens hem moet ik <hi rend="italics">quand même</hi> toch ook goed voor den dag komen wat kleeren betreft en het niet zoeken in al te veel zich bekrimpen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik schrijf U spoedig wel meer. <hi rend="italics">Ik wil</hi> <hi rend="italics">het niet als een ongeluk beschouwen</hi> dat het zoo geloopen is<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks allerlei emotie voel ik toch een zekere kalmte.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22"><hi rend="italics">There is safety in the midst of danger</hi>.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Wat zou het leven zijn als we niet wat durfden aanpakken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Ik heb overal rondgeloopen om dat atelier te vinden zoowel in stad als op Scheveningen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Scheveningen is horrible duur. Dit atelier kost maar f<c type="kp">_</c> 7.- per maand maar de meubels maken het moeielijk. Toch<c type="kk">/</c> heeft men een eigen gedoente dan loopt dat ook niet meer weg, en heeft men meer vastigheid onder de voeten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Het licht is van ’t zuiden zoo ongeveer maar het raam is groot en hoog<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en ik heb hoop het er over eenigen tijd wat aardig zal uitzien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ge kunt denken dat ik mij zeer geanimeerd gevoel<c type="kp">_</c> Hoe zal het over een jaar zijn met mijn werk? Kon ik maar uitdrukken wat ik voel – nu<c type="kk">/</c> Mauve begrijpt daar alles van en hij wil me zooveel technische wenken geven als hij kan – ’tgeen waarvan mijn hoofd &amp; hart vol is dat moet er uit komen in teekeningen of schilderijen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Mauve zelf is druk bezig aan een groot Schij van een pink die met paarden tegen de duinen opgesleept wordt.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik vind het heerlijk te s’Hage te zijn en ik vind hier zoo oneindig veel moois en ik moet daarvan iets zoeken weer te geven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">à Dieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang een handdruk in gedachten en schrijf spoedig, geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Veel groeten van M. en Jet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Ik heb nog een beetje geld maar hoe lang zal ik er mee kunnen rondkomen. Tot 1 Januarij moet ik in ’t logement blijven.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Adresseer Uw brieven maar adres A. Mauve. Uileboomen 198. ik kom daar toch bijna dagelijks.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">The Hague, Thursday evening</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Accept my thanks for your letter and the enclosure. When I received your letter I was back in Etten, following <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s advice, as I wrote to you. But now, as you see, I’m back in The Hague again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">At Christmas I had a rather violent argument with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, and feelings ran so high that Pa said it would be better if I left home. Well, it was said so decidedly that I actually left the same day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Things actually came to a head because I didn’t go to church, and also said that if going to church was something forced and I <hi rend="italics">had</hi> to go to church, I’d most certainly never go again, not even out of politeness, as I’ve been doing fairly regularly the whole time I’ve been in Etten. But oh, there’s actually much more to it, including the whole story of what happened this summer between me and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">K.V.</rs></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I was angrier than I ever remember being in my whole life, and I told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> plainly that I found the whole system of that religion loathsome, and precisely because I dwelled on those things too much during a miserable time in my life<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I don’t want anything more to do with it, and have to guard against it as against something fatal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Was I <hi rend="italics">too</hi> angry, <hi rend="italics">too</hi> violent? – so be it, but even supposing that to be the case, then at least now it’s over and done with.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I went back to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> and said, listen M., I can’t stay in Etten and I have to go and live somewhere else, preferably here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Well, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> said, stay here then. And so I’ve rented a studio here, namely a room and alcove which can be made suitable. Inexpensive enough, just outside town in Schenkweg, about 10 minutes from M.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> told me that if I needed money he would lend it to me if necessary, but now that’s impossible, I must remain completely independent of Pa. How? I don’t know yet, but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> is willing to help me if necessary, and you too, I hope and trust, and of course I’ll work and do my utmost to earn a little.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’m here now, and the fact is there’s no turning back. At an inconvenient time, but what’s to be done?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I must have some simple furniture, and my expenses for drawing and painting materials aren’t getting any lower.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I also have to try and dress better. It’s a daring move, and a question of sink or swim. But some day I’d have  set up house on my own, so what else can I do? Now things have gone faster than I expected.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">As far as the relations between <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> and me are concerned, they can’t be put to rights so very quickly. The difference in our mentality and outlook on life is simply too great.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">And although I spoke in anger, I said things that I also think when I’m in a calmer mood. So I don’t take back what I said, and anyway <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> has now heard it plainly. If I’d been calmer, I’d have said it in other, less extreme colours, but basically I’d have thought the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And I hope that in any case it will lead to something good. I must endure bad times and the waters will rise, possibly as high as the lips and possibly even higher, how can I know beforehand? But I’ll fight my fight and sell my life dearly and try to win and pull through. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’ll be moving into the studio around 1 January. Regarding furniture, I’ll take the very simplest, a wooden table, a couple of chairs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">For a bed, I’d be content with a woollen blanket and the floor. But <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> wants me to buy a bed and will lend me the money if necessary. When drawing up an account of the 100 francs, there turned out to be money left over, even though I made two journeys this summer, and once, the last time, for such a long time. It’s true that I ate and slept at home, but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> himself said at the time that he could spare it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You understand that I’m now extremely worried, and foresee much toil and tribulation. But still it’s a relief to me that I’ve gone so far that I <hi rend="italics">can no longer</hi> go back, and that even though the path is difficult, my path is now clear enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">It goes without saying that I’m asking you, Theo, if you can do it, to send me now and then what you can without going short yourself. And – in the circumstances, send it to me rather than giving it to others. Because if possible we shouldn’t get <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> mixed up in this, as far as financial matters are concerned. It’s already of inestimable value that he helps me artistically in word and deed. He insists, however, that I buy a bed, for instance, and a couple of pieces of furniture, and says, I’ll lend it to you if necessary. Because according to him I must, <hi rend="italics">no matter what</hi>, appear presentable as regards my clothing, and not try to scrimp and save. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I’ll write to you again soon. <hi rend="italics">I don’t want to consider it a misfortune</hi> that it’s turned out this way, on the contrary, despite all the emotion I feel a certain calm.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"><hi rend="italics">There is safety in the midst of danger</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> What would life be if we didn’t dare to take things in hand?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I ran around everywhere to find that studio, both in the city and in Scheveningen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Scheveningen is terribly expensive. This studio costs only 7 guilders a month, but the furniture makes it difficult. Still, if one has one’s own things, they won’t disappear, and one has surer ground beneath one’s feet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">The light comes from the south, more or less, but the window is large and high,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and I have hopes that it will look nice after a time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">You can imagine how stimulated I feel. What will my work be like in a year? If only I could express what I feel – well, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> understands all this and wants to give me as many technical tips as he can – what fills my head and heart must be expressed in drawings or paintings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> himself is very busy with a large painting of a pink against the dunes being hauled by horses.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I think it’s wonderful to be in The Hague, and I find no end of beautiful things and I must try and depict some of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Adieu, old chap, accept a handshake in thought and write soon, believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Many regards from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321 bio.xml#_323">M. and Jet</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I still have a bit of money, but how long will I be able to get by on it? I have to stay at the boarding-house until 1 January.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Just address your letters to the address<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323"> A. Mauve</rs>. Uilebomen 198, since I go there almost every day.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Donderdag avond’. The letter was written on a Thursday between Vincent’s departure from Etten on 25 December 1881 <ref target="#l-11">(l. 11)</ref> and his move into a new studio on 1 January <ref target="#l-75">(l. 75)</ref>, i.e. Thursday, 29 December 1881.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s love for Kee Vos <ref target="let179.xml">(179)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mauve gives Van Gogh advice (<ref target="let192.xml">192</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means the time he spent in Dordrecht, Amsterdam and the Borinage (from early 1877 until about August 1880, when he decided to become an artist).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In fact the flat was located in a small street off Schenkweg, though it was considered part of the same street. The house number was 138 (from 1884 number 9). The owner of the house was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">Adrianus Johannes van der Drift</rs>. Van Gogh made a drawing of the group of houses to which his flat belonged: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Houses on Schenkweg</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_685">F 915 / JH 122</rs>). See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 17-19, and Visser 1973, pp. 23-24. Visser suggests, incidentally, that Van Gogh sublet his room from another (unknown) tenant.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Regarding this saying, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let182.xml#n-7">see letter 182, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Artists prefer a north-facing studio because the northern light is the most constant in quantity and colour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fishing boat on the beach</hi>, 1882 (The Hague, Kunstmuseum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_239">Ill. 239</rs>. The canvas, measuring 115 x 172 cm, was shown at the 1882 Salon, which opened on 1 May 1882. Its title was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sur la plage à Scheveningue </hi>(On the beach at Scheveningen). See exhib. cat. Paris 1882, p. 157, cat. no. 1811.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    