<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, Friday, 30 December 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let195"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8341 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>195</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R7</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>195</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1881-12-30">Friday, 30 December 1881</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8341" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001586_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001586_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8341" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001586_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001586_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001586_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">den Haag 30 Dec. 1881.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Uw schrijven uit Brussel<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> heb ik ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het bevalt mij volstrekt niet maar enfin<c type="kk">/</c> ge hebt geschreven op een moment dat gij zooals ge zelf zegt wat abnormaal waart. Niets of zoo goed als niets in Uw brief houdt steek.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">’k Ben blij ge uit Brussel terug zijt. evenwel ge hoort daar niet mijns inziens en wat betreft de “technische vaardigheid” die ge hoopt op de Akademie op te doen<c type="kk">/</c> ge zult daarin vrees ik bedrogen uitkomen<c type="kp">_</c> Zelfs dat kan men van lui als Stallaert niet leeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar nu zit ik druk in allerlei werk want ik heb hier een klein atelier gehuurd &amp; tegen 1 Januarij betrek ik dat &amp; heb nog heel wat dingen te beredderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Als ik later eens wat tot rust kom zal ik U nog wel weer eens bedaard schrijven over een &amp; ander maar neem ’t me niet kwalijk, nu heb ik serieuser dingen te doen dan brieven schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Natuurlijk hebben mijn brieven niet de pretentie om altijd raak te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> altijd de dingen precies te verklaren<c type="kk">/</c> och neen, ik tast dikwijls mis. Maar als ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Rappard die akademische lui over wie ge U bekommert zijn geen dubbeltje waard<c type="kk">/</c> en ik bedoel daar Stallaert &amp; Severdonk<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> mee<c type="kk">/</c> dan meen ik dat van ganscher harte<c type="kk">/</c> en ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> als ik u was zou ik ze laten loopen. Maar ik heb U dit reeds een paar keer gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ’t niet meer<c type="kk">/</c> over die heele akademie wil ik geen syllabe meer hooren of geen syllabe er meer over zeggen. ’t is me de moeite niet waard.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">En ik groet U bij dezen – wat zijn dat nu voor lui<c type="kk">/</c> die artisten met wie ge dan lambiek<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> hebt gedronken. waarom noemt ge er niet eens een paar bij hun naam.– Zullen dat lui zijn aan wie ge iets hebben zult? Ik hoop het voor U maar betwijfel het zeer.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Goeden dag kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb nu geen tijd meer en geen lust ook er in om langer te schrijven. Als ge op Uw atelier zijt werk geregeld met model<c type="kk">/</c> daar zult ge meer satisfactie van hebben op den duur. Enfin – bonjour.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Als ge me nog eens zoudt willen schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> stuur Uw brieven maar naar Etten<c type="kp">_</c> Zij zullen ze wel opsturen – ik hang tusschen 2 of 3 ateliers en ik zal vóór 1 Januarij beslissen welk ik neem<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> maar op ’t moment heb ik nog geen vast adres<c type="kk">/</c> gij verneemt dat later wel eens. Ik heb Etten verlaten omdat ik al te veel gedonder had met mijn vader over allerlei dingen die eigentlijk de moeite niet waard zijn er over te spreken – over ’t naar de kerk gaan &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> en dat bragt me zelfs als ik hard &amp; veel werkte in een stemming van verveling en koelheid die niet deugt. Dus heb ik mij hier gevestigd en ben blij ik in een andere omgeving ben<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zit nu wel een beetje in de zorg maar dat is toch nog beter dan op den duur getwist en gezanik te hebben.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">The Hague, 30 Dec. 1881.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I received your letter from Brussels.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I don’t like it at all, but still, you wrote it at a time when, as you yourself say, you weren’t quite normal. Nothing or next to nothing in your letter holds water.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’m glad you’re back from Brussels. Still, you don’t belong there in my opinion, and as regards the ‘technical competence’ you hope to gain at the Academy, you will, I fear, end up being deceived. Even that can’t be learned from people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1365">Stallaert</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But now I’m busy with all kinds of work, for I’ve rented a small studio here and will be moving into it around 1 January and still have a lot of things to see to.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Later, when things have quietened down a bit, I’ll write to you again calmly about this and that, but don’t take offence if I’ve got more serious things to do now than write letters.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Of course my letters don’t pretend always to hit the mark, always to explain things precisely, oh no, I’m often wrong about things. But if I tell you, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, those academics you worry about aren’t worth tuppence, and I’m referring to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1365">Stallaert</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1352">Severdonck</rs><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> &amp;c., I mean it with all my heart, and I’m telling you, if I were you I’d forget about them. But I’ve already told you this a couple of times, I won’t say it again, I don’t want to hear another syllable or utter another syllable about the whole academy ever again. It isn’t worth the bother.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And I hereby send you my regards – what kind of people are they, those artists with whom you drank Lambiek?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Why don’t you mention even a couple of them by name? Are they people who’ll be of any use to you? I hope so, for your sake, but I seriously doubt it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Good-day, old chap, I have no more time, nor any desire, to write more. When you’re in your studio, work often with a model, you’ll get more satisfaction from it in the long run. Anyway – good-day.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Should you want to write to me again, send your letters to Etten. They’ll send them on – I’m wavering between 2 or 3 studios and will decide which one to take before 1 January,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> but at the moment I don’t have a fixed address, you’ll learn of it at some point. I left Etten because I was having too much trouble with my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> about all sorts of things that actually aren’t worth talking about – about going to church &amp;c. &amp;c., and even if I worked hard and a great deal, it put me in a state of weariness and coldness that’s not good for anything. So I’ve settled down here and am glad to be in different surroundings. I have a few worries, but that’s better than all that quarrelling and nagging.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘den Haag 30 Dec. 1881’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s quarrel with his parents (<ref target="let194.xml">194</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had studied for a time at the Brussels Academy (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let178.xml#n-1">see letter 178, n. 1</ref>). He had meanwhile returned to the Netherlands (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-7">see l. 7</ref>), but had apparently written to Van Gogh while still in Brussels. It is not clear whether the present letter is a response to that letter (in which he must have announced his return) or to another letter written after his return.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1352">Joseph van Severdonck</rs> taught at the Brussels Academy of Fine Arts, giving lessons in drawing and painting ‘after the antique head, torso and fragments’; from 1875 he gave the course in painting from life. See exhib. cat. Brussels 1987, pp. 246-247. For Stallaert cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let178.xml">letter 178</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Lambiek is a Belgian beer.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>There is nothing in any of the letters to suggest that Van Gogh was actually considering various studios. As regards his choice, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let194.xml#n-2">see letter 194, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    