<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 8 or Monday, 9 January 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let199"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b190 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>199</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>169</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>198</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-01-08">Sunday, 8 or Monday, 9 January 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0190 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000215_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000215_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0190 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000215_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000215_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000215_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0190 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0190 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000216_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Gij moet niet denken dat ik den brief terug stuur om te beleedigen maar ik vind dit de kortste manier om er duidelijk op te antwoorden. En als gij uw brief er niet bij terug hadt zoudt gij niet zoo goed begrijpen kunnen waar mijn antwoord op doelt<c type="kk">/</c> nu wijzen de nummers u den weg. Ik heb geen tijd<c type="kk">/</c> ik wacht nog model van daag.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ik wist omdat ik maar weinig tijd heb geen beter middel om te antwoorden op uw brief dan dat ik op deze manier in geregelde volgorde op een &amp; ander antwoord.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">(1) Daar heb ik het niet op “<hi rend="italics">aangelegd</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel toen Pa hier was<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> hebben Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> Pa &amp; ik er over gesproken dat ik een atelier zou huren te Etten – daar den winter doorbrengen – in ’t voorjaar terug komen te s’Hage. Om reden van de modellen en omdat ik daar te Etten mijn werk geregeld had &amp; het begon te vlotten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dat neemt niet weg dat ik mijn verblijf te s’Hage nog wel wat had willen rekken toen ik toch hier was<c type="kk">/</c> maar het was niet te min wel degelijk mijn voornemen de studies van de Brabantsche boerentypen voort te zetten<c type="kp">_</c> En toen ik gecontrarieerd werd in het ten uitvoer brengen van dat plan nadat het met M. overlegd was &amp; ik reeds in correspondentie was met hem over het bewuste atelier (eene loods waaraan eenige reparatiën moesten geschieden)<c type="kk">/</c> toen kon ik mijn drift niet bedwingen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Herinner U een schrijven van mij aan U waarin ik U meer in het breede over mijn plan om die studies door te zetten schreef.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik bedoel den brief waarin ik U verzocht om Pa &amp; Moe nog eens met een hartig woordje op t’hart te drukken dat den werkkring te Etten van zooveel belang voor mij was &amp;c. ik herinner mij de uitdrukking die ik bezigde: het zou toch wat te erg zijn als ik om een gril van Pa een werk moest opgeven dat nu aan het vlotten is en waaraan ik reeds sedert maanden arbeid. Denk zelf na – ondanks de hulp van Mauve zit ik hier veel meer in de penarie dan t’huis en ik weet waarachtig niet hoe ik er doorkomen zal.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">2) Die uitdrukking <hi rend="italics">dat ik het er op aanleg om Pa &amp; Moe het</hi> <hi rend="italics">leven bitter te maken</hi> is eigentlijk niet van U<c type="kk">/</c> ik ken die en van ouds als een jesuitisme van Pa zelf en heb Pa gezegd &amp; Moe ook dat ik het als een jesuitisme beschoude en er mij niets van aantrok.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Pa komt als men hem iets zegt waarop hij niet meer weet te antwoorden geregeld voor den dag met een dergelijk gezegde en o.a. zegt<c type="kk">/</c> “gij vermoort me”<c type="kk">/</c> terwijl hij doodkalm de courant zit te lezen en zijn pijp rookt. Dus neem ik dergelijke uitdrukkingen voor ’t geen ze zijn.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">of anders wordt Pa fameus driftig en is gewoon dat de lui dan bang worden en ’t verwondert Pa als iemand voor zijn drift niet wijkt.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Pa is vreesselijk ligtgeraakt en prikkelbaar en vol eigenzinnigheden in het huisselijk leven en is gewoon zijn zin te krijgen. En onder de rubriek “de vormen en regels van dit huis” waarnaar ik mij dan zou moeten schikken<c type="kk">/</c> daar hoort letterlijk alles toe wat Pa maar in den zin komt.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">3) “Vechten met een oud man is geen kunst &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c>” Om reden dat Pa een oud man is heb ik Pa honderdmaal gespaard &amp; dingen verdragen die ondragelijk zijn ten naaste bij. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ditmaal was ’t ook geen vechten maar eenvoudig een “basta” zeggen en omdat er niet geluisterd werd naar rede en gezond verstand heb ik het eens op een vierkante manier gezegd &amp; ’t is erg best dat Pa nu eens rondborstig een &amp; ander heeft hooren uitspreken dat anderen ook wel eens denken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">4) Dat het zich niet gaauw redresseeren zal.– Voor het uiterlijke heb ik de zaak in orde gebragt door nog eens aan Pa te schrijven dat ik een atelier gehuurd had<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik verder met het nieuwe jaar gelukwenschte<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik hoopte wij in dat nieuwe jaar niet meer op die wijs noch ook op eenige andere manier twisten zouden. Meer doe ik er niet aan, meer hoef ik er niet aan te doen. Stond deze laatste scène op zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> was ’t iets anders<c type="kk">/</c> maar die is voorafgegaan door andere scènes<c type="kk">/</c> doch als wanneer<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> ik op bedaarder ofschoon besliste wijze veel dingen gezegd heb tot Pa die door ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> systematisch in den wind geslagen werden<c type="kp">_</c> Dus wat betreft die dingen die ik in drift gezegd heb<c type="kk">/</c> ook in bedaarder stemming denk ik er zoo over<c type="kk">/</c> alleen dan zwijg<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> ik ze uit politiek of zeg ze op een andere manier. Maar nu viel mijn politiek weg toen ik driftig werd en enfin<c type="kk">/</c> nu heb ik het eens uitgesproken. Ik vraag daar geen excuus voor en zoolang Pa &amp; Moe in die stemming blijven neem ik er niets van terug.– Worden zij later mogelijk wat menschelijker en gevoeliger en opregter dan zal ik gaarne dat alles terugnemen.– Maar ik betwijfel of dat wel gebeuren zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">5) Dat Pa &amp; Moe niet kunnen leven als er geharrewar is &amp;c. dat is in zoover waar dat zij een woestijn om zich scheppen en zich een kwaden ouden dag bezorgen als zij een goeden en tevredenen konden hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Maar toch<c type="kk">/</c> wat betreft die uitdrukkingen “ik kan het niet uithouden”<c type="kk">/</c> “ik word vermoord”<c type="kk">/</c> “mijn leven wordt verbitterd”<c type="kk">/</c> ik hecht er niet meer aan want dat is maar een maniertje<c type="kp">_</c> En als zij niet veranderen zou ik gelijk ik reeds zeide vreezen dat zij zich nog veel kwade en eenzame dagen bereiden zullen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">6) Dat ik er spijt van zal hebben &amp;c. Vóór het zoover kwam als het nu gekomen is heb ik veel spijt en smart gehad en ’t mij moeielijk gemaakt omdat het zoo slecht ging tusschen Pa en Moe en mij. Maar nu het eenmaal zoover gekomen is<c type="kk">/</c> welnu het zij zoo en nu heb ik om U de waarheid te zeggen geen spijt meer maar onwillekeurig een gevoel van verlossing. Zie ik later in dat ik verkeerd deed<c type="kk">/</c> ja dan zal ik er spijt van hebben natuurlijkerwijs maar tot nog toe zie ik niet precies in hoe het mogelijk was anders te handelen<c type="kp">_</c> Wanneer iemand mij gedecideerd zegt “ga mijn huis uit<c type="kk">/</c> hoe eer hoe liever, liever binnen ’t half uur dan over een uur”<c type="kk">/</c> welnu, kerel, dan duurt het geen kwartier of ik ben er uit en kom er niet weer in ook. Dat is wat te bar<c type="kp">_</c> Om finantieele reden zou ik om U of anderen geen meer last te veroorzaken niet ligt uit mijn eigen zijn vertrokken<c type="kk">/</c> gij begrijpt dit wel doch nu niet van mijn maar van hun kant gezegd wordt “ga weg”<c type="kk">/</c> welnu dan is mijn weg duidelijk genoeg aangewezen.–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">7) Wat betreft Mauve – ja zeker houd ik veel van M. en sympathizeer met hem<c type="kk">/</c> van zijn werk houd ik veel – en ik acht mij gelukkig wat van hem te leeren maar evenmin als Mauve zelf kan ik mij in een systeem of rigting opsluiten en behalve van Mauve en het werk van Mauve houd ik ook van anderen die heel anders zijn en werken. En wat betreft mijzelf en mijn eigen werk<c type="kk">/</c> misschien is er overeenkomst soms maar zeker ook wel degelijk onderscheid. Als ik van iemand of iets houd dan meen ik dat en er komt bepaald soms hartstogt en vuur bij doch daarom vind ik niet systematisch alleen enkele personen volmaakt en al de anderen niets waard – dat zij verre.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">8) Vrijdenkend dat is eigentlijk een woord waaraan ik erg het land heb ofschoon ik soms faute de mieux het wel eens gebruiken moet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">9) De zaak is dat ik mijn best doe om door te denken en probeer om bij doen of laten rekening te houden met rede en gezond verstand. En juist daartegen zou het strijden als men iemand tot niets wilde reduceeren. Het is dus volkomen waar dat ik wel eens tot Pa gezegd heb “denk toch eens door over dit of dat”<c type="kk">/</c> of “dit of dat houdt geen steek mijns inziens”<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat is niet iemand tot niets zoeken te reduceeren<c type="kp">_</c> En ik ben niet Pa’s vijand als ik hem eens de waarheid zeg<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs niet toen ik in drift het in zeemanstermen uitdrukte. Alleen het hielp me niets en Pa nam het slecht op. Is het dat Pa er op doelt dat ik gezegd heb dat de moraal en het godsdienstig systeem van de dominés en de akademische opvattingen voor mij geen dubbeltje waard zijn sedert ik er veel dessous de cartes van heb leeren kennen<c type="kk">/</c> dan neem ik dat volstrekt niet terug want ik meen het werkelijk. Alleen in bedaarde stemming spreek ik er niet over maar ’t wordt iets anders als men me b.v. wil dwingen om naar de kerk te gaan of er waarde aan te hechten<c type="kk">/</c> dan zeg ik natuurlijkerwijs dat dat geheel &amp; al buiten kwestie is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">10) Telt Pa’s leven voor niets? Ik heb reeds gezegd dat als ik iemand hoor zeggen “ge vermoort me”<c type="kk">/</c> en ondertusschen leest die man zijn courant en spreekt een halve minuut later over ik weet niet wat voor advertentie<c type="kk">/</c> ik zoo’n uitdrukking vrij ontoepasselijk en overbodig vind &amp; er me niets van aantrek. Zoodra die uitdrukking of dergelijke oververteld worden aan anderen die dan mij voor een moordenaar en zelfs oudermoordenaar gaan beschouwen min of meer<c type="kk">/</c> dan zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> zulke kwaadsprekerijen zijn noch meer noch minder dan jesuitismes. Ziedaar. Overigens nu is de moordenaar het huis uit en dus kort en goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik trek me daar niets van aan en ik vind het bespottelijk zelfs<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">11) Gij zegt “ik begrijp je niet”. Nu dat geloof ik graag want schrijven is eigentlijk maar een beroerd middel om elkaar dingen begrijpelijk te maken<c type="kp">_</c> En het kost veel tijd en gij en ik hebben toch al veel te doen. Maar we moeten maar wat geduld hebben met elkaar totdat we elkaar weer eens zien en spreken.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">12) Schrijf me weer eens<c type="kp">_</c> Ja natuurlijk<c type="kk">/</c> maar vooraf moet ik met U afspreken hoe.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Wilt gij dat ik in een soort koopmansstijl zal schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> droog en afgepast en mijn woorden wikkende en wegende en eigentlijk niets zeggende<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Of wilt gij dat ik zal voortgaan te schrijven net zoo als ik in den laatsten tijd gedaan heb<c type="kk">/</c> over allerlei U de gedachten zeggende die in me opkomen zonder bang te zijn eens door te slaan<c type="kk">/</c> zonder mijne gedachten te kortwieken of terug te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Dat laatste doe ik het liefst<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk vrijuit schrijven of zeggen wat ik bedoel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">En nu eindig ik het direkte antwoord op uw brief want ik heb nog met U te spreken over teekenen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp; daar praat ik liever over. Houd het mij ten goede dat ik voorloopig maar net doe als of Pa en Moe niet bestaan<c type="kk">/</c> het was veel beter geweest dat ik dezen winter te Etten had doorgebragt en het was vooral om finantieele reden veel makkelijker voor me geweest<c type="kp">_</c>– Ging ik daarover weer denken &amp; tobben<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou er melankoliek van worden dus het is uit<c type="kk">/</c> kort &amp; goed. Ik zit nu hier en moet er zien door te scharrelen. Als ik er nog over ging schrijven met Pa<c type="kk">/</c> ’t was olie in ’t vuur en ik wil niet meer zoo driftig worden en ik werp me met al mijn kracht in het leven en de zaken hier<c type="kk">/</c> en wat wil ik<c type="kk">/</c> Etten is verloren en het Heike maar ik zal iets anders zoeken terug te winnen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Nu dank ik U regt hartelijk voor ’t gezondene.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik behoef U niet te zeggen dat ik overigens eigentlijk toch erg in de zorg zit. Natuurlijkerwijs zijn mijn uitgaven meer dan te Etten en ik kan niet half zoo energiek te werk gaan als ik zou willen en zou kunnen als ik over meer te beschikken had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Maar mijn atelier komt in orde. Ik wou dat gij het eens zaagt<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb al mijn studies opgehangen en gij moet mij die gij hebt ook maar terug sturen want ik kan er nog dienst van hebben. Zij mogen onverkoopbaar zijn en ik zelf wil graag al de fouten er van erkennen maar er zit iets in van de natuur omdat zij gemaakt zijn met een zekere passie.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">En ge weet ik tob nu om aquarellen te maken en krijg ik daar den slag van dan zullen ze verkoopbaar worden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Maar Theo ge kunt er verzekerd van zijn dat toen ik voor ’t eerst bij Mauve was geweest met mijn penteekeningen en M<c type="kp">_</c> zei<c type="kk">/</c> ge moet het eens met houtskool &amp; krijt &amp; penseel &amp; doezelaar probeeren<c type="kk">/</c> ik er verdomd veel moeite mee gehad heb om met dat nieuwe materiaal te werken. Ik ben geduldig geweest en ’t scheen niets te helpen<c type="kk">/</c> toen werd ik soms zoo ongeduldig dat ik mijn houtskool vertrapte en gansch &amp; al moedeloos werd<c type="kp">_</c> En toch<c type="kk">/</c> een tijd daarna stuurde ik U teekeningen met krijt &amp; houtskool &amp; ’t penseel gemaakt<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en ik kwam bij Mauve terug met een heele partij dergelijken waarop hij wel aanmerking had natuurlijkerwijs en teregt<c type="kk">/</c> en gij ook<c type="kk">/</c> doch evenwel ik was een stap vooruit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Nu zit ik weer in een dergelijke periode van strijd en moedeloosheid<c type="kk">/</c> van geduld en ongeduld<c type="kk">/</c> van hoop en van desolatie. Maar ik moet daar doorworstelen en enfin<c type="kk">/</c> over een tijd zal ik het aquarelleeren wel beter vatten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Als het zoo makkelijk was zou er geen aardigheid aan zijn.– En met het schilderen is het dito dito. Nu komt er nog bij dat het weer ongunstig is en dezen winter ben ik nog niet voor mijn pleizier uit. Toch heb ik schik in mijn leven en vooral dat ik een eigen atelier heb vind ik onuitsprekelijk heerlijk. Wanneer komt ge eens bij me koffij of thee drinken? Ik hoop spoedig. Ge kunt desnoods logeeren ook<c type="kk">/</c> wat best en wat gezellig. En ik heb zelfs bloemen<c type="kk">/</c> ook een paar bakjes bollen. En bovendien heb ik nog een ander ornament voor mijn atelier opgedaan<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een verbazend koopje gehad aan prachtige houtsneden uit de Graphic<c type="kk">/</c> gedeeltelijk afdrukken niet van de clichés maar van de blokken zelf. Precies de dingen waarnaar ik jaren verlangd heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">De teekeningen van Herkomer<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Frank Holl<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Walker<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en anderen. Ik heb ze gekocht van Blok den boekenjood<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en heb uit een enormen stapel graphics &amp; London News uitgezocht wat het beste was voor vijf gulden. Er zijn dingen bij die superbe zijn<c type="kk">/</c> onder anderen de Houseless and homeless van 
<pb f="2r" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-7" facs="#zone-pb-2r-7"/>
Fildes (arme lui voor een nachthuis wachtende)<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en twee groote Herkomers en veel kleine<c type="kk">/</c> en de Irish emigrants van Frank Holl<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en de “Old gate” van Walker.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en vooral een meisjesschool van Frank Holl<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en dan nog die groote Herkomer<c type="kk">/</c> de invaliden.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Enfin dat is net het goedje dat ik noodig heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">En ik heb zulke mooie dingen met een zekere rust in huis omdat kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik er nog een heel eind van daan ben om ze zelf zóó mooi te maken<c type="kk">/</c> ik toch een paar studies van oude boertjes enz<c type="kp">_</c> aan den muur heb hangen die bewijzen dat mijn enthousiasme voor die teekenaars niet maar enkel ijdelheid is maar dat ik er op tob en er naar streef om zelf ook iets te maken dat realistisch is en toch met sentiment gedaan. Ik heb wel een stuk of 12 figuren van spitters en lui die op het aardappelveld bezig zijn<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en ik denk er over of ik daar niet iets van zou kunnen maken<c type="kk">/</c> gij hebt er ook nog een paar van<c type="kk">/</c> o.a<c type="kp">_</c> een man die aardappelen in een zak doet.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Enfin ik weet het nog niet maar hetzij nu hetzij later<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet dat toch eens maken want ik heb het dezen zomer zoo bekeken en hier in de duinen zou ik een goede studie van den grond en de lucht kunnen maken en dan de figuren er brutaal in. Toch hecht ik niet zoo heel veel aan die studies en hoop natuurlijk ze nog heel anders en beter te maken maar de brabantsche typen zijn karakteristiek en wie weet of er nog geen partij van te trekken is. Mogten er bij zijn die ge houden wilt ga gerust uw gang maar die waar ge niet aan hecht wil ik wel heel graag terug hebben. Door het bestudeeren van nieuwe modellen zal ik van zelf attent worden op de fouten in de proportie van mijn studies van dezen zomer en daarmee rekening houdende zijn ze mij alligt nog nuttig. Toen Uw brief zoo lang weg bleef (want doordat hij eerst naar Mauve ging kreeg ik hem nog later) moest ik naar den Hr Tersteeg toe gaan en die heeft mij f<c type="kp">_</c> 25 gegeven totdat ik Uw brief zou ontvangen. Het is misschien wel goed dat ik met Uw medeweten of gij met mijn medeweten ’t een of ander met den Hr T. afspreek. Want gij begrijpt Theo<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet zoo vast mogelijk weten waaraan ik mij te houden heb, en ik moet vooruit berekenen en weten<c type="kk">/</c> dit of dat kan ik doen of moet het laten. Gij zult mij dus veel genoegen doen als wij vast met elkaar afspreken en ik hoop gij mij daarover spoedig zult schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Mauve heeft me beloofd dat hij me zou voordragen om dadelijk buitengewoon lid van Pulchri<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> te worden omdat ik dan 2 maal in de week s’avonds daar naar ’t model kan teekenen en meer omgang met artisten hebben. Dan word ik later zoo spoedig mogelijk gewoon lid. Nu kerel, dank voor het gezondene – en geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">You mustn’t think that I’m sending the letter back to insult you, but I find this the quickest way to answer it clearly. And if you didn’t have your letter back, you wouldn’t be able to understand what my answer refers to, whereas now the numbers guide you. I have no time, I’m waiting for a model today.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Because I have only a little time, I knew no better means of answering your letter than to answer one thing and another like this, point by point.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">(1) I didn’t ‘<hi rend="italics">contrive</hi>’ to do it, on the contrary, when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was here,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, Pa and I talked about my renting a studio in Etten – spending the winter there – coming back to The Hague in the spring. Because of the models and because I’d arranged to work there, and it was beginning to go well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">All the same, I’d have liked to prolong my stay in The Hague a bit, since I was here anyway, but nonetheless I seriously intended continuing my studies of the Brabant peasant types. And when I was crossed in realizing that plan, after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> had been consulted and I had already written to him about the studio in question (a shed which needed some repairs), I couldn’t suppress my anger.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Please remember one of my letters to you in which I wrote to you in broad terms about my plan to continue those studies.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I mean the letter in which I asked you to say a few heartfelt words to impress upon <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> how important my work in Etten was to me &amp;c. I remember the words I used: it really would be too bad if a whim of Pa were to make me give up work which is now progressing so well and which I’ve been working on for months. Think about it yourself – despite <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s help, I’m in far more trouble here than at home, and I truly don’t know how I’ll get by.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">2) That expression <hi rend="italics">that I contrive to make <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>’s life miserable </hi>is actually not yours, I’ve known it for a long time as one of Pa’s Jesuitisms, and also told Pa and Ma that I considered it a Jesuitism and didn’t take the slightest notice of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> regularly comes up with some such saying if someone says something to him that he doesn’t know how to answer, and says, among other things, ‘you’ll be the death of me’, while calmly reading the newspaper and smoking his pipe. So I take such expressions at their face value. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Or else <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> gets incredibly angry and is used to people being afraid, and it surprises Pa if people don’t give way to his anger.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> is very easily hurt and irritable and full of obstinacies in domestic life and is used to getting his way. And the category ‘the conventions and rules of this house’, which I’m supposed to observe, includes literally everything that comes into Pa’s head.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">3) ‘Fighting with an old man isn’t difficult &amp;c.’ Because <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> is an old man I’ve spared him a hundred times, and tolerated things that are well-nigh intolerable. Well, this time it wasn’t fighting but simply saying ‘enough’, and because he wasn’t listening to reason and common sense I said it outright for once, and it’s very good indeed that Pa has finally heard one thing and another spoken plainly that others sometimes think as well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">4) That it won’t be put to rights quickly. For appearances’ sake I straightened things out by writing again to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> to say that I’d rented a studio, that I also wished him a happy New Year, that I hoped that in that new year we should no longer fight in that way or in any other manner. I’m not doing any more about it, I don’t have to do any more about it. If this last scene were the only one of its kind, it would be different, but it was preceded by other scenes, when I’d said to Pa, in a calmer yet resolute way, many things that His Hon. systematically brushed aside one by one. So as regards those things I said in anger, I think the same things in a calmer mood, only then I refrain from saying them out of diplomacy or I say them in another way. But all diplomacy abandoned me when I got angry, and, well, now I’ve finally said it. I’m not asking for an apology, and as long as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> take this attitude I won’t take any of it back. If, later on, they possibly become a bit more humane and sensitive and fair, then I’ll be glad to take it all back. But I doubt if that will happen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">5) That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> can’t stand it if there’s bad blood &amp;c. That’s true inasmuch as they create a desert around themselves and are making their old age miserable, even though it could be good and satisfying. But as to those expressions, ‘I can’t stand it’, ‘this will be the death of me’, ‘my life is a misery’, I no longer take any notice, because it’s only a mannerism. And if they don’t change, I fear, as I already said, that they’re in for many miserable and lonely days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">6) That I’ll regret it &amp;c. Before things got as bad as they are now, I felt a great deal of remorse and sorrow, and tormented myself because things were going so badly between <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> and me. But now that it’s come to this, well, so be it, and to tell you the truth I’m no longer sorry but can’t help feeling relieved. If I realize later that I did the wrong thing, yes, then of course I’ll regret it, but I still don’t exactly see how it would have been possible to act otherwise. When someone tells me in no uncertain terms, ‘leave my house, the sooner the better, within the half-hour rather than the hour’, well, old chap, then I’m out in less than a quarter of an hour, and won’t come back again either. It really is too bad. For financial reasons, and so as not to cause you or anyone else any more trouble, I wouldn’t have left so easily of my own accord, you surely understand that, but now that they and not I said ‘go away’, well, the path I must take is clear enough. 
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">7) As far as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is concerned – yes of course I’m very fond of M., and sympathize with him, I like his work very much – and I consider myself fortunate to learn something from him, but I can’t shut myself up in a system or school any more than Mauve himself can, and in addition to Mauve and Mauve’s work, I also like others who are very different and work very differently. And as far as me and my own work are concerned, perhaps there’s a similarity sometimes, but certainly also a distinct difference. If I love someone or something, then I mean it, and there is definitely passion and fire sometimes, but that doesn’t mean that I systematically find only some people perfect and all the others worthless – God forbid.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">8) Free-thinking: actually that’s a word I loathe, though I’m sometimes forced to use it for want of something better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">9) The thing is that I’m doing my best to think things through and try to take reason and common sense into account in what I do. And it would be totally inconsistent with that if one wanted to reduce someone to nothing. So it’s entirely true that I sometimes said to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> ‘do consider this or that fully’, or ‘this or that doesn’t hold water in my opinion’, but that isn’t trying to reduce someone to nothing. And I’m not Pa’s enemy if I tell him the truth for once, not even when I said it angrily in salty language. Only it didn’t help me at all, and Pa took it badly. Does Pa mean that I said that the morality and religious system of the clergymen and academic notions aren’t worth tuppence to me since I’ve learned many of their tricks, then I certainly won’t take it back, because I really mean it. It’s only in a calm mood that I don’t talk about it, but it’s something else if one tries, for instance, to force me to go to church or to attach value to it, then of course I say it’s absolutely out of the question.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">10) Does <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s life count for nothing? I already said that if I hear someone say ‘you’ll be the death of me’, and all the while that man is reading his newspaper and half a minute later starts talking about goodness knows what advertisement, then I find such an expression rather inappropriate and unnecessary and pay no attention to it. As soon as those words or suchlike are repeated to others, who then start to look upon me as something of a murderer or even a parricide, then I say, such calumnies are neither more nor less than Jesuitisms. So there you have it. Besides, now the murderer has left home and so, in a word, I take no notice of it, and I even think it ridiculous.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">11) You say ‘I don’t understand you’. Well, that I certainly believe, because writing is actually an awful way to explain things to each other. And it takes a lot of time, and you and I have rather a lot to do. But we must have a bit of patience with one another until we see and speak to one another again. 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">12) Write to me again. Yes of course, but first I have to agree with you on how.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> Do you want me to write in a sort of business style, dry and formal and picking and choosing my words and actually saying nothing?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Or do you want me to go on writing just as I’ve been doing recently, telling you everything that pops into my head without being afraid to let fly, without mincing my words or holding back.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I prefer to do the latter, namely write or say plainly what I mean.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And now I’ll end my direct answer to your letter because I still have to speak to you about drawing &amp;c., and I prefer to talk about that. Please bear with me if I pretend for the time being that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> don’t exist, it would have been much better if I’d spent this winter in Etten, and it would have been much easier for me, particularly for financial reasons. If I were to think and fret about it, it would make me despondent, so that’s it, it’s over. Now I’m here and I have to manage somehow. If I were to write to Pa about it again, it would be adding fuel to the flames, and I don’t want to get so angry again, and I’m throwing myself with all my might into life and things here, what else can I do? Etten is lost and Het Heike, but I’ll try to regain something else instead.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Now I thank you very much indeed for what you sent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I don’t need to tell you that I really have a great many worries besides. Naturally my expenses are more than in Etten and I can’t set to work with half as much energy as I should like and should be able to if I had more at my disposal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">But my studio is turning out well. I wish you could see it, I’ve hung up all my studies, and you must send back the ones you have because they might prove useful to me. They may be unsaleable, and I myself acknowledge all their faults, but they contain something of nature because they were made with a certain passion. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And you know that I’m now struggling to make watercolours, and if I become adept at it they’ll become saleable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">But Theo, you can be certain that when I first went to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> with my pen drawings and M. said, you should try it with charcoal and chalk and brush and stump, it was damned difficult for me to work with that new material. I was patient and it didn’t seem to help at all, and sometimes I grew so impatient that I trampled on my charcoal and was wholly and utterly discouraged. And yet, a while later I sent you drawings made with chalk and charcoal and the brush,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and I went back to Mauve with a whole batch of such drawings which of course he criticized, and rightly so, and you too, but all the same I had taken a step forward.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Now I’m going through a similar period of struggle and despondency, of patience and impatience, of hope and desolation. But I must plod on and anyway, after a while I’ll understand more about making watercolours.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">If it were that easy, one wouldn’t take any pleasure in it. And it’s exactly the same with painting. Moreover, the weather is bad, and this winter I haven’t yet gone out for pleasure. Still, I enjoy life and, in particular, having my own studio is too wonderful for words. When will you come and have coffee or tea with me? Soon I hope. You can stay here too, if necessary, that would be nice and companionable. And I even have flowers, and a couple of boxes of bulbs. And I’ve also acquired another ornament for my studio, I got a great bargain on some splendid woodcuts from The Graphic, some of them prints not of the clichés but of the blocks themselves. Just what I’ve been wanting for years.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">The drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Frank Holl</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1428">Walker</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and others. I bought them from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_293">Blok</rs>, the Jewish bookseller,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and chose the best from an enormous pile of Graphics and London News for five guilders. Some of them are superb, including the Houseless and homeless by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1026">Fildes</rs> 
      <pb f="2r" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-7" facs="#zone-pb-2r-7"/> (poor people waiting outside a night shelter)<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and two large Herkomers and many small ones, and the Irish emigrants by Frank Holl<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and the ‘Old gate’ by Walker.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> And especially a girls’ school by Frank Holl<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and also that large Herkomer, the invalids.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">In short, it’s exactly the stuff I need.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">And I have such beautiful things with a kind of restfulness in my house because, old chap, even though I’m still a long way from making them so beautifully myself, still, I have a couple of studies of old peasants and so on hanging on the wall that prove that my enthusiasm for those draughtsmen is not mere vanity, but that I’m struggling and striving to make something myself that is realistic and yet done with sentiment. I have around 12 figures of diggers and people working in the potato field,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and I’m wondering if I couldn’t make something of them, you also have a couple of them, including a man putting potatoes in a sack.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Anyway, I don’t know what yet, but whether it’s now or later, I must do it sometime, because I took a look at it this summer, and here in the dunes I could make a good study of the earth and the sky and then boldly put the figures in. Though I don’t value those studies so very much, and hope of course to make them very differently and better, but the Brabant types are distinctive, and who knows how they might be put to use. If there are some among them you’d like to keep, then by all means, but I’d very much like to have back those you don’t value. By studying new models I’ll automatically become alert to the mistakes in the proportion of my studies of this summer and, taking that into account, they can easily be of use to me. When your letter took so long to arrive (for because it went first to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> I got it even later), I had to go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> and he gave me 25 guilders to last until I received your letter. Perhaps it would be good if I, with your knowledge, or you, with my knowledge, were to settle a few things with Mr T. Because you understand, Theo, I must know as definitely as possible where I stand, and I have to work it out in advance, and know that I can or cannot do this or that. So you’ll be doing me a great favour by entering into a definite agreement, and I hope you’ll write to me about it soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> has promised to recommend me for an associate membership of Pulchri,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> because there I’d be able to draw from a model two evenings a week and would have more contact with artists. Later on I’ll become a regular member as soon as possible. Well, old chap, thanks for what you sent – and believe me, with a handshake,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent most likely responded to Theo’s letter of 5 January immediately after receiving it, considering the seriousness of the matter and the need he felt for unconstrained correspondence. <ref target="let197.xml">Letter 197</ref> probably arrived in The Hague on Friday, 6 or possibly Saturday, 7 August, but it was addressed to Mauve, so Vincent received it only ‘later’ <ref target="#l-246">(ll. 246-247)</ref>. His reply must therefore date from Sunday, 8 or Monday, 9 January 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s quarrel with his parents (<ref target="let194.xml">194</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> must have visited Vincent, who was taking lessons from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> in painting in both oils and watercolours, some time between 27 November and about 21 December 1881.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to his letter of 18 November 1881 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let186.xml">letter 186</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘tijdens welke scènes echter’ (during which scenes, however; translated here as ‘when’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘verzwijg’ (keep silent about, refrain from saying).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>There are several drawings from November-December in which Van Gogh used the drawing materials mentioned: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_251">F 886 / JH 69</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mother by a cradle and a child sitting on the floor</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_686">F 1070 / JH 74</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl with a black cap sitting on the ground</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_324">F 873 / JH 79</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The Van Gogh estate contains 22 prints after the work of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs>; they all came from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> and date from the period 1872-1879.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Three works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Francis Montague Holl</rs> have been preserved in Van Gogh’s estate; they all came from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> (1872-1873).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s estate contains three works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1428">Frederick Walker</rs>: two from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> (1871 and 1877) and one from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> (1875).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>There were two booksellers in The Hague by the name of Blok: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_293">Jozef Blok</rs>, known as the ‘open-air librarian of the Binnenhof’, who had a stall in Grote Markt and a book storeroom at Herderstraat 10, and his brother, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_294">David Blok</rs>, who had a shop at Stationsweg 3. Jozef – who sold collectors’ items, magazines and literary works – was well known among artists. In November 1882 Van Gogh made a portrait drawing of him (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2407">F 993 / JH 254</rs>) (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let280.xml">see letter 280</ref>). Regarding the Blok brothers, see J.E. Heijbroek, ‘Bij de nieuwe voorplaat’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Boekenwereld. Tijdschrift voor Boek en Prent</hi> 10-1 (1993), pp. 23-28.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Houseless and hungry</hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1026">Samuel Luke Fildes</rs> appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 1 (4 December 1869), p. 9 and was reprinted in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic Portfolio</hi>, 1877. Van Gogh’s copy is still extant. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1905">Ill. 1905</rs>. (t*151).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>In his letters Van Gogh mentions ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irish</hi> emigrants’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Francis Montague Holl</rs> three times and ‘Emigrants’ once (in the present letter, as well as in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let249.xml">letters 249</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let311.xml">311</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let307.xml">307</ref>). An engraving called ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gone’ – Euston station. Departure of emigrants, 9.15 p.m. Train for Liverpool, September, 1875</hi>, appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic </hi>13 (19 February 1876), pp. 180-181, but neither its title nor the accompanying commentary indicates that these emigrants are bound for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ireland</hi>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1906">Ill. 1906</rs>.</p>

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> 65 (5 September 1874), pp. 220-221, published an engraving titled <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irish emigrants leaving Queenstown harbour</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1907">Ill. 1907</rs>). Even though it was made by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1027">Michael FitzGerald</rs>, Van Gogh could nevertheless have had this print in mind (perhaps in addition to the above-mentioned work by Holl). Indeed, in a later letter he compares this print to ‘the women reading the Bible by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let249.xml">letter 249</ref>), and he writes: ‘The woman I wrote to you about is, as a type, rather like the central figure in that print, namely the mother with her child on her arm’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let311.xml">letter 311</ref>). Because both Rembrandt’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1724"><hi rend="italics">Holy Family in the evening</hi></rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let037.xml">see letter 37</ref>) and FitzGerald’s engraving show the woman with the baby – in the centre of the print – sitting and not standing, and because Van Gogh speaks specifically of ‘the central figure’ (in Holl’s’ ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gone</hi>’ there can be no mistaking this figure), the print in question is most likely <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irish emigrants leaving Queenstown harbour</hi>. About a year later Van Gogh drew <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman with a baby on her lap</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_427">F 1066 / JH 322</rs>) who, like FitzGerald’s main figure, is a seated woman wearing a cap on her head (see cat. Otterlo 2003, p. 188).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1428">Frederick Walker</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old gate</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 13 (29 January 1876), Supplement, between pp. 102-103. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1908">Ill. 1908</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Francis Montague Holl</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The school board elections – A board school</hi> appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 14 (2 December 1876), pp. 544-545. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1909">Ill. 1909</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
      
<p>An engraving with the title ‘The invalids’ is not known. Van Gogh is very probably referring to one of the prints relating to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs>’s painting <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_486"><hi rend="italics">The last muster (Sunday at Chelsea hospital</hi> / <hi rend="italics">Chelsea pensioners)</hi></rs>, 1875 (Port Sunlight, Lady Lever Art Gallery). A print titled <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunday at Chelsea hospital</hi>, after a drawing which Herkomer later used for the painting, was published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 3 (18 February 1871), p. 152. There is an impression in Van Gogh's estate. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_171">Ill. 171</rs> (t*163). An engraving of a detail from the painting, depicting two men and titled<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> The last muster. Sunday at the Royal hospital, Chelsea</hi>, appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 11 (15 May 1875), Supplement, between pp. 480-481. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1910">Ill. 1910</rs> (cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let303.xml">letters 303</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let304.xml">304</ref>).</p>

<p rend="indent">It is also possible that Van Gogh is referring to Herkomer’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Rome – On the steps of St. Peter’s – ‘Per carità, signori’</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 5 (24 February 1872), p. 172, a copy of which is also to be found in the estate. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1911">Ill. 1911</rs> (t*575).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let172.xml">See letter 172</ref> for the Etten diggers and people in the potato field. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>A drawing with the motif of the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man putting potatoes in a sack </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_323">F - / JH 60</rs>), which Vincent had sent to Theo in October 1881 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let175.xml">letter 175</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>At The Hague artists’ society <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pulchri Studio</hi>, located in the ‘Hofje van Nieuwkoop’ on Prinsengracht, artists drew from dressed models. The society also organized art viewings and mounted exhibitions. At first there were two categories of membership: ‘working’ and ‘art-loving’; only the ‘working’ members were allowed to take part in life-drawing. The annual contribution was either 10 guilders or 5 guilders, depending on the type of membership. Later on the categories were expanded to include ‘special members’ and ‘outside members’. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> was a member of the board from 1878 to 1883. See S. de Bodt, ‘Pulchri Studio. Het imago van een kunstenaarsvereniging in de negentiende eeuw’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Negentiende Eeuw </hi>14 (1990), pp. 24-42, espec. 28-29; and Van Kalmthout 1998, pp. 336-342. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let202.xml#n-1">letter 202, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    