<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 25 February 1882. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let206"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b198 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>206</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>177</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>206</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-02-25">Saturday, 25 February 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0198" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0198" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000225_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Zaturdag.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Uw laatsten brief met ingesloten f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 100 is mij in orde geworden &amp; ik dank U van harte voor de toezending daarvan.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zou U reeds onmiddelijk berigt van de goede ontvangst hebben gezonden maar ik heb het zeer druk gehad met een paar teekeningen waar ik model voor had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Want gij moet wel weten dat als gij het druk hebt zulks met mij ook het geval is &amp; meer &amp; meer worden zal omdat ik meer oog op mijn werk krijg &amp; dus slechts met inspanning mij er uit losruk om te schrijven of den een of ander op te zoeken als het noodig is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Hetgeen mij verheugde was dat gij schrijft dat ge welligt reeds spoedig eens naar Holland komt.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wanneer gij nu weer eens zult gezien hebben ’t geen waar ik nu in den laatsten tijd aan bezig ben geweest dan kunnen we misschien nog wel meer helderheid krijgen omtrent de toekomst. Wanneer gij komt dan hoop ik dat wij eens rustig zamen op ’t atelier zullen zijn en ik hoop ook dat gij ’t mij vooruit zult schrijven omdat ik het dan met ’t model zoo schik dat ik dat niet neem gedurende de dagen van Uw bezoek.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Gij schrijft nog over Pa's verjaardag<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet U zeggen dat ik er mij zoo goed bij bevind van alles af te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> het is mij zoo'n rust die ik zoo noodig heb bij mijn werk, er kan niet meer in mijn hoofd dan er in kan. en nu zie ik er zoo zeer tegen op om eene nieuwe correspondentie te beginnen dat ik het voorloopig nog stil zoo laat.– Toen ik nog t'huis was bekommerde ik er mij over<c type="kk">/</c> nu ’t eenmaal zoover gekomen is<c type="kk">/</c> qu'y faire<c type="kp">_</c> Alles maar blaauw blaauw laten &amp; doen als of er niets gebeurd was – als Pa &amp; Moe dat kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan dat niet – ik voel dat er helaas wel wat gebeurd is.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Als ik aan Etten denk dan krijg ik een soort rilling over mijn lijf net als of ik in een kerk was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Enfin qu'y faire &amp; nog eens qu'y faire.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">à Propos, ge moet ’t me niet kwalijk nemen Theo of denken dat ik nu aan ’t vitten ga doch gij hebt mij iets geschreven dat ge misschien dacht dat mij pleizier zou doen &amp; het deed mij geen pleizier.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ge zegt dat die kleine aquarel<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> ’t beste is dat ge van me gezien hebt – nu dat is toch niet zoo want de studies die gij van mij hebt die zijn veel beter en de penteekeningen van dezen zomer zijn ook beter want dat teekeningetje beteekent niets<c type="kk">/</c> althans ik zond het U alleen om te toonen dat het geen onmogelijke affaire was dat ik met der tijd met waterverf zou werken. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Doch in die andere dingen zit veel meer serieuse studie &amp; meer degelijkheid ondanks dat zij er nog groenezeepachtig uitzien. En als ik iets tegen den Heer Tersteeg had (maar ik heb niets tegen hem) dan zou het datzelfde zijn. Dat hij n.l. mij encourageert niet op moeielijke studie naar model doch veeleer op een procedé dat eigentlijk maar half geschikt is om datgene wat ik volgens mijn eigen karakter en volgens mijn eigen temperament uit wil drukken<c type="kk">/</c> weer te geven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het spreekt van zelf dat ik erg blij zou zijn als ik een teekening verkocht doch het doet me nog meer pleizier als een waarachtig artist zooals Weissenbruch van een onverkoopbare (???) studie of teekening zegt<c type="kk">/</c> dat is trouw &amp; daar zou ik naar kunnen werken. Zie<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon het geld vooral nu veel waarde voor me heeft zoo blijft toch iets te maken wat raisonable is voor mij N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 1. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> iets dergelijks als wat Weissenbruch zei van een landschap<c type="kk">/</c> een plaggenveld<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> dat zei Mauve van een figuur<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. een oud boertje dat bij den haard zit te denken of te suffen als of hij dingen uit ver verleden zag opdokken in het schijnsel van het vuur of den rook.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het moge wat langer of wat korter duren maar de weg is toch diep indringen in de natuur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14"><hi rend="italics">Il reste à être vrai</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zegt Gavarni.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Men moge dan voor een tijd in pecuniaire petites miseres zijn<c type="kk">/</c> daar komt men bovenop en de teekeningen die vroeger geweigerd werden verkoopt men alsdan.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu heb ik eens aan C.M. geschreven om hem te vertellen dat ik hier een atelier genomen had &amp; hij heeft mij teruggeschreven dat hij binnen kort te s'Hage dacht te komen &amp; me dan eens zou opzoeken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik heb onlangs ook de groete gehad van mijn ouden vriend Wisselingh uit Londen<c type="kk">/</c> die zou ook eens komen &amp; het deed hem pleizier dat ik aan ’t werk was. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop dat het U maar lukken zal om er eens uit te breken want ik verlang erg naar U. Ik denk dat als gij nu de studies van dezen laatsten tijd zult gezien hebben<c type="kk">/</c> ge ’t wel heelemaal goed zult vinden dat ik geregeld model neem. Naarmate ik de modellen wat leer kennen kan ik ze natuurlijker<c type="shy">-</c>wijs beter teekenen. En ik heb het nog al goed getroffen om modellen te vinden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Vandaag<c type="kk">/</c> nu terwijl ik U zit te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik een kind dat eens een half uurtje uitrusten moet &amp; dat half uurtje gebruik ik voor dezen brief.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Nogmaals dank voor ’t gezondene en een handdruk in gedachten, à Dieu,</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">P.S. ik heb er nog twee studies van het kindje gemaakt van daag.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> het wordt nu donker. bonsoir.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Saturday.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I received your last letter with the 100 francs enclosed in good order, and I sincerely thank you for sending it.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’d have sent you news of its safe receipt immediately, but I’ve been very busy with a couple of drawings for which I had a model.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">For I’ll have you know that if you’re busy, so am I, and will be so more and more, because I’m getting more of an eye for my work, and so can tear myself away from it only with a great effort in order to write or to go and visit someone if necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">What made me happy was that you write that you may be coming to Holland soon.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> When you’ve seen what I’ve been doing recently, perhaps we’ll have a better idea of the future. When you come, I hope we’ll have some quiet time together in the studio, and I also hope that you’ll write to me in advance, so that I can arrange with the model not to come during the days of your visit.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">You write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s birthday, I must say that I feel so good to have done with everything, it’s such a tranquillity, which I need so much in my work, my head can’t hold more than it does. And now I dread starting up a new correspondence, so much so that I’m quietly leaving things as they are for the present. When I was still at home I worried about it, but now that things have come to this, what can one do? Ignore everything and pretend that nothing happened – <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> might be able to do that, but I can’t – I feel that, sadly, something did in fact happen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">When I think of Etten, a kind of shiver runs down my body as though I were in a church.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">In short, what can be done, and again, what can be done?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Besides, you mustn’t blame me, Theo, or think that I’m carping, but you wrote something to me which you perhaps thought would make me happy, but it didn’t make me happy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">You said that that small watercolour<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is the best thing of mine you’ve seen – well, that isn’t true, because those studies of mine you have are much better, and the pen drawings of last summer are also better, because that little drawing means nothing; anyhow, I only sent it to you to show that my working with watercolour at some point wasn’t an impossibility. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> But there’s much more serious study and more substance in those other things, despite the fact that they still look yellow-soap-like. And if I had something against <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> (but I don’t have anything against him), then it would be the same thing. Namely that he encourages me not to undertake difficult study from a model but rather to adopt a procedure that’s actually only half suited to the rendering of what I want to express, according to my own character and according to my own temperament.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It goes without saying that I’d be very happy to sell a drawing, but it makes me much happier if a true artist like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> says of an unsaleable (???) study or drawing, that’s faithful and I’d be able to work from that. You see, although I place great value on money, especially now, still, for me the No. 1 thing is to make something that’s reasonable. Well, something like what Weissenbruch said of a landscape, a peat moor,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> said it of a figure, namely an old peasant sitting by the fireplace, thinking or daydreaming, as though seeing things from the distant past taking shape in the glow of the fire or the smoke.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">It may take a longer or shorter time, but the way is really to penetrate deeply into nature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><hi rend="italics">To be true is what remains</hi>, says <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> One may be caught up for a time in petty pecuniary vexations, but one will surmount them, and the drawings that were rejected earlier will then be sold.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ve written to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> to tell him that I’d taken a studio here, and he wrote back saying that he expected to be coming to The Hague soon and would come and visit me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Recently I was also given regards from my old friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs> from London, who’s also supposed to come, and he was glad that I was working. Well, I hope you’ll succeed in escaping, because I’m longing to see you. I think that when you’ve seen my recent studies you’ll agree completely with my taking a model regularly. The better I get to know the models, the better I can draw them, of course. And I’ve been rather lucky in finding models.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Today, now as I’m writing to you, I have a child that has to rest once in a while for half an hour, and I’m using that half-hour for this letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Thanks again for what you sent, and a handshake in thought, adieu,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">P.S. I’ve made two studies of the child today.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> It’s getting dark now. Good-night.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed ‘Zaturdag’. In <ref target="let205.xml">letter 205</ref> of Saturday, 18 February Vincent strongly urged Theo to send some money. In the present letter, written on a Saturday, he thanks his brother for the money he sent. Several days must have gone by in the meantime <ref target="#l-69">(l. 69)</ref>, so this letter must date from Saturday, 25 February 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mr van Gogh’s 60th birthday on 8 February <ref target="let204.xml">(204)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo had last written on 18 February 1882 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let208.xml">see letter 208</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo did not in fact travel to the Netherlands until August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let253.xml">see letter 253</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This must be the small watercolour Vincent sent to Theo with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let203.xml">letter 203</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>It is not clear which drawing this refers to. Cf. in this context the watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Barren field</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_742">F 904 / JH 98</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man sitting by the fireplace (‘Worn out’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2345">F 863 / JH 34</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This pronouncement occurs in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Edmond and Jules de Goncourt</rs>’s biography of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>. See Goncourt 1873, p. 67. Gavarni’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_237"><hi rend="italics">La mascarade humaine</hi></ref> likewise contains the words: ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">To be true is what remains.</hi> In six words, it is the fullest and widest of professions of faith. A few days later, Gavarni wrote this other sentence: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">It is from life that we must paint everything</hi>’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Il reste à être vrai</hi>. C’est en cinq mots la plus complète et la plus large des professions de foi. Gavarni, quelques jours après, écrit cette autre phrase: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">C’est d’après la nature qui faut tout peindre</hi>’). Gavarni 1881, p. 6. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let302.xml">letter 302</ref> Van Gogh says that he owns this book.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The only two known drawings from this period in which a child is depicted are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl standing, knitting</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2356">F 983 / JH 107</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl sitting, knitting</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2357">F 984 / JH 108</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    