<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh, The Hague, between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let209"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b196 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>209</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>175</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>204</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-03-06">between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0196" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0196" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000223_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dezen morgen nog toen ik U schreef<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> was ik in twijfelmoedigheid over iets wat mij fameus hinderde<c type="kk">/</c> waaromtrent ik voorloopig gerustgesteld ben. Ik kan U een slecht nieuws vertellen<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat Mauve eigentlijk weer zeer onwel is – natuurlijk het gewone.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Doch ook een goed nieuws<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik de verzekering heb dat het aan zijn ziekte te wijten is dat hij in den laatsten tijd mij zeer onvriendelijk heeft behandeld, en niet daaraan dat het met mijn werk den verkeerden weg opgaan zou.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Reeds schreef ik U in een vorigen brief dat ik een bezoek van Weissenbruch had gehad. Weissenbruch is op ’t moment zoowat de eenige die nog bij Mauve toegelaten wordt &amp; ik dacht dat ik hem eens moest gaan spreken. Toen ben ik heden op zijn atelier geweest op de U bekende zolder.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En zoodra hij mij zag begon hij te lagchen en zei<c type="kk">/</c> ge komt zeker eens hooren naar Mauve, zoodat hij dadelijk wist waarom ik kwam &amp; ik hem geen explicatie behoefde te geven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Hij deelde mij toen mede dat zijn bezoek bij mij eigentlijk tot oorzaak had dat Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> die omtrent mij in twijfeling was<c type="kk">/</c> hem er eens op afgezonden had om de opinie van Weissenbruch omtrent mijn werk te hebben.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En Weissenbruch heeft toen tot Mauve gezegd “hij teekent verdomd goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou naar zijn studies kunnen werken”.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En<c type="kk">/</c> voegde hij er bij<c type="kk">/</c> ze noemen mij het zwaard zonder genade en dat ben ik ook en ik zou ’t niet tegen Mauve gezegd hebben als ik geen goeds gevonden had in je studies.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik heb nu permissie om zoolang Mauve ziek is of het overdruk heeft met zijn groote sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi><c type="kk">/</c> bij Weissenbruch te komen als ik iets weten moet en W. heeft mij gezegd dat ik mij in geen enkel opzigt omtrent de verandering van stemming van M. moet ongerust maken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik heb toen ook aan W. gevraagd wat hij van mijn penteekeningen dacht. Dat zijn je besten zei hij<c type="kp">_</c> En ik ver<c type="shy">-</c>telde hem dat Tersteeg er me een standje over gemaakt had. Trek het je niet aan zei hij<c type="kk">/</c> toen Mauve zei dat er een schilder in je stak zei Tersteeg van neen<c type="kk">/</c> en Mauve heeft toen tegen Tersteeg je partij getrokken en ik was daarbij tegenwoordig en als ’t weer voorkomt zal ik<c type="kk">/</c> nu ik je werk gezien heb<c type="kk">/</c> zelf ook partij voor je trekken.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Dat “partij trekken” is niet wat ik begeer<c type="kk">/</c> alleen moet ik zeggen dat het mij soms ondragelijk is als Tersteeg altijd en eeuwig weer tot mij zegt “gij moet er onderdehand eens aan beginnen te denken dat ge Uw brood moet verdienen”<c type="kp">_</c> Dat vind ik zoo’n afschuwelijke uitdrukking dat het mij moeite kost om mij dan goed te houden. Ik werk wat ik kan en spaar mij zelven niet dus ik ben mijn brood waard en men moet mij er geen verwijt van maken als ik tot nog toe niet heb kunnen verkoopen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Gij hebt nu deze details omdat ik mij niet kan begrijpen waarom gij in deze maand mij noch geschreven hebt noch ook iets gestuurd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Mogelijk acht ik het dat gij misschien van Tersteeg een of ander gehoord hadt dat U weer overdonderde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ontvang nogmaals de verzekering dat ik er op werk om te vorderen met dingen die gemakkelijker te verkoopen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. aquarellen, maar dat kan niet op eens vlotten. Lukt het mij gaandeweg dan is het al spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> in aanmerking genomen den korten tijd dat ik bezig ben. Doch op staanden voet zal het mij niet lukken nog. Zoodra Mauve weer beter is en weer eens bij me komt of ik bij hem<c type="kk">/</c> zal hij mij nog wel eens weer op nieuw 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>nuttige dingen zeggen naar aanleiding van studies die ik ondertusschen maak.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">In den laatsten tijd heb ik bitter weinig aan Mauve gehad en hij heeft mij ook zelf eens gezegd: ik ben niet altijd gestemd om ’t je te wijzen<c type="kp">_</c> Soms ben ik zoo moe en dan moet je in godsnaam maar een beter moment afwachten.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik acht het een groot voorregt nu en dan eens bij zulke knappe lui als W. te komen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral als zij zoo als W. dezen morgen b.v<c type="kp">_</c> de moeite nemen om een teekening waar ze aan bezig zijn doch die nog niet af is<c type="kk">/</c> voor den dag te halen<c type="kk">/</c> en uitleggen hoe zij die aanzetten. Dat is ’t wat ik hebben moet. Als gij in de gelegenheid zijt om te zien schilderen of teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> let daar dan op want ik geloof dat menig kunstkooper anders over veel schilderijen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> zou gaan denken als hij goed wist hoe zij gemaakt waren. Het is wel waar dat men het bij instinkt wel eenigermate begrijpen kan doch dit weet ik wel<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik meer helderheid omtrent verscheiden dingen gekregen heb juist door het zien werken en door zelf ook wat te beproeven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik zou nog wel erg graag bij gelegenheid wat van dat papier Ingres hebben<c type="kk">/</c> het wordt misschien spoedig geschikt weer om buiten te zitten en dan zou het mij van veel nut zijn. Ik begin zuinig te worden op mijn studies en wou die bij U zijn wel terug hebben<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">à Dieu kerel, ontvang een handdruk in gedachten, arme Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> hij zal niet beter zijn voor zijn groote Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> klaar is en dan daarna uitgeput zijn.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">This morning when I wrote to you<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I was in two minds about something that has been a great source of worry to me, though for the moment my mind is at rest on that score. I have a bit of bad news to tell you, namely that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is in fact very ill again – the usual, of course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">But there’s also a bit of good news: I can rest assured that it’s due to his illness that he’s been so unfriendly to me recently, and not because my work was going in the wrong direction.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I already wrote to you in a previous letter that I’d had a visit from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs>. At the moment Weissenbruch is practically the only one who’s allowed to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, and I thought I should go and talk with him. So I went today to his studio in the attic you’re familiar with.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And as soon as he saw me he began to laugh, and said, you’ve surely come to hear about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, so he knew instantly why I’d come and I didn’t have to give him an explanation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">He then told me that the cause of his visit to me had actually been <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, who was doubtful about me and had sent him to see me to have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs>’s opinion about my work. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> then said to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, ‘he draws damned well, I’d be able to work from his studies’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And, he added, they call me the merciless sword and that I certainly am, and I wouldn’t have said that to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> if I’d found nothing good in your studies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I now have permission, so long as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is ill or too busy with his large painting, to go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> if I need to know something, and W. told me that in no way should I be worried about the change in M.’s mood.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I also asked <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">W.</rs> what he thought of my pen drawings. Those are your best, he said. And I told him that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> had criticized them. Take no notice of it, he said, when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> said there was a painter in you, Tersteeg said no, and Mauve took your side against Tersteeg, and I was there, and if it happens again, I too will take your side, now that I’ve seen your work. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">That ‘taking sides’ isn't what I want, though I must say that it’s sometimes unbearable to have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> forever saying to me ‘you should start thinking about earning your bread’. I find that such a loathsome expression that I have trouble keeping my temper. I work as hard as I can and don’t spare myself, so I’m worth my bread, and people shouldn’t reproach me if I haven’t yet been able to sell anything.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You now have these particulars because I can’t understand why you’ve neither written nor sent anything this month.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I think it possible that you may have heard something from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> that puzzled you again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Rest assured, yet again, that I’m trying to make headway with things that are easier to sell, namely watercolours, but it can’t happen overnight. If I gradually succeed then it will have been quickly, considering the short time I’ve been working at it. But I won’t succeed at it instantly. As soon as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is better and comes to see me again or I go to him, he’ll again tell me 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> useful things about the studies I’ve made in the meantime.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ve had very little help from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> recently, and he once said: I don’t always feel like showing you. Sometimes I’m so tired, and then, for God’s sake, you’ll just have to wait for a more opportune moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I consider it a great privilege to visit such clever people as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">W.</rs> once in a while, especially when they take the trouble – as W. did this morning, for instance – to take a drawing they’re working on but haven’t finished yet and to explain how they set about doing it. That’s what I need. If you’re in a position to see someone painting or drawing, pay attention, because I believe that many an art dealer would think differently about many paintings &amp;c. if he rightly knew how they were made. It’s true that one can understand it instinctively to some extent, but of this I’m certain, that I acquired a better understanding of various things precisely by seeing someone at work and by experimenting a little myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’d very much like to have some of that Ingres paper sometime. Soon the weather might be good enough to sit outdoors, and then it would be very useful to me. I’m beginning to be miserly with my studies and should like to have back the ones you’ve got.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Adieu, old chap, accept a handshake in thought, poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, he won’t be better before his large painting is finished and afterwards he’ll be exhausted.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">It was previously assumed that this letter was written after <ref target="let204.xml">letter 204</ref> but on the same day, 13 February. There are, however, a number of things that argue against this date. First of all, the letter that preceded the present letter must have been written in the morning (cf. <ref target="#l-3">l. 3</ref>). <ref target="let204.xml">Letter 204</ref>, however, was written in the afternoon or evening of 13 February, because it contains the information that De Bock had visited Van Gogh ‘this afternoon’ <ref target="#l-85">(l. 85)</ref>. Secondly, Van Gogh says that he mentioned Weissenbruch’s visit in ‘a’ previous letter <ref target="#l-14">(ll. 14-15)</ref>; if that had been <ref target="let204.xml">letter 204</ref> written that same morning, it would have been more logical for Van Gogh to refer to it as ‘the’ previous letter. Finally, the opening of the letter refers to a tense situation of which there is no trace in <ref target="let204.xml">letter 204</ref>.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">It is therefore more reasonable to view this letter as the continuation of <ref target="let208.xml">letter 208</ref>. The subjects discussed would then concur: Mauve puts the finishing touches on his large canvas <ref target="#l-40">(l. 40)</ref>; Theo has not yet written that month (March), so Vincent has not yet received any money <ref target="#l-73">(ll. 73-74)</ref>; Tersteeg criticizes Van Gogh’s pen drawings; and the striking word ‘twijfelmoedigheid’ (here translated as being ‘in two minds’) <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref> is used again in <ref target="let210.xml#l-79">letter 210 (l. 79)</ref>, which follows this letter in any case. Finally, this is the only way to explain the multiple ‘letters’ that Theo is presumed to have received when Vincent sits down to write <ref target="let211.xml#l-2">letter 211 (l. 2)</ref>.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">Since the letter therefore appears to have been written on the same day as <ref target="let208.xml">letter 208</ref>, we have given it the same date: between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mauve’s <hi rend="italics">Fishing boat on the beach</hi> for the Salon <ref target="let194.xml">(194)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let208.xml">letter 208</ref>; see also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> had a studio at Haagse Kazernestraat 112, the house he was born in (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let125.xml">see letter 125</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>It is not known which sketches and drawings Theo had meanwhile received (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let173.xml">letters 173</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let175.xml">175</ref>). One of them was a drawing with the motif seen in the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man putting potatoes in a sack </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_323">F - / JH 60</rs>), which Vincent had sent to Theo in October 1881 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let175.xml">letters 175</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let199.xml">199</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    