<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Sunday, 2 April 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let214"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b205 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>214</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>184</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>213</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-04-02">on or about Sunday, 2 April 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0205" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0205" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000235_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">verscheiden keeren reeds heb ik er mij toe gezet om U te schrijven doch ik kon er niet toe komen om den brief af te maken. En wel om reden dat ik U schrijven wilde nog verscheiden dingen waarom ik dacht dat het schilder worden van U zoo voor de hand lag.– Maar wat ik schreef beviel me niet en ik kon geen woorden vinden krachtig genoeg.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Uw bezwaren bestaan wel degelijk doch daartegenover staan veel andere dingen die er wel tegen opwegen.– Op Uw 30<hi rend="super">ste</hi> jaar kunt gij het zoo ver gebragt hebben dat de lui U als schilder respecteeren moeten &amp; rekening houden met Uw werk.– En op Uw 30<hi rend="super">ste</hi> jaar zijt ge nog jong. Door ’t geen gij geleerd hebt bij Goupil<c type="kk">/</c> door Uw kennis van veel zaken hebt gij juist iets wat U in staat stelt velen die “<hi rend="italics">vroeg begonnen zijn</hi>” in te halen. Want die vroege beginners hebben menigmaal een periode van jaren lang onvruchtbaar op één zelfde hoogte blijven en die periode hoeft iemand die energiek op later leeftijd begint niet door. Schilderen is even goed een vak waar men genoeg geld mee verdient om van te leven als b.v. Smid of dokter. Een artist is in elk geval lijnregt ’t tegenovergestelde van een rentenier en zooals ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> wil men paralel trekken dan heeft ’t zij een smid ’t zij een dokter meer overeenkomst.– Zeer wel herinner ik mij nu ge erover schrijft dat toen gij in der tijd er mij over gesproken hebt dat ik schilder zou worden<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> ik dacht dat het zeer ontoepasselijk was en er niet van hooren wilde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">’t Geen mij heeft doen ophouden te twijfelen is dat ik een begrijpelijk boek over perspectief las<c type="kk">/</c> Cassagne<c type="kk">/</c> Guide de l’Abc du dessin<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en 8 dagen daarna een interieur teekende van een keukentje met kagchel<c type="kk">/</c> stoel en tafel &amp; venster op hun plaats en op hun pooten terwijl vroeger ’t mij bepaald hekserij of toevalligheid scheen dat men <hi rend="italics">diepte</hi> &amp; juiste perspectief in een teekening had. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Als gij maar één ding geteekend hadt zooals ’t behoort dan zou de lust onweerstaanbaar zijn om nog 1000 andere dingen te attaqueeren. Doch dat ééne schaap dat over de brug moet om het er over te krijgen.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> Als een schilder U eens bij den arm pakte en zei<c type="kk">/</c> Kijk Theo<c type="kk">/</c> zóó moet ge dien akker teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> zóó loopen de lijnen van de voren<c type="kk">/</c> hierom en daarom loopen ze zóó en niet anders en moeten ze zoo in perspectief gebragt worden. En die knotwilg zoo groot zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> is die andere verder op daartegen zóó klein en dat verschil in grootte kunt ge zus en zoo meten en – kijk! als je dat op je papier dondert dan zijn die groote lijnen seffens<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> juist en hebt ge vasten grond onder de voeten waarop ge nu voortwerken kunt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Zoo’n gesprek<c type="kk">/</c> mits met de praktijk der zaak er bij<c type="kk">/</c> zou toepasselijker zijn in de gegevenen dan veel redenaties over ’t zij abstracte ’t zij finantieele dingen. En ik zal mij dus niet in dat vaarwater verder begeven doch gij staat net op ’t randje om den een of anderen dag licht te krijgen in de praktijk – en overkomt het U dat gij iets met juistheid teekent of kortom dat gij de perspectief der dingen leert zien dan is ’t met Uw kunsthandelaarsschap gedaan en dan voelt gij net als Correggio: ik ben ook een schilder<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en dan ziet ge meteen dat ge U in Uw element bevint en dan – dan – zijt ge jonger en levenslustiger dan ooit te voren<c type="kk">/</c> dan begint de tweede jeugd die beter is dan de eerste want die tweede vergaat niet meer<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Goddank – vergaat niet als de andere. Maar de eerste jeugd – is weg voor mij en – en – begint weg te gaan voor U<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wat betreft opvoeding van Cor of brood voor Moe – Die twee dingen zullen niet ontbreken<c type="kk">/</c> ook niet als gij schilder wordt. En wat U zelven betreft. Uw eten<c type="kk">/</c> drinken<c type="kk">/</c> slapen<c type="kk">/</c> Uw atelier<c type="kk">/</c> Uw model – ..... zij zijn niet ver van U af – als het wakker mogt worden in U<c type="kk">/</c> die gedachte aan het schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> dan zoudt gij zien dat het gedaan kan worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Evenwel opdat gij mij niet verdenken zoudt van ’t finantieele over ’t hoofd te zien zoo zou ik wel willen zeggen – echter met alle respect voor Uwe tegenwoordige betrekking als handelaar: tenzij men een bepaald handwerk hebbe en iets maken kan met eigen handen betwijfel ik de soliditeit van het middel van bestaan.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Zoodat ik b.v. de maatschappelijke positie van Jaap Maris solider en onafhankelijker vind dan die van H.G.T. Voor denkkracht en intelligentie heb ik veel respect<c type="kk">/</c> ontbreken die dan gaat men ondanks zijn handwerk ten gronde omdat men niet wederstaan kan en zijn eigen werk verdedigen – dat ziet ge aan Thijs Maris. Doch juist op menschen die denkkracht en intelligentie bezitten<c type="kk">/</c> en ’t spreekt van zelf ik U daar onder reken en ik wou er me zelf ook wel bij rekenen<c type="kk">/</c> is het toepasselijk dat zij bij uitnemendheid voor handwerk geschikt zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik resumeer. Als gij het schilderen aanpakt dan zal het U gelukken en tegen Uw 30<hi rend="super">ste</hi> jaar zijt ge als schilder er boven op<c type="kk">/</c> niet minder in eenig opzigt dan nu op ’t moment. Een mediocreteit in den slechten zin van ’t woord komt er gedecideerd niet van U als gij aan ’t schilderen gaat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Er zijn omtrent het schilderen twee redeneerwijzen<c type="kk">/</c> how <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to do it<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en <hi>how to do it</hi><c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">how to do it</hi>: – met veel teekening en weinig kleur. how not to do it: met veel kleur en weinig teekening.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu zie ik kans om zeer goed rond te komen als gij deze maand het zoo schikken kunt als gij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat ge mij omstreeks de helft nog frs. 100 geeft voor tot ’t begin van Mei. Van de nu gezondene frs 100 heb ik Tersteeg nog niet kunnen betalen<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – ik heb heel wat uitgaven – en ik kon b.v. niet langer wachten met mij een pantalon aan te schaffen en de huishuur. Tegen ’t midden van April als gij weer zend dan <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ik ze hem terug geven en zal het doen als gij het bepaald wilt. Liever echter maakte ik er over een tijd een teekening voor. Zoo moet het met mij gaan<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet geen contanten terug geven aan <hi rend="italics">handelaars</hi>. De schuld aan U is een ander geval. Wij weten niet hoe de dingen loopen zullen<c type="kp">_</c> Als gij kunsthandelaar blijft dan krijgt ge er met der tijd teekeningen en schilderijen voor – als gij schilder wordt dan in geld en dan met pleizier rente er bij.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wat betreft het geld aan Tersteeg<c type="kk">/</c> toen ik hier pas kwam waren hij en Mauve zoo vriendelijk en zeiden ik hoefde volstrekt me niet bezorgd te maken – doch in minder dan één maand draaiden ze om en spraken heel anders.– misschien denkende dat ik in elkaar zou zinken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dat griefde mij eerst – en toen later liet het mij tamelijk koel en ik dacht<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal er me niet verdrietig meer over maken.</p>
    
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Breitner ligt in ’t gasthuis<c type="kk">/</c> ik bezoek hem nog al eens om hem ’t zij boeken ’t zij teekengerij te brengen.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> C.M. heeft me betaald, en een nieuwe bestelling doch die moeielijk genoeg is<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">6 uitvoerige bepaalde stads</hi>gezigten.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Evenwel ik zal ze zien te maken omdat ik voor de 6 als ik wel begrijp, zoo veel krijg als voor de 12 eersten. En dan misschien nog schetsen Amsterdam<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Blommers is bij me geweest om te spreken over kunst<c type="shy">-</c>beschouwing houtsneden.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Heeft 3 uur lang ze zitten te bekijken en was boos van wege ’t bestuur Pulchri gemopperd had omtrent “van die dingen die wel eens in ’t zuid-Hollandsch Koffijhuis lagen.”<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Als dat alles is wat ze van de houtgravure weten dan zijn ze wel competent om te veroordeelen! Evenwel bestuur Pulchri had bezwaar gemaakt. Blommers wilde evenwel doorzetten en heeft me gezegd ik ze voor den volgenden Zaturdag moet klaar houden. Het is zeer curieus om sommige schilders hier te hooren redeneeren over wat zij noemen “illustrateurs”<c type="kk">/</c> over Gavarni b.v. of Herkomer!! Dàt NIET op de hoogte zijn van de zaak maakt bij sommigen een deel uit van wat zij hun “<hi rend="italics">algemeene ontwikkeling</hi>” noemen<c type="kp">_</c> Geluk er mee<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ontvang mijn dank voor een heerlijk pak Papier Ingres en voor de studies<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Op een goeden dag dat de lui zullen beginnen te zeggen dat ik wel iets teekenen maar niet schilderen kan dan kom ik misschien eens met een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> voor den dag op ’t moment dat zij het niet verwachten maar zoolang het een air heeft als zou ik het <hi rend="italics">moeten</hi> doen en als <hi rend="italics">mogt ik niet</hi> iets anders, dan doe ik het zeker niet.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve set about writing to you several times, but I couldn’t bring myself to finish the letter, because I wanted to write to you about various reasons why I thought it such a natural thing for you to become a painter. But I didn’t like what I’d written, and I couldn’t find any words that were strong enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Your objections are indeed serious, but on the other hand there are a great many things that weigh against them. By your 30th year you could have progressed to the extent that people must respect you as a painter and take your work seriously. And in your 30th year you’ll still be young. What you’ve learned at Goupil, your knowledge of many things, means that you have exactly what it takes to catch up with many who ‘<hi rend="italics">started early</hi>’. Because those early starters often have a period of staying at the same level fruitlessly for years, and that period isn’t necessary for someone who starts energetically at a later age. Painting is just as good a profession by which to earn a living as, for example, smith or doctor. An artist, in any case, is the exact opposite of someone living a life of leisure, and as I said, if one wants to draw a parallel, then either a smith or a doctor corresponds more closely. Now that you write about it, I remember very well that when you spoke to me back then about my becoming a painter,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I thought it very inappropriate and wouldn’t hear of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">What made me stop doubting is that I read a clearly written book on perspective, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_922">Cassagne</rs>, Guide de l’Abc du dessin,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and a week later drew an interior of a little kitchen, with stove, chair and table and window in their place and on their legs, whereas it used to seem to me downright witchcraft or coincidence that one had <hi rend="italics">depth</hi> and proper perspective in a drawing. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> If you drew just one thing as it should be drawn, the desire to attack 1,000 other things would be irresistible. But the most difficult part is taking that first step. If a painter took you by the arm and said: Look, Theo, <hi rend="italics">this</hi> is how you should draw that field, <hi rend="italics">this</hi> is how the lines of the furrows run, for this reason or that they run like <hi rend="italics">this</hi> and not otherwise, and must be brought into perspective like this. And that pollard willow being this big, the other one further on is by contrast <hi rend="italics">that </hi>small, and that difference in size can be measured this way or that and – look! if you fling that down on paper then the broad outlines are immediately correct, and you have firm ground beneath your feet on which to continue.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Such a talk, provided it’s accompanied by practice, would be more appropriate in the circumstances than a lot of discussion about either abstract or financial matters. And so I won’t venture further into that territory, but you’re on the verge of getting an idea of the practice one day soon – and if you should happen to draw something correctly or, in short, if you learn to see things in perspective, then your art dealership has had it, and you’ll feel, just like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_961">Correggio</rs>: I, too, am a painter,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and then you’ll see immediately that you’re in your element and then – then – you’ll be younger and more full of life than ever before, then your second youth will begin, which is better than the first, because the second never ends, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> thank God – doesn’t end like the other one. But the first youth – has left me and – and – is beginning to leave you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">As regards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>’s education and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s bread – those two things won’t be lacking, not even if you become a painter. And as far as you’re concerned, your food, drink, sleep, your studio, your model – ..... they aren’t far off – and if the idea to paint should awaken in you, you’d see that it could be done.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Nevertheless, so that you won’t suspect me of overlooking the financial side, I’d just like to say – yet with all due respect for your present position as an art dealer: unless one has a certain handicraft and can make something with his own hands, I doubt the soundness of the means of subsistence.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Meaning that I consider the social position of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jaap Maris</rs>, for example, more solid and independent than that of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> – I have a lot of respect for intellect and intelligence, if those are lacking then one comes to nought in spite of one’s handicraft, because one can’t stand up and defend one’s own work – you see this in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs>. But it’s precisely those people who have the intellect and intelligence, and it goes without saying that I count you among them and I’d like to count myself among them too, it’s fitting that they’re eminently suited to handiwork.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I repeat: if you take up painting you’ll succeed and, by your 30th year, you as a painter will have worked your way up, no less so in any respect than at present. A mediocrity in the bad sense of the word will certainly not be the case with you if you take up painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">As regards painting, there are two lines of reasoning, how <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to do it<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and <hi>how to do it</hi>. <hi rend="italics">How to do it</hi>: with much drawing and little colour. How not to do it: with much colour and little drawing. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Now I see the opportunity to manage very well if you can arrange it this month as you said, namely that around the 15th you give me another 100 francs to last until the beginning of May. From the 100 francs just sent I haven’t yet been able to pay <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – I have a lot of expenses – and I could wait no longer to buy a pair of trousers and pay the rent, for example. If you send some again around the middle of April, then I <hi rend="italics">could</hi> pay him back, and will do so if you really wish it. Though I’d rather pay it back later with a drawing. That’s what I ought to be doing, I mustn’t give any cash back to <hi rend="italics">dealers</hi>. My debt to you is something else. We don’t know how things will turn out. If you carry on as an art dealer, then in time you’ll be getting drawings and paintings for it – if you become a painter, then money, and gladly with interest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Regarding the money owed to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>, when I first came here, he and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> were so friendly and said I didn’t have to worry at all – but in less than a month they’d turned around and were talking completely differently. Perhaps thinking that I’d collapse.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">At first that grieved me – and then later it left me rather cold and I thought, I won’t let it upset me any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs>’s in hospital, I visit him quite often to bring him books or drawing materials.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> paid me, and a new order, but difficult enough, <hi rend="italics">6 detailed, specific, town</hi>scapes.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I’ll see that I make them in any case, because if I understand correctly I’ll get for these 6 as much as for the first 12. And then perhaps sketches of Amsterdam.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs> was here to talk about a viewing of the woodcuts.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Sat here looking at them for 3 hours, and was angry because Pulchri’s board had complained about ‘those things one sees now and then in the Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> If that’s all they know about wood engraving they’re indeed competent to condemn! Still, Pulchri’s board had complained. Blommers wanted to go ahead with it anyway, and told me to have them ready for next Saturday. It’s very strange to hear some painters here discussing what they call ‘illustrators’, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>, for instance, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>!! This NOT keeping abreast of things is part of what some of them call their ‘<hi rend="italics">general education</hi>’. Good luck to them!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Now, with a handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Accept my thanks for a wonderful box of Ingres paper and for the studies.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">One fine day when people start to say that I can in fact draw but not paint, perhaps I’ll appear with a painting just when they least expect it, but as long as it looks as though I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> do it and <hi rend="italics">may not</hi> do anything else, then I certainly won’t do it.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This is the first of a series of eight letters which Vincent sent to Theo in April 1882. They are all undated, but it is certain that the last one (<ref target="let221.xml">letter 221</ref>) was written at the latest on 27 April (see <hi rend="italics">Date</hi> of that letter).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The chronology of the letters can be determined on the basis of their contents, our reasons being given in the <hi rend="italics">Date</hi> for each letter. At the beginning of the month it is financial matters which help to establish the chronological order, whereas in the second half of the month it is the weather conditions and Vincent’s state of mind which yield the most clues.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">On 11 March Vincent received 100 francs (<ref target="let211.xml">letter 211</ref>), 10 guilders (20 francs) of which he owed to Tersteeg. Later in the month (<ref target="let212.xml">letters 212</ref> and <ref target="let212.xml">212</ref>) he again asks Theo for money. When it is not forthcoming, he again borrows money from Tersteeg, this time 25 guilders. Theo came to know of this (<ref target="let214.xml">see letters 214</ref> and <ref target="let215.xml">215</ref>), which explains why he sent 100 francs at the beginning of April (<ref target="let214.xml">letter 214</ref>) and again, later that month, the large sum of 150 francs, because Vincent had still not paid off his debt to Tersteeg (<ref target="let217.xml">letter 217</ref>).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The fact that Vincent’s letter-writing proceeded apace as the month wore on is attributable in part to the bad weather, which hindered him in his work, and in part to his need to blow off steam in an attempt to raise his low spirits, caused by Mauve and Tersteeg’s negative attitude towards him (<ref target="let218.xml">letters 218</ref>-<ref target="let220.xml">220</ref>).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">It is impossible to date these letters precisely, so we have distributed them evenly over the month, providing them with a more exact time frame when allowed to do so by certain details (e.g. the weather conditions mentioned in <ref target="let215.xml">letters 215</ref>, <ref target="let218.xml">218</ref>, <ref target="let219.xml">219</ref> and <ref target="let222.xml">222</ref>. This strategy has yielded the following dates: on or about 2 April (<ref target="let214.xml">214</ref>), on or about 6 April (<ref target="let215.xml">215</ref>), on or about 10 April (<ref target="let216.xml">216</ref>), on or about 14 April (<ref target="let217.xml">217</ref>), 18 or 19 April (<ref target="let218.xml">218</ref>), on or about 21 April (<ref target="let219.xml">219</ref>), on or about 23 April (<ref target="let220.xml">220</ref>) and on or about 26 April (<ref target="let221.xml">221</ref>); the weather conditions mentioned do not contradict these dates).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The present letter must date from the very beginning of April, as suggested by <ref target="#l-117">ll. 117-125</ref>, which undoubtedly refer to the allowance for the first half of April, mentioned here for the first time.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent tries to persuade Theo to become a painter <ref target="let211.xml">(211)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Uncle Cor’s first order for drawings <ref target="let210.xml">(210)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Strained relations with Mauve and Tersteeg (<ref target="let209.xml">209</ref> and <ref target="let208.xml">208</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Request for Ingres paper <ref target="let209.xml">(209)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This reveals that in 1880 Theo had suggested that Vincent become an artist, which goes a long way towards explaining why Theo must have felt it his duty to continue to offer his brother both moral and financial support. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 14. Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let363.xml">letters 363</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let401.xml">401</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is most likely referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_922">Armand Théophile Cassagne</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_204"><hi rend="italics">Guide de l’alphabet du dessin</hi></ref> (1880), which he had possibly received as early as September 1880 in Cuesmes (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let158.xml">letter 158</ref>). See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 18-21 and cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let640.xml#n-14">letter 640, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>A Dutch saying.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘meteen’ (immediately, at once).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>A reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_961">Correggio</rs>’s famous utterance: ‘anch’io sono pittore’ (I, too, am a painter), his response to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs>’s assertion that he would never become a great painter. See Giuseppe Fumagalli, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Chi l’ha detto? Tesoro di citazioni</hi>. Milano 1921, pp. 244-245, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Geflügelte Worte</hi> 1961, pp. 606-607.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
<p>For the expression ‘How (not) to do it’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let179.xml#n-3">see letter 179, n. 3.</ref></p>

                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
<p>Although Van Gogh had previously declared his intention not to see <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> for the time being (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let208.xml">see letter 208</ref>), he must meanwhile have borrowed 25 guilders from him (see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let215.xml">letter 215</ref>). Evidently Theo knew about this.</p>

                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>From 21 March to 17 June 1882 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">George Breitner</rs> was a patient at the Gemeentelijk Ziekenhuis (Municipal Hospital), the Burgergasthuis, situated on Zuidwal and Brouwersgracht in The Hague, where he was being treated for gonorrhoea. Some time before 28 March 1882 Van Gogh visited him there and took along a copy of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11"><hi rend="italics">L’amour</hi></ref> to give him. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brieven Breitner </hi>1970, pp. 30, 72, and Hefting 1970, p. 48.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh worked from early April to early June on this new series of townscapes for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>. The letter in which he says he has sent them (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">see letter 235</ref>, with indications of their measurements) mentions a total of seven drawings. The series included the following works (the first five are also named in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let232.xml">letter 232</ref>): 1. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sien’s mother’s house</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2373">F 941/ JH 146</rs>), medium-sized, 29 x 45 cm; 2. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sien’s mother’s house </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2374">F 942 / JH 147</rs>), large, 46 x 59.5 cm; 3. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Nursery on Schenkweg</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2369">F 930 / JH 138</rs>), large, 29.5 x 58.5 cm; 4. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2375">F 939 / JH 150</rs>), medium-sized, 28.5 x 47 cm; 5. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fish-drying barn </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3032">F 938 / JH 152</rs>), 28 x 44 cm; 6. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3014">F 946a / JH 151</rs>), 27.5 x 46.5 cm; 7. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Nursery on Schenkweg</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3015">F 923 / JH 125</rs>), small, 23.5 x 33 cm. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 172-177.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The plan for Van Gogh to show his woodcuts at Pulchri had been proposed by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs> shortly before this (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let213.xml">see letter 213</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>‘Het Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’ (The South-Holland Coffee House) – popularly known as ‘Het Zuid’ – had opened in 1882 at Haagse Groenmarkt 37. It featured a reading table and was an important meeting place for The Hague’s painters and poets. See [R.L. de Haes], ‘Van Haagsche Koffiehuizen (eenige historische gegevens) met dertien afbeeldingen’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Die Haghe. Bijdragen en mededeelingen</hi>. The Hague 1906, pp. 377-463, espec. 407-415; and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Geïllustreerde gids voor ’s-Gravenhage</hi>. 2nd ed. The Hague 1894, pp. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xvii</hi>, 21; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboeken</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">1882-1883</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This suggests that Theo had returned some of Vincent’s studies to him, as requested – and sent along some Ingres paper – on 13 February (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let209.xml">see letter 209</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    