<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 1 May 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let222"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b217 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>222</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>195</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>221</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-05-01">Monday, 1 May 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0217 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0217 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000253_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0217 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000254_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000254_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0217 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000254_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000254_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief met ingesloten frs 100 heb ik ont<c type="shy">-</c>vangen &amp; dank er U ten zeerste voor. Uw brief heeft mij meer licht gegeven dan al mijn hoofdbreken &amp; tobben over die kwestie Mauve &amp; HGT. Ik maak er U mijn compliment over want nu geloof ik<c type="kk">/</c> ik het beter begrijp. En wat mij te doen staat is<c type="kk">/</c> als ik wel heb<c type="kk">/</c> bedaard voortwerken zonder er mij in te verdiepen of het mij zoo erg aan te trekken als ik deed. Als ik mij daarin verdiep dan heb ik ’t zelfde gevoel van duizeling hetwelk<c type="kk">/</c> zegt gij<c type="kk">/</c> iemand die de perspectief niet bestudeerd heeft gevoelt wanneer hij het wegschieten der lijnen in de natuur wil nagaan &amp; zich er reden van geven. En ik geloof dat evenals de heele perspectief verandert bij verandering der oogshoogte<c type="kk">/</c> welke afhangt niet van de voorwerpen doch van den man die kijkt (of hij bukt dan wel ergens op gaat staan)<c type="kk">/</c> zoo ook de verandering van Mauve &amp; H<c type="kp">_</c>G.T. voor een deel slechts schijnbaar is &amp; zijn reden had in mijn eigen stemming. Ik zie niet klaar in die affaires doch uit Uw brief heb ik duidelijk meenen te zien dat er geen reden is er mij overbezorgd over te maken als ik maar doorwerk. En omdat er nu nog andere dingen te schrijven zijn<c type="kk">/</c> genoeg daarover.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">De sympathie van Heyerdahl heeft mij zeer getroffen<c type="kk">/</c> wil hem voor mij groeten &amp; zeggen ik zeer zeker hoop dat ik eens met hem in kennis zal komen &amp; dat op prijs zou stellen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu heb ik twee grootere teekeningen klaar. Vooreerst Sorrow doch in grooter formaat, het figuur alleen zonder entourage. Doch de pose is eenigzins gewijzigd<c type="kk">/</c> het haar hangt niet naar achteren op den rug doch naar voren<c type="kk">/</c> gedeeltelijk in eene vlecht<c type="kp">_</c> Daardoor komt het schoudergewricht<c type="kk">/</c> den nek &amp; rug in ’t gezigt<c type="kp">_</c> En ’t figuur is met meer zorg geteekend.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">De andere<c type="kk">/</c> “<hi rend="italics">Les racines</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> is eenige boomwortels in een zandgrond<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Nu heb ik getracht in het landschap ’t zelfde sentiment te leggen als in ’t figuur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">het zich als ’t ware krampachtig en hartstogtelijk vastwortelen in de aarde en het toch half losgerukt zijn door de stormen. Ik wilde zoowel in dat blanke slanke vrouwenfiguur als in die zwarte knorrige wortels met hun knoesten iets uitdrukken van den strijd des levens. Of liever omdat ik getracht heb trouw te zijn aan de natuur welke ik voor mij had zonder er bij te philosopheeren<c type="kk">/</c> is er haast onwillekeurig in beide gevallen iets van dien grooten strijd ingekomen. Althans het kwam mij voor dat er eenig sentiment in was maar kan mij vergissen<c type="kk">/</c> enfin ge moet maar eens zien.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Vindt ge er iets in dan zijn ze voor Uwe nieuwe woning welligt geschikt<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> &amp; dan heb ik ze voor uw verjaardag<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> gemaakt waarmede ik U nog gelukwensch<c type="kp">_</c> Maar omdat ze tamelijk groot zijn (1 heel vel Ingres)<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> weet ik niet of ik ze dadelijk moet opzenden. Zeg mij dit eens<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien zou H.G.T. het brutaal of pedant vinden als ik vroeg ze als remise<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> in een kist te pakken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">ofschoon <hi rend="italics">Les racines</hi> maar een “potlood”teekening is zoo is er toch met het potlood in geborsteld &amp; weer afgekrabd gelijk men schildert.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Aangaande het timmermanspotlood redeneer ik aldus. De oude meesters<c type="kk">/</c> waar zouden die mee geteekend hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Zeker niet met Faber B<c type="kk">/</c> BB<c type="kk">/</c> BBB<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c. maar met een ruw stuk graphiet. Het werktuig waarvan Michel ange &amp; Durer zich bedienden had welligt veel van een timmermans<c type="shy">-</c>potlood. Doch ik ben er niet bij geweest &amp; weet het niet<c type="kk">/</c> dit weet ik wel<c type="kk">/</c> dat men met een timmermanspotlood krachten verkrijgen kan anders dan met die fijne fabers &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik heb het graphiet liever in zijn natuurlijken vorm dan zoo bijster fijn gezaagd in de dure fabers. En het blinken gaat weg door ’t fixeeren met melk. Als men buiten zit &amp; werkt met conté weet men door ’t schelle licht niet regt wat men doet &amp; merkt dat ’t te zwart is geworden maar graphiet is eer grijs dan zwart en men kan altijd nog een paar octaven er bij krijgen door er op nieuw in te werken met de pen zoodat de sterkste krachten graphiet toch weer licht worden door ’t repoussoir van de pen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Houtskool is best doch als men er veel op sjouwt gaat de frischheid er af en om de finesse er in te houden moet men op de plaats zelf fixeeren. Ook voor landschap zie ik dat de teekenaars als b.v. Ruysdael<c type="kk">/</c> V. Goyen<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en Calame<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Roelofs<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> ook b.v. onder de modernen<c type="kk">/</c> er veel partij van trokken. Doch als iemand een goede pen uitvond om buiten mee te werken<c type="kk">/</c> met bijbehoorenden inktkoker dan kwamen er misschien meer penteekeningen in de wereld.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Met houtskool die in olie gelegen heeft kan men fameuse dingen doen<c type="kk">/</c> dat heb ik van Weissenbruch gezien. de olie fixeert dan en het zwart wordt warmer &amp; dieper.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Maar beter is het ik zulks over een jaar dan nu doe denk ik bij me zelven<c type="kk">/</c> van wege ik niet wil dat de mooiigheid door mijn materiaal doch door mij kome. Ben ik nog wat verder dan trek ik eens nu en dan een mooi pak aan<c type="kk">/</c> ik bedoel werk met een dankbaar teekenmateriaal. En mits ik dan zelf maar wat doen kunne vlot het dan dubbel &amp; valt mogelijk mee. Maar eerst, voor alle succes<c type="kk">/</c> den strijd corps à corps met de dingen in de natuur.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Nu heb ik U verleden jaar een groot aantal brieven geschreven over wat ik zoo al dacht omtrent de liefde. Nu doe ik zulks niet van wege ik het druk heb met het in praktijk brengen der zelfde dingen. De persoon voor wie ik gevoelde wat ik U schreef is niet op mijn weg<c type="kk">/</c> is buiten mijn bereik ondanks al het smachten dat ik naar haar deed.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Had ik beter gedaan met aan haar te denken en voorbij te zien wat op mijn weg kwam. In hoeverre ik consequent of inconsequent handel weet ik zelf niet te beslissen. Gesteld ik begin van daag een teekening b.v. van een spitter – doch die man zegt ik moet weg en wil of kan niet weer poseeren – te meer omdat ik hem begon te teekenen zonder hem permissie te vragen heb ik ’t regt niet ’t hem kwalijk te nemen hij mij daar staan laat met een ter naauwernood geschetste teekening. Moet ik nu echter het teekenen van een spitter opgeven. Ik meen neen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral niet als ik morgen een ander tegen kom die zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil niet alleen heden maar ook morgen en overmorgen komen en ik begrijp wat gij noodig hebt<c type="kk">/</c> ga Uw gang<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er geduld &amp; goeden wil voor. Ik ben dan wel is waar niet precies bij mijne oorspronkelijk impressie gebleven maar had ik beter gedaan te redeneeren, neen ik moet bepaald die eerste spitter hebben als hij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan en wil niet. En ben ik eenmaal begonnen aan N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 2 dan mag ik gedecideerd niet buiten de natuur die voor mij staat om werken &amp; terwijl zitten denken aan N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 1<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo staat de zaak. En daaromtrent voeg ik bij mijn vorig schrijven nog dit. Om de zaak te doen gelukken zoudt gij mij wat moeten helpen doch de uitgaaf daarvoor zou geloof ik niet meer maar wel minder zijn dan ’t geen gij mij de laatste maanden hebt gezonden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik zou willen en durven ondernemen indien ik gedurende nog een jaar kon rekenen op frs 150 per maand. Wel hoop ik alsdan er nog iets bij te verdienen doch liep dat mis dan zou ik met veel behelpen wel is waar toch er doorscharrelen. En nu later – als dat jaar om is.– Mij dunkt er zijn geen teekenen te bespeuren in mijn werk waaruit blijkt dat ik er niet in slagen zal mits ik doormarcheere en mij moeite blijve geven. En dan ben ik niet iemand die langzaam of zeurig werkt. Het teekenen wordt een hartstogt bij me &amp; ik ga er hoe langer hoe meer in op en where there is a will is a way<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Where is a will is a way doch dat moet van twee kanten gaan. <hi rend="italics">The will</hi> bij mij moet zijn het maken der dingen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">the will</hi> bij wie sympathie voor mij hebben of krijgen mogten<c type="kk">/</c> het verkoopen of koopen van die dingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16"><hi rend="italics">The will</hi> daar zijnde meen ik <hi rend="italics">the way</hi> te vinden zij. Maar als allen redeneerden zoo als H.G.T. “onverkoopbaar”<c type="kk">/</c> “onbehagelijk”<c type="kk">/</c> dan kwam er een berg displeizier mij voor den neus. Enfin – wat hier ook van zij – om het onbehagelijk &amp; onverkoopbaar te overwinnen zal ik mij nog meer op het werk inspannen.</p>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Gedurende 3 nachten heeft het hier erg gestormd.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Den nacht van Zaturdag op Zondag is het raam van mijn atelier bezweken. (het huis waar ik woon is zeer wrak<c type="kp">_</c>) 4 groote ruiten kapot en het venster losgerukt. Gij kunt denken dit niet alles was. De wind kwam over de vlakke weilanden aanzeilen en mijn raam kreeg hem uit de eerste hand. De schutting beneden ook omver, de teekeningen van den muur gescheurd<c type="kk">/</c> ’t ezel tegen den grond. Met behulp van mijn buurman heb ik evenwel het raam nog vastgebonden &amp; tegen het gat<c type="kk">/</c> zeker een □ meter<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> groot<c type="kk">/</c> een wollendeken gespijkerd. Den heelen nacht geen oog digt gedaan zoo als ge denken kunt<c type="kp">_</c> En nog veel gescharrel om ’t gemaakt te krijgen om reden van den Zondag. De huisheer is een arme scharrelaar<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> hij heeft het glas gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> ik het werkloon. Maar reden te meer waarom ik er over denk om hier naast te gaan wonen. Er is daar een bovenhuis aldus.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">’t atelier is grooter dan ’t mijne<c type="kk">/</c> ’t licht zeer goed<c type="kp">_</c> Er is een zolder geheel met planken beschoten zoodat men de pannen niet ziet. enorm groot<c type="kk">/</c> waar men nog zooveel kamers kan afschieten<ptr target="#note-t-d"/> (en ik heb de schotten er voor) als men maar wil. Huurprijs fl<c type="kp">_</c> 12.50 per maand<c type="kk">/</c> een sterk goedgebouwd huis doch het doet niet meer omdat het “maar op den Schenkweg” staat en daar de rijke huurders niet komen die de eigenaar<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> wel wachtte<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik zou er zeer veel zin in hebben, en de eigenaar zou mij er wel in willen hebben en heeft er mij ’t eerst over gesproken en toen ben ik gaan zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">En nu eindig ik met te zeggen, dat ik U verzeker ik veel aan t’huis denk en van meening ben dat als het een half jaar verder is en de zaak waarover ik U schreef ondernomen en Pa en Moe eens bij me komen<c type="kk">/</c> dit wel een verandering van stemming van weerskanten ten gevolge zou hebben. Doch dat ’t nu helaas nog niet ’t moment is en we eerst het ding op zijn pooten moeten zien te krijgen. Want Pa en Moe die ik in de gegevenen wel als leeken mag beschouwen zullen het heel mooi vinden als ’t verder af is (meer <hi rend="italics">gefinesseerd</hi> zeggen de belgische kooplui volgens Mauve) doch van de ruwe schets die gij begrijpen zoudt als ge hier waart zouden zij minstens duizelig worden. à dieu – het beste U toegewenscht.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Is het dat gij spoedig komt zoo zend ik de teekeningen niet. Maar het is tijd dat gij langzamerhand wat van mij krijgt, ik doe er mijn best op en bevielen U deze twee b.v. dan kreegt ge er nog veel meer en van allerlei<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Als gij die welke gij geschikt oordeelt op Uw kamer eens laat kijken aan dezen &amp; genen dan is dat misschien ’t begin om ze ook aan den man te brengen, en het is juist als er meer bij een zijn en verschillende van dezelfde hand dat ze elkaar releveeren &amp; ’t een ’t ander aanvult en expliceert.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Hetgeen waar ik ’t meest aan hecht is de sympathie van U. Mogt ik die bepaald winnen dan zou de verkoop ook komen. Doch die sympathie van U moet noch ik noch gijzelf forceeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik geloof ik heel wat produceeren kan<c type="kk">/</c> ik bedoel grif werken en niet lanterfanten. En als ik nu op nieuw nadat gij de oude studies teruggezonden hebt zooals ik U vroeg<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> er een paar gezonden heb, (de laan v<c type="kp">_</c> Meerdervoort &amp; Sorrow)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> dan is het om U een teeken te geven dat ik er zoo meer kan maken als gij wilt. Zegt gij ’t is nog niet rijp<c type="kk">/</c> dan werk ik nog door voor ik begin te zenden want dat wat ik zond is niet iets toevalligs<c type="kk">/</c> maar wat ik kan dat kan ik. Om het nu weer een eind op te voeren moet ik weer een tijd voortwerken. Maar dit wil ik zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> is het dat de laatstgezondene U voorkomen iets te hebben dat gij kunt beginnen aan dezen &amp; genen te laten zien dan kan ik beginnen te zenden naarmate ik iets heb. Wat U dan goed voor kwam zou in grijze passepartouts<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> moeten en zoo zou zich langzamerhand een portefeuille er van vormen<c type="kp">_</c> Denk hier eens over.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik heb nog een teekening van een mannetje bij den haard<c type="kk">/</c> “de bestedeling”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-21"/> een oud wijf van de Geest<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/> een paar vrouwenfiguren<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> die gevoegd bij de anderen dunkt mij goed zouden doen. Verder kleine schetsen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik zeg het echter niet om te haasten maar het kan geen kwaad er eens over te denken.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Gij zijt begonnen mij te helpen niet wetende wat er van komen zou en toen anderen niet wilden. Ik zou wel graag willen dat het zoo uitkwam dat gij heel leuk<ptr target="#note-t-e"/> kondet zeggen tegen degenen die het gek vinden van U dat gij mij helpt<c type="kk">/</c> dat ge er niets aan verloren hebt. En dat prikkelt mij nog te meer en mij dunkt gij moest een begin maken om eenige teekeningen bij U te nemen, en iedere maand komt er dan iets bij. Er zijn dagen dat ik er 5 maak doch ge moet rekenen bij teekeningen dat er 1 van de 20 lukt<c type="kp">_</c> Die 1 uit de 20 is echter nu geen toeval meer<c type="kk">/</c> daar kan ik op rekenen<c type="kp">_</c> Er zal er wel iedere week 1 onder doorloopen waarvan ik voel “die blijft”. ’t Is beter gij degenen “die blijven” bij U bewaart voorloopig dan dat ik ze voor een gulden of 10 en dan nog als bij de gratie Gods &amp; een groote genade zou geven aan den een of ander hier. Hier vallen <hi rend="italics">allen</hi> op de manier van doen maar van allen hoor ik ook dezelfde lieux communs over de Engelsche teekeningen b.v. Alleen Weissenbruch zei toen ik hem vertelde, ik <hi rend="italics">zie</hi> de dingen als teekeningen met de pen – dan moet ge met de pen teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Hij<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. Weiss.<c type="kk">/</c> heeft niet de kleine doch de groote Sorrow gezien en heeft er mij dingen van gezegd die me pleizier deden. Daarom durf ik over de groote zeggen wat ik zeg. Ik heb geen “leiding”<c type="kk">/</c> “onderwijs” gehad van anderen om zoo te zeggen doch mij zelven geleerd en het is geen wonder dat mijn manier van doen bij oppervlakkige beschouwing verschilt van die van anderen. Maar dat is niet een reden waarom mijn werk onverkoopbaar zou blijven. Ik maak mij sterk dat de groote Sorrow<c type="kk">/</c> het wijf van de Geest<c type="kk">/</c> de bestedeling<c type="kk">/</c> en meer anderen<c type="kk">/</c> als gij wilt den een of anderen dag wel degelijk een liefhebber zullen vinden. Maar het kan wel zijn dat ik later er nog eens wat aan doe. Ik heb weer op de Laan v. Meerdervoort gewerkt ook. Ik heb voor me liggen een vrouwenfiguur in japon van zwart merinos<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> waarvan ik zeker weet dat als gij het eenige dagen bij U gehad zoudt hebben gij met de manier van doen verzoend zoudt zijn &amp; ’t niet verlangen het anders ware gedaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">De engelsche teekeningen begreep ik den eersten dag ook niet<c type="kk">/</c> evenmi<supplied>n</supplied> als een ander vreemdeling maar “ik heb mij de moeite gegeven er kennis mee te maken”<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> en daar geen spijt van gehad.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> voor heden genoeg.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter with the enclosed 100 francs and thank you most sincerely for it. Your letter enlightened me more than all my worrying and fretting about the question of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">HGT</rs>. I compliment you on it, because now I believe I understand it better. And, if I understand correctly, what I have to do is go on working calmly without dwelling on it or taking it to heart as much as I did. If I dwell on it, I have the same feeling of dizziness which, you say, someone who hasn’t studied perspective feels when he tries to follow the receding lines in nature and give an account of them. And I believe that just as the whole perspective changes with a change in eye level, which depends not on the objects but on the man viewing them (whether he stoops or stands on top of something), so too the change in Mauve and H.G.T. is in part only an outward seeming and can be explained by my own mood. I don’t see these affairs clearly, but I think I see plainly from your letter that there’s no reason for me to be overly concerned about it if only I go on working. And now enough about it, because there are other things to write.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs>’s sympathy moved me deeply, will you give him my regards and say that I hope very much to make his acquaintance some day, and that I set great store by it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve now finished two larger drawings. First of all, Sorrow, but in a larger format, the figure alone without surroundings. But the pose has been altered somewhat, the hair doesn’t hang down the back but to the front, part of it in a plait. This brings the shoulder, the neck and back into view. And the figure has been drawn with more care.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The other one, ‘<hi rend="italics">Roots</hi>’, is some tree roots in sandy ground.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve tried to imbue the landscape with the same sentiment as the figure.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Frantically and fervently rooting itself, as it were, in the earth, and yet being half torn up by the storm. I wanted to express something of life’s struggle, both in that white, slender female figure and in those gnarled black roots with their knots. Or rather, because I tried without any philosophizing to be true to nature, which I had before me, something of that great struggle has come into both of them almost inadvertently. At least it seemed to me that there was some sentiment in it, though I may be mistaken, anyway, you’ll have to see for yourself. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">If you see something in them, perhaps they’ll be suitable for your new home,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and then I’ll have made them for your birthday,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> on which I congratulate you. But because they’re rather large (1 whole sheet of Ingres),<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I don’t know if I should send them straightaway. Let me know. Perhaps <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> would find it impertinent or priggish if I asked him to pack them in a crate as a return shipment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Although <hi rend="italics">Roots</hi> is only a ‘pencil’ drawing, it has been brushed in and scraped off, the same as one paints.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">As regards the carpenter’s pencil, my reasoning is as follows. The old masters, what would they have drawn with? Certainly not with Faber B, BB, BBB,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> &amp;c. &amp;c., but with a rough piece of graphite. The implement <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Dürer</rs> used was perhaps very similar to a carpenter’s pencil. But I wasn’t there and don’t know. This I do know, that with a carpenter’s pencil one can achieve intensities differently than with those fine Fabers &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I like graphite better in its natural form than cut too fine in those expensive Fabers. And the shininess disappears by fixing it with milk. If one sits outdoors and works with Conté, one can’t really tell what one’s doing because of the bright light and notices that it’s become too black, but graphite is more grey than black, and one can always obtain a couple of extra octaves by working it over with the pen, so that the strongest intensities of graphite actually lighten up through the repoussoir of the pen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Charcoal is best, but if one works with it too long it loses its freshness, and to keep the subtlety one has to fix those spots. For landscapes as well, I see that such draughtsmen as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1056">Van Goyen</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_923">Calame</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1318">Roelofs</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> too, among the moderns, used it to great advantage. But if someone invented a good pen to work with outdoors, with accompanying inkwell, perhaps more pen drawings would be made.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">One can do wonderful things with charcoal that has been soaked in oil, I’ve seen this from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs>. The oil is then the fixative, and the black becomes warmer and deeper.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> But I imagine it would be better for me to do that in a year and not now, because I want the fine appearance to come from me and not from my material. When I’m a bit further along I’ll put on a nice suit now and then, meaning I’ll work with rewarding drawing materials. And provided I myself am capable of doing something, I’ll make twice as much progress, and perhaps it will prove easier than expected. But first, before any success, hand-to-hand combat with the things in nature. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Last year I wrote you a great many letters telling you what I thought about love. I’m not doing so now, because I’m busy putting those same things into practice. The person for whom I felt what I wrote to you is not on my path, is beyond my reach, despite all my longing for her.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Would I have done better to go on thinking of her and to overlook what came my way? I cannot decide whether I’m acting consistently or inconsistently. Suppose I were to start today on a drawing of a digger, for example – but the man says, I have to leave and won’t or can’t pose again – I don’t have the right to blame him for leaving me there with a barely sketched drawing, the more so because I started to draw him without asking permission. Must I then give up drawing a digger? I think not, especially not if tomorrow I encounter one who says, I want to come not only today but also tomorrow and the day after, and I understand what you need, go ahead, I’m patient and have the good will to do it. To be sure, I didn’t stick exactly to my first impression, but would I have done better to reason: no, I definitely need that first digger, even if he says, I can’t and won’t? And once I’ve started on No. 2, then I may certainly not work without reference to the nature standing before me, thinking the while of No.<hi rend="super"> </hi>1. That’s how things stand. And concerning that, I add this to my previous letter. In order for me to succeed, you’ll have to help me a bit, but I believe the expense would be not more but less than what you’ve been sending me these last few months.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I’d be willing and daring enough to embark on this undertaking if I could count on 150 francs a month for another year. I do hope in that case to earn something as well, but if that were to fail I’d be able to scrape by anyway, though admittedly in straitened circumstances. And then later – when that year has passed? It seems to me that there’s nothing in my work to indicate that I won’t succeed, provided I plough on and continue to make an effort. And I’m not one to work slowly or fretfully. Drawing is becoming a passion with me, and I’m becoming increasingly absorbed in it, and where there is a will is a way.<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> <ptr target="#note-t-13"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Where is a will is a way,<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> but that has to come from both sides. For me <hi rend="italics">the will</hi> must be the making of things, and for those who have or may acquire sympathy for me, <hi rend="italics">the will</hi> is selling or buying those things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"><hi rend="italics">The will</hi> being there, I think <hi rend="italics">the way</hi> can be found. But if everyone reasoned like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> – ‘unsaleable’, ‘disagreeable’ – then I’d be confronted with a mountain of trouble. Oh well – be that as it may – I’ll put more effort into my work to defeat the disagreeable and unsaleable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">There’s been a terrible storm here for 3 nights running.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> In the night from Saturday to Sunday the window of my studio gave out. (The house where I live is very dilapidated.) 4 large panes broken and the window wrenched loose. You can imagine this wasn’t all. The wind came sailing over the flat pastures directly at my window. The fence below was also knocked down, the drawings ripped from the wall, the easel on the floor. I nevertheless tied the window down with my neighbour’s help, and nailed up a woollen blanket against the opening, certainly a □ metre<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> in size. Didn’t sleep a wink the whole night, as you can imagine. And lots of trouble to fix it because it was Sunday. The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">landlord</rs> is a poor pedlar,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> he gave me the glass, I paid for the work. All the more reason why I’m thinking of moving next door. There’s an upstairs flat like this:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">The studio is larger than mine, the light very good. There’s an attic, completely panelled over, so that one doesn’t see the roof tiles. Extremely large, where one can partition off as many rooms as one likes (and I have the planks to do it). Rent 12.50 guilders a month, a strong, well-built house, but it won’t bring in any more, because it’s ‘only in Schenkweg’ and the rich people the owner<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> had hoped for won’t come here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I’d like it very much, and the owner would like to have me rent it; he spoke to me about it first and then I went to see it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And now I’ll finish by saying that I assure you I think about home a great deal, and am of the opinion that half a year from now, if the matter about which I wrote to you has been undertaken and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> come to visit me, it would result in a change of feeling on both sides. Unfortunately, though, now is not the time, we have to get things started first. Because Pa and Ma, whom I consider to be lay people in the circumstances, will think it very nice if it’s more finished (Belgian merchants say more <hi rend="italics">finessed</hi>, according to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>), but the rough sketch, which you’d understand if you’d been here, would make them dizzy at the very least. Adieu – I wish you the best.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">If you’re coming soon, I won’t send the drawings. But it’s time you started to get things from me, I’ll do my best, and if you like these two, for example, you’ll get many more and of all kinds.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">If you show the ones you find suitable to the people who come to your room, perhaps that would be the beginning of selling them, and particularly when a number of them are shown together, and various ones by the same hand, they draw attention to one another, and the one complements and explains the other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">What I value most is your sympathy. If I positively win that, the selling will follow. But neither I nor you must force that sympathy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">I believe I can produce a great deal, I mean, work rapidly and not waste time. And if I’ve sent you another couple, since you sent back the old studies as I asked you to do<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> (the Laan van Meerdervoort and Sorrow),<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> it’s to give you a sign that I can make more of the same if you’d like. If you say they aren’t ready, I’ll go on working before sending more, because what I sent isn’t something accidental: what I can do, I can do. I must go on working for a time to make even more progress. But I want to say this: if the last batch I sent proves to have anything you could begin showing to people, I could start to send you things as soon as I have something. What you considered good would then have to be put into grey mounts,<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> and a portfolio would gradually take shape in this way. Think about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I have another drawing of an old man by the fireplace, ‘the boarder’,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> an old woman from the Geest district,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> a couple of female figures<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> which I think would go well with the others. Also small sketches.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I’m not saying this to make you hurry, but it can’t do any harm to think it over. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">You started helping me without knowing what would come of it, and when others wouldn’t. I do hope that one day you’ll be able to say calmly to those who think it’s foolish of you to help me that you haven’t lost anything by it. And that stimulates me all the more, and I think you should start by taking a few drawings, and every month there will be more. There are days when I make 5, but with drawings you must count on 1 in 20 succeeding. That 1 in 20 is no longer an accident, though, I can count on that. There will probably be 1 every week about which I feel ‘that will remain’. For the time being it’s better for you to keep the ones that ‘will remain’ than for me to give them to someone here for 10 guilders or so, and then only by the grace of God and as a great favour. Here <hi rend="italics">everyone</hi> criticizes the technique, but I also hear the same platitudes from everyone about English drawings, for example. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> alone said, when I told him that I <hi rend="italics">see</hi> the things as pen drawings – then you must draw with the pen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">He, namely <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weiss</rs>., saw the large rather than the small Sorrow, and he said things about it that pleased me. That’s why I dare to say what I say about the large one. I’ve had no ‘guidance’, no ‘instruction’ from others, but have taught myself, as it were, so it’s no wonder that on the face of it my way of doing things differs from that of others. But that’s no reason for my work to remain unsaleable. I’ll wager that the large Sorrow, the woman from the Geest district, the boarder and others too, if you will, will indeed find a buyer one day. But it could well be that I’ll work on them again later. I’ve even worked again on the Laan van Meerdervoort. I have a female figure in a black merino frock in front of me,<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> and I’m certain that if you had it for a few days you would become reconciled to its manner and wouldn’t wish it had been done differently.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I didn’t understand English drawings either at first, as little as any other foreigner, but ‘I took the trouble to become acquainted with them’<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> and haven’t regretted it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Adieu, enough for today.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent congratulates Theo on the occasion of his birthday (1 May); he usually did this on the day itself. It is not very likely that he wrote the letter on Sunday, 30 April, because he says that he spent that day trying to get a window repaired that had been wrenched loose by the wind. Van Gogh reports terrible storms for three nights, but the <hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi> recorded storms for only two nights around the time this letter was written (see also <ref target="#n-14">n. 14</ref>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent has sent Theo the drawings <hi rend="italics">Sorrow</hi> and ‘Laan van Meerdervoort’ (<ref target="let216.xml">216</ref> and <ref target="let218.xml">218</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Strained relations with Mauve and Tersteeg (<ref target="let209.xml">209</ref> and <ref target="let208.xml">208</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s plans to come to the Netherlands <ref target="let206.xml">(206)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This larger version of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrow</hi> is unknown. See Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 38-48.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Study of a tree</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2371">F 933r / JH 142</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Theo had moved at the beginning of April; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let218.xml">see letter 218</ref>, in which Vincent promises to send drawings to decorate Theo’s walls.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo turned 25 on 1 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2371">Study of a tree</rs></hi> measures 50 x 69 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            
      
<p>This probably means ‘als retourzending’ (as a return shipment).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The drawing was done in black and white chalk, black ink, pencil and watercolour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The hardness of pencils was (and still is) indicated by letters, B and H being the customary ones. Soft pencils were given a designation ranging (in increasing degrees of softness) from B to BBBBBB. The 1870 catalogue of the German firm A.W. Faber recommends these for ‘paysagistes’ (landscapists). Communicated by Renate Hilsenbeck, archivist of A.W. Faber-Castell GmbH &amp; Co., Stein (Germany).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Both <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Jacob van Ruisdael</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1056">Jan van Goyen</rs> drew in black chalk and not in charcoal. It is no wonder that Van Gogh was mistaken about this, since it is difficult to see the difference, and he might have known their drawings only from reproductions.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_923">Alexandre Calame</rs> mainly used charcoal for his portraits, especially those dating from his early years. Landscape drawings in charcoal – frequently in combination with gouache and (white) chalk – are to be found chiefly in his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carnet bleu. Gothard 1859 – Pilate 1861</hi>. See E. Rambert, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Alexandre Calame. Sa vie et son oeuvre</hi>. Paris 1884, p. 36, and Valentina Anker, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Alexandre Calame. Vie et oeuvre. Catalogue raisonné de l’oeuvre peint</hi>. Fribourg 1987, pp. 23, 294-302.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Which of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1318">Roelofs</rs>’s charcoal drawings Van Gogh had in mind can no longer be ascertained. Roelofs sold his work through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M. van Gogh</rs> and Goupil, which perhaps explains how Van Gogh became familiar with his drawings.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> frequently used charcoal soaked in oil to make underdrawings. See Laanstra and Ooms 1992, p. 22.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
      
<p>This is a reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">where ... way</hi>: in English.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
      
<p>A saying. Perhaps Vincent is reminding Theo of something he himself said. Later on Vincent writes: ‘You yourself said to me: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Where there is a will there is a way</hi>’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let527.xml">letter 527</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            
<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Where ... way</hi>: in English.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The weather reports indicate that there were storms only on the nights of 29 and 30 April (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KNMI</hi>); see also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Read: ‘a square metre’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The landlord was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">Adrianus Johannes van der Drift</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="d" xml:id="note-t-d">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘afscheiden door middel van een wand’ (to partition off by means of a wall).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The owner of the apartment Vincent hoped to move to was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_813">Pieter Willem de Zwart</rs>, master-mason and builder with headquarters in Voorburg. De Zwart had built the houses in Schenkstraat. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 19-22 , 24. His rental business was looked after by his son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">Michiel Antonie de Zwart</rs>. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let243.xml">letter 243</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let214.xml">See letter 214</ref> for a previous occasion on which Theo returned Vincent’s studies.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>These drawings are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>For this advice, probably prompted by reading <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Edmond and Jules de Goncourt</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_224"><hi rend="italics">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let216.xml#n-4">see letter 216, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man sitting by a stove (‘The pauper’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2370">F 1116a / JH 139</rs>). A ‘boarder’ was a person living in a hostel or boarding-house at the community’s expense.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old woman with a shawl and a walking-stick</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2358">F 913 /JH 109</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>For drawings of ‘female figures’ from this period, see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sien with a cigar sitting on the floor near the stove</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_248">F 898 / JH 141</rs>) and the drawings mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-24">n. 24.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="e" xml:id="note-t-e">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘rustig’ (calmly).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Cf. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman in a dark dress</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_249">F 936 / JH 140</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Seated woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_250">F 935 / JH 143</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Seated woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_250">F 937 / JH 144</rs>); and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2372">F 932 / JH 145</rs>). Merino is a lightly twilled material produced from the combing wool of merino sheep.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>The quotation marks indicate that this is direct speech (or a quotation). The source is unknown.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    