<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 10 May 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let225"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b216 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>225</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>194</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>224</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-05-10">on or about Wednesday, 10 May 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0216" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0216" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000252_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Als ik in mijn vorig schrijven dingen gezegd heb omtrent haar die tamelijk somber zijn dan is het omdat ik van ’t begin af er op wilde wijzen dat ik hier niet sta in een rozentuin  doch in de werkelijkheid. En om vooruit te protesteeren tegen sentimenteele beschouwingen<c type="kk">/</c> zooals b.v. Pa &amp; moe niet in gebreke zouden blijven te opperen indien het ware ik hun advies vroeg of alleen maar hun de zaak mededeelde. Sentiment &amp; sentimentaliteit zijn twee zeer verschillende dingen welke zij niet weten te onderscheiden<c type="kp">_</c> En Pa zou indien ik er over sprak alligt een rol van gendarme meenen te moeten spelen die ten eenemale ontoepasselijk ware en ook weinig baten zou.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gij zult het mij dus ten goede houden wanneer ik tot Pa en Moe geen syllabe over deze zaak zeg en niet verlang dat zij zich er mede bemoeien zullen. Indien Pa zijne toestemming niet wilde geven zoo zijn er termen in de wet welke mij als meerderjarig toch mijn onafhankelijkheid guarandeeren doch ik geloof niet dat het zoover zal komen dat Pa er zich tegen verzetten zou.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Men zal zeggen “gij gaat uit uw stand en gij zijt te arm”. Ik antwoord daarop<c type="kk">/</c> Indien ik van plan was op grooten voet te gaan leven zoo zou ik verkeerd uit komen. Als ik ga huizen in een huis bestaande uit een atelier<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">1</hi> kamer en een keukentje<c type="kk">/</c> slaapplaats op den zolder<c type="kk">/</c> en wat betreft levenswijs het zeer eenvoudig aanleg dan kan het geschipperd worden en dan hebben twee zamenlevende personen minder noodig dan een alleen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">On est sûr de périr à part<c type="kk">/</c> on ne se sauve qu’ensemble.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik heb Kee Vos gevraagd of zij ’t met mij wagen wilde. Hoe ik geweigerd ben is U bekend<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen ik alleen nog verzocht heb is de ontvangst bij gelegenheid van mijn bezoek te Amsterdam. Alstoen werd mij gezegd dat ik wilde forceeren – zij wilde mij niet zien<c type="kk">/</c> niet te woord staan, niet bij èèn bezoek maar gedurende de 3 dagen van mijn vertoef aldaar.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als mij gezegd wordt “gij wilt forceeren”<c type="kk">/</c> dan zeggen dat alleen zulken Theo<c type="kk">/</c> die mij ten eenemale misverstaan<c type="kp">_</c> Ten bewijze dat ik toen niet heb willen forceeren diene bij dezen dat ik nu iets doe ’t welk genoeg bewijst dat ik niet als een die forceeren wil tegenover Kee Vos stond.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Deze vrouw met welke ik nu ben heeft mij beter begrepen. In korten tijd werd zij zoo mak als een tamme duif<c type="kk">/</c> zeker niet door forceeren van mijn kant doch omdat <hi rend="italics">zij</hi> zag dat ik niet ruw was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Enfin deze heeft het gevat en zij zeide tot mij<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet dat gij niet veel geld hebt doch al hadt gij nog minder<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil mij naar alles schikken als gij maar bij mij blijft en mij bij U laat blijven, ik ben te veel aan je gehecht dan dat ik weer alleen zou kunnen zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Als iemand dit tot mij zegt en in alles toont veel meer door daden dan door woorden dat zij zulks meent<c type="kk">/</c> dan is het geen wonder dat ik tegenover haar het masker van koelheid &amp; ruwheid bijna<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik lang voorgehouden heb omdat ik niet vleijen wilde<c type="kk">/</c> heb laten vallen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En nu<c type="kk">/</c> is deze vrouw er slechter bij gevaren of ben ik er slechter mee gevaren dat het zoo is gegaan. Ik sta er verwonderd over haar met den dag te zien opstijven<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> en opfleuren<c type="kk">/</c> zij is zoo veranderd dat het een heel ander persoon lijkt dan die zieke bleeke vrouw die ik dezen winter ontmoette. En toch<c type="kk">/</c> veel heb ik niet aan haar gedaan<c type="kk">/</c> alleen ik heb haar gezegd: doe dit<c type="kk">/</c> doe dat en gij zult gezond worden – en zij heeft dat niet in den wind geslagen en toen ik zag dat zij het niet in den wind sloeg heb ik er nog meer mijn best op gedaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik was er misschien beter toe in staat dan een ander om haar te begrijpen omdat zij een paar eigenaardigheden heeft die menig ander zouden afgestooten hebben.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vooreerst haar spraak die leelijk is en die zij uit haar ziekte heeft gehouden<c type="kk">/</c> dan haar humeur dat uit een zenuwachtig gestel voortkomt waardoor zij buijen heeft die voor menigeen ondragelijk zijn. Ik begrijp die dingen, mij hinderen ze niet en tot nog toe kon ik er evenwel mee rondspringen. En van haar kant begrijpt zij mijn eigen humeur en ’t is als ’t ware een stilzwijgende afspraak tusschen ons niet op elkaar te vitten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Als gij de groote teekening uit de Graphic van Frank Holl kent<c type="kk">/</c> “the deserter”<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik zeggen dat zij veel heeft van het vrouwenfiguur daarop.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Het poseeren leert zij met den dag beter en dat is enorm veel voor mij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zij is niet een last, een blok aan mijn been maar zij helpt en werkt mee.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Zij heeft geen pretenties<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet het sus of zoo hebben<c type="kk">/</c> maar als er niets is dan brood en koffij doet zij het er mee zonder mopperen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Doch Theo<c type="kk">/</c> ik smacht er naar om U te zien &amp; te spreken<c type="kp">_</c> Naar een brief van U verlang ik ook erg. Als ik wist dat gij om deze reden niet van mij afkeerig zult worden dan was ik zoo gelukkig als een mensch maar zijn kan. Dat ik in ’t begin eenige hulp noodig hebben zal dat is zoo. Moest ik die missen ik was er slecht aan toe en zij ook; doch die hulp is niet meer dan voor mij alleen. En mijn werkkracht vermeerdert<c type="kk">/</c> en als ik mijn best gedaan heb er mij boven op te werken (’t spreekt van zelf zulks nu nog veel meer ’t geval is)<c type="kk">/</c> en juist door nog eenigen tijd op Uwe hulp &amp; medewerking te mogen rekenen<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik er zoo boven op komen dat ik het noodige door den verkoop van mijn werk verdien.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">De eerste stap die ik graag doen wilde is het atelier hiernaast nemen<c type="kk">/</c> waarover ik U schreef. Zoodra zij dan uit Leiden komt zal ik haar trouwen zonder iemand daar kennis van te geven<c type="kk">/</c> in stilte &amp; zonder omhaal. En dan kunnen wij het doen met dat huis en zijn bereid het zoo eenvoudig aan te leggen als maar eenigzins mogelijk is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">En was het dat gij zelf eens kondt komen kijken gij zoudt geloof ik zien dat gij er staat op kunt maken dat zoowel zij als ik ons best doen op het werk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik wou maar dat hare bevalling achter den rug was. Dat is nog een vuurproef voor haar. Doch tot heden gaat alles goed sedert zij daar te Leiden geweest is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Evenwel noch zij noch ik staan in een rozentuin of in den maneschijn te droomen<c type="kk">/</c> wij staan voor barre dingen – tant mieux.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">’t Geen ik van harte hoop is dat gij dit niet melankoliek zult op vatten. ’t Spreekt van zelf dat als Kee Vos in eenig opzigt beantwoord had ’t geen ik voor haar voelde dit niet gebeurd zou zijn. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> na mijn bezoek te Amsterdam was ik zoo gedecideerd geweigerd dat ik niet de minste kans had om haar te krijgen. Tenzij mijne finantieele omstandigheden in korten tijd geheel veranderd waren<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Geen nu niet geschieden zal want ofschoon ik wel zooveel zal verdienen gaandeweg dat <hi rend="italics">deze</hi> er met mij van leven kan zal het niet zooveel zijn dat ik er een <hi rend="italics">stand</hi> van kan voeren waartoe ik bovendien geen roeping of lust gevoel. Gij weet wat ik zoek, het allernoodigste om van te leven doch ’tgeen daarboven gaat laat mij tamelijk koel. ’t Geen ik graag hebben zou is een vast weekgeld als een ander arbeider waarvoor ik werken wil met al mijn kracht en verstand. En werkman zijnde hoor ik ’thuis in den werkmansstand en zal meer en meer daarin leven &amp; mij wortelen. Ik kan niet anders en ik heb geen lust in iets anders<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan mij iets anders niet begrijpen. à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">If I said things in my last letter about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> that are rather sombre, it’s because I wanted to point out from the beginning that I’m not living in a bed of roses but in reality. And to protest in advance against sentimental considerations of the kind <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> wouldn’t fail to suggest, if I were to ask their advice or merely to inform them of the matter. Sentiment and sentimentality are two very different things which they are unable to distinguish from one another. And if I were to speak of it, Pa would most likely think he had to play the part of policeman, which would be completely inappropriate and of little use.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">So you’ll excuse me if I don’t breathe a word of this to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>, and have no desire for them to interfere. If Pa refused to give his consent, there are legal provisions that guarantee me, as an adult, my independence, but I don’t think that Pa will go so far as to oppose it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">People will say, ‘you’re lowering yourself and you’re too poor’. To which I reply, If I were intending to set up house in style, it would end badly. If I go to live in a house consisting of a studio, <hi rend="italics">1</hi> room and a little kitchen, a sleeping place in the attic, and, as regards my way of life, go about things very simply, it can be done, and two people living together need less than one alone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">One is certain of sinking separately, only together can one be saved.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I asked <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs> if she would chance it with me. You know how I was refused, the only thing I asked for after that was to be received during my visit to Amsterdam. At that time I was told that I wanted to force the matter – she wouldn’t see me, wouldn’t speak to me, not only upon that one visit but during the 3 days of my stay there.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If I’m told ‘you want to force the matter’, the only ones who say that, Theo, are those who completely misunderstand me. As proof that at the time I didn’t want to force the matter, I now do something which proves that I wasn’t confronting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs> as one who wanted to force her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The woman I’m with now understands me better. In a short time she became as gentle as a tame dove, certainly not by force on my part but because <hi rend="italics">she</hi> saw that I wasn’t rough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Anyway, this one understood, and she said to me, I know you don’t have much money, but if you had even less, I’d do anything if only you’d stay with me and let me stay with you, I’m too attached to you to be capable of being alone again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">When someone says this to me and shows in everything that she means it, much more through actions than words, it’s no wonder that in front of her I dropped the mask of coolness, and roughness almost, which I’ve long worn because I didn’t want to cajole.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now then, is this woman worse off or am I worse off because it turned out this way? I’m amazed at the sight of her getting stronger and more cheerful every day, she’s so changed that she seems like a completely different person from the sick, pale woman I met this winter. And yet, I haven’t done much for her, I only said to her: do this, do that and you’ll get better – and she didn’t disregard it, and when I noticed that she didn’t disregard it, I tried even harder to do my best.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I was perhaps more able than others to understand her, because she has a couple of peculiar habits that many would find repellent. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">First of all, her speech, which is ugly and which is the result of her illness, then her temper, which stems from a nervous disposition, causing her to have moods that many would find unbearable. I understand these things, they don’t bother me, and until now I’ve been able to deal with them. And for her part, she understands my own temper, and we have a tacit agreement, as it were, not to carp at each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">If you know the large drawing from The Graphic by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Frank Holl</rs>, ‘The deserter’, I’d say she closely resembles the female figure in it.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">She’s learning to pose better every day, and that’s extremely important to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">She isn’t a burden, a millstone round my neck; instead, she helps and works with me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">She has no pretensions, I’ve got to have things just this way or that, and if there’s nothing but bread and coffee she makes do with that without complaining.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">But Theo, I’m longing to see you and talk to you. I’m also very much looking forward to a letter from you. If I knew that you wouldn’t turn away from me for this reason, I’d be as happy as a person can be. It’s true that I’ll need some help in the beginning. If I had to do without it, I’d be badly off and so would she, but that help amounts to no more than is necessary for me alone. And my energy is increasing, and when I’ve done my best to succeed (naturally such a thing is now the case more than ever), and precisely by being able to count on your help and cooperation for a while longer, I’ll succeed to the extent that I’ll earn what’s necessary by selling my work.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The first step I’d like to take is to rent the studio next door, which I wrote to you about. As soon as she returns from Leiden I’ll marry her without telling anyone about it, quietly and without any fuss. And then we’ll be able to manage with that house and are prepared to live as simply as possible.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">And if you were able to come and have a look, I believe you’d see that you can rely on both of us doing our best as regards work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I only wish her confinement were already over. That will be an ordeal for her. But until now everything has been all right, since she’s been to Leiden.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Still, neither she nor I are living on a bed of roses or dreaming in the moonlight, we’re facing hard things – so much the better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">What I sincerely hope is that you won’t take this pessimistically. Obviously if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs> had in any way reciprocated the feelings I had for her this wouldn’t have happened. Well, during my visit to Amsterdam, I was refused so resolutely that I didn’t have the slightest chance of winning her. Unless my financial circumstances were to change quickly and completely. Which won’t happen now, because even though I’ll eventually earn enough for <hi rend="italics">this one</hi> to live with me, it won’t be so much that I can afford to occupy a <hi rend="italics">station in life</hi> for which, moreover, I feel no calling or desire. You know what I’m seeking, the barest essentials, but anything more rather leaves me cold. What I’d like to have is a weekly wage like any other labourer, for which I’d work with all my might and powers of reason. And being a labourer, I belong to the working class and shall live and put down roots in that sphere more and more. I can’t do anything else and I have no desire to do anything else, I can’t imagine anything else. Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This letter must have been written after <ref target="let224.xml">224</ref>, because several aspects of Van Gogh’s relationship with Sien that were revealed in <ref target="let224.xml">letter 224</ref> are here explained in more detail (cf. <ref target="#l-2">ll. 2-3</ref>). Moreover, it precedes <ref target="let226.xml">letter 226</ref> of 12 or 13 May, in which Vincent again asks Theo to say what he thinks about the present situation. Because he writes in <ref target="let226.xml">letter 226</ref> that he has written ‘so often these last few days’ <ref target="#l-27">(ll. 27-28)</ref>, we have decided to date <ref target="let224.xml">letter 224</ref> to on or about Sunday, 7 May 1882 and <ref target="let225.xml">letter 225</ref> to on or about Wednesday, 10 May.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s relationship with Sien <ref target="let224.xml">(224)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s wants to move to the house next door <ref target="let222.xml">(222)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12"><hi rend="italics">La femme</hi></ref>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let189.xml#n-28">see letter 189, n. 28.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>From 25 to 27 November 1881 Van Gogh had been in Amsterdam, attempting to win <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee</rs>’s love, but his efforts had ended in rejection. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let191.xml">See letters 191</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let193.xml">193</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Meaning; ‘sterker worden’ (to grow stronger).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Francis Montague Holl</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The deserter</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 12 (25 September 1875), pp. 312-313. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_941">Ill. 941</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    