<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, Tuesday, 6 June 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let236"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8343 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>236</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R9</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>236</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-06-06">Tuesday, 6 June 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8343" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001588_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001588_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8343" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001588_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001588_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001588_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ingesloten zend ik U in dank terug de f<c type="kp">_</c> 2.50 die gij zoo goed waart mij te leenen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik heb antwoord op mijn teekeningen doch ontving er nog minder voor dan ik verwachtte ofschoon mijne verwachting f<c type="kp">_</c> 30.– voor 7 stuks niet te boven ging<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ontving f<c type="kp">_</c> 20 met nog een soort standje op den koop toe: “dacht ik dan dat zulke teekeningen ook maar de minste handelswaarde hadden”.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gij zult wel toegeven dat de tijden niet makkelijk zijn en soortgelijke ervaringen (en er zijn nog zooveel erger dingen<c type="kk">/</c> dit is in vergelijking van andere behandelingen nog royaal) en<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> soortgelijke ervaringen niet precies bijzonder encourageant zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">De kunst is jaloersch en vergt al onzen tijd<c type="kk">/</c> al onze kra<supplied>cht</supplied><ptr target="#note-t-2"/><hi rend="italics"> </hi>en dan<c type="kk">/</c> wanneer men die er aan toewijdt<c type="kk">/</c> door te gaan voor een soort onpraktisch mensch<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> &amp; weet ik wat meer<c type="kk">/</c> dat smaakt wel eens bitter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Enfin – we moeten zien door te sabelen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik heb geantwoord<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> dat ik niet de pretentie had au courant te zijn van de handelswaarde der dingen<c type="kk">/</c> dat nu hij als handelaar mij zeide dat er geen handelswaarde in zat ik zulks hem niet verlangde tegen te spreken of te betwisten<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik voor mij meer hechtte aan de artistieke dan aan de handelswaarde en mij liever verdiepte in de natuur dan in de berekening van prijzen<c type="kp">_</c> En dat wanneer ik met hem sprak over den prijs en de dingen niet voor niets gaf<c type="kk">/</c> zulks was omdat ik toch als ieder ander mensch mijne menschelijke behoeften aan voeding<c type="kk">/</c> woning &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> had en ’t een pligt rekende te zorgen ik die betrekkelijk geringe zaken regelde. Maar dat ik ZEd. mijn werk niet wilde opdringen tegen zijn zin en bereid was hem op nieuw teekeningen te zenden als hij wilde<c type="kk">/</c> maar ook bereid mij er in te schikken zijn clandisie te verliezen. Ik weet echter zoo goed als zeker dat er nog bij zal komen dat deze handelwijs van mij zal aangemerkt worden als ondankbaar<c type="kk">/</c> grof en brutaal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En mij verweten zal worden als ’t in de rede te pas komt<c type="kk">/</c> “Uw oom in Amsterda<supplied>m</supplied> die het zoo goed met U meende en zoo vriendelijk tegen U was en U zoo hielp<c type="kk">/</c> hebt gij door Uwe pretentieusheid en Uw onwil zóó ondankbaar behandeld dat het Uw eigen schuld is” &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Amice Rappard, ik weet eigentlijk niet of ik met zoo’n geval moet lagchen of dat ik er om schreien zal. Ik vind het zoo echt<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Natuurlijk – de rijke handelaars zijn de brave<c type="kk">/</c> eerlijke<c type="kk">/</c> opregte<c type="kk">/</c> loyale<c type="kk">/</c> fijngevoelige lui en wij arme donders die daar zitten te teekenen ’t zij buiten, ’t zij op straat, ’t zij op ’t atelier, soms s’morgens vroeg, soms diep in den nacht<c type="kk">/</c> soms in ’t heet van de zon, soms in de sneeuw<c type="kk">/</c> wij zijn de menschen zonder fijngevoeligheid<c type="kk">/</c> zonder praktisch verstand<c type="kk">/</c> zonder “vormen” vooral<c type="kp">_</c> Best hoor!–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Die Oom van mij uit Amsterdam wist mij ook met veel aplomb te zeggen dat de Groux eigentlijk een slecht mensch was.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Gij begrijpt in hoeverre zulks mijne opinie omtrent vader de Groux heeft veranderd<c type="kp">_</c> Het eenige wat ik gezegd heb<c type="kk">/</c> waarop hij mij tot dusverre ’t antwoord schuldig is gebleven, die edele handelaar, is ’t geen ik hem zeide “cependant il me semble qu’il s’agit bien moins de <hi rend="italics">gagner</hi> que de <hi rend="italics">mériter</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Enfin – ik spreek er maar eens over met U bij wijze van de veiligheidsklep van de machine eens open te zetten<c type="kk">/</c> anders mogt ik over de geschiedenis soms rancune houden en ik wensch niets liever dan er niet meer over te denken en ’t te vergeten maar die lui beginnen zoo lief en weten zoo innemend te zijn aanvankelijk dat men te meer verbluft staat aan ’t einde van de markt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">à dieu, nogmaals bedankt &amp; geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I gratefully enclose the 2.50 guilders you were good enough to lend me.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’ve had a reply to my drawings, but received even less for them than I expected, although my expectation was no more than 30 guilders for 7 items. I received 20 guilders with a sort of reprimand to boot: ‘did I imagine that such drawings had the least commercial value?’</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You must admit that the times aren’t easy, and that such experiences (and there are so many worse things; this is generous compared with other treatment) and, I say, that such experiences aren’t exactly very encouraging. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Art is jealous and demands all our time, all our strength,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and then, when you give it all that, you’re made out to be a sort of impractical type<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and I don’t know what else — that leaves a bitter taste. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well, we must keep hacking our way through. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I replied<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> that I didn’t pretend to be well-informed as to the commercial value of things, that now that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">he</rs>, as a dealer, told me that they were of no commercial value, I had no desire to contradict or question that, that for my part I attached more importance to the artistic than to the commercial value, and would rather immerse myself in nature than calculate prices. And that when I talked to him about the price and didn’t give him the things for nothing, that was because I, like everyone else, had my basic needs for food, accommodation, &amp;c., and saw it as a duty to ensure that I took care of these relatively minor matters. But that I didn’t want to force my work on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">His Hon.</rs> against his will, and was prepared to send him new drawings if he wanted, but was also prepared to accept the loss of his custom. I have little doubt, though, that my course of action will be viewed as ungrateful, rude and impertinent. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And I’ll be accused as follows, when it suits the purpose: ‘With your pretensions and obstinacy you behaved so ungratefully towards your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">uncle</rs> in Amsterdam, who had your best interests at heart and was so kind to you and helped you so much, that it’s your own fault’ &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, I really don’t know whether to laugh or weep at this sort of thing. I find it so typical. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Of course, the rich dealers are the good, honest, genuine, loyal, sensitive characters, and we poor devils who sit there drawing, whether out of doors, on the street, or in the studio, sometimes in the early morning, sometimes deep at night, sometimes in the heat of the sun, sometimes in the snow, we’re the people without sensitivity, with no understanding of practical matters, without ‘manners’ above all. Fine by me!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">uncle</rs> of mine in Amsterdam also informed me with considerable aplomb that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> was in fact a bad person.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> You will understand how much this has changed my opinion about <hi rend="italics">père</hi> Degroux. All I said to him, to which as yet he has given me no reply, the noble dealer, what I said to him was: ‘It seems to me much less a matter of <hi rend="italics">earning </hi>than of<hi rend="italics"> deserving</hi>.’ </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Anyway — I mention it to you as a way of opening the safety valve on the machine, otherwise I might remain bitter about the business, and my dearest wish is not to think about it any more and to forget it. But these people begin so kindly and manage to be so winning at first that you’re all the more amazed when you eventually see their true colours.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Adieu, thanks again, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written after the receipt of a letter from Uncle Cor which arrived on 6 June (<ref target="let237.xml">see letter 237</ref>). Assuming that the present letter was written before Van Gogh’s admission to hospital on 7 June (he informs Van Rappard about that in <ref target="let240.xml">letter 240</ref>), the most likely date for it is 6 June 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s visit <ref target="let231.xml">(231)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Second order for drawings from Uncle Cor <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For this loan, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let231.xml">see letter 231</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>According to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_742">Silvestre</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs> characterized the art of painting as follows: ‘Cette maîtresse jalouse qui veut avoir son homme tout entier’ (This jealous mistress who wants to have her man all to herself); see Silvestre 1878, p. 23, and Silvestre, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Histoire</hi>, p. 69. Moreover, Ralph Waldo Emerson wrote in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The conduct of life</hi> (1860 and 1876 [revised]): ‘Art is a jealous mistress, and, if a man have a genius for painting, poetry, music, architecture or philosophy, he makes a bad husband and an ill provider, and should be wise in season, and not fetter himself with duties which will embitter his days, and spoil him for his proper work.’ See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Essays and lectures</hi>. Ed. Joel Porte. New York 1983, p. 1004. Quoted again in slightly different phrasing in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let249.xml">letter 249</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh originally wrote ‘everything that’s ugly’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>But cf. 237, in which Vincent writes to Theo that he has not replied to the letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> and does not intend to do so.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh referred earlier to this discussion with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let211.xml">letters 211</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let228.xml">228</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    