<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Thursday, 8 June 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let237"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b228 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>237</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>206</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>237</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-06-08">on or about Thursday, 8 June 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0228" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0228" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000269_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Gemeente gasthuis (4<hi rend="super">e</hi> klasse. Zaal 6 n<hi rend="super">o</hi> 9)</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Brouwersgracht.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Als gij tegen ’t einde Junij mogelijk naar hier komt<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> vindt ge me hoop ik weer aan ’t werk doch nu op ’t moment ben ik in ’t gasthuis waar ik evenwel slechts 14 dagen ongeveer blijven zal<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik had al een week of 3 veel last gehad van slapeloosheid<c type="kk">/</c> binnenkoorts<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> &amp; pijn gevoeld bij ’t wateren. En nu blijkt het dat ik eigentlijk, maar in zeer ligten graad, datgene heb wat men “een druiper” noemt<c type="kp">_</c> Waarvoor ik nu hier stil te bed moet blijven<c type="kk">/</c> veel quinine pillen slikken en ook nu en dan inspuitingen krijg ’t zij met schoon water ’t zij met aluin water<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> dus zoo onschuldig als zijn kan. Waarom ge U ook hierover in ’t minst niet hoeft te verontrusten<c type="kp">_</c> alleen<c type="kk">/</c> gij weet met zoo iets moet men niet spotten en dadelijk er achter heen zitten omdat onachtzaam<c type="shy">-</c>heid er mee de zaak verouderen<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> en verergeren kan. Getuige Breitner die nu ook nog steeds hier ligt ofschoon in een andere zaal<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en waarschijnlijk gaat hij weldra weg – hij weet niet ik hier ben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Gij zult mij pleizier doen er maar niet over te spreken want de lui denken soms er iets heel ergs van<c type="kk">/</c> of door opgevoerde praatjes wordt het heel erg<c type="kk">/</c> alleen zeg ik U natuurlijk precies wat het is en hoeft gij ’t ook niet te verzwijgen als mogelijk iemand er U direkt naar vragen mogt en in geen geval hoeft gij het zwaar te tillen. Ik heb natuurlijkerwijs 14 dagen vooruit moeten betalen<c type="kk">/</c> f<c type="kp">_</c> 10.50 voor verpleegkosten. Tusschen de personen die voor de rekening der armenkas kosteloos verpleegd worden &amp; die welke zelf f<c type="kp">_</c> 10.50 betalen bestaat geen onderscheid wat voeding of behandeling betreft. Men ligt met 10 personen op een zaal en ik moet U zeggen dat de behandeling in alle opzigten heel best is. Ik verveel mij niet en de rust en flinke praktische geneeskundige behandeling doet mij goed.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als het U convenieert wees dan zoo goed tegen 20 Junij te zenden aan bovenstaand adres<c type="kk">/</c> doch <hi>niet</hi> per aanget. brief maar zonder den brief aan te teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> frs. 50. Gij weet 1 Junij ontving ik frs 100<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodoende ben ik dan in elk geval geborgen. Moet ik nog blijven<c type="kk">/</c> betaal ik bij en blijf nog en anders heb ik om weer mee voort te gaan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik ging liever weer werken over 14 dagen natuurlijk en zal over 14 dagen er naar snakken weer naar de duinen te gaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Sien komt bij mij op de bezoekdagen en houdt het oog op ’t atelier. Nu moet gij nog weten dat ik den dag voor ik naar hier ging nog een schrijven ontving van C.M<c type="kp">_</c> waarin hij een heele boel schrijft over “belangstelling” die hij voor mij heeft, en die<c type="kk">/</c> zegt hij<c type="kk">/</c> ook de Hr Tersteeg mij heeft getoond doch<c type="kk">/</c> gaat hij voort<c type="kk">/</c> hij vond het niet goed van mij ik zoo ondankbaar was geweest voor die belangstelling van H<c type="kp">_</c>G.T. Que soit<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik leg<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> hier nu waarlijk kalm en bedaard genoeg maar ik verzeker U Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik erg uit mijn humeur zou raken als een of ander persoon mij op nieuw zulk een soort van belangstelling kwam opdisschen als H.G.T. bij zekere gelegenheden. En als ik nadenk hoe Z.Ed<c type="kp">_</c> die belangstelling zoo ver dreef dat hij mij bij een opiumrooker durfde vergelijken dan verwondert het me nog dat ik hem toen niet van mijn kant mijn belangstelling getoond heb in den vorm van een: donder op.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Van opiumrooken gesproken – de comfort en luxe<c type="kk">/</c> de soort van glorie waarin H.G.T. zich beweegt en een tamelijke sterke doses vleijerij die de gaande en komende man hem mee brengt<c type="kk">/</c> dat zijn dingen die ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> zelf misschien nu en dan meer benevelen dan hij zich wel bewust is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Kortom met al zijn oppervlakkige fijnheid van vormen<c type="kk">/</c> met zijn oppervlakkig beschaafde manieren<c type="kk">/</c> zijne nette kleeren enz<c type="kp">_</c> enz<c type="kp">_</c> vindt ik ook bij nadenken er over<c type="kk">/</c> ook bij terugdenken er aan in ’t karakter van ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> iets <hi rend="italics">valschs</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Ik wenschte ’t zoo niet ware doch ik kan niet anders spreken. Dat ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> een knap man zij voor een oogenblik geheel en al niet in twijfel trekkende<c type="kk">/</c> blijft nog een andere kwestie op den voorgrond voor ik hem respecteer. Is hij een goed man? n<c type="kp">_</c>l. iemand die niet uit principe haat<c type="kk">/</c> rancune<c type="kk">/</c> chicane<c type="kk">/</c> sarcasme van binnen in zich expres opkweekt<c type="kp">_</c> Ziedaar de kwestie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb C.M. niet geantwoord op zijn laatsten brief noch zal het ook doen.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Dat ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> mij zegt dat hij ook later nog wel eens iets nemen zal<c type="kk">/</c> uit belangstelling zeker ook<c type="kk">/</c> apprecieer ik<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel vooral wanneer hij het meent<c type="kk">/</c> ’t welk van zelf blijken zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Te meer ben ik er niet rouwig om hier eens een paar dagen rustig te liggen omdat ik<c type="kk">/</c> in geval zulks mij noodig mogt zijn<c type="kk">/</c> van den dokter hier<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> eene officieele verklaring kan krijgen ik volstrekt niet iemand ben die naar Gheel<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> of onder curateele moet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En als dat niet genoeg is ook nog een<c type="kk">/</c> als ik er werk van maak<c type="kk">/</c> van den Professor direkteur van de inrigting voor kraamvrouwen te Leiden.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Maar misschien zijn die personen die het eventueel in den zin mogten krijgen om te verklaren dat <hi rend="italics">de familie</hi> of <hi rend="italics">de maatschappij</hi> er zooveel bij winnen zou als iemand als ik gek verklaard of onder curateele gesteld werd<c type="kk">/</c> wel zoo fameus groote lui dat zij in zulke dingen ’t veel beter weten dan b.v. de dokter van hier<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Enfin. Een brief van U zou mij natuurlijk wel pleizier doen dezer dagen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Sien maakt zich klaar te vertrekken<c type="kp">_</c> Ik denk veel aan haar<c type="kk">/</c> strak<ptr target="#note-t-d"/> wacht ik haar weer<c type="kp">_</c> Moge zij er maar behouden doorkomen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik heb er mij tegen verzet zoolang ik kon en nog doorgewerkt maar eindelijk begreep ik het urgent was een dokter te raadpleegen. Maar hij zei me van morgen nog ik er spoedig af zou zijn. Hebt gij de twee teekeningetjes nog gekregen.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">à dieu met een handdruk &amp; U toewenschende zooveel voorspoed als een mensch tegen kan<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik moet U nog eens zeggen dat het antecedent van <hi rend="italics">Gheel</hi><c type="kk">/</c> als wanneer men om <hi rend="italics">physieke</hi> redenen iets in den zin had in den trant van curateele tegen mij<c type="kk">/</c> het nu moeielijk maakt voor de familie ineens te veranderen van chapiter en ’t niet meer in ’t <hi rend="italics">physieke</hi> doch in ’t <hi rend="italics">finantieele</hi> te zoeken.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Zulke dingen kunnen geen steek houden. Nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop men zoover niet zal gaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Maar schrijf gij eens spoedig want ik verlang er naar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Gij begrijpt Theo<c type="kk">/</c> ik spreek met den geneesheer hier noch met den professor te Leiden over familiezaken – alleen omdat ik zelf onder behandeling van eerst- en Sien onder behandeling van laatstgenoemde is hoeft het mij maar een woord te kosten in geval van nood om het getuigenis dezer heeren te kunnen overstellen tegen die andere mogelijke verklaring van een paar personen waarvan gij spraakt.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Municipal hospital (4th class, Ward 6, no. 9)</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Brouwersgracht.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Should you come here towards the end of June,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I hope you’ll find me back at work, but at present I’m in hospital, although I’ll only be here for about a fortnight.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> For some 3 weeks I’d been suffering a good deal from sleeplessness and chronic fever, and felt pain on passing water. And now it turns out that I’ve got a very mild case of what’s known as ‘a dose of the clap’. So I have to stay quietly in bed, swallow a lot of quinine tablets and from time to time have instillations of pure water or alum water,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> thus as harmless as could be. There’s no reason for you to be in the least concerned about this, but as you know one has to take this sort of thing seriously and act immediately, because neglect can make it incurable or exacerbate matters. Take the case of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs>, who’s still here, though in another ward,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and will probably leave soon — he doesn’t know I’m here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’d be grateful if you didn’t mention this, because people sometimes think it’s terribly serious or make it sound serious by telling exaggerated tales. Of course I’m telling you exactly what it is, and you needn’t keep silent if someone asks you directly, and in any event you needn’t worry. Naturally I had to pay for a fortnight in advance, 10.50 guilders for nursing costs. There’s no difference in food or treatment between those whose nursing is paid for by poor relief and those who pay the 10.50 guilders themselves. There are 10 beds in a ward, and I must say that the treatment is very good in every respect. I’m not bored, and the rest and proper, practical medical treatment are doing me good. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If it’s convenient, be so good as to send around 20 June to the above address, but <hi>not</hi> by registered letter, 50 francs without registering the letter. As you know, I received 100 francs on 1 June, so I’m taken care of in any event. If I have to stay longer, I’ll pay the extra and stay on, and otherwise I’ll have enough to carry on with. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’d prefer to get back to work in a fortnight, of course, and I’ll be dying to go back to the dunes in a fortnight. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> comes to see me on visiting days and is keeping an eye on the studio. Now I must tell you that the day before I came here I received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> in which he writes a good deal about the ‘interest’ that he takes in me and which, he says, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> has shown, but, he continues, he didn’t approve of how ungrateful I was for H.G.T.’s interest. So be it. I’m lying here completely calmly and quietly now, but I assure you, Theo, that I would be put in a very bad mood if someone again dished me up with the same sort of interest as H.G.T. on certain occasions. And when I think how His Hon. took that interest to the point of daring to compare me to an opium smoker, I’m still amazed that for my part I didn’t show my interest by telling him to go to hell. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Talking of smoking opium, the comfort and luxury, the sort of glory in which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> moves and the fairly strong doses of flattery that his visitors bring for him — those are things that perhaps befuddle His Hon. now and again more than he realizes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In short, with all his superficially refined politeness, with his superficially civilized manners, his smart clothes and so on and so on, on consideration and also looking back on it, I find something <hi rend="italics">malicious</hi> in His Hon.’s character. I wish it weren’t so, but I can’t say otherwise. I don’t doubt for a moment that His Hon. is a clever man, but another question comes first before I can respect him: is he a good man? Namely someone who doesn’t deliberately and on principle cultivate hatred, rancour, bickering and sarcasm inside himself. That is the question.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I haven’t replied to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">C.M.</rs>’s last letter, nor shall I.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I appreciate His Hon.’s telling me that he’ll also take something else later, no doubt out of interest too, but especially if he means it, which time will tell. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Another reason for not regretting lying here quietly for a few days is that, should I need it, I can get an official statement from the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">doctor</rs> here<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> that I’m absolutely not the sort of person who should be sent to Geel<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> or made a ward of court. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And if that isn’t enough, I can also get another, if I make an effort, from the professor in charge of the lying-in clinic in Leiden.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But perhaps those people who might possibly get it into their heads to declare that <hi rend="italics">the family</hi> or <hi rend="italics">society</hi> would be so much better off if someone like me were to be declared mad or made a ward of court are so extraordinarily brilliant that in such cases they know far better than, for example, the doctor here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Anyway, a letter from you would of course give me great pleasure at the moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> is getting ready to leave. I think of her a great deal — I expect her again later. May she come through it safely. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I resisted as long as I could and carried on working, but in the end I realized I needed to see a doctor urgently. But he told me just this morning that I would soon be rid of it. Did you get the two little drawings?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Adieu with a handshake, and wishing you as much good fortune as anyone could deal with.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I must tell you again that the precedent of <hi rend="italics">Geel</hi>, at which time they were minded to make me a ward of court on <hi rend="italics">physical</hi> grounds, makes it difficult for the family suddenly to change their story now and look for <hi rend="italics">financial</hi> rather than <hi rend="italics">physical</hi> reasons.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Such arguments won’t hold water. Again, I hope they won’t go that far. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">But write soon, for I’m longing for a letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">You do understand, Theo, that I don’t discuss family matters with the doctor here or the professor in Leiden — but because I’m being treated by the former and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> by the latter, it will only take a word from me in the last resort to secure the testimony of these two gentlemen to set against any possible statements by a few people of which you spoke. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written after Van Gogh was admitted to hospital on 7 June 1882, but there is no concrete evidence for a precise date. Assuming that Van Gogh wanted to inform his brother about his situation fairly quickly, we date the letter to on or about Thursday, 8 June 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Breitner is in the hospital <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Strained relations with Tersteeg <ref target="let208.xml">(208)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Sien will give birth in Leiden <ref target="let224.xml">(224)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s fear of being made a ward of court <ref target="let227.xml">(227)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On 7 June Van Gogh had been admitted to the hospital where <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> was also a patient, the Municipal Hospital located on Zuidwal and Brouwersgracht. It was still often referred to by its old name of Burgergasthuis. His internal address while he was in hospital remained 4th Class, Ward 6, Bed 9, but after something over 14 days he was moved to a ward ‘without curtains’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let239.xml">see letter 239</ref>). Cf. also exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, p. 178 (n. 14).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo’s visit, which Vincent had been looking forward to since March, would eventually take place at the beginning of August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let252.xml">see letters 252</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let253.xml">253</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was to stay there a little longer, namely until 1 July. On admission he had 25 centimes according to the ‘Admissions Register’, which has been lost. Illustrated in Tralbaut 1968, pp. 14-15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘een aanhoudende koorts die het gestel langzaam ondermijnt’ (a persistent fever that gradually undermines the constitution).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The official diagnosis, as stated in the patients’ register, was ‘Gonorrhoea’; the method of treatment was ‘Injectiones c[um] Sol[utione] Sulph[atis] Zinc[icum]’. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2096">Ill. 2096</rs> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>, book no. 424, inv. no. 959).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>To be construed as: ‘Last too long to be able to be cured’; cf. the expression ‘een verouderde kwaal’. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> was treated in the 3rd class (the ward is not specified in the patients’ register). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2097">Ill. 2097</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Read: ‘lig’ (lie).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This contradicts <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let236.xml">letter 236</ref>, in which Van Gogh writes at length to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> about how he replied to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>’s reaction. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was treated by the assistant physician <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">Cornelis Anthonie Molenaar</rs> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>; on him Haeseker and Koch 1992, p. 41). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For the ‘Geel affair’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let185.xml">see letter 185</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_217">A.E. Simon Thomas</rs>, the doctor who treated <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let224.xml#n-4">see letter 224, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="d" xml:id="note-t-d">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘straks’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>These would have been <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2377">F 940 / JH 154</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>), which were sent on Saturday, 3 June (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">see letter 235</ref>). By ‘little drawings’ he is not referring to the format, but rather taking a fairly modest attitude – they measure 28.5 x 45 cm and 27 x 43.5 cm respectively.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>One could be made a ward of court on the grounds of insanity or wastefulness. It can be deduced from this remark that the Van Gogh family evidently intended to use Vincent’s financial incompetence as the basis for the procedure.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    