<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 6 and Friday, 7 July 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let245"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b235 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b236 V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>245</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>213</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>245</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-07-06">Thursday, 6 and Friday, 7 July 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0235" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0235" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000279_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0236" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000280_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000280_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0236" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000280_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000280_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Donderdag</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">’t Is nu den avond voor dat ik weer naar het gasthuis ga en ik weet niet wat zij daar zeggen zullen – misschien ben ik er maar heel kort<c type="kk">/</c> misschien komen ze weer met sondes en zal ik dagen lang rust moeten houden in mijn bed. Daarom schrijf ik nu ’thuis nog eens. Het is zoo stil en rustig nu hier in ’t atelier – het is reeds laat – alleen buiten stormt en regent het – dat maakt de kalmte binnen nog grooter. Wat wenschte ik, broer, dat ik U op dit stille uur eens hier had – wat zou ik U veel te wijzen hebben. Het atelier ziet er zoo echt uit dunkt mij – effen grijsbruin behangsel<c type="kk">/</c> geschrobde planken vloer, neteldoek op latten gespannen voor de ramen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> alles helder<c type="kp">_</c> En natuurlijk de studies aan den muur<c type="kk">/</c> een ezel aan iederen kant en een groote withouten werktafel. Dan sluit aan ’t atelier een soort alkoof waar de teekenplanken<c type="kk">/</c> portefeuilles<c type="kk">/</c> doozen<c type="kk">/</c> stokken &amp;c. staan &amp; waar ook al de prenten liggen. En in den hoek een kast met al de potjes en flesschen en verder al mijn boeken. Dan het huiskamertje met een tafel, eenige keukenstoelen<c type="kk">/</c> een petroleumstel<c type="kk">/</c> een grooten rieten leuningstoel voor de vrouw in ’t hoekje bij het raam dat op die U uit de teekening bekende werf en weilanden uitziet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en daarnaast een klein ijzer wiegje met een groen wiegekleed. Dat laatste meubel kan ik niet zonder emotie aanzien – want het is een sterke en magtige emotie die een mensch aangrijpt als men naast de vrouw die men liefheeft gezeten heeft met een kindje bij zich in ’t wiegje. En al is het in een gasthuis waar zij lag en ik bij haar zat – het is altijd die eeuwige poezie van den Kerstnacht met het kindje in den stal zooals de oude hollandsche schilders het hebben opgevat en Millet en Breton – – – dat licht in het donker – een helderheid midden in een donkeren nacht.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik heb dan ook de groote ets naar Rembrandt er boven gehangen<c type="kk">/</c> die twee vrouwen bij de wieg waarvan een bij een kaars uit den Bijbel leest terwijl de groote slagschaduws het heele vertrek in diep clair obscur brengen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb nog andere prenten daar opgehangen maar allen bijzonder mooie<c type="kk">/</c> de Christus consolator van Scheffer<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> een phot<c type="kp">_</c> naar Boughton<c type="kk">/</c> le Semeur en les becheurs van Millet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> le buisson van Ruysdael<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en prachtige groote houtgravures van Herkomer &amp; Frank Holl<c type="kk">/</c> de banc des pauvres van de Groux<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu dan<c type="kk">/</c> in het keukentje heb ik het allernoodigste maar zóó dat als de vrouw vóór mij beter mogt zijn zij alles wat onontbeerlijk is vinden kan en in 10 minuten wat te eten kan klaarmaken, enfin zóó dat zij zien kan er veel om haar gedacht is en zij komt in een huis met bloemen in ’t venster waar zij zitten zal. En boven op de groote zolder een groot ledekant voor haar en mij en het oude van mij voor het kind met al het beddegoed in orde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar gij moet nu niet denken dat ik dit alles in eens gekocht heb. Wij hebben al van den winter begonnen zachtjes aan een en ander aan te schaffen ofschoon ik toen niet wist hoe het loopen zou en waar wij teregt zouden komen. En nu is Goddank de uitkomst dat het nestje voor haar klaar is<c type="kk">/</c> na al haar pijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Haar moeder en ik hebben ons echter geweerd dezer dagen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral zij<c type="kp">_</c> En het moeielijkste was het beddegoed<c type="kk">/</c> alles zelf gemaakt of vermaakt – stroo gekocht<c type="kk">/</c> zeegras gekocht<c type="kk">/</c> grof linnen &amp;c. en zelf op zolder de bedden gevuld. Anders zou het te duur geworden zijn. En nu na afbetaling van mijn ouden huisbaas<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> heb ik nog f<c type="kp">_</c> 40 over na ’t geen gij mij gezonden hebt. Het is waar dat ik daar morgen f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 van in ’t gasthuis betalen moet doch daar heb ik dan ook 14 dagen mijn voeding en geneeskundige behandeling voor<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodat deze maand ofschoon daarin mijn heele verhuizing en installage valt en de terugkomst van Sien na haar bevalling met al wat dat meebrengt van wieg &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> ik toch toe zal komen zonder dat gij meer dan gewoonlijk zendt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">On est sûr de périr à part</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> on ne se sauve qu’ensemble</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> ik geloof dat dit woord waarheid is en ik grond er mijn leven op<c type="kk">/</c> zou dat eene vergissing zijn en een fout in de rekening.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zie broer, ik denk dezer dagen zoo bijzonder veel aan U, vooreerst omdat alles wat ik bezit<c type="kk">/</c> alles eigentlijk van U is, met mijn eigen levenslust en energie ook want nu kan ik mij door Uw hulp bewegen en voel ik mijn werkkracht vlot worden<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ook om eene andere reden denk ik veel aan U. Ik weet hoe nog voor korten tijd geleden ik t’huis kwam in een huis maar dat nog niet een eigentlijk ’t huis met al de emotie van nu was<c type="kk">/</c> waar twee groote leegtes mij aangaapten dag en nacht<c type="kp">_</c> Er was geen vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> er was geen kind<c type="kp">_</c>– Gevolgelijk minder leed geloof ik niet maar minder lief geloof ik wel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En op straat bleven regts en links die twee leegtes mij vergezellen<c type="kk">/</c> bij ’t werk en overal en altijd. Er was geen vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> er was geen kind.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Zie<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet niet of gij dat gevoel kent dat maakt dat wanneer men alleen is op sommige momenten<c type="kk">/</c> men een soort zucht of klagt voelt rijzen van binnen: Mijn God waar is mijn vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> mijn god waar is mijn kind – is dan alleenzijn leven?<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Als ik aan U denk dan meen ik mij niet te vergissen als ik geloof dat bij U misschien minder hartstogtelijk en zenuwachtig dan bij mij maar toch ook in zekere mate alligt iets van dienzelfden weemoed moet aanwezig zijn, op sommige momenten althans. En ik weet niet of gij het goed of niet goed van mij vind<c type="kk">/</c> juist of niet juist gezien<c type="kk">/</c> als ik U zeg dat ik wel eens zoo aan U denk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Dit echter geloof ik van U en dit weet ik ondanks mijn zenuwachtigheid van mij zelf<c type="kk">/</c> dat er in elk geval in Uw en in mijn karakter een basis is van sereniteit – sereniteit quand bien même en dat dus noch gij noch ik ongelukkig zijn<c type="kk">/</c> omdat 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>die sereniteit voortkomt daaruit dat wij ons vak en werk waarachtig en te regt lief hebben en de kunst eene groote plaats in onze gedachten inneemt en het leven interessant maakt. Dus wil ik U zeer zeker niet tot melankolie brengen maar wel door iets in Uw eigen gemoedsstemming mijn handelwijs en levensopvatting begrijpelijk maken. Ik denk nu eens aan Pa – zoudt gij denken dat Pa koel zou blijven en bezwaar zou vinden – bij een wieg<c type="kp">_</c>– Zie<c type="kk">/</c> een wieg is niet als iets anders – daar is geen verneukerij bij – en wat ook in ’t verleden van Sien zij – ik ken geen andere Sien dan die van dezen winter – dan die moeder uit het gasthuis wier hand de mijne drukte toen wij beiden onze oogen vochtig voelden worden toen wij keken naar het kindje waarvoor wij dezen winter getobd hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En hoor eens, entre nous soit dit – zonder preektoon<c type="kk">/</c> als er geen God is dan is er toch ergens een heel digte bij en men voelt Zijn tegenwoordigheid wel op zoo’n moment. Hetgeen te zeggen wel gelijk staat en ik voor mij gaarne verwisselen wil voor de rondborstige verklaring<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof in een God en dat het zijn wil is men leve niet alleen<c type="kk">/</c> maar met een vrouw en met een kind<c type="kk">/</c> als alles normaal wil zijn.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> En ’tgeen ik hoop is dat gij mijn handelwijs begrijpen zult en nemen voor ’tgeen zij is<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk natuurlijk en er niet in zien zult een verneuken of verneukt worden. En – kerel, als gij komt, en als ge kunt<c type="kk">/</c> kom spoedig kijken – zie dan net als ik in Sien een moeder en eene gewone huisvrouw en niets anders. Want dat is zij werkelijk en mijns inziens te beter omdat zij le revers de la medaille kent. Het laatst wat ik mij aangeschaft heb was een paar borden<c type="kk">/</c> vorken, lepels<c type="kk">/</c> messen – want noch Sien noch ik bezaten die tot nog toe – ik dacht<c type="kk">/</c> 3 personen dus 3 stel<c type="kk">/</c> maar toen dacht ik er bij – en nog een voor Theo of voor Pa als ze eens komen kijken<c type="kp">_</c>– Dus Uw plekje bij het raam en Uw plaats bij ons zijn open en wachten op U..... Dus, wil ik maar zeggen – gij komt immers zonder kwestie... en Pa ook. Dat gij tot heden er Pa en Moe niet over spraakt vind ik wijs en discreet van U – nu de bevalling achter den rug is komen de bloemen weer kijken – en – vóór nu was het beter Pa en Moe er niet in te mengen. Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> ik dacht het wel was de doornen voor mij zelf te houden en Pa en Moe alleen maar de roos te laten zien. Als dus de vrouw terug en ik beter ben wou ik er over spreken op de manier die ik U zeide – en gij kunt dunkt mij nu als zij U naar iets vragen wel iets los laten. adieu – wel te ruste<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vrijdag avond.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">bij mijn ingesloten brief van gisteren avond schrijf ik heden nog een woordje<c type="kp">_</c> En kan U melden ik bij den dokter in ’t gasthuis geweest ben en deze mij zeide ik nu ik mij dezer dagen vrij wel bevonden had niet hoefde terugkomen tenzij in geval het erger worden mogt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Dat ik ofschoon nog niet geheel normaal &amp; niet geheel zonder pijn<c type="kk">/</c> toch gedurende die dagen geregeld mijn water heb kwijt kunnen raken<c type="kk">/</c> is het bewijs het op den goeden weg blijft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik heb toen dadelijk dezen middag (niet aan den direkteur) aan den dokter die mij behandeld heeft<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> een teekening gestuurd als een kleine attentie. Het was een Scheveningsch breistertje<c type="kk">/</c> bij Mauve op ’t atelier gemaakt<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> &amp; eigentlijk de beste aquarel die ik had<c type="kk">/</c> ook vooral om reden Mauve er veegen in gezet had en er telkens bij gekomen om mij hier of daar attent op te maken terwijl ik aan den gang was. Als souvenir had ik ze wel graag behouden maar het was mij bij het heerlijk gevoel van beter worden behoefte een bewijs van erkentelijkheid te geven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Van Pa &amp; Moe ontving ik een brief heden en heb hun geschreven zoodra ik hoorde ik niet meer terug hoefde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Nu wou ik morgen wel eens een togtje naar Schevening maken met de tram &amp; op ’t strand wat teekenen.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Naar aanleiding van ZEd<c type="kp">_</c>’s bezoek heb ik ’t ook aan den Hr Tersteeg met een woordje geschreven ik er uit was en hem bedankt voor zijn onverwacht bezoek.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Zondag zou ik naar de vrouw willen gaan van wie ik een briefje heb zij gisteren voor ’t eerst een half uur mogt opstaan &amp; alles ook met het kindje goed ging.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik word nog bijzonder gaauw mat en vermoeid<c type="kk">/</c> wat komt omdat ik zoo lang mij heb moeten stil houden &amp; in bed blijven en dat is een gek gevoel. Maar in veel opzigten voel ik me wel en gezonder dan dezen winter. en ik gevoel mij zoo opgeruimd &amp; dankbaar voor veel dingen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik hoop dat gij dezer dagen nog eens een half uurtje vinden zult om eens te schrijven of gij het plan om ’t op die manier aan Pa &amp; Moe te vertellen goedkeurt. Maar eerst moet de vrouw wat aansterken want ze mag nu geen emotie van buiten hebben of in spanning zijn over een of ander vooreerst, <hi rend="italics">zeer</hi> <hi rend="italics">gedecideerd niet</hi>. Maar over een maand of een week of zes<c type="kk">/</c> naarmate het vordert met haar beterschap.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Zij heeft Pa gezien bij gelegenheid van zijn bezoek want het was ’t bezoekuur en zij zat beneden in den gang te wachten maar Pa kende haar natuurlijk niet.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Het is al laat &amp; ik wou morgen wat vroeg opstaan &amp; stilletjes met mijn teekengerij naar buiten gaan als of er niets was tusschen nu &amp; de vorige keer ik te Scheveningen in de duinen zat. Ik wou wel ’t mij lukte wat te maken voor Rappard.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">adieu Theo, wel te ruste, maar wat is het heerlijk weer in zijn gewone doen te komen. heb het goed &amp; voorspoed en wat ik U vooral in groote dosis toewensch dat is die bewuste sereniteit<c type="kp">_</c> Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">P.S. Die Emile Zola is een fameus artist<c type="kk">/</c> ik lees nu “le ventre de Paris”<c type="kk">/</c> het is alle<c type="shy">-</c>magtig knap.–<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Mijn adres is dus nu Schenkweg <hi rend="italics">136</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Thursday</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It’s now the evening before I go back to the hospital and I don’t know what they’ll say there — perhaps I’ll be there only briefly, perhaps they’ll use their probes again and I’ll have to rest in bed for several days. So I’m writing again from home. It’s so silent and peaceful now here in the studio — it’s already late — but outside a gale is blowing and it’s raining — that makes the calm inside all the greater. Brother, how I wish I had you here at this silent hour — how much I would have to show you. The studio looks so authentic, it seems to me: plain, grey-brown wallpaper, scrubbed floorboards, muslin fixed to laths in front of the windows,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> everything bright. And of course the studies on the wall, an easel on each side, and a big pine-wood work-table. Adjoining the studio is a sort of alcove where the drawing boards, portfolios, boxes, sticks, &amp;c. are, and also where all the prints lie. And in the corner a cupboard with all the little pots and bottles, and also all my books. Then the little living room with a table, some kitchen chairs, a paraffin stove, a big wicker armchair for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> in the little corner by the window overlooking the yard and meadows familiar to you from the drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and next to it a small iron cradle with a green coverlet. I can’t look at the last piece of furniture without emotion, for it’s a strong and powerful emotion that grips a person when one has sat beside the woman one loves with a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs> in the cradle near her. And even if it was a hospital where she lay and I sat with her, it’s always that eternal poetry of Christmas night with the baby in the manger as the old Dutch painters conceived of it, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Breton</rs> — — — that light in the darkness — a brightness in the midst of a dark night.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> So I’ve hung the big etching after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> above it — those two women beside the cradle, one reading from the Bible by the light of a candle, while the great cast shadows put the whole room in deep chiaroscuro.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve hung up other prints there as well, and all very beautiful: Christus Consolator by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Scheffer</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> a photo after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>, The sower and The diggers by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> The bush by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and splendid, big wood engravings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Frank Holl</rs> and The paupers’ pew by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now in the small kitchen I have the very basic necessities, but such that if the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> recovers before me she can find all the essentials and cook something in 10 minutes, in short so that she can see that she has been thought about a great deal, and she will enter a house with flowers in the window where she will sit. And upstairs in the large attic a big bedstead for her and me, and my old one for the child with all the bedding in good order. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But you mustn’t imagine that I bought all of this at once. In the winter we’d already begun buying one thing and another, bit by bit, even though I didn’t know at the time what course it would take or where we’d end up. And now, thank God, the outcome is that the little nest is ready for her after all her pain. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">However, her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> and I have made a huge effort in the last few days, she especially. The most difficult thing was the bedding — all made or altered by us — bought straw, bought eel-grass, ticking &amp;c. and stuffed the beds ourselves in the attic. Otherwise it would have been too expensive. And now, after paying off my old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">landlord</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I still have 40 guilders left after what you sent me. Admittedly, tomorrow I’ll have to pay 10 guilders of that to the hospital, but in return I’ll get food and medical treatment for a fortnight. So that this month, even though it includes my entire move and settling in and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>’s return after her confinement with all that that involved, such as a cradle &amp;c., I’ll get by without your having to send more than usual. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Alone, one is sure to perish, only with another can one be saved</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I believe this saying to be true and I’m basing my life on it; is it a mistake and a miscalculation? 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">You see, brother, I’ve thought of you so very much recently, first because everything I possess is really yours, including my zest for life and energy, because through your help I can move and I feel my capacity for work returning. But I also think of you often for another reason. I remember how I came home not long ago to a house that wasn’t yet a real home with all the emotion of now, where two great empty spaces stared at me day and night. There was no woman, there was no <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs>. I don’t believe there was less suffering as a result, but I do believe there was less love. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And on the street those two empty spaces accompanied me right and left, at work and everywhere and all the time. There was no woman, there was no <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">You see, I don’t know whether you know that feeling, when you’re alone at certain moments, that causes one to feel a kind of sigh or lament rising up from within: My God, where is my woman, my God, where is my child — is being alone living?<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> When I think of you, I believe I’m not mistaken in thinking that in you too, though perhaps less passionately and nervously than in me, the same sadness must be present in some measure, at least at times. And I don’t know whether you believe I’m right or wrong, seeing correctly or incorrectly, when I say that I sometimes think of you this way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">However, there’s something I believe about you and know about myself despite my nervousness — that in any event there is in your character and mine a basis of serenity, serenity in spite of everything, and that therefore neither you nor I is unhappy, because 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> that serenity arises from the fact that we truly and rightly love our occupation and work, and that art occupies a large place in our thoughts and makes life interesting. So it’s certainly not my intention to make you melancholy, but to help you understand my action and outlook on life through something in your own state of mind. I’m thinking now of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> — do you believe Pa would remain cool and still object — in front of a cradle? You see, a cradle isn’t like anything else — there’s no flim-flam involved — and whatever may have been in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>’s past, I know no other Sien than the one of this winter, than the mother from the hospital whose hand pressed mine when we both felt our eyes getting moist as we looked at the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">baby</rs> we were so anxious about this winter. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And just listen, between ourselves, without being preachy, it may be true that there is no God here, but there must be one not far off, and at such a moment one feels His presence. To say which is the same as saying — and for my part I would gladly exchange it for the straightforward statement — I believe in a God and that it is his will that man should not live alone but with a woman and with a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs>, if everything is to be normal.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> And what I hope is that you’ll understand my action and take it for what it is, namely natural, and not regard it as a case of deceiving or being deceived. And, old chap, when you come — and if you can, come and look soon — see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> as I do, as a mother and an ordinary housewife and nothing else. For that’s what she really is, and in my view all the better for having seen the other side of life. The latest things I’ve bought are a few plates, forks, spoons, knives, because neither Sien nor I had any until now. I thought 3 people so 3 sets, but then I thought — and another for Theo or for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> when they come to have a look. So your spot by the window and your place with us are open and waiting for you..... I only mean to say — after all, you will come without question... and Pa too. I think it was wise and discreet of you not to say anything to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> up to now. The birth is now behind us, the flowers come out again, and up to now it was better not to involve Pa and Ma. I mean, I thought it best to keep the thorns for myself and to show Pa and Ma only the rose. So when the woman is back and I’m better, I would like to talk about it in the way I described to you — and if they ask you, I believe that now you can say something. Adieu, sleep well.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Friday evening.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’m adding a word today to my enclosed letter of yesterday evening. And can tell you that I’ve been to the doctor at the hospital and he said that since I had been feeling quite well recently I needn’t come back unless it got worse. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">While not completely normal and not entirely free of pain, the fact that I was able to pass water regularly on those days is proof that things are on the mend. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">So, this afternoon I at once sent a drawing (not to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_779">director</rs>) as a small gesture to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">doctor</rs> who treated me.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> It was a Scheveningen woman knitting that I did at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s studio<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and in fact the best watercolour I had, largely because Mauve had added some touches and repeatedly came across to draw my attention to one point or another while I was working. I would have liked to keep it as a souvenir, but with that delightful feeling of getting better I wanted to show my gratitude. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> today and wrote to them as soon as I heard that I needn’t go back. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Now tomorrow I’d like to take a trip to Scheveningen by tram and do some drawing on the beach. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Following His Hon.’s visit, I also wrote a line to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> to say that I was out and to thank him for his unexpected visit. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I’d like to go to see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> on Sunday. I’ve had a note from her saying that yesterday she was allowed to get up for half an hour for the first time, and that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">baby</rs> is also doing well. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I still get tired and weary remarkably quickly, which comes from having had to stay quiet and lie in bed for so long, and that’s a strange feeling. But in many respects I feel well and healthier than last winter. And I feel in such good spirits and thankful for many things. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I hope you’ll be able to find half an hour one of these days to write and say whether you approve of my plan as to how to tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>. But first the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> must get stronger, because she mustn’t be subjected to any emotions from without now, or be tense about anything for the time being, <hi rend="italics">most decidedly not</hi>. But in a month or six weeks, depending on how she progresses. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">She saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> when he came because it was the visiting hour and she was sitting downstairs in the corridor waiting, but of course Pa didn’t know her.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">It’s already late and I wanted to get up early tomorrow and go out quietly with my drawing materials as if nothing had happened between now and the last time I was sitting in the dunes at Scheveningen. I would like to succeed in making something for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Adieu Theo, sleep well, how wonderful it is to be back in one’s normal routine. I wish you well and good fortune, and what I wish you above all in large measure is that serenity. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">P. S. That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs> is a superb artist. I’m now reading ‘Le ventre de Paris’, it’s mightily clever.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">So my address is now Schenkweg <hi rend="italics">136</hi>.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed ‘Donderdag’. In the letter Van Gogh says that next day he has to go to the hospital for a check-up <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>. This visit took place on Friday, 7 July (<ref target="let245.xml">see letter 245</ref>), so the present letter must date from Thursday, 6 July. Van Gogh’s remark that there is a fierce wind and rain is confirmed by the weather reports for that day (<hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi>).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">So on that Thursday Van Gogh wrote twice (cf. <ref target="let244.xml">letter 244</ref>). This second letter was not sent until the following day, because on Friday evening he added a sheet <ref target="#l-160">(l. 160)</ref>. On this Friday Van Gogh’s intention was to visit Sien in hospital on the following Sunday. Since she was discharged on Saturday, 15 July, he must have meant Sunday, 9 July, and the Friday on which the present letter was written was Friday, 7 July 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The second sheet was previously regarded as a separate letter. However, given Van Gogh’s wording ‘I’m adding a word today to my enclosed letter of yesterday evening’ <ref target="#l-162">(ll. 162-163)</ref>, the sheet is a continuation of the letter and must have been sent in the same envelope. </p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo <ref target="let237.xml">(237)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Sien has given birth in Leiden <ref target="let242.xml">(242)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This fabric of linen-like cotton served to filter the light. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Either <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>) or another, unknown drawing of the same subject (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml#n-2">see letter 235, n. 2</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Earlier in a similar context Van Gogh wrote: ‘In medio noctis vim suam lux exerit’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let133.xml">letter 133</ref>). We know of no <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> print with this inscription.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For this print after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1724"><hi rend="italics">Reading the Bible</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let037.xml#n-4">see letter 37, n. 4.</ref> Rembrandt is known as the great master of chiaroscuro. Cf. Fromentin 1902, chapter 13, pp. 350 ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For this print after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Scheffer</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1771"><hi rend="italics">Christus Consolator</hi></rs> , <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let085.xml#n-7">see letter 85, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
    
<p>For prints after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1888"><hi rend="italics">The sower</hi></rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1876"><hi rend="italics">The two diggers</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml#n-3">see letters 156, n. 3</ref> and  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let142.xml#n-18,">142, n. 18</ref>, respectively.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For this print after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Jacob van Ruisdael</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1717"><hi rend="italics">The bush</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let035.xml#n-5">see letter 35, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1880"><hi rend="italics">The paupers’ pew</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let148.xml#n-12">see letter 148, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">A.J. van der Drift</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Borrowed from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12"><hi rend="italics">La femme</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let189.xml#n-28">see letter 189, n. 28.</ref> See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-12">n. 12</ref> below.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Possibly a quotation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>In the sentence before the quotation (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-10">see n. 10</ref>) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> wrote in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12"><hi rend="italics">La femme</hi></ref>: ‘Nature has made life a threefold and unbreakable knot: man, woman and child’ (La nature a formé la vie d’un noeud triple et absolu: l’homme, la femme et l’enfant) (Michelet 1863, p. 67).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The director was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_779">Gerrit Pieter van Tienhoven</rs>; the physician in charge was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">Cornelis Anthonie Molenaar</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let237.xml">see letters 237</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let243.xml">243</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Scheveningen woman knitting</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2352">F 870 / JH 84</rs>); cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let192.xml#n-4">letter 192, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The suspicion on the part of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> that his unease during the visit was caused by the arrival of someone he was not supposed to meet was thus justified; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let239.xml#n-7">see letter 239, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_246"><hi rend="italics">Le ventre de Paris</hi></ref> (1873) is set mainly in ‘Les Halles’, the newly-built food markets of Paris. The leading character Florent is arrested soon after the coup d’état of 1851 and deported to Cayenne to do forced labour. He escapes and in 1858 returns to Paris, where he searches out his half-brother Quenu, who is married to Lisa Macquart. Florent is given a job as a salesman in their butcher’s shop. Having suffered years of injustice, he sets up a secret socialist society through which he naively plots against the state. His sister-in-law, the embodiment of the ‘petite-bourgeoisie’, discovers his plans and betrays him. After Florent has again been arrested, the neighbourhood is once more peaceful, and prosperous times lie ahead for the shop.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    