<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Wednesday, 19 July 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let248"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b239 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>248</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>217</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>249</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-07-19">Wednesday, 19 July 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0239 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0239 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000286_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0239 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000287_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000287_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0239 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000287_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000287_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ik kan niet genoeg het ontijdige bezoek van Tersteeg betreuren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het is mij een aanleiding om nog vóór Uw komst een paar dingen te bespreken die ik liever als gij hier waart zou behandeld hebben. Ik heb U gezegd dat ik Sien wil trouwen, en wel zoo spoedig mogelijk – let evenwel op dat ik vooral dit chapiter met U persoonlijk wenschte besproken te hebben ook voor &amp; aleer ik verder tot Pa iets zeg. Ik kan met U beter overweg, gij voelt de dingen juister dan al de anderen zamen en ik heb er iets aan als gij dit of dat zegt. Ook al zijn wij over een of ander ’t niet eens<c type="kk">/</c> er is tusschen U en mij altijd een middenweg te vinden omdat wij met sympathie &amp; bedaardheid spreken. Ik geloof ook dat als er niemand anders zich ongevraagd mee bemoeide het zich schikken zou in alle opzigten<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodra er echter kwestie van trouwen is vliegen de lui op met een haast en een lawaai van de andere wereld &amp; er is niet meer te redeneeren of een woord er tusschen te brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik wacht nu niet langer te schrijven over iets wat ik liever besproken had. Gij hebt over ’t trouwen gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> trouw haar niet &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> en gij dacht dat Sien mij voor den gek hield &amp;c. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Ik heb toen over een en ander geschreven dat ik dat zoo maar niet met U eens was &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Maar ik heb liever niet U zoo bepaald willen tegenspreken als het bij me op kwam omdat ik geloofde &amp; nog geloof dat met der tijd gij zelf veel van Sien zult gaan houden als ge haar meer kent en dan natuurlijk niet meer denken zult zij me verneukt of zoo iets.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Is dat eenmaal zoo ver<c type="kk">/</c> kunnen we eens weer over het trouwen praten dacht ik. Maar gij zult U dan ook wel herinneren dat in mijn latere brieven ik het daar niet zoo direkt meer over gehad heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Alleen ik heb toen in der tijd bepaald gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">er is een trouwbelofte tusschen haar &amp; mij</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en ik wil niet dat ge denken zult ik haar beschouwen wil als een maintenée of als iemand met wie ik een liaison zonder consequenties zou hebben. Nu kom ik er nog eens op terug: <hi rend="italics">die</hi> <hi rend="italics">trouwbelofte gegeven door haar aan mij</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> door</hi> <hi rend="italics">mij aan haar</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> van weerskanten van harte</hi> <hi rend="italics">en opregt</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> is mij heilig en zal mij heiliger</hi> <hi rend="italics">blijven dan iets anders</hi>.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Die trouwbelofte is tweeledig<c type="kk">/</c> n<c type="kp">_</c>l. eene belofte van burgerlijk trouwen – zoo spoedig de omstandigheden het toelaten<c type="kk">/</c> maar ten tweede is het eene belofte om ondertusschen van stonde af aan elkander te helpen<c type="kk">/</c> te steunen<c type="kk">/</c> lief te hebben als waren wij reeds getrouwd<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin door alles zamen te deelen<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>door geheel en al voor elkaar te leven en door niets ons van elkaar te laten brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Voor de familie nu is ’t burgerlijk trouwen waarschijnlijk de belangrijkste vraag. Die is voor haar &amp; mij wel belangrijk doch ondergeschikt evenwel aan het wezen der zaak<c type="kk">/</c> de liefde &amp; trouw tusschen haar &amp; mij zoo als die reeds bestaat en dagelijks aangroeit. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik wilde U wel voorstellen nu het heele chapiter van burgerlijk trouwen voor een onbepaalden tijd te laten rusten en b.v. uit te stellen er over te spreken tot op ’t oogenblik dat ik door verkoop van mijn werk s’maandelijks ± 150 francs verdien waardoor de hulp van U niet meer noodig zal zijn. Met <hi rend="italics">U</hi> maar met U alleen, wil ik dus dat wel afspreken dat we voorloopig vaststellen ik haar niet trouw – burgerlijk – vóór de zaken van het teekenen zoo ver gevorderd zijn dat ik onafhankelijk ben. Naarmate ik begin te verdienen stuurt gij gaandeweg minder en eindelijk als het geld van U geheel kan ophouden dan spreken we eens weer over het ook burgerlijk trouwen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Maar nu den tusschentijd – het zou ten eenemale absurd zijn mij na dezen heelen winter en vooral na alles wat in de laatste maanden gebeurd is te willen aftrekken of scheiden van haar. Wij zijn geketend en gehecht aan elkaar met een sterken band van opregte genegenheid.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Verder door de hulp die we wederkeerig elkaar verleenen<c type="kp">_</c> Want als ik ’t zoo mag zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> zij is mijn associée in ’t werk en meer<c type="kk">/</c> oneindig meer dan een gewoon model omdat zij voor ’t poseeren zoo gewillig en intelligent is dat ik ’t niet genoeg prijzen kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wij moeten dus voorloopig zoo kalm mogelijk de moeielijkheden van dag tot dag bestrijden<c type="kk">/</c> en hoop ik gij na ’t geen ik U nu gezegd heb nog wel met meer gerustheid de dingen beschouwen zult. Ge hebt van den winter b.v. van Heyerdahl beter dingen gehoord van me dan b.v. Tersteeg wel van mijn werk denkt.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik voel nu zooveel nieuwen lust in ’t werk dat ik alle hoop heb dezen herfst nog weer een eind op te schieten. Misschien tegen kerstmis<c type="kk">/</c> als dus ’t bewuste jaar om is<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> zal ik U kleine aquarellen zenden waarvan de laatste teekeningetjes<c type="kk">/</c> waar al wat bruin &amp; rood &amp; grijs in was<c type="kk">/</c> het begin waren.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> En ik voel soms grooten lust tot schilderen ook<c type="kk">/</c> erg grooten lust en ambitie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Vooral nu t’betere licht &amp; t’betere atelier er me van zelf weer op brengt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik mag nog niet zoo als ik zou willen van den dokter<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – ik ben nog zeer spoedig vermoeid maar dat komt teregt en dan – gaan we aan den gang met alle energie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik hoop nu alleen Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dat wat ik U zeg omtrent het trouwen U zien doet dat ik niet bepaald in alle dingen geheel mijn eigen zin wil hebben<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik wel voor zoo ver ik kan mij schikken wil naar wat gij denkt maar zie dan daarin ook ’t bewijs dat ik verdien gij mij vertrouwt en met mij schrijft over de verschillende dingen. Met de anderen kan ik niet overweg en met U kan ik praten &amp; schikken.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Wat ik wil is de behoudenis van ’t leven<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> van Sien &amp; haar twee kinderen. Ik wil niet dat zij weer terug zinke in dien afschuwelijken toestand van ziekte en misere waarin ik haar vond<c type="kk">/</c> waaruit zij voorloopig gered is. Dat heb ik aangepakt en dat moet ik voortzetten. Ik wil niet dat een oogenblik langer zij verlaten &amp; alleen zich behoeve te gevoelen<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil dat zij merke &amp; in alles zie dat ik een teere liefde voor haar heb en hart voor de kinderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En dat – wie ’t ook verkeerd vinden moge – gij zult het begrijpen en ’t mij niet willen verhinderen. Ik stel haar er boven op komen dan ook op Uw credit in zoover dat ik er mezelf de verdienste er aan niet toereken dan voor een klein deel. Ik ben maar ’t middel er toe geweest.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik behoud mij nu wel voor in ’t algemeen over trouwen<c type="kk">/</c> over kosten van een huishouden enz. als gij komt eens te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat ik geloof dat er kwesties zijn waarin gij U vergist maar dat is geheel in ’t vriend<c type="shy">-</c>schappelijke en dat heeft niet direkt betrek<c type="shy">-</c>king op het burgerlijk trouwen met Sien. Door dat een &amp; ander mij er toe dringt daar nu direkt over te schrijven verzoek ik alleen dat deze zaak blijve rusten tot den tijd dat ik meer verdien door direkte verkoop van mijn werk. Als gij komt zal ik U ook nog wel de redenen zeggen waarom ik veel liever direkt getrouwd was maar gij moet dat niet beschouwen als een verder aandringen van mij. Neen<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben bereid om zoo ver toe te geven als ik zeg uit eigen beweging en vrijwillig<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Wordt U over de zaak gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> mij dunkt gij kunt zeggen dat tusschen U en mij genoeg vertrouwelijkheid is dan dat gij van mij alle inlichtingen kunt krijgen maar dat gij het niet noodig oordeelt dat er over deze zaak gesproken wordt voor als nog. Zulke gesprekken als dat met Tersteeg zetten de vrouw en mij evenzeer meer achter uit dan de guurste noordewind<c type="kp">_</c> Zij moeten vermeden worden. Het geheel beter worden is ’t allereerste wat voor de hand ligt en het weer in staat komen om geregeld te werken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik zeg nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> het spijt me dat wat ik nu per brief zeg ik ’t U niet<c type="kk">/</c> terwijl gij persoonlijk tegenwoordig waart &amp; eerst de vrouw eens nader had leeren kennen<c type="kk">/</c> heb mondeling kunnen zeggen – dan kon ik er misschien nog meer bij zeggen om U te doen inzien dat ik niet onredelijk ben. Maar ook nu hoop ik dat gij niet lang wegblijft en in elk geval eens spoedig schrijft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">De vrouw zal met U spoedig op haar gemak zijn<c type="kk">/</c> weet dat maar voor zeker<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij zult trouwens haar ook niet op zoo’n manier opnemen &amp; uit de hoogte bekijken als H.G.T<c type="kp">_</c> gisteren deed.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Wees gij steeds ten volle verzekerd van haar en van mijn meest warme toegenegenheid &amp; ontvang in gedachten een handdruk en geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Wat ik ook nog wel eens bespreken zal met U is den toestand waarin ik haar vond &amp; dingen uit haar verleden. Het arme schepsel heeft het al bijzonder bar gehad. En toch is er in haar nog een levenslust en fijn gevoel dat niet verdoofd is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik zeg ook nog eens dat ik toch zoo bijzonder naar U verlang<c type="kk">/</c> afgescheiden van alles<c type="kk">/</c> omdat ik behoefte heb aan sympathie en aan warmte<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zou zoo graag eens met U loopen – <hi rend="italics">al is</hi> <hi rend="italics">[de] Rijswijksche molen er niet meer</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Enfin.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I cannot deplore <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>’s untimely visit enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It prompts me to discuss a few things before you come which I would rather have dealt with while you were here. I’ve told you that I want to marry <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>, and as soon as possible — note, though, that I especially wanted to discuss this matter with you in person and before I said anything to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>. I get on better with you, you sense things more correctly than all the others put together, and if you say something it’s useful to me. Even if we disagree about this or that, there’s always a middle way to be found between you and me, because we speak with sympathy and calmness. I also believe that if no one else interfered unasked, agreement could be reached in every respect. However, the minute that the issue of marriage is raised, people instantly fly into a temper and there’s an infernal outcry, and you can no longer reason with them or get a word in edgeways. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I shan’t wait any longer to write about something I would rather have discussed face to face. On the subject of marriage you said, don’t marry her, &amp;c., and you thought that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> was making a fool of me, &amp;c. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I wrote to you about a few thing at the time, saying that I didn’t agree with you, &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> But I didn’t want to argue with you as strongly as I felt, because I believed and still believe that in time you’ll come to care a great deal for Sien as you get to know her, and then, of course, will no longer imagine that she’s deceiving me or something like that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Once we’d got that far, I thought, we could talk about marriage again. But you will remember that in my later letters I didn’t speak of that so directly any more. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But I did say at that time <hi rend="italics">there is a promise of marriage between her and me</hi>, and I don’t want you to think that I regard her as a kept woman or as someone with whom I’m having an affair with no further consequences. Now I return to this point: <hi rend="italics">that promise of marriage given by her to me, by me to her, sincerely and honestly on both sides, is sacred to me, and will remain more sacred to me than anything else.</hi></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">This promise of marriage is twofold, namely a promise of civil marriage — as soon as circumstances permit – but secondly it’s a promise henceforth to help each other in the meantime, to support and cherish each other as if we were already married. In short, to share everything, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> to live entirely for each other, and not to let ourselves be separated by anything. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For the family the most important question is probably civil marriage. That’s important to her and me, but all the same secondary to the essence of the matter, the love and loyalty between her and me as it already exists and daily grows. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I want to propose that we let the whole subject of civil marriage rest for a while and, for example, postpone speaking about it until such time as I earn around 150 francs a month by selling my work, so that help from you is no longer required. Thus with YOU, but with you alone, I want to agree that for the time being I won’t marry her — in a civil marriage — until the drawing business is going so well that I’m independent. As soon as I begin to earn, you will gradually send less, and eventually, when you can stop sending money altogether, we’ll return to the question of civil marriage. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But now, as to the meantime — it would be quite absurd after this entire winter, and above all after everything that has happened in recent months, to want to detach or part me from her. We are chained and tied to each other by a strong bond of sincere affection.</p><pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"> And through the help we give each other. For, if I may put it this way, she’s my associate in the work and more, infinitely more than an ordinary model, because she’s so willing and intelligent in posing that I can’t praise her too much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"> So for the present we must combat the difficulties as calmly as possible day by day, and I hope that you’ll view things with greater peace of mind after what I’ve told you now. In the winter, for example, you heard better things about me from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs> than, for example, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>’s opinion of my work.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I now feel so much new pleasure in work that I have every hope of making good progress again this autumn. Perhaps towards Christmas, thus when the year in question is up,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’ll send you small watercolours, which had their beginnings in the last small drawings that already had some brown and red and grey in them.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And sometimes I feel a strong desire to paint as well, a very strong desire and ambition.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Especially now that the better light and the better studio automatically put the idea in my mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"> The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">doctor</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> won’t yet let me do as I would wish — I still tire very quickly, but that will pass and then... we can set to work full of energy.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"> I just hope, Theo, that what I’ve said about marriage will make you see that I don’t demand to have my own way in everything, that I’ll go along with what you think as far as I can, but see this also as proof that I deserve to have your trust and to have you write to me about various things. I can’t get on with the others, and with you I can talk and reach a compromise.</p><pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"> What I want is to preserve the lives<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> and her two <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>. I don’t want her to sink back into that terrible state of illness and misery in which I found her and from which she has been rescued for the time being. I undertook that and I must persist with it. I don’t want her to feel abandoned and alone for a moment longer, I want her to realize and to see in everything that I feel a tender love for her and hold her children dear.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"> And that — no matter who thinks it wrong — you will understand and not try to stop me. I accordingly give you the credit for her recovery, in that I attribute only a small part to myself. I was merely the means.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"> Now I reserve the right to raise the subjects of marriage in general, the cost of running a home and so on when you come, especially because I believe there are points you’re mistaken about, but that’s entirely in a spirit of friendship and has no direct relation to civil marriage to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>. Since one thing and another force me to write about that straightaway, I ask only that this matter be allowed to rest until such time as I earn more through selling my work straightaway. When you come I’ll tell you the reasons why I would much prefer to marry straightaway, but you mustn’t see that as further insistence on my part. No, I’m ready to concede as much as I’ve said of my own accord and voluntarily. </p><pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19"> If you’re asked about the matter, I believe you can say that there’s enough trust between you and me for you to get full information from me, but that you don’t consider it necessary to discuss the matter for the time being. Conversations like the one with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> put the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and me further back than the cruellest north wind. They must be avoided. What comes first is full recovery and being able to start regular work again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"> I repeat. I regret I haven’t been able to say to you face to face — in your presence and after you had got to know the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> better — what I say now by letter. Then I might have been able to say more to make you see that I’m not being unreasonable. But even so, I hope you won’t stay away long, and will write soon in any case.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> Rest assured, the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> will soon be at ease with you. You, after all, won’t observe her and look down on her the way <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> did yesterday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"> Rest assured of her and my warmest affection, and accept in thought a handshake, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">What I’ll also discuss with you sometime is the state in which I found <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> and things from her past. The poor creature has suffered appallingly. And yet there’s still a zest for life and sensitivity in her that hasn’t been extinguished. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I also repeat that I long for you so much, isolated from everything and everyone else, because I need sympathy and warmth. I would so much like to take a walk with you — <hi rend="italics">even though the Rijswijk mill isn’t there any more</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Oh well. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written one day after H.G. Tersteeg’s visit <ref target="#l-186">(l. 186)</ref>. Since that took place on 18 July (<ref target="let247.xml">see letter 247</ref>), the letter dates from Wednesday, 19 July 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Disagreeable visit by Tersteeg <ref target="let247.xml">(247)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo <ref target="let237.xml">(237)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On this, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let225.xml">see letters 225</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let227.xml">227</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs> had been sympathetic towards Van Gogh’s work; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let222.xml">see letter 222</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This must refer to the plan, known to Theo, to make something saleable within a year (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let205.xml">see letter 205</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2377">F 940 / JH 154</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>): cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let246.xml#n-7">letter 246, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was treated by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_151">C.A. Molenaar</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let237.xml#n-7">see letter 237, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 45:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Vincent mentions this location several times. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let011.xml#n-15">See letter 11, n. 15.</ref> It was not true that the Laak mill – or another mill, such as the popular Oude Koren mill at Hoornbrug at the end of the Trekvliet or the Broeksloot mill – had disappeared. There were plans in 1882, however, to replace the Laak mill by a steam pumping station. These plans came to nothing, but modifications were made to the mill instead. It may be that Van Gogh saw this activity as a sign of impending demolition. Another possibility is that he means that the café was (temporarily) closed, possibly because of this work. At this time Van Gogh painted a watercolour of the underside of this mill (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Archief Rijswijk</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Archief Delftland</hi>; see also exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 34, 36-37).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    