<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 21 July 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let249"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b240 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>249</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>218</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>250</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-07-21">on or about Friday, 21 July 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0240" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0240" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000288_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste Broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Het is reeds laat maar toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou U nog eens schrijven<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij zijt niet hier – toch heb ik behoefte aan U &amp; is het mij als waren we soms niet ver van elkaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb vandaag iets met mezelf afgesproken, dat is mijn ongesteldheid of liever de restes er van te beschouwen als niet bestaande. Er is genoeg tijd verloren<c type="kk">/</c> het werk moet worden doorgezet<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dus wel of niet wel<c type="kk">/</c> ik ga weer teekenen geregeld van s’morgens tot s’avonds. Ik wil niet dat iemand me weer kan zeggen “o dat zijn maar oude teekeningen.”<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik heb een studie geteekend van het kinderwiegje van daag met veegen kleur er in.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Verder ben ik ook doende aan een dito als die weilanden welke ik U ’t laatst zond.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Mijn handen zijn wat te blank geworden naar mijn zin maar wat kan ik er aan doen. Ik zal weer buiten gaan ook<c type="kk">/</c> het kan me minder scheelen dat het me mogelijk eens opbreekt dan dat ik langer van ’t werk afblijf. De kunst is jaloersch<c type="kk">/</c> zij wil niet dat men ongesteldheid stelt boven haar.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Dus ik geef haar haar zin. Gij zult dus hoop ik binnen kort wel weer eens een paar redelijken krijgen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Zulken als ik <hi rend="italics">mogen</hi> eigentlijk niet ziek zijn. Gij moet goed begrijpen hoe ik de kunst beschouw. Om te komen tot het waarachtige moet men lang &amp; veel werken<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat ik wil &amp; mij ten doel stel is bliksems moeielijk en toch geloof ik niet dat ik te hoog mik.– Ik wil teekeningen maken die sommige menschen <hi rend="italics">treffen</hi>. Sorrow<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> is een klein begin – misschien is zoo’n klein landschapje als de laan v<c type="kp">_</c> Meerdervoort<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> de Rijswijksche weilanden<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> de Scharrendroogerij<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ook een klein begin. Daarin is ten minste iets direkt uit mijn eigen gemoed.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Hetzij in figuur hetzij in landschap zou ik wel willen uitdrukken niet iets sentimenteel weemoedigs doch ernstige smart<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Enfin ik wil ’t zoo ver brengen dat men zegt van mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> die man voelt diep en die man voelt fijn. Ondanks mijn zoogenaamde grofheid – begrijpt ge – misschien juist daarom. Het lijkt nu nog pretentieus om zoo te spreken maar dat is dan ook de reden waarom ik er kracht achter wil zetten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat ben ik in ’t oog van de meesten – een nulliteit of een zonderling of een onaangenaam mensch – iemand die in de maatschappij geen positie heeft of hebben zal<c type="kk">/</c> enfin wat minder dan de minsten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Goed – gesteld dat alles ware precies zoo<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik door mijn werk eens willen toonen wat er zit in ’t hart van zoo’n zonderling<c type="kk">/</c> van zoo’n niemand.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dit is mijn ambitie die minder gegrond is op wrevel dan op liefde malgré tout<c type="kk">/</c> meer gegrond op een gevoel van sereniteit dan op hartstogt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Al is het dat ik dikwijls in de beroerdigheid zit toch is er binnen in mij een kalme<c type="kk">/</c> reine harmonie en muziek. In het armste huisje<c type="kk">/</c> in het smerigste hoekje zie ik schilderijen of teekeningen<c type="kp">_</c> En als met onweerstaanbaren aandrang gaat mijn geest die rigting uit<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Hoe langer hoe meer gaan andere dingen er uit en hoe meer zij er uitgaan hoe sneller wordt mijn blik om het schilderachtige te zien. De kunst vraagt een hardnekkig werken<c type="kk">/</c> een werken ondanks alles en een altijd doorgaande observatie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Met hardnekkig bedoel ik vooreerst een gedurigen arbeid maar ook het niet loslaten van zijn opvatting op ’t zeggen van dezen of genen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb wel hoop broer<c type="kk">/</c> dat over eenige jaren en ook zelfs reeds nu zoo gaandeweg gij zulke dingen van mij zien zult als U eenige satisfactie geven zullen voor Uwe opofferingen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik heb in den laatsten tijd al bijzonder weinig conversatie gehad met schilders. Ik heb mij daar niet slecht bij bevonden<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is niet de taal van de schilders zoozeer als de taal van de natuur waar men naar luisteren moet.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ik kan me nu beter begrijpen dan ruim een half jaar geleden waarom Mauve zei: praat me toch niet over Dupré<c type="kk">/</c> praat me liever van dien slootkant, of zoo iets<c type="kp">_</c> Dat schijnt wel bar en toch is ’t volkomen juist<c type="kp">_</c> Het voelen van de dingen zelf<c type="kk">/</c> van de werkelijkheid<c type="kk">/</c> is van meer belang dan het voelen van schilderijen, althans het is vruchtbaarder en meer leven<c type="shy">-</c>wekkend.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Omdat ik nu zoo’n breed<c type="kk">/</c> zoo’n ruim gevoel heb van de kunst en van het leven zelf<c type="kk">/</c> waar de kunst de essence van is ook<c type="kk">/</c> klinkt het me zoo schril en zoo valsch als er lui zijn die maar jagen zooals Tersteeg.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik voor mij vind toch in veel moderne schilderijen een eigenaardig charme dat de ouden niet hebben. Voor mij is een van de hoogste en nobelste uitdrukkingen van kunst altijd de Engelsche<c type="kk">/</c> b.v<c type="kp">_</c> Millais en Herkomer en Frank Holl. Wat ik zeggen wil met betrekking tot ’t verschil tusschen oude kunst &amp; hedendaagsche is – misschien zijn de nieuwen meer denkers<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Er is nòg een groot onderscheid in sentiment tusschen de Chill October van Millais<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en de bleekerijen van Overveen van Ruysdael<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> b.v. En evenzeer tusschen de Irish emigrants van Holl<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en de vrouwen die in den Bijbel lezen van Rembrandt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Rembrandt &amp; Ruysdael zijn subliem en voor ons evenzeer als voor hun tijdgenooten maar er is iets in de modernen dat meer persoonlijk intiem bij ons ’thuiskomt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Zoo is ’t met de houtsneden van Swain &amp; die van de oude duitsche meesters eveneens<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Het was dan ook een vergissing toen de modernen eenige jaren geleden een rage hadden om de ouden te imiteeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Daarom vind ik zoo juist wat vader Millet zegt<c type="kk">/</c> Il me semble absurde que les hommes veuillent paraître autre chose que ce qu’ils sont.–<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Dat schijnt maar een gewoon woord en toch is het peilloos diep als een oceaan en ik voor mij houd het er voor men wel doet het in alles ter harte te nemen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik wou U maar eens zeggen dat het werk weer geregeld zijn gang zal gaan en moet gaan quand même – en ik wou er nog eens bij zeggen ik zoo naar een brief verlang en verder U wel te ruste wenschen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Denk s.v.p. aan het <hi rend="italics">dikke</hi> Ingres als ge kunt<c type="kk">/</c> ingesloten nog een staaltje<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Van het dunne ben ik nog voorzien<c type="kp">_</c> Op het <hi rend="italics">dikke Ingres</hi> kan ik wasschen met aquarel<c type="kk">/</c> op ’t Sans fin b.v<c type="kp">_</c> wordt het altijd troebel zonder dat zulks geheel mijn schuld is.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik zal ’t wiegje hoop ik nog wel honderd keer teekenen behalve die van van daag. met <hi rend="italics">hardnekkigheid</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear Brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">It’s already late, but I wanted to write to you again. You aren’t here, yet I’m in need of you, and it seems to me as if we aren’t far apart sometimes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Today I made an agreement with myself, which was to regard my illness, or rather what’s left of it, as non-existent. Enough time has been lost, the work must be carried on. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">So, well or not well, I’m going to draw again regularly from morning till evening. I don’t want anyone else to be able to say, ‘Oh, those are only old drawings.’<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’ve drawn a study of the cradle today with touches of colour in it.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’m also working on a ditto like the meadows I recently sent you.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">My hands have become rather whiter than I care for, but what can I do about it? I’ll also go outdoors again. It matters less to me that it may strike me down than that I’m kept longer from my work. Art is jealous; she won’t allow illness to be placed above her.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> So I’ll let her have her way. I hope, therefore, that you’ll soon have a few reasonable ones. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">People like me aren’t really <hi rend="italics">allowed</hi> to be ill. You must really understand how I regard art. One must work long and hard to arrive at the truthful. What I want and set as my goal is damned difficult, and yet I don’t believe I’m aiming too high. I want to make drawings that <hi rend="italics">move </hi>some people. Sorrow<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> is a small beginning — perhaps small landscapes like the Laan van Meerdervoort,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> the Rijswijk meadows<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and the Fish-drying barn<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> are also small beginnings. At least they contain something straight from my own feelings. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Whether in figures or in landscapes, I would like to express not something sentimentally melancholic but deep sorrow. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In short, I want to reach the point where people say of my work, that man feels deeply and that man feels subtly. Despite my so-called coarseness — you understand — perhaps precisely because of it. It seems pretentious to talk like this now, but that’s why I want to push on.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What am I in the eyes of most people? A nonentity or an oddity or a disagreeable person — someone who has and will have no position in society, in short a little lower than the lowest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Very well — assuming that everything is indeed like that, then through my work I’d like to show what there is in the heart of such an oddity, such a nobody. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This is my ambition, which is based less on resentment than on love in spite of everything, based more on a feeling of serenity than on passion. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Even though I’m often in a mess, inside me there’s still a calm, pure harmony and music. In the poorest little house, in the filthiest corner, I see paintings or drawings. And my mind turns in that direction as if with an irresistible urge. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> As time passes, other things are increasingly excluded, and the more they are the faster my eyes see the picturesque. Art demands persistent work, work in spite of everything, and unceasing observation. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">By persistent I mean in the first place continued labour, but also not abandoning your approach because of what someone else says. I have hopes, brother, that in a few years, and even now already, you’ll gradually see things by me that will give you some recompense for your sacrifices. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’ve had very little conversation with painters lately. I felt none the worse for that. It isn’t the language of painters one ought to listen to but the language of nature.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I can now understand, better than six months ago or more, why <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> said: don’t talk to me about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Dupré</rs>, talk to me instead about the side of that ditch, or something like that. It sounds crude and yet it’s perfectly correct. Feeling things themselves, reality, is more important than feeling paintings, at least more productive and life-giving. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Because I now have such a broad, such a large sense of art and of life itself, of which art is the essence, it sounds to me so shrill and false when there are people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> who are always on the hunt.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">For my part I find a peculiar charm in many modern paintings that the old ones don’t have. For me one of the highest and noblest expressions of art is always that of the English, for instance <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Frank Holl</rs>. What I mean to say as regards the difference between old and contemporary art is: perhaps the new artists are deeper thinkers.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">There’s another great difference: in sentiment, between Chill October by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and the Overveen bleaching grounds by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> for example. And equally between the Irish emigrants by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Holl</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and the women reading the Bible by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs> are sublime, for us as much as for their contemporaries, but there’s something in the moderns that strikes us as more personally intimate. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">That’s how it is with the woodcuts by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1382">Swain</rs>, and those by the old German masters too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">So it was a mistake a few years ago when there was a vogue among the moderns for imitating the old masters. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">This is why I think what <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> says is so right: I think it absurd that people want to appear to be something other than they are.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> That seems to be an unremarkable observation and yet it’s as unfathomably deep as the ocean, and I for one think it advisable to take it to heart in all things. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I just wanted to tell you that regular work will and must be resumed, come what may — and I want to add that I’m longing so much for a letter from you, and also to wish you good-night.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Please remember the <hi rend="italics">thick </hi>Ingres if you can, a sample is enclosed.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I still have enough of the thin. I can wash in watercolour on the <hi rend="italics">thick Ingres</hi>; on the <hi rend="italics">sans fin</hi>, for example, it always gets muddy without it being entirely my fault.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I’ll draw the cradle, I hope, a hundred times apart from the one today. With <hi rend="italics">persistence</hi>. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In its content <ref target="let249.xml">letter 249</ref> follows on from <ref target="let247.xml">247</ref> and <ref target="let248.xml">248</ref> (the last dates from Wednesday, 19 July), because Van Gogh returns to an earlier comment by Tersteeg (see <ref target="#l-12">ll. 12-13</ref>). It precedes <ref target="let250.xml">letter 250</ref>, which dates from Sunday, 23 July and in which it is said that the present letter must have crossed with a letter from Theo. For this reason <ref target="let249.xml">letter 249</ref> may be dated to on or about Friday, 21 July 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo <ref target="let237.xml">(237)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>A reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>’s remark as noted in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let247.xml">letter 247</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 it was assumed that <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Child in a cradle by the stove</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_276">F - / JH 155</rs>) was also sent. However, Van Gogh talks about touches of colour, but there are none to be seen – the possibility that they have disappeared over time cannot be ruled out.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>‘The meadows’ refers to one of the views from Van Gogh’s house. Around this time he was working on <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Rooftops</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2378">F 943 / JH 156</rs>), which he describes in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let250.xml">letter 250</ref> and of which he would send a letter sketch in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let251.xml">letter 251</ref>. The drawing of the meadows that Vincent ‘recently’ sent to Theo was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">See letter 235</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For this pronouncement, known from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_68">Emerson</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let236.xml#n-2">see letter 236, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
      
<p>There were four versions of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrow</hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let216.xml#n-3">see letters 216, n. 3</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let222.xml#n-1">222, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This drawing of vegetable gardens in Laan van Meerdervoort, mentioned earlier in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let218.xml">letters 218</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let222.xml">222</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let231.xml">231</ref>, is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The Rijswijk meadows can be seen in the background of several drawings: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2375">F 939 / JH 150</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Rooftops</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2378">F 943 / JH 156</rs>); Theo probably had the second (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-3">n. 3</ref> above).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2377">F 940 / JH 154</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">see letter 235</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Given what follows, this idea is borrowed from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This remark may be based on a passage in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Thomas Carlyle</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_197"><hi rend="italics">Sartor resartus</hi></ref>. See Dorn in exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, pp. 33, 48 (n. 13). Van Gogh does not mention <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sartor resartus</hi> until March 1883, but he already knew the book in 1875, when he quoted from it in a poetry album (Pabst 1988, p. 25).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs>’ <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1839"><hi rend="italics">Chill October</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let122.xml#n-19">see letter 122, n. 19.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Jacob van Ruisdael</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1671"><hi rend="italics">View of Haarlem with bleaching grounds</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let037.xml#n-3">see letter 37, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh may be referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Holl</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1906"><hi rend="italics">‘Gone’ – Euston station</hi></rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1027">FitzGerald</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1907"><hi rend="italics">Irish emigrants leaving Queenstown harbour</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let199.xml#n-9">see letter 199, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1724"><hi rend="italics">Reading the Bible</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let037.xml#n-4">see letter 37, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>This observation does not occur in exactly this form in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>’s book about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, but the picture of him that emerges is that of a sincere and modest artist, who does not pretend to be other than he is. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had already asked for the thick Ingres in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let243.xml">letter 243</ref>. He had sent a sample then too.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    