<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 17 September 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let264"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b253 a V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>264</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>231</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>265</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-09-17">Sunday, 17 September 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0253 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000310_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000310_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0253 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000310_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000310_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">De weken gaan snel om – en wij hebben alweer Zondag<c type="kp">_</c> Was nog al eens op Schevening dezer dagen en trof op een avond heel aardig het aankomen van een pink. Bij het monument<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> staat een planken huisje waar een kerel op den uitkijk zit<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodra de pink duidelijk zigtbaar naderde kwam de kerel te voorschijn met een groote blaauwe vlag &amp; gevolgd door eene bende klein grut van kinderen die hem niet tot de knieën reikten. Het was blijkbaar een groot pleizier voor hun om bij den man met de vlag te staan en zeker in hun verbeelding zoodoende mee te helpen om de pink te doen arriveeren. Een paar minuten nadat de man gewaaid had met zijn vlag kwam een kerel op een oud paard er bij die ’t anker moest gaan halen. Daarna voegden zich bij de groep verschillende mannen en vrouwen – ook moeders met kinderen – om de equipage te ontvangen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Toen de pink digt genoeg bij was ging de kerel te paard in zee en kwam terug met het anker.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Daarna werden de mannen op den rug van kerels met hooge waterlaarzen aan ’t strand gebragt en was ’t een heel lawaai van verwelkoming bij iederen aankomeling.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Toen ze er allen waren marcheerde de kudde naar huis als een troep schapen of een karavaan met de kerel op den kameel<c type="kk">/</c> ik bedoel op het paard<c type="kk">/</c> er als een hooge schim boven uitstekende.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Natuurlijk heb ik met al mijn attentie de verschillende incidenten trachten te schetsen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Heb er ook iets van geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk het groepje dat ik hierbij heb gekrabbeld.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dan schilderde ik nog een studie van eene marine<c type="kk">/</c> niets dan een stukje zand<c type="kk">/</c> zee<c type="kk">/</c> lucht<c type="kk">/</c> grijs en eenzaam<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> ik heb wel eens behoefte aan die stilte – waar niets is als de grijze zee – met een enkele zeevogel. maar anders<c type="kk">/</c> geen andere stem is als het ruischen van de golven. Het is om mij eens op te frisschen van het lawaai van de Geest of de aardappelmarkt. Verder heb ik deze week meest gewerkt aan schetsen van aquarellen. De groote van de bank<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> heb ik ook een eind verder gebragt en dan verder er bij eene schets van vrouwen in den tuin van ’t gasthuis<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en een stuk van de Geest.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ge ziet aan bijgaande krabbeling<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> wat mijn zoeken is<c type="kp">_</c> Van die groepen volk die ’t een of ander doen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar wat is het moeielijk daar leven en beweging in te krijgen en de figuren op hun plaats en van elkaar af te krijgen. Het is dat groote vraagstuk – <hi rend="italics">moutonner</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> groepen figuren die<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon een geheel vormende<c type="kk">/</c> van boven met de koppen of schouders den een over den ander heen komen kijken terwijl op den voorgrond de beenen der eerste figuren zich krachtig afteekenen en hooger op de rokken en broekspijpen weer een soort warreboel vormen waar toch nog teekening in zit. Dan regts en links<c type="kk">/</c> naarmate de plaats van het oogpunt<c type="kk">/</c> de meerdere uitbreiding of verkorting van de kanten. Qua compositie baseeren zich alle mogelijke scenes met figuren<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij eene markt<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij ’t aankomen van een schuit<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij een troep volk bij de gaarkeuken – in de wachtkamer<c type="kk">/</c> het gasthuis<c type="kk">/</c> de bank van leening<c type="kk">/</c> de groepen op straat<c type="kk">/</c> pratend of wandelend<c type="kk">/</c> zich op dat zelfde principe van de kudde schapen waar zeker het woord moutonner van daan komt – en komt het alles neer op dezelfde kwesties van licht en bruin en perspectief. Het effekt van de kastanjeboomen dat gij in Uw laatsten brief beschrijft, is hier ook, zoo als ge aan de teekening van het bankje zult bemerkt hebben – alleen hier ziet men maar heel weinig van die nieuwe groene blaadjes meer ofschoon eenigen tijd geleden ik ’t ook opmerkte – doch hier zijn ze door ’t menigvuldige stormweer verlept. We zullen hier spoedig reeds misschien het eigentlijke algemeene vallen van de blaren krijgen, het is dan vooral dat ik nog veel studies van het bosch hoop te schilderen. En van het strand niet minder, want ofschoon daar geen effekten van herfstbladeren zijn zoo doet wel het eigenaardige licht van herfstavonden zijne werking en is het er als overal in dezen tijd dubbel mooi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">Ik zit er een beetje in met de verf</hi> en met een en ander – maar ge weet er alles van – ik kan op verschillende manier mijn werk varieeren en er is en blijft zoo eeuwig veel te teekenen. Want – dat groepje volk van bijgaand krabbeltje varieert tot in ’t oneindige en vereischt ontelbare aparte studies en krabbels van afzonderlijke figuurtjes die men als in de vlugt op straat moet opvangen. Op die wijs moet er langzamerhand karakter en beteekenis in komen. Zoo heb ik onlangs een studie geteekend van heeren en dames op het strand<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> – een gescharrel van wandelaars. Ik zou het altijd aardig vinden als ik vroeger of later na nog meer of nog minder moeite teekeningen voor illustratie kon leveren. Welligt vloeit het een uit het ander voort. Voortwerken is de kwestie<c type="kp">_</c> Van harte hoop ik het U goed gaat en zeer recomandeer ik mij voor alle nieuws omtrent U zelf en de dingen die U zoo in de omgeving waarin ge zijt<c type="kk">/</c> treffen. à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een hartelijken handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik ben zoo bezorgd dat gij zelf door ’t geen waarover ge schreeft erg in ongelegenheid zijt misschien en hoo<supplied>p</supplied> zoo het zich schikken zal.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">The weeks pass quickly — and we’re at Sunday again. Have been to Scheveningen quite often lately, and one evening, very interestingly, happened to see a pink arriving. There’s a wooden shed near the monument<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> where a fellow keeps a look-out. As soon as the pink could clearly be seen approaching, the fellow emerged with a big blue flag, followed by a gang of children no higher than his knees. It was evidently a great pleasure for them to stand next to the man with the flag, and no doubt in their imagination to help bring the pink in. A few minutes after the man had waved his flag, a fellow rode up on an old horse – he was to get the anchor. The group was then joined by several men and women – including mothers with children — who were to receive the crew. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">When the pink was close enough, the fellow on the horse went into the sea and returned with the anchor.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then the men were carried onto the beach on the backs of fellows in high waders, and there was a noisy welcome for each arrival. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">When they were all ashore, the crowd trooped off home like a flock of sheep or a caravan, with the fellow on the camel, I mean the horse, rising above them like a tall wraith.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Naturally, I tried to sketch the various events with my full attention. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I also painted something of it, namely the small group in the enclosed scratch.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Then I also painted a study of a seascape, nothing but a bit of sand, sea, sky, grey and lonely<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — sometime I feel a need for that silence — where there’s nothing but the grey sea — with an occasional seabird. But otherwise, no other voice than the murmur of the waves. It’s in order to refresh me after the din of the Geest district or the potato market. Apart from that, this week I’ve worked mostly on sketches in watercolours. I’ve also come a long way with the large one of the bench,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and in addition done a sketch of women in the hospital garden,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and a bit of the Geest district.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> You’ll see from the accompanying scratch<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> what I’m searching for. Groups of people doing something or other. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But how hard it is to get life and movement into it, and to get the figures in place and separate from each other. It’s that great problem — <hi rend="italics">moutonner</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> groups of figures who, though forming a whole, gather to look with the heads and shoulders one above the other at the top, while in the foreground the legs of the first figures stand out clearly, and higher up the skirts and trouser-legs again form a sort of confused tangle in which there is nevertheless some detail. Then to right and left, depending on the viewpoint, the extension or shortening of the sides. As to composition, all possible scenes with figures, be it a market or the arrival of a boat, or a crowd of people at the soup kitchen — in the waiting room, the hospital, the pawnshop, the groups on the street, talking or strolling, are based on that same principle of the flock of sheep from which the word moutonner certainly derives — and everything comes down to the same questions of light and shade and perspective. The effect of the chestnut trees that you describe in your last letter is here too, as you’ll have seen from the drawing of the bench — it’s just that here one sees very little left of the new green leaves, although some time ago I noticed it too. But here they’ve been withered by the frequent gales. Perhaps we may soon have the true falling of the leaves here — that’s when, above all, I hope to paint many more studies of the woods. And no fewer of the beach for, though there are no effects of autumn leaves there, the peculiar light of autumn evenings does its work and it’s doubly beautiful there, as everywhere, at this time. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">I’m a little concerned about paint</hi> and a few other things, but you know all about it, I can vary my work in several ways, and there is and will continue to be an endless amount of things to draw. Because the group of folk in the accompanying scratch has endless variations and requires countless separate studies and scratches of individual figures which one must catch on the street as if on the wing. Character and meaning must gradually come into it in that way. For instance, I recently drew a study of gentlemen and ladies on the beach<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> — a flurry of strollers. I would be really pleased if sooner or later, after even more or even less effort, I could supply drawings for illustrated magazines. One might follow from the other. The point is to keep on working. I sincerely hope that you’re well, and would greatly welcome any news about yourself and what strikes you in your surroundings. Adieu, with a hearty handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’m so concerned that you yourself might perhaps be in serious difficulties as a result of what you wrote to me about, and do hope that it will be settled. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">A second sheet with a letter sketch (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_66">F - / JH 205</rs>) and thirteen lines of text was previously placed with this letter, probably on account of ll. 29-30. But because Van Gogh writes in the sheet in question that he has spoken in a <hi rend="italics">previous letter</hi> about the grouping of figures around the arrival of the pink (<ref target="let265.xml#l-84">letter 265, l. 84</ref>), and thus refers to the present letter, the sheet must have belonged to <ref target="let265.xml">letter 265</ref>. </p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo had not been repaid for a loan <ref target="let262.xml">(262)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On the so-called Zeekant, on the south side of the coast at Scheveningen, the ‘Obelisk in memory of 1813’ had been unveiled in 1865. It was designed by J.M. van der Made and commemorated the return of the Prince of Orange (later King William <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">i</hi>), who had gone into exile in England after the French invasion of the Netherlands in 1795. See Jeroen van Zanten, ‘Het strand van Scheveningen. De aankomst van koning Willem <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">i</hi> op 30 november 1813’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Plaatsen van herinnering. Nederland in de negentiende eeuw</hi>. Ed. Jan Bank and Marita Mathijsen. Amsterdam 2006, pp. 60-71.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Neither the scratch nor the painting of this group of figures on the beach is known; cf. also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arrangement</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This painted ‘seascape’ study is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Four people and a baby on a bench </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2395">F 951 / JH 197</rs>). Vincent had sent Theo the smaller watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Four people on a bench</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_63">F - / JH 195</rs>): <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let262.xml">see letter 262</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This watercolour of women in the garden of the hospital is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This watercolour of the Geest district is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This is the ‘scratch’ mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-3">l. 30</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>‘Moutonner’ means ‘Grouping in the correct way and distinctly figures who stand together like a flock of sheep (moutons),’ as Van Gogh himself explains.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>It is unclear which study of ladies and gentlemen on the beach is meant. It may have been the pen drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">People strolling on the beach</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_367">F 980 / JH 204</rs>) – cf. in this connection the watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">People strolling on the beach</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_368">F 1038 / JH 228</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    