<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 19 September 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let267"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8347 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>267</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R13</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>267</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-09-19">on or about Tuesday, 19 September 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8347 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8347 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001592_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8347 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001593_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001593_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8347 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001593_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001593_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief, zeer welkom, ontvang ik daareven – en daar ik er naar verlang weer eens met U te praten beantwoord ik dien meteen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ge schrijft me: hebt ge veel duitsche dingen – toevalligerwijs schreef ik omtrent Vautier &amp; andere duitschers<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> zoo ongeveer net precies ’t zelfde wat gij er van zegt<c type="kk">/</c> in een brief aan mijn broer<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> naar aanleiding van figuurstudies die ik geteekend had. Ik zeide hem geweest te zijn op een tentoonstelling van aquarellen waar veel van de Italianen was<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Knap<c type="kk">/</c> zeer knap – en die toch bij mij een leeg gevoel achterlieten en ik zeide tegen mijn broer<c type="kk">/</c> kerel wat was het toch een prettige tijd in de kunst toen die club artisten uit den Elzas begonnen<c type="kk">/</c> Vautier<c type="kk">/</c> Knaus<c type="kk">/</c> Jundt<c type="kk">/</c> Georges Saal<c type="kk">/</c> v. Muyden<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Brion</hi> vooral<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Anker</hi><c type="kk">/</c> Th<c type="kp">_</c> Schuler die meest teekeningen maakte<c type="kk">/</c> die om zoo te zeggen geexpliceerd en ondersteund werden door andere artisten<c type="kk">/</c> nl. schrijvers als Erckmann Chatrian en Auerbach.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ja zeer zeker zijn de italianen knap maar waar is hun sentiment<c type="kk">/</c> hun menschelijk gevoel. Ik zie liever een graauw krabbeltje van Lancon – een paar vodderapers die hun soep eten terwijl ’t buiten sneeuwt &amp; regent<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – dan die schitterende paauweveeren van de Italianen – die dagelijks schijnen te vermenigvuldigen terwijl die meer sobere artisten niet minder zeldzaam blijven dan ze steeds waren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik meen het Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> ik was net zoo lief b.v. kellner in een hotel als zoo’n soort van aquarellenfabriekant als sommige italianen zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dit zeg ik niet van allen maar gij voelt er mijn gedachte omtrent de rigting &amp; strekking van die school wel uit<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Geen ik zeg neemt niet weg dat ik er ook veel ken die ik mooi vindt – n.l. van die artisten die iets <hi rend="italics">Goya</hi> achtigs hebben<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. Fortuny soms en Morelli<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en soms zelfs Tapiro &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> Heilbuth, Duez.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Toen ik een jaar of 10 of 12 geleden er voor ’t eerst van zag, ik was toen bij Goupil, vond ik het prachtig en dacht zelfs het veel mooier was dan de doorwrochte dingen van ’t zij die duitschers ’t zij b.v. de Engelsche teekenaars ’t zij b.v. Rochussen of Mauve. Sedert ben ik er lang van teruggekomen omdat ik vind dat die artisten wel iets hebben van vogels die maar één noot op hun zang hebben terwijl ik meer sympathie heb voor leeuwrikken of nachtegalen die wat meer te vertellen hebben met minder lawaai en meer passie. Ik heb evenwel niet heel veel van de Duitschers – men vindt de mooien uit den tijd van Brion nu moeielijk. In der tijd heb ik een verzameling gemaakt van houtsneden voornamelijk naar bovengenoemde artisten die ik heb weggegeven aan een vriend in Engeland toen ik bij Goupil van daan ging.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Ik heb daar nu spijt genoeg van. Wilt gij er iets heel moois van hebben, bestel dan aan ’t bureau van de Illustration <hi rend="italics">l’Album des Vosges</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dessins de Th. Schuler<c type="kk">/</c> Brion<c type="kk">/</c> Valentin<c type="kk">/</c> Jundt &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof dat het 5 francs kost.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Maar ik vrees dat het uitgeput<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> is. Het is echter de informatie waard. Misschien<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs waarschijnlijk ook<c type="kk">/</c> is ’t verhoogd in prijs – op zigt wordt het niet gezonden<c type="kk">/</c> daarom heb ik ’t zelf niet durven vragen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Bijzonderheden omtrent Engelsche teekenaars weet ik weinig in zoover dat ik geen levensbeschrijving van hun zou kunnen geven<c type="kp">_</c> In ’t groot heb ik echter doordat ik volle 3 jaar in Engeland was<c type="kk">/</c> door veel van hen te zien heel wat omtrent hun en hun werk geleerd. Zonder in Engeland lang geweest te zijn is het naauwelijks mogelijk dat men ten volle hen apprecieert.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het is een andere manier van voelen<c type="kk">/</c> opvatten<c type="kk">/</c> uitdrukken<c type="kk">/</c> waar men zich eerst aan moet wennen – dubbel en dwars is het de moeite waard ze te bestudeeren want het zijn groote artisten die Engelschen. <hi rend="italics">Israels</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> Mauve en Rochussen</hi> komen er ’t digst bij – maar in aspect is toch een Schij van Thomas Faed b.v. zeer verschillend van een Israels<c type="kk">/</c> en een teekening van Pinwell<c type="kk">/</c> Morris of Small ziet er anders uit dan een van Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> en een Gilbert<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> of Dumaurier anders dan Rochussen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Van Rochussen gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> ik zag een prachtige teekening van hem<c type="kk">/</c> Fransche generaals die in een kamer van een oud Hollandsch raadhuis aan den burgemeester en de raadsleden inlichtingen &amp; papieren vragen.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Ik vond het net zoo mooi als b.v. de scene bij Dr. Wagner in Madame Thérèse van Erckmann Chatrian.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Ik weet dat in der tijd gij Rochussen weinig apprecieerdet maar ik houd mij verzekerd dat als ge zijn importante teekeningen ziet ge zeer veel van hem zult houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Voor mij zijn de Engelsche teekenaars wat Dickens op ’t gebied van litteratuur is<c type="kp">_</c> Het is één zelfde sentiment<c type="kk">/</c> nobel en gezond en waar men altijd weer op terugkomt<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wou erg graag dat vroeger of later gij eens gelegenheid hadt om rustig mijn heele verzameling door te zien<c type="kp">_</c> Juist door veel er van bij elkaar te zien krijgt men een overzigt en begint het voor zich zelf te spreken en ziet men duidelijk wat een prachtig geheel die school van teekenaars vormt<hi rend="italics">.</hi> Net als men Dickens of Balzac of Zola in zijn geheel moet lezen om hen afzonderlijk te kennen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Zoo b.v. heb ik nu wel een 50tal bladen over Ierland – op zich zelf zag men ze ligt over ’t hoofd maar ziet men ze bij elkaar<c type="kk">/</c> wordt men er door getroffen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Het portret van Shakespeare door Menzel<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> is mij onbekend<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou het erg graag eens zien hoe die eene leeuw de andere begrepen heeft. Want het werk v<c type="kp">_</c> Menzel heeft wel overeenkomst met Shakespeare – van wege het zoo LEEFT<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb de kleene<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> uitgaaf van Fred. de Groote van Menzel.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Breng het eens mede als ge wilt in geval ge weer eens te s’Hage komt. <hi rend="italics">De prenten waarover ge schrijft heb ik niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">(behalve de Regamey)</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Heilbuth</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> Marchetti</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Jacquet heb ik</hi> <hi>niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Van <hi rend="italics">Whistler</hi> bezit ik niets maar zag wel van hem mooie etsen<c type="kk">/</c> figuur en landschap<c type="kk">/</c> in der tijd.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">De marines van Wyllie uit de Graphic waarover ge schrijft hebben mij ook getroffen.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">The widows field van Boughton ken ik<c type="kk">/</c> dat is zeer mooi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Ja van dat een en ander ben ik zoo zeer vervuld dat ik er mijn heele leven op inrigt om die dingen uit het dagelijks leven die Dickens beschrijft en die bewuste teekenaars teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> te maken. Millet zegt – <hi rend="italics">dans l’art – il faut y mettre</hi> <hi rend="italics">sa peau</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Ik ben reeds in de worsteling<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet wat ik wil en kletspraatjes over het illustratieve brengen mij niet van mijn weg. De omgang met artisten heeft om zoo te zeggen geheel voor mij opgehouden zonder dat ik mij precies expliceeren kan hoe en waarom<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ga door voor allerlei zonderlings en slechts<c type="kp">_</c>– Dit maakt dat ik soms wel eens een zekere verlatenheid gevoel maar van den anderen kant concentreert het mijn aandacht meer op die dingen welke niet veranderlijk zijn<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk het eeuwig mooie in de natuur. Ik denk dikwijls aan de oude historie van Robinson Crusoe<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> die door zijn eenzaamheid niet den moed verloor maar ’t zoo aanlei dat hij zich een werkkring schiep zóó dat hij een zeer actief en zeer animeerend leven kreeg door eigen zoeken en sjouwen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Enfin – ik ben in den laatsten tijd ook aan ’t schilderen en aquarelleeren en verder teeken ik veel figuren naar model en krabbels op straat. Ik heb in den laatsten tijd nog al eens een man uit het Oudemannenhuis te poseeren gehad.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu is het toch hoog tijd ik U Karl Robert<c type="kk">/</c> le fusain eens terugstuur.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Ik heb het meer dan eens doorlezen en geprobeerd en toch vlot mij ’t fusain niet en werk ik liever met een timmermanspotlood. Ik wou wel eens iemand een fusain zien maken – bij mij wordt het zoo gaauw gefatigueerd en dat moet ergens in zitten dat geloof ik weg zou gaan als ik het eens zag doen<c type="kk">/</c> als ge eens komt heb ik U daar nog een paar dingen over te vragen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Enfin ik ben toch blij het eens gelezen te hebben en ik ben ’t met den schrijver volkomen eens dat het een heerlijk middel is om mee te werken en ik wou wel dat ik er beter mee wist om te gaan. Misschien zal ik ’t nog wel vinden met meer andere zaken die me nog duister zijn.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Dus ik zend het in dank terug<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik voeg er bij nog eenige houtsneden.– daar zijn net twee duitsche bij van Marchal.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> De Lançons zijn dunkt me mooi en vooral de Green,<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> en de mijnwerkers.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik recommandeer mij steeds zeer dan wanneer gij iets dubbel hebt<c type="kk">/</c> ’t te ontvangen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ook recommandeer ik mij voor brieven – en als ge eens iets leest wat U treft deel me dat ook mee want ik ben zoo weinig op de hoogte van wat er tegenwoordig uitkomt – ik weet iets meer van de litteratuur van een jaar of wat terug. Toen ik ziek was en sedert heb ik met veel bewondering de boeken van Zola gelezen. Ik dacht dat Balzac alleen stond maar ik zie dat hij opvolgers heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Toch – Rappard – die tijd van Balzac en Dickens<c type="kk">/</c> die tijd van Gavarni en Millet – ’t is nu ver te zoeken. Want al is ’t niet lang geleden dat die mannen heengingen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is al een heelen tijd geleden <hi rend="italics">dat zij begonnen</hi> en sedert zijn er wel veel veranderingen gekomen die mijns inziens niet precies verbeteringen zijn. Ik las eens in Eliott “al is het dood<c type="kk">/</c> ’k denk ’t alles mij in leven”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-26"/> zoo is het met dat tijdvak waarover ik U schrijf in mijn gedachte. En daarom houd ik ook bijzonder veel b.v. van Rochussen. Ge schrijft over illustraties van sprookjes – weet ge wel dat Rochussen prachtige aquarellen heeft gemaakt uit duitsche legenden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ken eene serie die Lenore heet<c type="kk">/</c> prachtig van sentiment.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> Maar de importante teekeningen van Rochussen zijn niet druk in de wandeling maar in de portefeuilles van rijke liefhebbers. Is het dat ge wat kracht zet achter het houtsneden verzamelen<c type="kk">/</c> zult ge ook wel eens redenaties over “het illustratieve” hooren – maar hoe gaat het met de houtsneden – de mooie worden hoe langer hoe zeldzamer<c type="kk">/</c> hoe langer hoe moeielijker te krijgen – en later zullen er lui naar zoeken die ze niet meer zullen kunnen vinden. Laatst zag ik het heele werk over Londen van Doré – ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> dat is prachtig mooi en het is nobel van sentiment – b.v. in die zaal van het nachtverblijf voor bedelaars<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> die gij hebt<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik – en anders nog krijgen kunt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">à dieu, met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik heb o.a. een aquarel van weeskinderen<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> onderhanden – verscheiden dingen aangelegd – ik zit druk in het werk.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Toen ik mijn brief klaar had ben ik uitgegaan &amp; teruggekomen met nog een pak illustraties<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. oude Holl. Illustr.<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-30"/> waardoor ik nog eenige dubbelen kan voegen bij dit partijtje.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Vooreerst 3 zeer mooie <hi rend="italics">Daumiers</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">              1 <hi rend="italics">Jacque<c type="kp">_</c></hi><ptr target="#note-t-32"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Hebt ge ze reeds retourneer ze dan s.v.p. bij gelegenheid.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">De les quatre ages d’un buveur van Daumier heb ik altijd een van zijn mooiste dingen gevonden.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Er zit ziel in als in een <hi rend="italics">de Groux</hi>. Zeer blij ben ik dit blad U te kunnen sturen<c type="kk">/</c> de Daumiers worden zeldzaam<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Al hadt ge niets anders van Daumier dan dit zoo was die meester toch goed vertegenwoordigd in uw verzameling. Ik heb wel prachtige <hi rend="italics">teekeningen</hi> van Frans Hals gezien in der tijd<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> – ik vind in dit blad iets – ja alles van Frans Hals of Rembrandt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Verder voeg ik bij zeer mooie <hi rend="italics">Morins</hi> en oude Dorés – bladen die hoe langer hoe zeldzamer worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Gij hebt zeker al wel reeds even als ik praatjes gehoord – bij gelegenheid van “’t illustratieve” – tegen Doré vooral – natuurlijkerwijs ook tegen Morin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Ik geloof wel van U dat gij desniettegenstaande dat toch wel van het werk dezer artisten zijt blijven houden – maar toch<c type="kk">/</c> als men er niet op verdacht is influenceeren zulke dingen iemand toch min of meer. Daarom acht ik het niet overbodig nu ik deze bladen U stuur te zeggen dat ik voor mij er in die vuilgeworden houtsneden nog een geur uit de dagen van Gavarni vind en van Balzac en V. Hugo – iets uit de nu haast vergeten Bohême – waar ik respect voor heb en dat ze mij telkens als ik ze weer zie een prikkel zijn om mijn best te doen dat ik de dingen energiek aanpak.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Ik zie natuurlijk ook het onderscheid tusschen een teekening van Doré en een van Millet maar het een sluit het ander niet uit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Is er onderscheid – er is ook overeenkomst<c type="kp">_</c> Doré kan een tors modeleeren en de gewrichten in elkaar zetten<c type="kk">/</c> beter<c type="kk">/</c> oneindig beter dan menigeen die met waanwijze wijsneuzigheid op hem schimpt – getuige b.v. dat blad<c type="kk">/</c> dat voor hem niets dan een krabbeling is<c type="kk">/</c> van de zeebaden.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Ik zeg maar<c type="kk">/</c> als iemand als Millet aanmerking op ’t teekenen v. Doré maakte – ik betwijfel of hij dat doen zou – maar gesteld hij deed het<c type="kk">/</c> welnu hij had het regt zulks te doen – maar als zulken die met hun twee handen niet het tiende kunnen doen van wat een vinger van Doré kan<c type="kk">/</c> op zijn werk schelden<c type="kk">/</c> zoo is dit niets dan blague en pastte ’t hun beter te zwijgen en zelf beter te leeren teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Het is zoo mal dat het tegenwoordig zoo algemeen is<c type="kk">/</c> dat niet apprecieeren van het teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">Ge hebt wel de teekeningen van Lynen gezien in Brussel<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> – wat waren die geestig en leuk en knap – sprak men er iemand over zoo antwoordde hij uit de hoogte met een zekere minachting<c type="kk">/</c> ja dat was “wel aardig”. Lynen zelf zal b.v. wel altijd tamelijk arm blijven ofschoon hij waarschijnlijk zeer actief en zeer productief is en nog meer worden zal. Nu – ik voor mij heb op conditie van ’t actief blijven<c type="kk">/</c> productief worden meer &amp; meer – mits ik mijn dagelijks brood houden mag – er niets op tegen om betrekkelijk arm te zijn mijn leven lang.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Nu, nogmaals gegroet, ik hoop de houtsneden naar Uw zin zullen zijn en dat ik spoedig weer eens iets van U hoor.– à dieu.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter, very welcome, has just arrived, and I’m answering at once because I’m longing to talk to you again. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You ask: do you have many German things? As it happens, on the subject of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1403">Vautier</rs> and other Germans<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in a letter to my brother<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> about some figure studies I had drawn, I wrote almost exactly the same as what you say. I told him that I’d been to an exhibition of watercolours where there was a great deal by the Italians.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Clever, very clever, and yet they left me with an empty feeling, and I said to my brother, old chap, what a pleasant time it was in art when that group of artists from Alsace began, Vautier, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1131">Knaus</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1120">Jundt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1347">Georg Saal</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Van Muyden</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs></hi> above all, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Anker</rs></hi>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">T. Schuler</rs>, who mainly made drawings, who were, so to speak, explained and supported by other artists, namely writers like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_525">Auerbach</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Yes, the Italians are most definitely clever, but where is their sentiment, their human feeling? I’d rather see a grey scratch by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs> — a few rag-pickers eating their soup while it’s snowing and raining outside<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> — than the dazzling peacock’s feathers of the Italians, who seem to multiply daily, while the more sober artists are no less rare than they always were. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I mean it, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>. I would rather be a waiter in a hotel, for example, than the sort of watercolour manufacturer some Italians are. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I don’t say that this applies to all of them, but you get my drift as regards the direction and tenor of that school. What I say doesn’t detract from the fact that I also know many whom I find beautiful, namely the artists who have something <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs></hi>-like, such as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Fortuny</rs> sometimes, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1238">Morelli</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and sometimes even <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1380">Tapiró</rs> &amp;c., <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1087">Heilbuth</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_989">Duez</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> When I first saw some of this work 10 or 12 years ago, I was with Goupil at the time, I thought it was splendid, and even found it much more beautiful than the well-wrought things by either the Germans or, for example, the English draughtsmen or, for example, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>. I’ve long since changed my mind, because I believe those artists are rather like birds with only one note in their song, whereas I feel more sympathy for larks or nightingales that have more to say with less noise and more passion. However, I don’t have a great deal by the Germans — the beautiful ones from the time of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs> are hard to find now. I once put together a collection of woodcuts, mainly after the above artists, which I gave away to a friend in England when I left Goupil.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I regret that so much now. If you want to have something really beautiful by them, put in an order at the offices of L’Illustration for <hi rend="italics">L’Album des Vosges</hi>, drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">T. Schuler</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1406">Valentin</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1120">Jundt</rs>, &amp;c. I believe it costs 5 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> But I fear that it’s sold out. It’s worth asking, though. Perhaps, indeed probably, the price has gone up — they won’t send it on approval, that’s why I didn’t dare ask for it myself. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I can give few details about English artists, in the sense that I couldn’t provide biographies of them. Having spent 3 full years in England, however, and having seen the work of many of them, I’ve learned quite a lot in broad outline about them and their work. It’s hardly possible to appreciate them fully without having spent a long time in England. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">It’s a different way of feeling, conceiving, expressing, which one has to get used to first. Studying them more than repays the effort, for they are great artists, the English. <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs></hi> come closest, but in appearance a painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1011">Thomas Faed</rs>, for example, is very different from an Israëls, and a drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1269">Pinwell</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1235">Morris</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1359">Small</rs> looks different from one by Mauve, and a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1047">Gilbert</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1197">Du Maurier</rs> different from Rochussen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Speaking of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs>, I saw a splendid drawing by him: French generals demanding information and papers from the mayor and councillors in a room in an old Dutch town hall.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I thought it was just as beautiful as, say, the scene at Dr Wagner’s in Madame Thérèse by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I know that you didn’t greatly appreciate Rochussen at the time, but I’m sure that when you see his important drawings you’ll like him very much indeed. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">For me the English draughtsmen are what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs> is in the sphere of literature. It’s one and the same sentiment, noble and healthy, and something one always comes back to. I would very much like it if sooner or later you had an opportunity to quietly look through my whole collection. It’s through seeing a lot together that one gets an overall view and it begins to speak for itself, and one sees clearly what a splendid entity this school of draughtsmen forms. Just as one must read Dickens or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> in their entirety to know them separately. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Thus, for example, I now have as many as 50 prints about Ireland — one might well overlook them seen individually, but they are striking when seen all together. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1214">Menzel</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> is unknown to me; I’d very much like to see how the one lion interpreted the other. For Menzel’s work has some resemblance to Shakespeare’s in that it LIVES, so. I have the small edition of Menzel’s Frederick the Great.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Bring it with you if you would, if you come to The Hague again. <hi rend="italics">I don’t have the prints you write about (except for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1301 bio.xml#_1302">Régamey</rs>)</hi>, <hi rend="italics">I do</hi> <hi>not</hi> <hi rend="italics">have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1087">Heilbuth</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1205">Marchetti</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1115">Jacquet</rs></hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I have nothing by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1444">Whistler</rs></hi>, but in the past I’ve seen beautiful etchings by him, figures and landscape.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I was also struck by the seascapes by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1451">Wyllie</rs> from The Graphic which you write about.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I know The widow’s field by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>; it’s very beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Yes, I’m so taken by all of it that my whole life is aimed at making the things from everyday life that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs> describes and these artists draw. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> says – <hi rend="italics">in art one must give one’s heart and soul</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> I’m already wrestling, I know what I want, and nonsense about the illustrative won’t divert me from my path. Contact with artists has, so to speak, completely ceased for me, without my being able to explain exactly how or why. I’m made out to be everything peculiar and bad. This means that I sometimes have a certain sense of being abandoned, but on the other hand it concentrates my attention on the things that aren’t changeable, namely the eternal beauty of nature. I often think of the old story of Robinson Crusoe,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> who didn’t lose heart because of his solitariness but organized things so that he created work for himself and had a very active and very stimulating life through his own searching and toiling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Anyway, lately I’ve also been painting and watercolouring, and in addition I’m drawing many figures from the model as well as scratches on the street. Lately I’ve quite often had a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">man</rs> from the Old Men’s Home to pose.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Now it’s high time that I sent <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1309">Karl Robert</rs>, Le fusain, back to you.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> I’ve read it through more than once and tried, and yet I make no progress with charcoal, and I prefer to work with a carpenter’s pencil. I would like to see someone make a charcoal drawing — with me it so quickly becomes flat, and the cause is something that I believe would go if I saw it being done. If you come sometime, I have a few things to ask you about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">In any case I’m glad that I’ve read it, and I entirely agree with the writer that it’s a delightful medium to work in, and I wish that I could handle it better. Perhaps I’ll discover the secret, along with other things that are still unclear to me. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">So I’m returning it with thanks. I’m adding a few woodcuts, two German ones by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1193">Marchal</rs>, as it happens.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs>s seem beautiful to me, and especially the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1059 bio.xml#_1058">Green</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> and The miners.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">If you have any duplicates, I would always welcome having one of them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I would also welcome letters — and if you read something that strikes you let me know, for I’m out of touch with what comes out these days — I know a little more about the literature of a few years ago. When I was ill and afterwards I read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s books with great admiration. I thought that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> stood alone, but I see that he had successors.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Yet, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, the age of Balzac and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs>, the age of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, is now far behind us. For while it isn’t long since those men passed on, it’s a very long time <hi rend="italics">since they began</hi>, and in the meantime there have been many changes that aren’t exactly improvements in my view. I once read in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs> ‘though it be dead, yet let me think it lives’,<ptr target="#note-t-26"/> so it is with the period I’m writing to you about, in my opinion. And that’s why I’m so especially fond of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs>, for example. You mention illustrations of fairy tales — did you know that Rochussen did splendid watercolours of German legends? I know a series called Lenore, splendid in sentiment.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> But Rochussen’s important drawings aren’t in circulation much, but in the portfolios of wealthy art lovers. If you go about collecting woodcuts energetically, you too will hear rhetoric about ‘the illustrative’. But what happens with woodcuts? The fine ones become rarer as time passes, harder and harder to find — and later people will search for them and not be able to find them any more. The other day I saw the whole of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs>’s work on London — I say, that’s splendidly beautiful and noble in sentiment — for example in the room in the night refuge for beggars,<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> which you have, I believe, and otherwise can still get.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I’m working on a watercolour of orphans<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> — various things started — I have my hands full.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">When I had finished my letter, I went out and came back with another pile of illustrations, namely old Hollandsche Illustraties,<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> so I can add some duplicates to this batch. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">First 3 very beautiful <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>s</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">1 <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1117">Jacque</rs>.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-32"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">If you have them already, please return them when you get the chance. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">The four ages of the drinker by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> has always seemed to me one of his most beautiful things.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">There is soul in it as in a <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs></hi>. I’m very glad to be able to send you this print. The Daumiers are becoming rare.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Even if you had nothing else by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, the master would still be well represented in your collection. I saw splendid <hi rend="italics">drawings</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Frans Hals</rs> once.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> In this sheet I find something — in fact, everything — of Frans Hals or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I’m also adding some very beautiful <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1236">Morin</rs>s</hi> and old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs>s — prints that are becoming rarer and rarer. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Like me, you’ve no doubt heard talk — on the subject of ‘the illustrative’ — against <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs> above all, and of course against <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1236">Morin</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">I believe that notwithstanding this you’ve continued admiring the work of these artists all the same. But if one isn’t on one’s guard, things like that can still influence one more or less. That’s why I don’t think it superfluous, now that I’m sending you these prints, to say that for me there’s still the smell of the days of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">V. Hugo</rs> in these grubby woodcuts — something of the Bohème, now almost forgotten — which I respect, and that each time I see them again they encourage me to do my best and tackle things energetically. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Of course, I too see the difference between a drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs> and one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, but the one doesn’t rule out the other. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">There may be a difference, but there’s also correspondence. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs> can model a torso and construct the joints better, infinitely better, than many a person who scoffs at him like a conceited know-all — witness, for example, that print of sea bathing, which for him is no more than a scratch.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">I’m only saying that if someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> made comments about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs>’s drawing — I doubt if he would, but suppose he did — well, he would have the right to do so. But when those who with their two hands can’t do a tenth of what Doré can do with one finger rail against his work, that’s nothing but arrogance, and they’d be well advised to be silent and to learn to draw better themselves. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">It’s so silly that this lack of appreciation of drawing is so widespread these days. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">You saw the drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1192">Lynen</rs> in Brussels<ptr target="#note-t-36"/> – how witty and amusing and clever they were. If you talked to anyone about them, they answered loftily with a certain contempt that yes, they were ‘quite nice’. Lynen himself, for example, will always remain fairly poor even though he’s probably very active and very productive and likely to become more so. Well, for my part, provided I stay active and become more and more productive, I have nothing against being fairly poor all my life, provided I have my daily bread. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">Well, regards again, I hope you like the woodcuts, and that I’ll soon hear from you again. Adieu.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh sent Van Rappard a number of wood engravings earlier in September (<ref target="let263.xml">see letter 263</ref> of between about Tuesday, 12 and Sunday, 17 September). He responds to Van Rappard’s thank-you letter ‘at once’ <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>. This letter will have been written shortly after <ref target="let265.xml">letter 265</ref> of Sunday, 17 or Monday, 18 September 1882, to which reference is made <ref target="#l-6">(l. 6)</ref> and in which similar phrasing is used. The next letter to Van Rappard dates from on or about 23 September (<ref target="let268.xml">letter 268</ref>). Since, moreover, there was another letter from Van Rappard between that letter and the present one, we have dated <ref target="let267.xml">letter 267</ref> to on or about Tuesday, 19 September 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1403">Benjamin Vautier</rs> (the Elder) was Swiss by birth, as were <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Albert Anker</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1253">Alfred van Muyden</rs>, both mentioned later; the other ‘Alsace’ artists mentioned were German. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml">letter 265</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This was the ‘Tentoonstelling van teekeningen van het Koninklijk Genootschap van Nederlandsche Aquarellisten. Gotische Zaal, Noord-Einde te ’s Gravenhage’ (Exhibition of drawings by the Royal Society of Dutch Watercolourists. Gothic Room, Noordeinde at The Hague): <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml#n-5">see letter 265, n. 5.</ref> Five Italians were represented: Alberti, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_376"><hi rend="italics">Een valkenier</hi></rs> (A falconer); Cabianca, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_377"><hi rend="italics">Ruïne</hi></rs> (Ruin); Cremone, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_378"><hi rend="italics">Bouderie</hi></rs> (Sulking); Ricardi, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_379"><hi rend="italics">Waterdragers in Rome</hi></rs> (Water-carriers in Rome) and Zona, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_380"><hi rend="italics">Studiekopje</hi></rs> (Study of a head). See exhib. cat. The Hague 1882-3, pp. 3, 5, 11, 16, cat. nos. 8, 28, 29, 126 and 199.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For this remark about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_525">Auerbach</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml#n-16">see letter 265, n. 16.</ref> The everyday scenes in Alsace depicted by the artists mentioned are also found in the folk tales of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs> and Auerbach. They worked together: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Théophile Schuler</rs>, for example, illustrated 13 books by Erckmann-Chatrian.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>A reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs>’s print <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1029"><hi rend="italics">A rag-pickers’ tavern in Paris</hi></rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let261.xml#n-5;">see letter 261, n. 5;</ref> also mentioned in the previous letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml">see letter 263</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Mariano José Maria Bernardo Fortuny y Carbó</rs> was strongly influenced by Spanish Old Masters, particularly <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1238">Domenico Morelli</rs> is known for his realistic depiction of romantic subjects, his striking light-dark effects and his use of richly contrasting colours. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1380">José Tapiró y Baró</rs> took his inspiration from the work of his friend <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Fortuny</rs> and from the modern Italian genre painters. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1087">Ferdinand Heilbuth</rs> was influenced by Italian Renaissance painting. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_989">Erneste Ange Duez</rs> is known for his use of colour and the way in which he applied modern techniques to traditional subjects (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">DoA</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>On his departure from the London branch, Van Gogh evidently gave his prints to a certain <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_636">Richardson</rs>, a representative for Goupil, as shown by <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let277.xml">letter 277</ref>. It seems less likely that he gave them to the Englishman <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_394">Harry Gladwell</rs>, who replaced Van Gogh when he left Goupil in Paris at the end of March 1876 (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let071.xml">letters 71</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let072.xml">72</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>By <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_543">Album des Vosges</ref></hi> Van Gogh may mean <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le veilleur de nuit. Album d’Alsace et de Lorraine, illustré par MM. P. Ballet, E. Boetzel, de Beylié, Beyer, Brion, Gluck, Haffner, Jundt, Lallemand, Laville, Lévy, Oesinger, Picquart, Th. Schuler, L. Schützenberger, Touchemolin, H. Valentin</hi>. We have traced only one volume of this magazine. It was published in 1857 in Strasbourg by G. Silbermann, place Saint-Thomas 3 (Bibliothèque Nationale; Universitaire de Strasbourg, and Bibliothèque Municipale de Nancy).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘uitverkocht’ (sold out), cf. French ‘épuisé’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote down Sir <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1047">John Gilbert</rs> (and not <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1046">Achille Isidore Gilbert</rs>) in a list of English monograms he was to send to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> in October (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let273.xml">see letter 273</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1952"><hi rend="italics">Headquarters in a townhall</hi></rs>,<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml#n-6">see letter 265, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>For the scene in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_53"><hi rend="italics">Madame Thérèse</hi></ref>, in which Dr. Wagner is questioned by an officer, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml#n-7">see letter 265, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1214">Adolf Menzel</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Shakespeare</hi>, 1850. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1604">Friedrich Ludwig Unzelmann</rs> made a wood engraving after it in 1852 (Staatliche Museen zu Berlin, Kupferstichkabinett). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_255">Ill. 255</rs>. Cf. cat. Berlin 1984, p. 342, cat. no. 236.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘kleine’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            
      
<p>For this edition of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_678">Franz Theodor Kugler</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_31"><hi rend="italics">Geschichte Friedrichs des Großen. Gezeichnet von Adolph Menzel</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let133.xml#n-19">see letter 133, n. 19</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml#n-49">235, n. 49.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1444">Whistler</rs>’s etchings, cf. Katherine Lochnan, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The etchings of James McNeill Whistler</hi>. New Haven and London 1984.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1451">William Lionel Wyllie</rs> painted seascapes, port scenes and the ships of the British fleet. From 1870 he produced numerous prints for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi>. See Roger Quarm and John Wyllie, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">W.L. Wyllie, marine artist, 1851-1931</hi>. London 1981. The estate has his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Mediterranean fleet at Sigri – The annual regatta: Start for the Admiral’s Cup</hi>, from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 20 (23 August 1879), p. 172. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1953">Ill. 1953</rs> (t*664). There were several seascapes by Wyllie in the current, twenty-sixth volume of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> (1882), which may explain why <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> mentioned them. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must mean the engraving after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The widow’s acre</hi> (1879) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">George Henry Boughton</rs>; it was in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 20 (15 November 1879), p. 473. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_621">Ill. 621</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            
      
<p>For this quotation from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> in Sensier, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238">La vie et l’oeuvre de J.F. Millet</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let210.xml#n-5">see letter 210, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_581">Defoe</rs>’s novel <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_186"><hi rend="italics">Robinson Crusoe</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let143.xml#n-41">see letter 143, n. 41.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>This is the first mention in the correspondence of the model that Van Gogh was to draw often for several months from September: the elderly <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Adrianus Zuyderland</rs>, who had such prominent side-whiskers. He lived in the Old Men’s and Women’s Home in Om en Bij (a street in The Hague), which was supported by the poor board of the Dutch Reformed Congregation. The male residents were known as ‘men on the parish’, ‘almsmen’ (diakoniehuismannetjes). It is not known which drawings are being referred to here. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 128-145, 160-164, 197-205, cat. nos. 31-36, 42, 55-57.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1309">Georges Karl Robert</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_211"><hi rend="italics">Le fusain sans maitre. Traité pratique et complet sur l’étude du paysage au fusain</hi></ref>, which Van Gogh had borrowed from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> as long before as October 1881, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let174.xml#n-8">see letter 174, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>It is not clear whether Van Gogh means that he is sending wood engravings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1193">Charles Marchal</rs>, or prints in the style of his work. The term ‘German’ must refer to the genre-like scenes in Alsace that Marchal depicted. Several of these prints are reproduced in Gautier 1992, pp. 140-142.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>This might be the work of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1059">Henry Towneley Green</rs> or of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1058">Charles Green</rs>. Van Gogh earlier sent <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_906"><hi rend="italics">“Restoring the sign”</hi></rs> by the former, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let232.xml#n-10">see letter 232, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Roll</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1950"><hi rend="italics">A miners’ strike</hi></rs>; Van Gogh thought that this print would also please <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml">letter 263</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>Vincent had earlier written to Theo: ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> is actually <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">ii</hi>’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let250.xml">see letter 250</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>Van Gogh borrowed this line from <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_57"><hi rend="italics">Felix Holt, the radical</hi></ref>; it is both the motto and the conclusion of Chapter 6.</p>

<p rend="indent">‘Though she be dead, yet let me think she lives,</p>

<p rend="indent">And feed my mind, that dies for want of her.’</p>

<p>See Eliot 1980, pp. 66, 80. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs> took the quotation from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_584">Tamburlaine the Great</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1812">Christopher Marlowe</rs>. See ed. J.S. Cunningham. Manchester 1981, p. 253.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>In 1869 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Charles Rochussen</rs> painted the series <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_944">La ballade: Léonore. <hi>xviii</hi>e Siècle</rs></hi> (Ballad. Léonore. 18th century), consisting of four watercolours entitled: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’arrivée dans le village des troupes revenues de la guerre. Léonore cherche son fiancé</hi>; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le désespoir de Léonore</hi>; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Mort à la porte de la jeune fille. Clair de lune</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La course au cimetière</hi> (The arrival of the soldiers in the village, returning from the war. Léonore searching for her fiancé; Léonore’s despair; Death at the little girl’s door, moonlight; Walk in the churchyard) (present whereabouts unknown; in the possession of Hugo Tutein Nolthenius in 1944). See Franken and Obreen 1894, pp. 97-98, cat. nos. 672-675. Rochussen made a lithograph of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Léonore’s despair</hi> for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Nederlandsche Spectator</hi> (22 January 1870), no. 4. Album no. 7, as supplement to p. 35. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1288">Ill. 1288</rs>. The watercolours illustrated Gottfried August Bürger, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Lenore</hi> (1773). See Albrecht Schöne, ‘Bürger’s Lenore’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Deutsche Vierteljahrschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und Geistesgeschichte</hi> 28 (1954), pp. 324-344.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Gustave Doré</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_676">[William] Blanchard Jerrold</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_157"><hi rend="italics">London – A pilgrimage</hi></ref>. London 1872, and the engraving <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_792"><hi rend="italics">Scripture reader in a night refuge</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let129.xml#n-36">see letter 129, n. 36.</ref> At the beginning of June Vincent had expressed to Theo his regret that he had not been able to buy the book – it cost 7.50 guilders: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let234.xml">see letter 234</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>This must be the unknown watercolour a sketch of which Vincent had sent to Theo in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml">letter 265</ref>: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orphan boys and girls out for a walk </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_67">F - / JH 203</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> was the first illustrated weekly in the Netherlands, and began as the Dutch version of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi>. See Hemels and Vegt 1993, pp. 220-224.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>Most of the engravings sent can no longer be identified. In the first five volumes (1864-1869) there were five <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>s, 33 works after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Doré</rs>, and one after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1117">Jacque</rs>. There were 42 works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1236">Edmond Morin</rs> between 1864 and 1875 (the 11th volume). (Eight issues were missing from the volumes 1864-1882 that we consulted.)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>The only print by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1117">Charles Emile Jacque</rs> in this magazine was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het eerste april-gras. Teekening van Ch. Jacques</hi> (The first grass in April. Drawing by Ch. Jacque), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> 2 (1865-1866), no. 21, p. 168. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1954">Ill. 1954</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="33" xml:id="note-t-33">
                            


<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Honoré Daumier</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De vier leeftijden van den drinker</hi> (The four ages of the drinker) uit <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> 2 (1865-1866), no. 4, p. 32. Van Gogh’s copy survives. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_51">Ill. 51</rs>. (t*1057). In 1890 he made a painted copy after this work, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Men drinking </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2887">F 667 / JH 1884</rs>). This is why the print has the pencil lines of the squaring used to make copying easier. The engraving by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1568">C. Maurand</rs> after Daumier’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_421"><hi rend="italics">Physiologie du buveur – Les quatre âges</hi></rs> (The physiology of the drinker – The four ages) originally appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 6 (25 October 1862), no. 289, p. 268 and was also published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Journal Illustré</hi> (21 May 1865) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Presse Illustré </hi>(29 March 1868). See Bouvy 1995, cat. no. 935.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="34" xml:id="note-t-34">
                            

<p>Van Gogh may have seen drawings still attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Frans Hals</rs> at that time or reproductions after them somewhere; no original drawings by Hals are known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="35" xml:id="note-t-35">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De zeebaden. Humoristische teekening van Gustave Doré</hi> (Sea bathing. Humorous drawing by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_998">Gustave Doré</rs>), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> 2 (1865-1866), no. 10, p. 76. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1955">Ill. 1955</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="36" xml:id="note-t-36">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1192">Amédée Ernest Lynen</rs> was one of the founders of the Brussels artists’ society <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Essor</hi> (1876-1891). Van Gogh is referring to the drawings by Lynen at the sixth annual exhibition by this society, from 7 January to 8 February 1882 at the Palais des Beaux-Arts in Brussels, namely <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Un livre (7 dessins)</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mon vieux</hi> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">7 dessins)</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’hiver</hi> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">7 dessins)</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dessins</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marée basse</hi> (A book (7 drawings), Old chap (7 drawings), Winter (7 drawings), Drawings, At low tide). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>, himself a member of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Essor</hi>, was represented by two (unidentified) paintings, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_245"><hi rend="italics">Jardin botanique à Bruxelles</hi></rs> (Botanical Garden at Brussels) and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_382"><hi rend="italics">En Hollande</hi></rs> (In Holland). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Essor Bruxelles. Catalogue de la <hi>vi</hi>e exposition annuelle</hi>. Exhib. cat. Brussels 1882, p. 13, cat. nos. 137-141 (Lynen) and 201-202 (Van Rappard).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    