<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, on or about Saturday, 23 September 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let268"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8348 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>268</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R14</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>269</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-09-23">on or about Saturday, 23 September 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8348" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8348" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001594_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Daareven ontvang ik Uw schrijven waarvoor ik U dank. Het verheugt mij op nieuw daarin te zien dat gij toch in de houtsneden pleizier hebt. Verder respecteer ik Uwe zienswijs met betrekking tot hetgeen ik nu &amp; dan gezonden heb &amp; hoop te blijven zenden tenzij ge er op tegen mogt krijgen. Doch ik sta voor een lastige kwestie<c type="kk">/</c> voor mij eigentlijk onbeslisbaar ofschoon ik ze beslissen zal<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. te zeggen wat ze mij gekost hebben. Ik voor mij zooals ge weet heb een bijzondere liefhebberij voor de houtsneden. Meestal koop ik ze zeer goedkoop en toch besteed ik er voor mijn doen nog al wat aan &amp; heb daar nooit spijt van gehad. Of ik er nu meer of minder voor gaf is echter onafhankelijk van hetgeen ik aan U zond – daar ik U dubbelen zond en geen die ik zelf niet reeds had<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ge trouwens dezen zomer gezien hebt toen we zamen de dubbelen hebben uitgezocht.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat ik U zond kocht ik niet expres voor U – op een paar uitzonderingen na en voor die paar uitzonderingen gaf ik maar weinig en wenschte maar ik meer zulken kan vinden. Daar ge er echter op staat zoo zal ik er U voor rekenen b.v. een daalder<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> die ge als ge wilt me bij gelegenheid in postzegels b.v. zenden kunt en dan hoeft ge er geen gewetensbezwaar over te hebben mij in ’t finantieele te kort gedaan te hebben. Dus op die manier is deze kwestie dunkt me beslist.–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu heb ik U gevraagd mij eens op te geven of gij tijdschriften als b.v. Illustr. of Graphic geregeld ontvangt – nl. die van ’t loopende jaar.– Dat is omdat ik in besprek ben met iemand die een aantal tijdschriften uit een leesinrigting<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> afkomstig te koop heeft. Ik ben besloten die in alle geval te nemen maar ik heb reeds een &amp; ander van ’t loopende jaar en dus ik zal waarschijnlijk weer dubbelen krijgen. Zijn die b.v. uit Illustration en weet ik gij de illustration reeds hebt dan geef ik de dubbelen bij gelegenheid aan een ander die er pleizier in hebben mogt &amp; ze verzamelt (ofschoon momenteel ik geen mensch er voor weet)<c type="kp">_</c> Maar weet ik gij hebt ze niet dan zijn ze natuurlijkerwijs voor U.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik ben juist afgesproken<c type="kk">/</c> reeds vóór ik Uw brief ontving<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik die partij maar nemen zou &amp; hoop ze binnen een dag of 14 te ontvangen, misschien reeds vroeger – dus als ge wilt geef mij dan maar op hoe gij gesteld zijt met tijdschriften over 1882.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Of ik meer of minder dubbelen hebben zal weet ik natuurlijk nog niet doch zoo goed als zeker toch een &amp; ander. <hi rend="italics">Wees dus zoo goed en laat</hi> <hi rend="italics">me dit weten</hi>. Is ’t de moeite waard<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal er U ook weer wat voor rekenen of we vinden het wel bij gelegenheid doch doe me pleizier en zeg het als ik er U mee van dienst kan zijn. Ik stel belang in Uwe collectie en wou graag zien dat die heel mooi werd. Later kan ik misschien nog wel importanter dingen zenden.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Van Renouard heb ik reeds een 40tal grootere &amp; kleenere<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> bladen.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Zoo vond ik onlangs van hem la bourse<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en Un discours de M. Gambetta<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en nog bladen Enfants assistés.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Maar vooral weet ik zeker ge veel pleizier zoudt hebben in een paar groote Lançons<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Caton Woodville</hi><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> is ook wel erg knap<c type="kk">/</c> ik begin meer van hem te houden naarmate ik er meer van zie. Kent gij <hi rend="italics">Montbard </hi>– ik meen ge in elk geval landschappen van hem moet hebben – doch nu onlangs kreeg ik schetsen door hem uit <hi rend="italics">Ierland</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en van <hi rend="italics">Jernsey</hi><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> waarin bijzonder veel sentiment was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Van harte hoop ik ge pleizier zult hebben van Uw Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> op Arti,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> ik denk niet ik die tentoon<c type="shy">-</c>stelling zien zal<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik ben druk bezig met teekeningen van een <hi rend="italics">wees</hi>man<c type="kk">/</c> zooals hier de diakoniemannetjes genoemd worden in de wandeling<c type="kp">_</c> Vindt gij die expressie weesman en weesvrouw niet echt.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> ’t Is niet makkelijk die types die men zoo op straat ziet te maken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat aquarellen aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er verscheiden die aangezet zijn<c type="kk">/</c> toch ben ik nog niet naar mijn zin er in geslaagd maar wel heb ik er meer pleizier in als vroeger. Ziehier nog een krabbel van een Weesman<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> – adieu<c type="kk">/</c> ik schrijf in haast – laat me dus maar eens spoedig vernemen hoe ’t met die houtsneden staat, of ge ze hebt ja dan neen. Met een handdruk,</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter has just arrived, for which I thank you. I’m glad to read once more that you take pleasure in the woodcuts. I also respect your views regarding what I’ve sent from time to time, and hope to go on sending unless you have an objection. But I’m faced by a difficult question — one that’s actually impossible for me to decide and yet I will decide it — namely, to say what they cost me. As you know, I have a particular liking for woodcuts. I usually buy them very cheaply, and yet by my standards I spend quite a lot on them and have never regretted that. Whether I paid more or less for them, though, has nothing to do with what I sent to you — since I sent you duplicates and nothing that I didn’t already have myself, as you saw in fact this summer when we sorted out the duplicates together. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I didn’t buy what I sent you especially for you — apart from a few exceptions, and for those few exceptions I only paid a little and only wish I could find more like them. But since you insist, I will charge you, say one <hi rend="italics">daalder</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which you can send me if you like, for example in stamps at your convenience. Then you needn’t have any misgivings about not dealing fairly with me financially. So in this way I believe this question is settled. 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Now I’ve asked you to tell me whether you receive magazines like, for example, L’Illustration or The Graphic regularly, that’s to say this year’s issues. This is because I’m in negotiations with someone who’s selling a number of magazines that come from a subscription library.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve decided to take them in any case, but I already have one or two from the current year, so I’ll probably get some duplicates again. If they come from L’Illustration, for example, and if I know you already have L’Illustration, I’ll give the duplicates, when there’s an opportunity, to someone else who might enjoy them and collects them (though at the moment I don’t know of anyone for them). But if I know you don’t have them, then of course they’re yours. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I had just agreed to take this batch, even before I had received your letter, and hope to have them within a fortnight or so, perhaps even sooner — so let me know, if you would, what your position is as regards magazines in 1882. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Of course I don’t yet know whether I’ll have a lot of duplicates or not, but there are bound to be some. <hi rend="italics">So be so good as to let me know about this</hi>. I’ll charge you something again if it’s worth the trouble, or we can settle it when the opportunity arises, but oblige me by telling me if I can be of service. I take an interest in your collection, and would like to see it become a very fine one. Later I may be able to send more important things. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I already have about 40 large and small prints by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Recently I found The exchange<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and A speech by M. Gambetta<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and prints from the orphanage<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> by him. But above all I’m certain you would take great pleasure in a couple of large <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs>s.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Caton Woodville </hi><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> is also very good. The more I see of him, the more I’m beginning to like him. Do you know <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1170">Montbard</rs></hi>? I believe you do at least have landscapes by him. But lately I got some sketches by him of <hi rend="italics">Ireland</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and of <hi rend="italics">Jernsey</hi><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> in which there was a great deal of sentiment. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I sincerely hope that you’ll take pleasure in your painting at Arti.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I don’t think I’ll see the exhibition. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m very busy with drawings of an <hi rend="italics">orphan</hi> man, as the almsmen are usually called here. Don’t you think that the expressions orphan man and orphan woman are just right?<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> It isn’t easy to do the types one comes across on the street. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">As to watercolours, I have several that I’ve started, but they haven’t yet worked out as I wished, but I’m enjoying it more than in the past. Here’s a scratch of an orphan man<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> — adieu, I write in haste — so let me know soon about the woodcuts, whether you have them or not. With a handshake,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh has replied immediately to a letter from Van Rappard <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, who was replying to Van Gogh’s letter of on or about Tuesday, 19 September 1882 (<ref target="let267.xml">letter 267</ref>). <ref target="let269.xml">Letter 269</ref> of Monday, 25 September says: ‘I received a letter from Rappard the other day’ (<ref target="let269.xml#l-87">l. 87</ref>); this must have been the one mentioned in the present letter. Because Vincent wrote to Theo that he had begun drawing his new model (<ref target="let266.xml">letter 266</ref> of Monday, 18 September) and reports to Van Rappard that he is ‘busy’ <ref target="#l-80">(l. 80)</ref> with that, this letter must date from a few days after <ref target="let266.xml">letter 266</ref>. Based on this, we date it to on or about Saturday, 23 September 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh sends wood engravings to Van Rappard (<ref target="let263.xml">263</ref> and <ref target="let267.xml">267</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Zuyderland is a model <ref target="let267.xml">(267)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>A daalder is 1.50 guilders.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For the subscription library, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml#n-1">see letter 263, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘kleinere’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For the prints by Renouard in the estate, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml#n-44">see letter 235, n. 44.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Paul Renouard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La bourse et les boursiers</hi> (The exchange and the brokers), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 79 (18 February 1882), p. 104. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_381">Ill. 381</rs>. (t*22).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Paul Renouard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Un discours de M. Gambetta: Gestes et attitudes</hi> (A speech by M. Gambetta: Gestures and attitudes), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 78 (17 September 1881), p. 188. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_385">Ill. 385</rs>. (t*23).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The following prints from the series <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les enfants assistés</hi> (The orphanage) are in the estate: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La crèche</hi> (The crèche), engraved by Charles Baude<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">.</hi> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1956">Ill. 1956</rs> (three copies: t*61, t*644 and t*768); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le change</hi> (The change) engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1512">Charles Baude</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1957">Ill. 1957</rs> (three copies: t*761, t*765 and t*766), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 79 (25 March 1882), p. 192 and p. 197; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le repas des sevrés – Scrofuleux – Rachitique – On apprend a marcher</hi> (The meal of the weaned babies – A scrofulous child – A rachitic child – They learn to walk) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1970">Ill. 1970</rs> (t*762); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’heure de la bouillie</hi> (Time for porridge) engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1600">Henry Thiriat</rs>.<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1959">Ill. 1959</rs> (t*763); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La première division passe au réfectoire</hi> (The first group goes to the dining room), engraved by Henry Thiriat.<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_396">Ill. 396</rs> (t*747) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le numéro 68,782</hi> (Number 68.782), engraved by Henry Thiriat<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">. </hi><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_395">Ill. 395</rs> (t*767), all from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 79 (1 April 1882), pp. 209, 213, 212. Van Gogh must also have had <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Aux enfants trouvés. L’abandon</hi> (In the foundlings’ house. Abandonment) engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1583">Stéphane Pannemaker</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 79 (25 March 1882), pp. 194-195, as is evident from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let321.xml">letter 321</ref>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1978">Ill. 1978</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For the prints by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs> in the estate, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml#n-16">see letter 235, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>In the estate there are seven prints by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1454">Richard Caton Woodville (II)</rs>, all from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> 76-78 (1880-1881).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>In the estate there are the following prints by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1170">G. Montbard</rs> on Irish themes: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Types et physionomies d’Irlande – Halte de paysans irlandais au retour d’une fête</hi> (Irish types and physiognomies – Irish peasants resting on the way back from a party), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1581">Henri Pierre Paillard</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 62 (16 August 1873), p. 116. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1958">Ill. 1958</rs>; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Types et physionomies d’Irlande – Un intérieur irlandais </hi>(Irish types and physiognomies – An Irish interior), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 62 (13 September 1873), p. 173 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1979">Ill. 1979</rs>; and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Moeurs irlandaises – Une expulsion</hi> (Irish customs – An eviction), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 63 (10 January 1874) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1980">Ill. 1980</rs>, p. 25. (t*827, t*826 and t*478 respectively.)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            
      
<p>The Channel Islands are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Jersey</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Guernsey</hi>. This must be a case of conflation. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1170">Montbard</rs> did at least one work about Jersey, namely a view of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Montorgueil à Jersey</hi>. See Béraldi 1885-1892, p. 111, no. 17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had submitted a painting of a Drenthe woman at the spinning wheel (present whereabouts unknown) for the exhibition of ‘Levende Meesters’ (Living Masters) at the artists’ society <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arti et Amicitiae</hi>, of which he had been a member since 1881; the painting was to be rejected. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 12, 76, cat. nos. 75-77; and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let277.xml">letter 277</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The term ‘orphan man’ was in fact used mainly for the elderly in the Roman Catholic Orphanage and Old People’s Home in Warmoezierstraat, but evidently more widely applied too. For Van Gogh’s model <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Zuyderland</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let267.xml#n-20">see letter 267, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>This letter sketch, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man with an umbrella seen from the back </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_68">F - / JH 214</rs>), corresponds to the drawing of the same name (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3026">F 968 / JH 213</rs>). The legend ‘N 199’ refers to the number that residents of the Old Men’s and Women’s Home were required to wear visibly. Van Gogh also sketched this number on the right sleeve – which eventually made it possible to identify the model as <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Zuyderland</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 128-131, cat. no. 31.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    