<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 15 October 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let272"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b260 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>272</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>238</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>273</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-10-15">Sunday, 15 October 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0260" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0260" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000318_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief &amp; den inhoud<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel schriftelijken als geldelijken<c type="kk">/</c> deed mij niet weinig genoegen &amp; ik dank er U wel voor, in ’t eerste opzigt was ik vooral blij te hooren dat het misschien niet heel lang hoeft te duren voor ge eens weer naar Holland komt. Zoodra ’t U mogelijk is te bepalen of zulks vóór dan wel nà nieuwe jaar zijn zal<c type="kk">/</c> wil ik dat wel heel graag zoo bij benadering vooruit weten.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik ben zeer blijde dat gij de studies afgezonden hebt<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – ik gevoel het zoo sterk dezer dagen terwijl ik er veel nieuwe bijmaak<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik het werk naar ’t model bij elkaar moet zien te houden. Wat zou ik het heerlijk vinden als ik wat meer met U eens kon overleggen omtrent het werk – doch we zijn te ver van elkaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik zag dezer dagen, en heb het ook in mijn verzameling, eene groote houtsnee naar een Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van <hi rend="italics">Roll</hi><c type="kk">/</c> Une grève de charbonniers<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Kent gij dien schilder soms en indien ja<c type="kk">/</c> wat hebt ge van hem gezien? Dit stelt voor de werf van een charbonnage, waarvoor een talrijke groep mannen en vrouwen en kinderen die blijkbaar het gebouw hebben bestormd. Zij staan of zitten rond een omgestulpte<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> kar, en worden in bedwang gehouden door gendarmes te paard<c type="kp">_</c> Een kerel gooit nog een steen maar eene vrouw tracht zijn arm te grijpen. De karakters zijn uitmuntend en het is ruw en brutaal geteekend en zeker ook geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> geheel in overeenstemming met den aard van het onderwerp. Het is niet als Knaus of Vautier maar met meer hartstogt als ’t ware gedaan – bijna geen details<c type="kk">/</c> alles gemasseerd<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> en vereenvoudigd – maar er is veel stijl in. Er is veel expressie en stemming en sentiment in en de bewegingen van de figuren – de verschillende acties – zijn meesterlijk uitgedrukt. Het trof mij erg en evenzeer Rappard aan wie ik er ook een zond<c type="kp">_</c> Het stond in de Illustration – maar een oud nummer.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb toevalligerwijs er nog een van een Engelsch teekenaar<c type="kk">/</c> Emslie, wiens motief is<c type="kk">/</c> mannen die in de mijn gaan om verongelukten zoo mogelijk nog te helpen terwijl de vrouwen staan te wachten.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Anders zijn zulke onderwerpen slechts zelden gemaakt<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat dat van Roll betreft – ik heb zoo’n scène zelf bijgewoond in al zijn geur en kleur<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – ik vind het mooie van zijn schilderij dat het geheel zoo echt zoo’n toestand uitdrukt – ofschoon men er maar weinig van de details in terug vindt. Ik dacht er bij aan een woord van Corot – il y a des tableaux où il n’y a rien <hi rend="italics">et</hi> <hi>pourtant</hi> <hi rend="italics">tout y est</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Er is in ’t geheel iets groots en klassieks als in een mooi historie schilderij<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – in de compositie en de lijnen en dat is een kwaliteit die tegenwoordig even zeldzaam blijft als ze altijd geweest is en blijven zal.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het doet mij eenigzins aan Gericault denken<c type="kk">/</c> n.l<c type="kp">_</c> aan de Radeau de la Méduse,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en toch tegelijk aan Munkaczy<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> b.v.<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Deze week heb ik eenige groote koppen geteekend en ook eenige kinderfiguren en dan nog weesmannen.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Wat gij zegt van die kleine teekeningetjes<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> ben ik wel met U eens – dat n.l. dat van ’t bankje<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> meer op de ouderwetsche manier gedaan is. Toch deed ik dit min of meer opzettelijk, en zal ’t nog wel eens meer doen misschien. Hoezeer ik ook veel schilderijen en teekeningen die bepaald met ’t oog op den fijn grijze<c type="kk">/</c> harmonieuze kleur en op den localen toon gemaakt zijn prachtig mooi vind<c type="kk">/</c> zoo geloof ik toch dat veel artisten die daar minder bepaald op werkten en nu voor ouderwetsch doorgaan altijd frisch en groen zullen blijven om reden hun manier van doen <hi rend="italics">ook</hi> zijn raison d’être had en <hi rend="italics">houden blijft</hi>. Om U de waarheid te zeggen zou ik noch de ouderwetsche noch de nieuwere opvatting willen missen. In beide rigtingen zijn te veel dingen hors ligne dan dat ik voor mij bepaald aan de een of de andere de voorkeur kan geven systematisch. En niet in alle opzigten zijn de veranderingen door de nieuweren in de kunst gebragt verbeteringen<c type="kk">/</c> niet alles is vooruitgang – noch in ’t werk noch in de personen zelf der artisten en dikwijls komt het mij voor dat velen en hun uitgangspunt en hun doelwit uit ’t oog verliezen – of met andere woorden geen voet bij stek houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Uw beschrijving van dat avondeffekt vond ik weer heel mooi.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> het ziet er hier vandaag heel anders uit maar in zijn soort is het ook mooi. b.v. het terrein bij de Rijnspoor.– op den voorgrond de kolenweg met de populieren die hun blaren beginnen te verliezen – dan de sloot of vaart vol kroos<c type="kk">/</c> met een hoogen kant begroeid met verflenst gras en lisch<c type="kk">/</c> dan de grijze of bruingrijze grond van omgespitte aardappellandjes of plekken beplant met groenachtig paarsche roode kool – hier en daar een heel erg frisch groen van versch opgeschoten herfst onkruid waarbovenuit boonestaken met verwelkte stengels en de roodachtige of groene boonenpeulen – achter die strook grond de rood verroestte en zwarte rails in geel zand – hier &amp; daar stapels oud hout – bergen steenkool<c type="kk">/</c> afgedankte wagons – daarbovenuit regts eenige daken en de goederen remise – links een uitzigt op uitgestrekte<c type="kk">/</c> vochtig groene weien<c type="kk">/</c> aan den horizon wijd weg afgesloten 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>door een graauwe strook waarin men nog boomen<c type="kk">/</c> roode daken &amp; zwarte fabrieksschoorsteenen onderscheiden kan. Er overheen een iets of wat geele maar toch grijze lucht<c type="kk">/</c> erg kil en winterachtig – die laag neer hangt en waaruit een soort stofregen komt bij vlagen en waarin veel hongerige kraaien vliegen. Toch valt er veel licht op alles<c type="kk">/</c> wat vooral uitkomt als een paar figuurtjes met blaauwe of witte kielen over het terrein rondscharrelen<c type="kk">/</c> als wanneer de schouders en koppen licht pakken. Mij dunkt evenwel dat het er te Parijs heel wat helderder zal uitzien en minder kil. Want de killigheid komt tot in huis, en als men een pijp aansteekt is er iets van den motregen in als ’t ware. Maar het is erg mooi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Alleen ’t is op zulke dagen dat het wel gezellig zou zijn eens een vriend op te zoeken of er een bij zich te hebben en ’t is op zulke dagen dat men wel eens iets leegs voelt als men nergens heen kan gaan en er niemand komt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Maar juist dan voel ik toch wat het werk is<c type="kk">/</c> hoe toch onafhankelijk van goedkeuring of afkeuring het toon geeft aan het leven en men op dagen dat men anders melankoliek zou worden blij is een wil te hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik had nog een paar uur model, vandaag een jongen met een schop, opperman van zijn beroep. een heel echt type<c type="kk">/</c> platten neus<c type="kk">/</c> dikke lippen<c type="kk">/</c> erg steil ruw haar – en toch<c type="kk">/</c> als hij iets doet is er gratie in ’t figuur, of liever althans tournure en karakter.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Ik denk wel dat ik nog mooie modellen zal krijgen dezen winter. de baas van de werf heeft mij beloofd de arbeiders die om werk komen vragen<c type="kk">/</c> zooals telkens voorkomt nu en dan in den slappen tijd<c type="kk">/</c> naar mij toe te sturen.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Ik geef ze altijd graag een paar kwartjes voor een middag of morgen want dat is net wat ik hebben moet. Ik zie geen anderen weg dan werken met model<c type="kk">/</c> men mag zeer zeker zijn verbeeldingskracht niet uitdooven – maar juist het voortdurend onder de oogen hebben van de natuur en het worstelen er mee scherpt de verbeeldingskracht en maakt ze juister.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Den volgenden zondag hoop ik dienzelfden jongen weer te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou dan hem eens teekenen zoo als ze de schuiten met steenen voorttrekken – die men hier veel in de vaart ziet. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Het is uit met het buiten gaan werken – dat is bepaald stilzittende werken want het is te guur – dus moeten we maar de winterkwartieren betrekken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Zoo in mijn gevoel heb ik wel lust in den winter<c type="kk">/</c> het is wel een heerlijk saizoen als men geregeld werken kan. Ik heb wel hoop dat het wat vlotten zal<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Dat ik van harte hoop gij het bewuste binnen zult krijgen behoef ik U niet te zeggen. Ik heb zooals ge weet met schilderen &amp; aquarelleeren meer doorgezet dan eerst het plan was en ik moet er nu nog al krom voor liggen. Doch daar zullen we wel doorkomen, en zelfs mag het geen reden zijn om te verslappen. Ik varieer het nu door druk met model te werken ofschoon dat ook nog al oploopt – maar ik krijg er mijn portefeuilles door gevuld naarmate mijn portemonnaie leeger wordt. Mogt het zijn gij tegen den twintigsten de heele gewone som niet bij elkaar hebt stuur dan een gedeelte<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zou liever een dag vroeger dan later ontvangen daar ’t zoo uitkomt met den dag dat ik de huur te betalen heb voor die week.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Behalve dat èèn muur erg vochtig is blijft het huis mij best bevallen. Het werken met model kan hier veel beter dan op het andere atelier – ik kan zelfs met meer personen te gelijk werken<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. twee kinderen onder een parapluie<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> twee vrouwen die staan te praten<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> een man en eene vrouw gearmd,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar wat hebben we hier eigentlijk weinig lente en zomer gehad<c type="kk">/</c> het is mij soms net als of er niets tusschen lag<c type="kk">/</c> tusschen verl. najaar en nu dit<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat kan wel zijn omdat er den tijd tusschen ligt dat ik ziek was. Ik voel me anders nu weer normaal tenzij als ik erg vermoeid ben<c type="kk">/</c> dan heb ik soms een dag of een halve dag dat ik onbeschrijfelijk flaauw en zwak ben<c type="kk">/</c> veel meer dan vroeger. Alleen ik stoor er me niet meer aan want het verveelt me te erg en komt me te slecht gelegen, daar er te veel werk aan den winkel is. Het helpt mij dikwijls dan b.v. eens hard naar Schevening te loopen of zoo.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf vooral weer tegen den twintigsten. ik heb deze keer weer Whatman moeten opdoen en penseelen. Ge kunt niet begrijpen hoe veel dingen men soms noodig heeft. Enfin dat is zoo met ieder schilder. in gedachten een handdruk en geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter and the contents, both written and monetary, gave me not a little pleasure and I do thank you for them. Regarding the first, I was especially glad to hear that it needn’t be very long before you come to Holland again. As soon as it’s possible for you to determine whether it will be before or after the New Year, I’d very much like to know that, roughly, in advance.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’m very glad that you’ve sent the studies<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — I feel so strongly these days while working on many new ones that I must keep the work from the model together. How delightful it would be if I could consult you more often about the work — but we’re too far apart. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The other day I saw, and also have in my collection, a large woodcut after a painting by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Roll</rs></hi>, A miners’ strike.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Do you happen to know this painter and, if so, what have you seen by him? This shows the yard of a coal-mine, in front of which there’s a large group of men, women and children who have evidently stormed the building. They stand or sit around an overturned cart, and are held back by mounted police. One chap throws a stone, but a woman tries to grab his arm. The characters are outstanding, and it’s roughly and boldly drawn, and certainly painted in that way too, entirely as befits the nature of the subject. It’s not like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1131">Knaus</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1403">Vautier</rs>, but done, as it were, with greater passion — almost no details, everything massed together and simplified — but there’s plenty of style in it. There’s a great deal of expression and mood and sentiment in it, and the movements of the figures — the different actions — are masterfully depicted. I was very struck by it, and so was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, to whom I sent one too. It was in L’Illustration, but an old issue.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">As it happens, I have another one by an English draughtsman, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_999">Emslie</rs>, in which the subject is men going into the mine to help the casualties of an accident if possible, while the women stand and wait.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> For the rest, such subjects are rarely treated. As for the one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Roll</rs>, I myself was present at such a scene in all its vivid reality.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> What I find so good in his painting is that as a whole it depicts such a situation so truly, even though one finds few of the details. It reminded me of a remark by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> — ‘There are paintings in which there is nothing <hi rend="italics">and</hi> <hi>yet</hi> <hi rend="italics">everything is there</hi>.’<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> In the whole thing there’s something grand and classical as in a fine history painting<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — in the composition and the lines, and that’s a quality which is just as rare today as it always has been and will remain. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">It reminds me a little of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_606">Géricault</rs>, namely the Raft of the Medusa,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and yet at the same time of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1231">Munkácsy</rs>, for example.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">This week I’ve drawn some large heads and some figures of children as well as orphan men.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I agree with what you say about the small drawings<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> — namely, that the one of the bench<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> is done more in the old-fashioned way. Yet I did that more or less deliberately, and may well do it more. However strikingly beautiful I find many paintings and drawings clearly done with an eye to the subtly grey, harmonious colour and to the local tone, I believe nonetheless that many artists who worked less definitely to that end, and are now seen as old-fashioned, will always remain fresh and green because their approach had its <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi> <hi rend="italics">too</hi> and <hi rend="italics">still does</hi>. To tell you the truth, I wouldn’t like to be without either the old-fashioned or the newer attitude. There are too many excellent things in both schools for me to be able to give preference systematically to one or the other. And the changes introduced in art by the new people aren’t improvements in every respect, it isn’t all progress, neither in the work nor in the persons of the artists, and it often seems to me that many lose sight of both their starting-point and their target, or in other words don’t stand firm.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Your description of that evening effect was again very beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Today it looks very different here, but it’s beautiful too in its way, the Rijnspoor yards, for example. In the foreground the cinder road with the poplars that are starting to lose their leaves — then the ditch or canal full of duckweed, with a high bank with withered grass and bulrushes growing on it, then the grey or brown-grey earth of dug-over potato fields or patches planted with greenish purple red cabbage — here and there a really very fresh green of autumn weeds newly shot up, and above them beanpoles with wilting stalks and the reddish or green beanpods — beyond this strip of land the red rusted and black rails in yellow sand — here and there piles of old wood — mountains of coal, disused wagons — above them on the right several roofs and the goods depot — to the left a view of extensive, damp green meadows, cut off at the horizon far away 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> by a grey band in which trees, red roofs and black factory chimneys can be made out. Over it a slightly yellow but still grey sky, very chilly and wintery, which hangs down low and from which a sort of drizzle comes in waves and in which many hungry crows fly. Yet a good deal of light falls on everything, which is especially evident when a few figures in blue or white smocks potter about in the yards, when their shoulders and heads catch the light. However, I imagine that it looks considerably brighter and less chilly in Paris. For the chillness gets into the house, and when you light a pipe there’s something of the drizzle in it, as it were. But it’s very beautiful. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But on such days it would be nice to look up a friend or to be in the company of one, and on such days one sometimes has an empty feeling if one can’t go anywhere and nobody comes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Yet it’s precisely then that I feel what the work is; how, regardless of approval or disapproval, it gives tone to life, and how on days when one would otherwise feel melancholy one is glad to have a will. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I had a model for a few hours, today a boy with a spade, a builder’s labourer by trade. A very genuine type, flat nose, thick lips, very straight, coarse hair — and yet, when he does something there’s grace in the figure, or rather expression at any rate, and character.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> I think I’ll get more good models this winter. The boss of the yard has promised to send me the labourers who come to ask for work, as regularly happens now and then in the slack time.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I like to give them half a guilder for an afternoon or morning, because that’s just what I need. I see no other way than to work with models. One very definitely shouldn’t snuff out one’s power of imagination, but it’s precisely the constant looking at nature and the struggle with it that sharpens the power of imagination and makes it more accurate. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Next Sunday I hope to get the same boy again. I then want to draw him the way they are when they pull the barges with bricks, which is a common sight on the canal here. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> Going out of doors to work is all over now — you have to do that sitting still, and it’s too raw — so we must move into winter quarters. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The way I feel, I’m looking forward to the winter, it’s a marvellous season if you can work regularly. I hope that it’ll make more headway. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I don’t need to tell you that I sincerely hope you’ll receive the you know what. As you know, I’ve carried on longer with painting and watercolouring than first planned, and now I must scrimp and save. But we’ll get through that, and even more it can be no reason to slacken off. I’m varying it now by working a good deal with models, though that also mounts up — but I’m filling my portfolios as I empty my wallet. Should you not have all of the normal sum towards the twentieth then send a part, but I would prefer to receive it a day earlier rather than later, since it works out that on that day I have to pay the rent for the week. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m still pleased with the house, except that one wall is very damp. Working with a model can be done much better here than in the other studio — I can even work with more than one person at a time, for example two children under an umbrella,<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> two women who stand talking,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> a man and a woman arm in arm,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> &amp;c. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But how little spring and summer we’ve had here. It sometimes seems to me as if there has been nothing in between, between last autumn and this one now, but that may be because the time in between was when I was ill. By the way, I feel normal again now, except when I’m very tired, then I sometimes have a day or half a day when I’m indescribably faint and weak, much more so than in the past. But I no longer let it disturb me, for it annoys me too much and is too inconvenient, since there’s too much to do. It often helps, for example, if I take a brisk walk to Scheveningen, or something like that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Well, do write again towards the twentieth. This time I’ve had to get in Whatman again and brushes. You can’t imagine how many things one needs sometimes. Well, that goes for every painter. In thought a handshake, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent writes that he has received Theo’s letter and remittance and remarks: ‘Should you not have all of the normal sum towards the twentieth then send a part’ <ref target="#l-140">(ll. 140-141)</ref>. So the letter dates from before 20 October. The same day he had as a model ‘a boy with a spade’, who would probably come again ‘next Sunday’ (<ref target="#l-107">l. 107</ref> and <ref target="#l-122">l. 122</ref>). So it is likely that the session ‘today’ was also on a Sunday, which means that the present letter dates from Sunday, 15 October 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo had not been repaid for a loan <ref target="let262.xml">(262)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo would not visit The Hague again until August 1883 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let373.xml">see letter 373</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Vincent had asked Theo more than once to return earlier sketches and studies (from the model). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>For the engraving after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Roll</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1950"><hi rend="italics">A miners’ strike</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml#n-5">see letter 263, n. 5.</ref> The painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A miners’ strike</hi> (lost) is reproduced in Weisberg 1992, p. 98, ill. 108.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘gekantelde’ (overturned).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘als één geheel (‘masse’) samengebracht, zonder dat de details zijn uitgewerkt’ (brought together as one whole ((mass)), without the details being elaborated).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> of 29 October 1881.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_999">Emslie</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1951"><hi rend="italics">A colliery explosion</hi></rs>, to which Van Gogh implicitly referred earlier, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml#n-6">see letter 263, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let152.xml">letter 152</ref> Van Gogh writes that he had once spoken to a man who managed to restrain striking workers; it is not known when he himself was present at a strike.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Here Van Gogh is referring to the conclusion of the following conversation: ‘One day, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> said to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>: I’m not happy: I lack skill. What do you mean, you lack skill? replied Daubigny. You put nothing on the canvas, and it’s all there!’ (Un jour, Corot disait à Daubigny:– Je ne suis pas content: je manque de métier.– Comment, tu manques de métier? répliqua Daubigny. Tu ne mets rien sur la toile, et tout y est!). Quoted in Corot 1946, p. 102, and in L. Roger-Milès, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Corot</hi>. Paris 1891, p. 38.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>A ‘history painting’ is a painting on a subject taken from classical antiquity, the Bible or history. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_606">Théodore Géricault</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The raft of the Medusa</hi>, 1819 (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_870">Ill. 870</rs>. There were various prints after this work. See Lorenz Eitner, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Géricault’s raft of the Medusa</hi>. London 1972.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The painter<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1231"> Mihály (von) Munkácsy</rs> was acclaimed for his virtuoso painting technique, dramatic chiaroscuro and forceful portrayal of character.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The descriptions of these figure drawings are too general for them to be identified with specific works. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>These are the small watercolours of the four seasons that Vincent had sent to Theo – of them <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Miners in the snow: winter</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_73">F 1202 / JH 229</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard in blossom with two figures: spring</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_72">F 1245 / JH 230</rs>) are known; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let271.xml">see letter 271</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Four people on a bench</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_63">F - / JH 195</rs>), sent with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let262.xml">letter 262</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Theo had earlier sent descriptions of a scene in Montmartre and ‘the effect of the chestnut trees’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let260.xml">letters 260</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let264.xml">264</ref>). Immediately after referring to Theo’s third evocation, Vincent begins a detailed evocation of his own that is full of colour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            
      
<p>This boy is possibly depicted in the drawings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Boy with a spade</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_833">F 827 / JH C.B.</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Boy with a spade</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_389">F 986 / JH 231</rs>). See cat. Otterlo 2007, p. 160.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The drawings modelled for by workers from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812 bio.xml#_813">De Zwart</rs>’s carpenter’s yard at this time may include <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_390">F 1043 / JH 206</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter seen from the back</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_391">F 1042 / JH 207</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Carpenter with an apron</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_392">F 1044 / JH 208</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>A drawing of two children under an umbrella is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Two women</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2403">F 988 / JH 232</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man and woman seen from the back</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2404">F 991 / JH 233</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    