<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Wednesday, 1 November 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let278"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b262 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>278</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>240</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>279</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-01">Wednesday, 1 November 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0262" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0262" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000320_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">1 Nov.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Sedert een paar dagen ben ik zeer vervuld van iets dat mogelijk U ook interesseeren zal &amp; ik acht het de moeite wel waard er eens in ’t bijzonder over te schrijven. In een brief van Rappard ontving ik een uittreksel van een discours van <hi rend="italics">Herkomer</hi><c type="kk">/</c> tot onderwerp hebbende de houtgravures van den nieuweren tijd.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik kan in zijn geheel U alles niet uitvoerig zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> mogelijk hebt gij zelf het artikel (dat in een Engelsch tijdschrift over kunst gestaan heeft<c type="kk">/</c> misschien ’t Art Journal) wel gelezen. Het was vooral over de teekeningen in the Graphic.– <hi rend="italics">Herkomer</hi> verhaalt hoe hij zelf met groote ambitie &amp; enthousiasme er aan mee gewerkt heeft en brengt vooral de prachtige bladen uit de eerste jaargangen in herinnering.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Heeft geen woorden genoeg naar zijn zin om krachtig uit te drukken hoe belang<c type="shy">-</c>rijk hij het werk van die oorspronkelijke artisten vindt. Hij geeft een overzigt over den vooruitgang in procédé en techniek, over ’t verschil tusschen de oude en de moderne houtgravure, &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c. Spreekt dan over den dag van heden en komt dan op de eigentlijke bedoeling van zijn discours. Hij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> de houtgraveurs zijn knapper dan ooit doch evenwel zie ik voor mij een decadence als ik denk aan den tijd toen de Graphic begon.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En – gaat hij voort – dat zit hem mijns inziens in twee dingen, waar ik tegen protesteer. ’t Eene gaat den uitgevers – ’t laatste den artisten aan.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Er zijn fouten bij beiden en die zullen de boel bederven als er niet tegen gestreden wordt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De uitgevers<c type="kk">/</c> zegt hij<c type="kk">/</c> eischen dingen die op effekt gewerkt zijn<c type="kk">/</c> “correct &amp; honest drawing is no longer wanted, complete designs are no longer in request<c type="kk">/</c> a “bit” just covering an awkward corner of a page, is all that is required”.–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">The managers declare that the public require the representation of a public event or so and are satisfied if it is correct &amp; entertaining<c type="kk">/</c> caring nothing for the artistic qualities of the work. I do not believe what they say.– The only excuse you may accept is “dearth of good draughtsmen”.–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Hij komt dan<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> op de artisten &amp; zegt dat hij het betreurt tegenwoordig maar al te dikwijls het de houtgraveur<c type="kk">/</c> niet de teekenaar is die de bladen mooi maakt. Spoort de artisten aan dit niet te willen – sober en krachtig te teekenen zoo dat de graveur blijve wat hij zijn moet<c type="kk">/</c> de vertolker van het werk van den teekenaar<c type="kk">/</c> en hun niet de baas worde. Dan komt zijn conclusie<c type="kk">/</c> een krachtige stem tot allen om warm te blijven voor de zaak, en niet toe te laten er verslapping plaats hebbe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Er is in zijn stem wel als een verwijt en ’t is niet zonder ietwat melankolie dat hij spreekt<c type="kk">/</c> en als strijdende tegen de hem onuitstaanbare onverschilligheid.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">To you – the public – the art offers infinite pleasure &amp; edification. For you it is really done. Therefore clamour loudly for good work and be sure it will be forthcoming.– is zijn laatste woord.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Het geheel is door &amp; door gezond<c type="kk">/</c> flink<c type="kk">/</c> eerlijk. zijn manier van spreken maakt op mij een indruk als sommige brieven van Millet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Mij is het een opwekking en het doet mij van harte goed eens zóó te hooren spreken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik zeg dat het verbazend jammer is dat voor de meest voor het eigentlijke volk geschikte kunst hier om zoo te zeggen geen animo is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Als de schilders zich combineerden om te zorgen hun werk (dat toch m.i. voor ’t volk gemaakt wordt – althans dit vind ik de hoogste<c type="kk">/</c> nobelste roeping voor elk artist) ook in handen van ’t volk komen kon &amp; in ieders bereik gesteld werd dan zou dat iets zijn waarvan men dito resultaten kon krijgen als verkregen werden in de eerste jaren van de Graphic.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Neuhuys<c type="kk">/</c> v.d. Velden &amp; een paar anderen maakten dit jaar teekeningen voor “de Zwaluw”<c type="kk">/</c> een blad dat maandelijks verschijnt en 7 1/2 cent kost.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Er zijn goede bij<c type="kk">/</c> toch<c type="kk">/</c> men kan zien aan de meesten dat het met slappe hand gedaan is (Niet de oorspronkelijke teekeningen doch de manier om ze te populariseeren) en naar ik hoor kan het blad ’t weer evenmin houden als zijn voorgangers. Waarom gaat het niet – de boekhandelaars zeggen, er is niets aan te verdienen en in plaats van te verspreiden houden ze tegen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">En ik geloof dat wat de schilders aangaat zij de zaak nog niet met alle kracht ter harte hebben genomen. De definitie die menig schilder hier in Holland ten antwoord geeft op de vraag Wat is een houtgravure? is: “’t zijn <hi rend="italics">van die dingen</hi> die in ’t Zuid Hollandsch Koffijhuis liggen”.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Dus ze rangschikken ze onder de borreltjes.– En de makers er van misschien onder de dronkaards.–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En wat zeggen de handelaars – gesteld ik ging met een 100tal schetsen dat ik nu eens bijeen gezocht heb naar wie dan ook hier – op zijn best zou ik hooren<c type="kk">/</c> vrees ik<c type="kk">/</c> “dacht ge soms dat <hi rend="italics">die dingen</hi> handelswaarde hadden?”</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Mijn liefde en respect voor de groote teekenaars<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel van den tijd van Gavarni als voor die van tegenwoordig<c type="kk">/</c> neemt toe hoe meer ik van hun werk kennis krijg en vooral ook terwijl ik mijn best doe zelf iets van datgene te maken wat men alle dagen op straat ziet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Wat ik in <hi rend="italics">Herkomer</hi><c type="kk">/</c> in <hi rend="italics">Fildes</hi><c type="kk">/</c> in <hi rend="italics">Holl</hi> en de andere stichters van de Graphic op prijs stel<c type="kk">/</c> waarom zij mij nog meer dan Gavarni &amp; Daumier sympathiek zijn en blijven zullen<c type="kk">/</c> is dat terwijl laatstgenoemden de maatschappij meer met malice schijnen te beschouwen<c type="kk">/</c> eerstgenoemden in overeenstemming met mannen als Millet<c type="kk">/</c> Breton<c type="kk">/</c> de Groux<c type="kk">/</c> Israels<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> sujetten kiezen – even <hi rend="italics">waar</hi> als Gav. of Daum. – maar die iets nobels hebben en waar een ernstiger sentiment in is. Dat vooral moet blijven dunkt mij<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Een artist hoeft geen dominé of collectant te wezen maar toch wel degelijk een warm hart hebben voor de menschen en ik vind het b.v. iets nobels dat er geen winter voorbijging of de Graphic deed iets om sympathie voor de armen wakker te houden. b.v. heb ik een blad van Woodville<c type="kk">/</c> voorstellende een uitdeeling van turfkaartjes in Ierland,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> een ander van Staniland<c type="kk">/</c> getiteld <hi rend="italics">Help the helpers</hi><c type="kk">/</c> voorstellende allerlei scenes uit een gasthuis – waar geld te kort kwam<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Christmas in the Workhouse van Herkomer<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Homeless &amp; hungry van Fildes<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> Dat vind ik nog mooier dan de teekeningen van Bertall of zoo voor de Vie élégante of andere élégances<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Misschien vindt ge dit schrijven vervelend – maar het kwam me weer alles frisch in de gedachten. Ik had mijn 100tal studies bijeen gezocht en opgezet en toen ik met dit karweitje klaar was kwam er een wat melankoliek gevoel bij me op van à quoi bon – maar toen deed mij dat energiek woord van Herkomer<c type="kk">/</c> die de lui oproept om niet te verflaauwen en zegt dat meer dan ooit het noodig is de hand te houden aan den ploeg<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> zoo goed<c type="kk">/</c> en ik dacht<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou U den inhoud van wat hij zei eens in ’t kort meedeelen. Met een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kk">/</c> geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Ik hoop dezer dagen van U te hooren, ik ontving van t’huis een goeden brief<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">1 Nov.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">For several days I’ve been completely taken up by something that may also be of interest to you and I think it well worth writing to you about it especially. In a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> I received an extract from a lecture by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs></hi> on the subject of the wood engravings of recent times.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I can’t tell you about the whole thing in detail, you may have read the article yourself (which was in an English art magazine, perhaps the Art Journal). It was mainly about the drawings in The Graphic. <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs></hi> relates how he himself worked on them with great ambition and enthusiasm, and he particularly recalls the splendid prints in the first volumes.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Feels that no words can express sufficiently forcefully how important he finds the work of those first artists. He reviews the progress made in process and technique, the difference between the old and the modern wood engraving, &amp;c. &amp;c. Then talks about the present day, and that brings him to the real subject of his lecture. He says: the wood engravers are cleverer than ever, but nonetheless I see a decadence if I think back to when The Graphic began.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And — he goes on — in my view the reason lies in two things against which I protest. One has to do with the publishers, the other with the artists. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Both have their faults, which will ruin things if one doesn’t combat them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The publishers, he says, demand things done for effect: ‘correct and honest drawing is no longer wanted, complete designs are no longer in request, a “bit” just covering an awkward corner of a page, is all that is required’.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">‘The managers declare that the public require the representation of a public event or so and are satisfied if it is correct and entertaining, caring nothing for the artistic qualities of the work. I do not believe what they say. The only excuse you may accept is “dearth of good draughtsmen”’.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Then<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> he comes to the artists, and says that he regrets that these days all too often it’s the wood engraver, not the draughtsman, who makes the prints beautiful. Urges the artists not to accept this — to draw soberly and forcefully so that the engraver remains what he should be, the translator of the draughtsman’s work, and doesn’t get the upper hand. Then comes his conclusion, a forceful plea to all to continue supporting the cause warmly, and not to allow any weakening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">There’s something of a reproach in his plea, and it isn’t without some melancholy that he speaks, and as one fighting against the indifference he finds intolerable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">‘To you — the public — the art offers infinite pleasure and edification. For you it is really done. Therefore clamour loudly for good work and be sure it will be forthcoming’ — are his closing words.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The whole thing is thoroughly sound, firm, honest. His manner of speaking makes the same impression on me as some letters by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It gives me encouragement, and it truly does me good to hear someone talk like that for once. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I say that it’s a terrible pity that here there’s no enthusiasm, so to speak, for the art that’s most suitable for the common people. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">If the painters were to close ranks to ensure that their work (which, after all, is made for the people, in my view — at least I believe that is the highest, noblest vocation for any artist) could also come into the hands of the people and was put within everyone’s reach, that would be something that would produce the same results as were produced in the first years of The Graphic. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1248">Neuhuys</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1400">Van der Velden</rs> and a few others made drawings this year for ‘De Zwaluw’, a magazine that appears monthly and costs 7 1/2 cents.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> There are some good ones, but one can see that most were done with a weak hand (not the original drawings but the way of popularizing them), and from what I hear the magazine is no more likely to keep going than its predecessors. Why doesn’t it work? — the booksellers say they earn nothing from it, and instead of circulating it they block it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And as for the painters, I believe they haven’t yet made every effort to take the matter to heart. The definition that many a painter here in Holland gives in reply to the question ‘What is a wood engraving?’ is: ‘it’s <hi rend="italics">those things </hi>lying in the Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> So they rank them among the drinks. And the makers of them among the drunks, perhaps. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">And what do the dealers say? Suppose I went to anyone here with around 100 sketches that I’ve gathered together. At best I fear I would be told ‘did you imagine <hi rend="italics">those things</hi> had commercial value?’</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">My love and respect for the great draughtsmen of both the age of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> and of the present day increases the better acquainted with their work I become, and above all as I do my best myself to make something from what one sees every day on the streets.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">What I value in <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs></hi>, in <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1026">Fildes</rs></hi>, in <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Holl</rs></hi> and the other founders of The Graphic, why I find and will continue to find them even more sympathetic than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, is that, while the latter seem to view society more with mockery, the former, like such men as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899 bio.xml#_905">Breton</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> choose subjects which — while as <hi rend="italics">true</hi> as those of Gav. or Daum. — have something noble and in which there’s a more serious sentiment. That, above all, must remain, it seems to me. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">An artist need not be a minister or a collector in church, but he must have a warm heart for people, and I find it a noble thing that, for example, no winter passed without The Graphic doing something to keep alive sympathy for the poor. For instance, I have a print by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1454">Woodville</rs> showing the distribution of turf tickets in Ireland,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> another by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1364">Staniland</rs> entitled <hi rend="italics">Help the helpers</hi> depicting various scenes in a hospital — where money was short,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Christmas in the workhouse by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Homeless and hungry by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1026">Fildes</rs><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> &amp;c. I find them even more beautiful than the drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_862">Bertall</rs> or somebody for the Vie Elégante or other élégances.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Perhaps you’ll find this a tedious letter — but everything was once more fresh in my mind. I had gathered together and mounted my 100 or so studies and when I had finished the job a slightly melancholy sense of ‘what’s the good?’ came over me — but then Herkomer’s forceful words calling on people not to weaken and saying that it’s more necessary than ever to keep the hand to the plough<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> did me so much good, and I thought I’d briefly tell you the substance of what he said. With a handshake in thought, believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I hope to hear from you in the coming days, I received a good letter from home. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘1 Nov.’ In view of the article by Herkomer that is the central topic (<ref target="#l-5">ll. 5</ref> ff.), this must be the same 1 November as in <ref target="let279.xml">letter 279</ref>, where it is again the main subject, and so it must be Wednesday, 1 November 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>The article, published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Art Journal</hi>, is ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_270">Drawing and engraving on wood</ref>’ (Herkomer 1882). A note to the article says: ‘This paper was delivered at the London Institution in January, 1882’. The tenor of the passages cited corresponds with what <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs> wrote. There is no way of knowing whether <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> enclosed the extracts from the article in his letter (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let276.xml">letter 276</ref>) or sent them separately, with or without an accompanying letter. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> first appeared in December 1869.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The word ‘decadence’ is found in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs> and must have particularly impressed Van Gogh; he refers to it several times. After a brief history of the wood engraving, in which the engraving was done by a person other than the draughtsman, Herkomer wrote: ‘Now, here we pass to modern times, when some of our best painters have drawn their best works on wood, and for whom a body of engravers has been raised up who have brought the art of engraving on wood to such a degree of perfection, that the most modern work, especially that of the Americans, is done to show the skill of the engraver rather than the art of the draughtsman. I do not hesitate to say that this is the first sign of a decadence’ (Herkomer 1882, p. 167, col. 2; cf. for the word also p. 133, col. 2).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>In the original article on p. 167, col. 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This quotation is on p. 168, col. 1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In the original article the passage cited below came <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">before</hi> the one above; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> may have turned them round in his extract.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This quotation is derived from p. 168, col. 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Zwaluw. Volksblad met Platen onder Toezicht van de Maatschappij tot Nut van ’t Algemeen</hi> (1882) was aimed at the lower classes. It included four folio pages in each issue, one with a large illustration and another with a small one. The short texts were moralistic or didactic in character. The magazine appeared only in the years 1882-1883 and was published under the supervision of the Society for General Welfare. The price was 7.5 cents per issue and 90 cents per volume in 1882, and 5 cents per issue and 60 cents per volume in 1883.</p>

<p rend="indent">Two drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1248">Albert Neuhuys</rs> were published: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_423"><hi rend="italics">Gerrit, Aaltje en de wieg</hi></rs> (Gerrit, Aaltje and the cradle) and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_424"><hi rend="italics">Rika met de kinderen</hi></rs> (Rika with the children). The engravers were <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1372">Auguste</rs> and Emile Tilly (no. 4, April 1882, p. 4 and no. 8, August 1882, p. 4).</p>

<p rend="indent">Two drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1400">Pieter van der Velden</rs> were published, both engraved by Johannes Walter: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_425"><hi rend="italics">Piet van den Visscher</hi></rs> (Piet van den Visscher) and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_426"><hi rend="italics">De bellenblazer</hi></rs> (The bubble-blower) (no. 2, February 1882, p. 1 and no. 7, July 1882, p. 1). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For the ‘Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let214.xml#n-9">see letter 214, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules</rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_905">Emile Adélard Breton</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1454">Richard Caton Woodville (<hi>ii</hi>)</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The state of Ireland: Distributing relief tickets in the turf-market, Westport, County Mayo</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> 76 (6 March 1880), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1574">W.I. Mosses</rs>, ‘Extra supplement’, between pp. 224 and 225. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1992">Ill. 1992</rs>. Van Gogh is mistaken in his interpretation of the print; the accompanying text speaks of the ‘distribution of relief tickets for small portions of “yellow meal” or maize flour doled out by the local Relief Committees’ (p. 227). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1364">Charles Joseph Staniland</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">“Help the helpers!” – Hospital Sunday, June 13 1880</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic </hi>21 (12 June 1880), pp. 596-597. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1351">Ill. 1351</rs>. Van Gogh derived his knowledge about the call for money from the commentary accompanying the illustration in the magazine (p. 594).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Christmas in a workhouse</hi>, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1591">Charles Roberts</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Graphic</hi> 14 (25 December 1876), Christmas Number, p. 30. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_166">Ill. 166</rs>. (t*93).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1026">Fildes</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1905"><hi rend="italics">Houseless and hungry</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let199.xml#n-8">see letter 199, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_862">Charles Albert Bertall, vicomte d’Arnoux</rs>, depicted the beau-monde in numerous magazine illustrations (fashion, horse racing, sport, hunting and at the beach). He also illustrated an edition of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_223"><hi rend="italics">Petites misères de la vie conjugale</hi></ref> (1845). As far as can be made out, he did not contribute to the sumptuous magazine <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Vie Elégante</hi>, that had the same type of illustrations. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
  Luke 9:62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    