<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Wednesday, 22 November 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let285"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b268 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>285</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>246</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>287</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-22">Wednesday, 22 November 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0268" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0268" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000328_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Woensdag morgen</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Tegelijk met dezen brief ontvangt ge de eerste epreuves van eene lith. <hi rend="italics">Spitter</hi> en van eene lith. <hi rend="italics">Koffijdrinker</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zeer gaarne verneem ik den indruk die ze U geven zullen zoodra mogelijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik ben voornemens ze nog te retoucheeren op den steen en wilde daarbij wel eens Uwe opinie hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De teekeningen waren mooier<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> vooral op den <hi rend="italics">Spitter</hi> had ik veel gesjouwd<c type="kk">/</c> nu zijn door ’t transporteeren<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> &amp; drukken verschillende dingen verloren gegaan<c type="kp">_</c> Doch wat ik van deze drukken vind is dat er iets ruws en ongegeneerds in zit wat ik er ook in wilde hebben<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen me betrekkelijk verzoent met het verloren gaan van dingen die in de teekening waren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">De teekening was niet alleen gedaan met lith. krijt doch bovendien de krachten versterkt door autographische inkt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Nu heeft de steen die autogr. inkt slechts ten deele gepakt &amp; we weten niet precies waar dit aan toe te schrijven is<c type="kk">/</c> waarschijnlijk aan het water waarmee ik ze aangemaakt heb.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">In elk geval heb ik er door gezien ’t daar waar ’t gepakt heeft flinke krachten van zwart geeft waarmee ik later hoop ik gelukkiger zal zijn. Dan – als de drukker tijd heeft gaan we proeven nemen met een soort lavis<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> er over te brengen onder ’t drukken en zullen verschillende soorten van papier probeeren en verschillende soorten van drukinkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik hoop dat deze twee steenen nog verbeteren zullen door de retouche naar de beide studies<c type="kk">/</c> direkt naar ’t model gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> welke ik nog heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">’t Is me eindelijk eens overkomen dat een schilder bij me geweest is<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. Van der Weele<c type="kk">/</c> die me op straat staande hield en bij wien ik ook eens geweest ben.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik heb wel hoop hij ook eens dit procede van lith. zal beproeven<c type="kp">_</c> ik wou hij er twee ploegen welke hij heeft<c type="kk">/</c> geschilderde studies (een morgen- &amp; avond effekt)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> mee deed<c type="kk">/</c> en een ossenkar op de hei<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Die kerel heeft verscheiden mooie dingen op zijn atelier<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Hij wou dat ik van mijn talrijke studies Weesmannen iets composeeren zou doch ik voel me nog niet klaar<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ge weet<c type="kk">/</c> ik schreef U over eene serie Spitters<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> nu ziet ge daar ook eens een blad uit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Van den brief nog geen nieuws<c type="kk">/</c> hier weet men niets aan ’t postkantoor er van en gooit het op Parijs.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Toen Uw laatsten brief kwam had ik doordat ik zoo lang gewacht had er op er direkt zooveel van te betalen dat er weinig overschoot.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Evenwel ik heb toch op nieuw deze beide proeven met de lith. genomen al waren er kosten aan<c type="kk">/</c> omdat ik vooral in moeielijke tijden in ’t werk nog ’t meeste heil zie en wil vechten om er bovenop te komen<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vandaag of morgen zal echter mijn geld op zijn. Is het U mogelijk iets te doen zoo doe het – kan het niet dan is dit buiten Uw en mijn schuld – doch het zouden harde dagen zijn. Enfin quand même zoolang we kunnen het hart hoog houden<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> zoo hoog we kunnen en zoo lang we kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> boven de melankolie of verslapping.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Er is hier een volksblad de Zwaluw genaamd<c type="kk">/</c> uitgave Elsevier Rotterdam<c type="kk">/</c> gesteund door Maatschappij Nut v. ’t algemeen.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ik heb dezer dagen wel eens er aan gedacht of die niet b.v. zoo’n spitter zouden kunnen gebruiken. Maandelijks 1 blad. Doch ’t zou me een reis n. Rotterdam kosten<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en ik vrees zoo zeer t’huis te komen met de boodschap: Het gaat te slap<c type="kk">/</c> we nemen niets &amp;c. Bovendien<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou dit liever niet dan wel doen daar ik veel liever langer werk tot er een flinke serie zou mogelijk zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Doch ik peins er al op om reden ik soms bar verlegen ben om er wat bij te verdienen. Que faire?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ook als ge geen geld hebt, kerel, schrijf toch want ik heb Uw sympathie noodig en die is me niet minder steun dan het geld. Het rolletje lith<c type="kp">_</c> waarin Sorrow was &amp; den brief daarbij hebt ge hoop ik ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> ik schrijf ’t nog eens om zeker te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> niet omdat ik reeds antwoord gewacht had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Het weer is zeer koud hier geweest; van daag erg donker grijs en triestig<c type="kk">/</c> dat echter wel weer een ruw aspect van non ébarbé<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> aan de dingen geeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">à Dieu<c type="kk">/</c> van harte het beste U toegewenscht en een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kk">/</c> geloof me steeds</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">In de teekening van den Koffijdrinker was het zwart veel meer gebroken door de rigting van de hachure.<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> Dit is nu dof geworden ongelukkigerwijs – maar welligt te redresseeren.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Wednesday morning</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Together with this letter you’re receiving the first proofs of one lithograph, <hi rend="italics">Digger</hi>, and one lithograph, <hi rend="italics">Coffee drinker</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’d very much like to know as soon as possible what impression they make on you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I still plan to retouch them on the stone, and would like to have your opinion for that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The drawings were better,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I put a lot of work into the <hi rend="italics">Digger</hi> especially; now various things have been lost through the transfer and printing. Yet what I think of these impressions is that there’s something rough and unabashed in them that I indeed wanted them to have, which partly reconciles me to the loss of things that were in the drawing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The drawing was done not only with lithographic crayon; the strengths were reinforced with autographic ink as well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Now the stone has only taken part of the autographic ink, and we don’t know exactly what to attribute this to, probably the water with which I mixed them.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Anyway, as a result I’ve seen that where it has taken it gives good strengths of black, with which I hope to be more successful later on. Then, when the printer has time, we’re going to experiment by putting on a kind of wash during printing, and will try out various types of paper and different sorts of printing ink.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I hope that these two stones will improve further through the retouching after the two studies, done directly from the model, which I still have. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">It has finally come about that a painter has been to visit me, namely <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>, who stopped me in the street and whom I had also visited once.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I have hopes that he too will try this lithographic process. I would like him to do two ploughs he has with it, painted studies (a morning and evening effect),<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and an ox-cart on the heath.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> That fellow has several beautiful things in his studio.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">He wanted me to compose something from my numerous studies of orphan men, but I don’t feel ready yet.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">As you know, I wrote to you about a series of Diggers,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> now you can see a print from it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">No news yet about the letter. The people at the post office here know nothing about it and blame it on Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">When your last letter arrived I had to pay so much immediately, because I had waited for it for so long, that little was left.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> All the same, I again did these two lithographic trials, even though there were costs involved, because I think work offers the most hope, especially in difficult times, and intend to fight to pull through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Today or tomorrow, however, I’ll run out of money. If it’s possible for you to do something, do it — if not, then it isn’t your fault or mine, but the days would be hard. Anyway, nonetheless, as long as we can lift up our hearts<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> as high as we can and as long as we can, above melancholy or weakening.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">There’s a popular magazine here called De Zwaluw which is published by Elsevier Rotterdam supported by the Society for General Welfare.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I’ve sometimes wondered in recent days whether they could use a digger like that, for example. 1 print a month. But it would cost me a trip to Rotterdam,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and I’m so afraid of coming back with the message: Things are too slack, we’re not taking anything &amp;c. Moreover, I would prefer not to do this, since I would much rather work longer until a substantial series is possible. Yet I do consider it, because I’m sometimes desperate to earn a little extra. What to do?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Even if you have no money, write anyway old chap, for I need your sympathy, and that’s no less of a support to me than the money. I hope you’ve now received the roll of lithographs with Sorrow in it and the letter.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I mention it again to be sure, not because I already expected an answer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">It has been very cold here. Today very dark grey and dreary, which, however, does give things a rough, burred look.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Adieu, I sincerely wish you all the best, and a handshake in thought, believe me always</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">In the drawing of the Coffee drinker the black was much more broken by the direction of the hatching. It has now become dull, unfortunately, but this can probably be corrected.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Woensdag morgen’. When Van Gogh says in <ref target="let286.xml">letter 286</ref> that a letter from him must have crossed Theo’s letter of 20 November 1882, he undoubtedly means the present letter; cf., for example, the reference in <ref target="let286.xml">letter 286</ref> to the sending of the roll with the lithographs of the <hi rend="italics">Digger</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi> (<ref target="#l-2">ll. 2-4</ref> of this letter) and the assumption that Theo will have understood from the letter that crossed how much he is looking forward to the next remittance (<ref target="#l-70">ll. 70-74</ref> of this letter). So the ‘Woensdag’ on which the letter was written must be 22 November 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is drawing diggers <ref target="let281.xml">(281)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Missing letter with money from Theo <ref target="let283.xml">(283)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The first of the two lithographs sent is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412">F 1656 / JH 262</rs>), of which four impressions are known. The other is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2415">F 1657 / JH 266</rs>), three impressions of which are known. There is one copy of each with the note ‘1re épreuve’ in the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The drawing on which <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> was based is not known. The basis for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2415"><hi rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi></rs> was probably the drawing <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2414">F 996a / JH 264</rs>; another possibility is <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2413">F 1682 / JH 263</rs>. See Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 43-51, 91-92, cat. nos. 3 and 4; and cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 133-135, cat. no. 32.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘overbrengen’ (transfer of the drawing).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘wassing’ (wash).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In December 1882 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Herman Johannes van der Weele</rs> was living at Hobbemastraat 17 in The Hague (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboeken 1881-1883</hi>). A separate address for his studio is not given. Photos of his studio in P.A. Haaxman Jr, ‘H.J. van der Weele’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Elsevier’s Geïllustreerd Maandblad</hi> 8 (1898), vol. 16, p. 305 and exhib. cat. The Hague 2005, p. 39, where the street is given as Statenlaan. As shown by <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let287.xml">letter 287</ref>, Van der Weele’s visit took place on Sunday, 19 November 1882.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> painted numerous ploughs and ox-carts with morning, afternoon and evening effects. It is not possible to identify the two ‘studies’ referred to here. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ox-cart on the heath</hi> may well be<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440"> Van der Weele</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peasant on an ox cart</hi> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_454">Ill. 454</rs>. Cf. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Van Gogh Museum Journal</hi> 1995, p. 207 and Hefting 1976, p. 135.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
      
<p>For the three known diggers from this period, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2410">F 906 / JH 260</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2411">F 907 / JH 261</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_429">F 908 / JH 258</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let281.xml#n-10">see letter 281, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>From this remark it is evident that Theo had again enclosed money with his letter that arrived on 16 or 17 November (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let283.xml">see letter 283</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For the expression ‘lift up our hearts’ (Sursum corda), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let143.xml#n-49">see letter 143, n. 49.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For the monthly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Zwaluw</hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let278.xml#n-8">see letter 278, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>A 3rd class return ticket from The Hague to Rotterdam would have cost Van Gogh about 1 to 1.25 guilders (Utrecht, Nederlands Spoorwegmuseum).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2409">F 1655 / JH 259</rs>) was sent at the same time as <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let283.xml">letter 283</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Means: ‘with the burr not removed’, hence rough. For ‘non ébarbé’ see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let217.xml#n-2">letter 217, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>‘Hachure’ is another word for hatching or shading of short lines.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    