<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Friday, 24 November 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let286"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b269 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>286</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>247</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>288</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-24">Friday, 24 November 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0269" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0269" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000329_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw aanget. brief van 20 Nov. heb ik in orde ontvangen &amp; dank U zeer voor het zenden er van, uit mijn brief die den Uwen moet gekruist hebben zult ge reeds hebben kunnen zien hoe welkom het was.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Doch ge schrijft dat tegelijk met dien brief ge het papier van Buhot zondt – dit nu was er niet bij en heb ik tot heden<c type="kk">/</c> Vrijdag<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Kan er op nieuw een fout van de post zijn ofwel is het misschien bij U blijven liggen. Ik wachtte tot heden met het beantwoorden van Uw schrijven om te zien of soms de post hier vergeten had het te bezorgen of zoo<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ge zult het rolletje waarin de Spitter was hoop ik ook hebben ontvangen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Heden en gisteren teekende ik twee figuren van een oud man die met de elbogen op de knieen en ’t hoofd in de handen zit<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik heb het indertijd van Schuitemaker gedaan &amp; bewaarde steeds de teekening<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> omdat ik ’t nog eens beter wilde doen. Misschien zal ik daar ook eene lith. van maken. Wat is zoo’n ouden werkman in zijn gelapt bombazijnen pak<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> met zijn kalen kop toch mooi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik heb het boek van Zola<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Pot bouille</hi><c type="kk">/</c> uit. de krachtigste passage vind ik dat accouchement van die keukenmeid Adele (bretonne pouilleuse) op het donkere zolderkamertje. Josserand is ook weerga’s knap en met sentiment geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> de rest der figuren ook doch die twee somberen<c type="kk">/</c> Josserand met zijn adressen schrijven s’nachts en dat meidenkamertje<c type="kk">/</c> troffen me ’t meest<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Wat zit het boek goed in elkaar – en het woord waarmede het eindigt: aujourd’hui toutes les maisons se valent<c type="kk">/</c> l’une ou l’autre c’est la même chose<c type="kk">/</c> c’est partout Cochon &amp; C<hi rend="super">ie</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> is wel bitter. Octave Mouret – eigentlijk ’t hoofdfiguur – zou die niet als type te beschouwen zijn van dergelijke personen als waarover ge onlangs eens schreeft<c type="kk">/</c> als ge ’t U herinnert<c type="kp">_</c> Hij is in veel opzigten veel beter dan de meesten<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel hij zal U evenmin als mij voldoen en ik voel iets leegs in hem<c type="kp">_</c> Had hij anders kunnen doen<c type="kp">_</c> hij misschien niet doch gij en ik kunnen iets anders en moeten anders dunkt mij<c type="kp">_</c> Wij toch hebben onzen wortel in een ander soort familieleven dan dat van Mouret en bovendien zal er altijd iets van de Brabantsche akkers en hei in ons blijven hoop ik<c type="kk">/</c> wat jaren van stadsleven te minder uit kunnen wisschen omdat de kunst het vernieuwt en vermeerdert<c type="kp">_</c> Hij – Oct. Mouret – is content als hij zijn balen nouveautés grif verkoopen kan (déballer des ballots de marchandises sur les trottoirs de Paris)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> andere aspiraties schijnt hij niet te hebben<c type="kk">/</c> behalve dan conquêtes van vrouwen. en toch had hij die niet werkelijk lief want Zola ziet met juistheid dunkt me als hij zegt “où perçait son mépris pour la femme”.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Enfin, ik weet niet wat ik van hem denken moet<c type="kp">_</c> Hij komt me voor te zijn een product van den tijd<c type="kk">/</c> eigentlijk meer passief dan actief – ondanks zijn activiteit.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Doch na het boek van Zola las ik <hi rend="italics">Quatre vingt treize</hi> van V. Hugo<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> eindelijk eens. Dat is geheel een ander terrein. Het is geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> ik bedoel geschreven als Decamps of Jules Dupré<c type="kk">/</c> met expressies als in oude Ary Scheffers<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. le larmoyeur en le coupeur de nappe<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – of de figuren op den achtergrond van de Christus consolator.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Ik zou U erg aanraden het eens te lezen indien ge ’t niet gelezen hebt want het sentiment waarin dit boek is geschreven wordt hoe langer hoe zeldzamer en <hi rend="italics">onder het nieuwe zie ik niets</hi> <hi rend="italics">dat edeler is</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Werkelijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het is makkelijker om te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> zooals Mesdag van zeker sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van Heyerdahl<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t sentiment van Murillo of Rembrandt gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> dat hij van U niet wilde hebben<c type="kk">/</c> “o dat’s de oude manier<c type="kk">/</c> die hebben we niet noodig”<c type="kk">/</c> dan die oude manier door iets equivalents<c type="kk">/</c> laat staan iets beters te remplaceeren<c type="kp">_</c> En overmits velen zóó redeneeren als Mesdag in dezen tijd<c type="kk">/</c> zonder er verder over na te denken<c type="kk">/</c> kan ’t geen kwaad anderen eens nadenken of we wel in de wereld zijn om af te breken in plaats van voort te bouwen. Het woord “<hi rend="italics">niet meer noodig</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> wat is men er grif mee en wat is het een dom en leelijk woord. Andersen geeft het in zeker sprookje geloof ik niet een mensch doch een oud varken in den mond.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Laat wie er mee kaatst den bal terug verwachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Het deed me bijzonder veel pleizier deze week (bij G&amp;C voor ’t raam) een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van de Bock te zien dat me veel<c type="kk">/</c> veel beter voorkwam dan die waaraan hij in ’t voorjaar werkte<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">dit was eene hut in de duinen met een laan boomen er voor. de fonds somber en toonig met een mooie lichte lucht er achter. Er was iets zeer groots en opgewekts in<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik zei daareven<c type="kk">/</c> laat wie met dezen bal kaatst hem terugverwachten<c type="kp">_</c> ik vrees Theo<c type="kk">/</c> het zal er van komen dat velen die ter wille van het nieuwe het oude opgeofferd hebben zich zulks erg berouwen zullen<c type="kp">_</c> Dit vooral ook op ’t gebied van kunst<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Er was een corps schilders<c type="kk">/</c> schrijvers<c type="kk">/</c> artisten enfin<c type="kk">/</c> die ondanks hun verdeeldheden eenheid hadden en eene kracht waren. Zij wandelden niet in ’t donker doch hadden dit licht dat ze terdeeg wisten wat ze wilden en niet twijfelden.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Ik spreek van den tijd toen Corot<c type="kk">/</c> Millet<c type="kk">/</c> Daubigny<c type="kk">/</c> Jacque<c type="kk">/</c> Breton<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> jong waren<c type="kk">/</c> in Holland Israels<c type="kk">/</c> Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> Maris<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> &amp;c. Het een steunde het ander<c type="kk">/</c> het was iets krachtigs en nobels. De winkels waren toen kleiner<c type="kk">/</c> op de ateliers was misschien meer overvloed dan nu – daar het mooie gaauw weggehaald wordt<c type="kp">_</c>– Die volgepropte ateliers<c type="kk">/</c> die kleinere vitrines – <hi rend="italics">la foi de charbonnier</hi><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> der artisten vooral<c type="kk">/</c> hun warmte<c type="kk">/</c> hun vuur<c type="kk">/</c> hun enthousiasme<c type="kk">/</c> wat waren het sublieme dingen. Noch gij noch ik hebben ’t precies bijgewoond maar door onze liefde voor dien tijd weten we er van wat we er van weten – laat ons het niet vergeten – ’t kan te pas komen – vooral als men voortgaat zoo grif te zeggen – niet meer noodig.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your registered letter of 20 Nov. in good order, and thank you very much for sending it. You’ll have seen how welcome it was from my letter, which must have crossed yours.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">But you write that you sent the paper from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs> at the same time as the letter — yet it wasn’t with it, and up to today, Friday, I <hi rend="italics">don’t</hi> have it. Has the post made a mistake again, or do you perhaps still have it? I’ve waited until today to reply to your letter to see whether the post here had forgotten to deliver it, or something like that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You also received the small roll with the Digger in it, I hope.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Today and yesterday I drew two figures of an old man with his elbows on his knees and his head in his hands.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I did it of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_692">Schuitemaker</rs> once and always kept the drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> because I wanted to do it better another time. Perhaps I’ll also do a lithograph of it. What a fine sight an old working man makes, in his patched bombazine suit with his bald head. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ve finished the book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Pot-bouille</hi>. I thought the most powerful passage was the kitchen maid Adele (scruffy Breton) giving birth in the dark attic room. Josserand is also portrayed with devilish skill and with sentiment. The rest of the characters too, but these two sombre ones, Josserand writing his addresses at night, and that tiny maid’s room, made the most impression on me.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> How well constructed the book is — and the words with which it ends are bitter: these days all houses are much of a muchness, it’s all the same, Swinery &amp; Co. everywhere.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Octave Mouret — actually the main character — couldn’t he be regarded as typical of the kind of people you wrote about recently, if you remember? He’s far better than most people, in many respects, but you won’t find him satisfactory any more than I do, and I sense an emptiness in him. Could he have done differently? Perhaps he couldn’t, but you and I can and must in my view. After all, we have our roots in a family life of a different kind from Mouret’s, and moreover there will always be something of the Brabant fields and heath in us I hope, which is all the less erasable by years of city life because art renews and adds to it. He — O. Mouret — is happy as long as he can sell his bales of novelties quickly (display his bales of goods on the pavements of Paris);<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> he appears to have no other aspirations, except for conquests of women, and yet he wasn’t really fond of them, for Zola is right I believe when he says, ‘where his contempt for the female was apparent’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Anyway, I don’t know what to think of him. He seems to me to be a product of the time, actually more passive than active — despite his activity. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s book I read <hi rend="italics">Quatre vingt treize</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">V. Hugo</rs><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> at long last. That’s entirely different territory. It’s painted, I mean written, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_979">Decamps</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs>, with expressions as in old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>s, such as The man in tears and The cutter of the tablecloth<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> — or the figures in the background of Christus Consolator.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I strongly recommend that you read it sometime if you haven’t read it, for the sentiment in which this book is written is becoming ever more uncommon, and <hi rend="italics">amid the new I see nothing more noble</hi>. Truly. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">It’s easier to say, as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1218">Mesdag</rs> did of a certain painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1084">Heyerdahl</rs> done in the sentiment of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1242">Murillo</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> that he didn’t want to buy from you, ‘Oh, that’s the old manner, we don’t need that’, than to replace the old manner by something equivalent, let alone something better. And since many reason like Mesdag these days, without giving it any further thought, it can do no harm if others do reflect on whether we are in the world to pull down rather than to build up. The phrase ‘<hi rend="italics">not needed any more</hi>’ — how eagerly people use it and what a stupid and ugly phrase it is. I believe that in a certain fairy tale <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">Andersen</rs> puts it in the mouth not of a person but of an old pig.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> People who live in glass houses shouldn’t throw stones. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">This week it pleased me very much indeed to see (in the window at G&amp;C) a painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> that seemed to me far, far better than the one he was working on in the spring. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">This was a hut in the dunes with an avenue of trees in front of it. The background sombre and rich in tone, with a beautiful light sky behind. There was something very grand and lively about it.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I just said, people who live in glass houses shouldn’t throw stones. I fear, Theo, that it will come about that many who have sacrificed the old for the sake of the new will deeply regret it. Especially in the realm of art. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">There was a body of painters, writers, artists in short, who were united despite their divisions, and formed one force. They did not walk in darkness but had this light, that they clearly knew what they wanted and did not doubt.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I’m speaking of the time when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1117">Jacque</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899 bio.xml#_905">Breton</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> were young, in Holland <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Maris</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> &amp;c. One thing reinforced the other, it was powerful and noble. The shops were smaller then, the studios perhaps had a greater abundance than now, since beautiful things soon went. Those crammed studios, those smaller shop windows, <hi rend="italics">collier’s faith</hi><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> of the artists above all, their warmth, their fire, their enthusiasm — what sublime things they were. Neither you nor I actually witnessed it, but through our love for that time we know of it what we know of it — let us not forget it — it may be useful — particularly if people go on saying so eagerly, not needed any more. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Ever yours, </p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written on the Friday after 20 November 1882 (see <ref target="#l-8">l. 8</ref> and <ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>), thus on Friday, 24 November 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is expecting lithographic paper from Buhot with explanatory information <ref target="let280.xml">(280)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Missing letter with money from Theo <ref target="let283.xml">(283)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The previous letter, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let285.xml">285</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For the sending of the lithographs <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412">F 1656 / JH 262</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2415">F 1657 / JH 266</rs>), see<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let285.xml#n-1">letter 285, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p>These are studies like <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">‘Worn out’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2416">F 997 / JH 267</rs>) and (the compositionally different) <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrowful old man</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_436">F 998 / JH 269</rs>). It is clear from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let287.xml">letter 287</ref>, however, that Van Gogh worked with two different models, one of them <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Adrianus Zuyderland</rs>, and only the study of him survived: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Study for ‘Worn out’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_994">F - / JH -</rs>), see Meedendorp 2021.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This drawing, done around mid-September 1881 in Etten, is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man sitting by the fireplace (‘Worn out’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2345">F 863 / JH 34</rs>) (see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let172.xml">letter 172</ref>). It depicts <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_692">Cornelis Schuitemaker</rs>. On him: C. de Bruyn-Heeren, ‘Cornelis Schuitemaker (1813-1884), model for Vincent van Gogh.’ In: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brabantse biografieën. Levensbeschrijvingen van bekende en onbekende Noordbrabanders</hi>. Vol. 4. J. van Oudheusden <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al</hi>. Amsterdam and Meppel 1996, pp. 109-112; and FR b3648.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>A workman’s suit in strong cotton that is patched.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_274"><hi rend="italics">Pot-bouille</hi></ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let283.xml#n-14">see letter 283, n. 14.</ref> The Breton maid Adèle manages to keep secret her pregnancy and delivery at night in her attic room. She at once abandons the child out of shame and fear of losing her job. See Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, pp. 366-371 (chapter 18). The detailed and realistic description of the birth was highly controversial at the time.</p>

<p rend="indent">Josserand is the father of three daughters who, together with his wife, spend so much to keep up appearances in their bourgeois circle that he has to work at night as well as doing a day job as a cashier. For the address writing (chapter 2), see pp. 24-25. Cf. also Sund 1992, p. 66.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This verdict comes from Julie, a maidservant, when she is congratulated on finding a new post. The end reads literally: ‘She shrugged and ended with this philosophical reply: “Dear God, mademoiselle, this one or that, every hovel’s like every other one. In this day and age, whoever has done one of them has done the other. They’re all a shoddy lot.”’ (Elle haussa les épaules et conclut par cette réponse philosophique: “Mon Dieu! mademoiselle, celle-ci ou celle-là, toutes les baraques se ressemblent. Au jour d’aujourd’hui, qui a fait l’une a fait l’autre. C’est cochon et compagnie.”) Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, p. 386 (chapter 18).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>A reference to the passage in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_274"><hi rend="italics">Pot-bouille</hi></ref> where Octave Mouret is judged by Mme Hédouin, his future wife: ‘Elle avait fini pourtant par lui témoigner une véritable estime, gagnée à ses idées larges, à ses rêves de grands comptoirs modernes, déballant des millions de marchandises sur les trottoirs de Paris.’ (Elle avait fini pourtant par lui témoigner une véritable estime, gagnée à ses idées larges, à ses rêves de grands comptoirs modernes, déballant des millions de marchandises sur les trottoirs de Paris.) Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, p. 165 (chapter 9).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Octave Mouret’s conquests are mentioned more than once in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_274"><hi rend="italics">Pot-bouille</hi></ref> (see Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, pp. 68, 235, 408). Van Gogh’s ‘quotation’ about Mouret’s contempt for women is not literal, but there are several passages in which it is expressed, such as: ‘he gave way to his streak of brutality, the fierce scorn he felt for women’ (il céda à son fond de brutalité, au dédain féroce qu’il avait de la femme) (chapter 1, p. 21; a similar quotation in chapter 12, p. 245) and ‘then he rose, full of contempt’ (alors, il se leva, plein de mépris) (chapter 4, p. 72).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s broadly conceived historical novel <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_278"><hi rend="italics">Quatre-vingt-treize</hi></ref> (1874) is set in the period after the French Revolution. It is a fictional story in a historical setting: royalist peasants in the Vendée rise up against the republican government in Paris. Their leader, the Marquis de Lantenac, is overpowered after he saves three children from a burning castle instead of fleeing from the republican leaders Gauvain and Cimourdain. Gauvain admires this humanitarian deed and helps Lantenac to escape. Gauvain is then arrested as a traitor and condemned to the guillotine by the blinkered Cimourdain, who is his friend but also president of the court martial. At the moment Gauvain is beheaded by the guillotine, Cimourdain shoots himself through the heart out of remorse. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Ary Scheffer</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Count Eberhard von Württemberg mourning beside the lifeless body of his son Ulrich</hi>, 1831. And Ary Scheffer, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Count Eberhard von Württemberg dividing the tablecloth between himself and his son Ulrich</hi>, 1851. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_416">Ill. 416</rs>. and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_413">Ill. 413</rs> (Rotterdam, Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1339">Scheffer</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1771"><hi rend="italics">Christus Consolator</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let085.xml#n-7">see letter 85, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Possibly an allusion to something said by the old snail (not a pig) in the tale ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_494">The happy family</ref>’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_512">Hans Christian Andersen</rs>: ‘“There is nothing beyond it!” quoth Father Snail ... “No place can be better than this; we have nothing to wish for”’. See Andersen 1861, p. 388.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>In view of Van Gogh’s description this is probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_437"><hi rend="italics">Road and cottage</hi></rs>, which was sold a short time later, namely on 5 December 1882. It was bought by the dealer Thomas Richardson of London (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RKD</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Goupil Ledgers</hi>). The painting <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_438"><hi rend="italics">The oak</hi></rs>, in a private collection in the USA in 1932 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RKD</hi>), comes close to matching the description given. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Cf. Isa. 59:9 and John 8:12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules Breton</rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_905">Emile Adélard Breton</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jacob Maris</rs>, for whom Van Gogh had a strong preference. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The uncomplicated perseverance of humble folk, automatic faith. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let397.xml">letter 397</ref> Van Gogh says that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> used this expression often, but it is not recorded in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>’s book on Millet. The only time it is found is in the <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_583">introduction</ref> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Paul Mantz</rs>, Sensier 1881, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">vi</hi>; it is cited in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let358.xml">letters 358</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let368.xml">368</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let396.xml">396</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let397.xml">397</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let403.xml">403</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let404.xml">404</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let494.xml">494</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    