<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, Friday, 24 November 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let287"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8352 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>287</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R18</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>289</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-24">Friday, 24 November 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8352" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8352" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001598_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Juist terwijl ik op weg was naar de drukkerij<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> kom ik den brievenbesteller tegen die me Uw brief geeft. Ontvang mijn regt hartelijken dank voor Uwe propositie waarover ik zoo aanstonds schrijf. Eerst wilde ik U zeggen dat ik nu aan mijn vierden steen ben, en U hierbij zend afdrukken van de drie welke gij niet hebt;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> twee daarvan zal ik nog retoucheeren<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. de spitter en de koffijdrinker. laatstgenoemde deed als teekening<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> veel beter. In de lith. heb ik autogr. inkt gebruikt welke niet goed overgebragt is en het snelle dat in de teekening was is er veel uitgegaan<c type="kp">_</c> Ook was er meer leven in het zwart doordat de hachure<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> de rigting &amp; vorm der plooien veel meer uitdrukte. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> datzelfde is ook met den spitter<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> ’t geval doch in dit blad is in ’t algemeen<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik meer verschil van toon gewild had<c type="kk">/</c> een zekere kracht &amp; ruwheid gekomen die in overeenstemming is met ’t karakter van ’t figuur. Nu ben ik doende om er iets op te vinden om het nieuwe procede (het transporteeren van een teek<c type="kp">_</c> op papier) te combineeren met het oude (’t werken direkt op den steen zelf)<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ge herinnert U die teekening Worn out<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> die heb ik dezer dagen op nieuw gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> tot driemaal toe<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> met twee modellen en zal er nog meer op sjouwen<c type="kp">_</c> Voorloopig heb ik er één die t’motief van een vijfden steen zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c> en dus voorstelt een oud werkman die zit te peinzen met de elbogen op de knieen en ’t hoofd (ditmaal een kale kruin) in de handen. Dit een en ander over de lithographies zeg ik om U te toonen dat ik er veel ambitie in heb<c type="kk">/</c> dat dus Uw voorstel met betrekking tot het weggeraakte geld mij hoogst welkom is.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">De brief is nog niet teregt gekomen en bevatte een biljet van vijftig francs. Voorloopig echter laat ons nog wachten<c type="kk">/</c> er wordt naar onderzocht. Ik heb den man van de drukkerij het ongeluk verteld en die is me tot heden genoeg genegen om me niet te presseeren met de kosten der steenen. Trouwens die steenen zijn in zijn handen en loopt hij geen risico of zeer weinig<c type="kp">_</c> Dus wat betreft Uw voorstel – in geval van nood zou ik er gaarne van gebruik maken en is het mij een 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>steun in den rug en durf ik een paar stappen verder gaan doch misschien is het niet noodig en komt de brief teregt. Eene aansporing om er dubbel mijn best op te doen is het zeer zeker en om U een bewijs te geven dat ik er nog al sjouwerij aan heb<c type="kk">/</c> den spitter teekende ik in 12 verschillende standen en ben nog zoekende naar beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het is een fameus mooi model<c type="kk">/</c> een echte veteraan spitter. Verl. Zondag had ik v.d. Weele<c type="kk">/</c> schilder en tevens leeraar in ’t teekenen aan de H. Burgerschool alhier<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> bij me en die zag de verschillende teekeningen van Weesmannen en spoorde me aan een groote compositie er van te maken<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik nog te vroeg zou vinden evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet nog meer studies hebben. de Koffijdrinker is er een van.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Hierbij nog een houtsnee naar Frank Hol<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Dit brengt me op ’t geen ge zegt omtrent die partij tijdschriften welke ge gekocht hebt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik feliciteer U daarmee<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">70-76</hi> is net de mooie periode<c type="kk">/</c> voor de Engelschen althans vooral.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Toen was de Black &amp; White<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> in vollen bloei en kracht. Mij dunkt er moeten prachtige dingen bij zijn.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">’k Zal U zeggen waarom ’t me ook bijzonder veel waard is kracht te zetten achter de lithographies. Indien ik gedaan kan krijgen dat ik een aantal goede steenen bijeen krijg (er zal er wel eens een mislukken ook!) zoo stelt me dit in staat te solliciteeren naar werk<c type="kk">/</c> ook b.v. in Engeland. ’t Spreekt van zelf men meer kans heeft op reussite als men<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. door epreuves van lith. te zenden<c type="kk">/</c> direkt werk kan toonen dan wanneer men met woorden alleen moet scharrelen<c type="kp">_</c> Teekeningen zenden is geen zaak<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> daar ze ligt verloren kunnen gaan. Dit nieuwe procede stelt me in staat te werken voor eene lithographische drukkerij ver weg<c type="kk">/</c> zonder steenen te expedieeren te hebben. Ik heb vandaag juist een nieuw soort inkt en een nieuw soort krijt (Kopal krijt)<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> me aangeschaft er voor.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">mijn adres is Schenkweg N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 13<hi rend="italics">6</hi> tegenwoordig<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Ik wil graag Uw opinie hebben over deze epreuves die ik zend<c type="kp">_</c> Is ’t me mogelijk nog fouten te verhelpen zoo zal ik het graag doen. Toch moet men voorzigtig zijn als ’t er eenmaal op staat en heeft niet alles in zijn magt. ’k geloof dat de nieuwe Worn out U wel eenigzins bevallen zou – ik hoop morgen den steen er van te attaqueeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> mijn papier is vol – meen niet<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik uitsluitend over zaken schreef<c type="kk">/</c> Uwe ongesteldheid me niet schelen kan. Integendeel geeft het me te meer te denken daar ik dezen zomer ook kou gevat had<c type="kk">/</c> ook tamelijk sterke koorts had en – en – ik alleen maar hoop dat ’t niet hetzelfde is evenwel. Quoi qu’il en soit<c type="kk">/</c> van harte U beterschap toegewenscht &amp; geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Just as I was on my way to the printer<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I ran into the postman, who gave me your letter. Please accept my sincerest thanks for your proposal, which I’ll write about shortly. First I wanted to tell you that I’m now on my fourth stone, and am sending you herewith impressions of the three you don’t have;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ll retouch two of them, namely the digger and the coffee drinker. The latter worked much better as a drawing.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> In the lithograph I used autographic ink that hasn’t transferred well, and much of the briskness that was in the drawing has been lost. There was also more life in the black, because the hatching conveyed the direction and form of the folds much better. Now the same is true of the digger,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> but in this print there is in general a certain strength and roughness that corresponds with the character of the figure, though I would have liked to have more variety of tone. Now I’m trying to find a way of combining the new process (transferring a drawing on paper) with the old (working directly on the stone itself). 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You remember that drawing Worn out?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> In the last few days I’ve done it again no fewer than three times<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> with two models, and will labour on it some more. For the present I have one that will be the subject of a fifth stone, which thus depicts an old working man who sits and ponders with his elbows on his knees and his head (a bald crown this time) in his hands. I’m telling you this and that about the lithographs to show that I’m very enthusiastic about them, and so your proposal as regards the lost money is most welcome to me.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">The letter still hasn’t been found, and contained a fifty-franc note. For the time being, though, let’s wait a little longer; it’s being investigated. I told the man at the printer’s about the accident, and so far he’s been good enough not to press me about the costs of the stones. For that matter, the stones are in his hands and he runs no risk, or very little. So as to your proposal — in an emergency I’d very much like to avail myself of it, and it’s a 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> helping hand for me and I dare to go a few steps further, but it may not be necessary and the letter may turn up. It’s most certainly an encouragement to redouble my efforts, and to prove to you that I put a lot of work into it: I drew the digger in 12 different poses and am still searching for better ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">He’s a splendidly fine model, a real veteran digger. Last Sunday I had <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>, painter and also drawing master at the high school here,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and he saw the various drawings of orphan men and urged me to make a large composition with them, although I would consider that premature as yet, I need to have even more studies. The coffee drinker is one of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Herewith a woodcut after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Frank Holl</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> This brings me to what you say about a batch of magazines you’ve bought.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I congratulate you on them. <hi rend="italics">70-76</hi> is precisely the finest period, at least for the English above all.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> The Black and White<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> was then in full bloom and in its prime. I’m sure there must be superb things among them. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I’ll tell you why it matters a very great deal to me to make an effort with the lithographs. If I can manage to assemble a number of good stones (one or two are bound to go wrong now and again!), this will enable me to apply for work, in England, for example, as well. It goes without saying that one has more chance of success if one can immediately show work, for instance by sending proofs of lithographs, than if one has to get by with words alone. Sending drawings isn’t an alternative, since they can easily be lost. This new process enables me to work for a lithographic printer far away without having to send stones. Just today I bought myself a new kind of ink and a new kind of crayon (copal crayon)<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> for this purpose.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">My address these days is No. 13<hi rend="italics">6</hi> Schenkweg.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> I would like to have your opinion about these proofs I’m sending. If it’s possible for me to rectify mistakes I’ll happily do so. Still, one has to be careful once something has been put on, and can’t control everything. I believe that the new Worn out will give you some pleasure — I hope to tackle the stone of it tomorrow.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Well, my paper is full — don’t think, although I write only about professional matters, that your illness is of no concern to me. On the contrary, it gave me all the more food for thought because last summer I also caught a cold, also had quite a high fever and — and — I only hope that it isn’t the same, though. Whatever the case may be, my cordial wishes for your recovery, and believe me, with a handshake,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">It appears from <ref target="let288.xml">letter 288</ref> of Sunday, 26 November and Monday, 27 November that Van Gogh has started work on his <hi rend="italics">fifth</hi> lithograph, whereas in the present letter that still lies in the future <ref target="#l-28">(l. 28)</ref>, so it must have been written a little earlier. Moreover, the letter cannot have been written on Sunday because Van Gogh had been able to buy crayon ‘today’ <ref target="#l-81">(l. 81)</ref>. Saturday is also unlikely because he may be going to the printer’s ‘tomorrow’ <ref target="#l-89">(ll. 89-90)</ref>. This is why we have dated the letter to Friday, 24 November 1882. Some time must have passed between this letter and the next one because in <ref target="let288.xml">letter 288</ref> Van Gogh has gained some experience with the new crayon, which does not yet seem to be the case in the present letter.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The letter was thus written on the same day as <ref target="let286.xml">letter 286</ref>, but later: Van Gogh now has one more drawing of an old man with his head in his hands than he was able to report to Theo <ref target="#l-26">(l. 26)</ref>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is working on a lithograph of an old man <ref target="let286.xml">(286)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Missing letter with money from Theo <ref target="let283.xml">(283)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is drawing diggers <ref target="let281.xml">(281)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The printer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1482">Smulders</rs> in Spuistraat.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> already had one lithograph, probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2408">F 1658 / JH 256</rs>), and otherwise <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2409">F 1655 / JH 259</rs>); for this uncertainty, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let284.xml#n-3">see letter 284, n. 3.</ref> In any case he received the others with this letter and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412">F 1656 / JH 262</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2415">F 1657 / JH 266</rs>) as well.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The model drawing for the lithograph was probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man drinking coffee</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2414">F 996a / JH 264</rs>), or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2413">F 1682 / JH 263</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let285.xml#n-2">See letter 285, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>‘Hachure’ is another word for hatching or shading of short lines.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The model drawing for the lithograph <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412"><hi rend="italics">Digger</hi></rs> is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man sitting by the fireplace (‘Worn out’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2345">F 863 / JH 34</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Two drawings connected to the lithograph ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">At eternity’s gate’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2417">F 1662 / JH 268</rs>) are known: ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Worn out’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2416">F 997 / JH 267</rs>), which was the immediate model for the lithograph, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Study for ‘Worn out’ </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_994">F - / JH -</rs>). The study with the other model remains unknown, see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let286.xml#n-3">letter 286, n. 3.</ref> The compositionally different <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrowful old man </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_436">F 998 / JH 269</rs>) was probably made somewhat later, see Otterlo 2007, pp. 172-4.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let289.xml">letter 289</ref> Van Gogh says a little more about the nature of the proposal. When <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> learned (through a letter that is no longer known) that the loss of the letter with money would put an end to the lithographic experiments, he replied: ‘don’t let that hold you back, and count on me if you can’t carry on or need something’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let289.xml#l-7">(ll. 7-8)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Herman van der Weele</rs> was a teacher at the secondary school in The Hague and at the Ambachtsschool (technical school).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>It is not known which engraving after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1089">Francis Montague Holl</rs> was enclosed.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s example may have encouraged Van Gogh to buy a large collection of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> just over a month later; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let302.xml">see letters 302</ref> ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>In this context Black and White is the term applied to the engraved magazine illustrations such as those published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘komt niet in aanmerking’ (is not feasible).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The hardest types of lithographic crayon are called ‘copal’ because copal, a fossil resin, is added to them.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had been living at this address since July 1882 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let243.xml">see letter 243</ref>). Perhaps <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> was still sending letters to the old address (at number 138), although in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let256.xml">letter 256</ref> to Van Rappard Van Gogh talked about the ‘new studio’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    