<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Sunday, 3 December 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let290"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b272 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>290</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>250</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>292</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-03">on or about Sunday, 3 December 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0272 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0272 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000335_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0272 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000336_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000336_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0272 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000336_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000336_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ontvang mijn hartelijken dank voor Uw aanget. brief alsmede voor het rolletje. Daarin vond ik het papier van Buhot.– ik zou er echter wel eenige explicatie bij willen hebben. b.v. <hi rend="italics">Waarmede</hi> moet men op dit papier teekenen? Misschien hoor ik dat later.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">De Renouards<c type="kk">/</c> Enfants assistés<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> zijn prachtig<c type="kk">/</c> ook zijn nieuwe teekening Banc des accusés<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – ofschoon die laatste minder important is dan b.v. zijn groote bladen van de gevangenis Mazas.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik ben er erg blij mee &amp; bedank er U wel voor.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ge zult ontvangen hebben een druk van eene lithographie.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Eigentlijk is die mislukt – toch zond ik ze om reden er eenige brokken in zijn die geworden zijn zooals ik ’t geheel bedoeld had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">De autographische inkt had ditmaal erg gevloeid en dat moest verholpen worden later en er bleven overal toch zwarte partijen. Maar kijk b.v. het linkerbeen met den beslijkten laars. Daar kan men aan zien dat met dit procede men de stoffen kan uitdrukken en er eigenaardige effekten mee te krijgen zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Handen en kop zijn slecht doch in ’t andere oude mannetje<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> zijn die weer de beste partij. Opnieuw heb ik het op steen transporteeren &amp; het drukken goed gezien en ik moet U zeggen dat ik geloof er met het procede veel te doen is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Heden was ik bij Van der Weele – die had nog al pleizier in het oude mannetje met ’t hoofd in de handen en is zelf voornemens het te beproeven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Hij is iemand die soms fameus goede dingen maakt. Ik kreeg 4 etsen van hem<c type="kk">/</c> een schapestal<c type="kk">/</c> kalven in ’t hakhout – twee zandkarren en een ossenploeg, en hoop er later nog meer te krijgen als hij weer drukken laat maken.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Hij schijnt niet veel van Tersteeg te houden<c type="kk">/</c> ten minste zonder dat ik iets over hem zei en we ’t over studies van vd. W. zelf hadden zei hij – nu ja<c type="kk">/</c> maar als ik dit doe of dat doe en ik kom bij Tersteeg maakt hij deze en die aanmerking<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik geloof hij waarheid sprak en werkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> het spijt mij erg dat de dingen zoo zijn. Ik wou liever dat ik me vergist had in mijn 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>opinie omtrent Tersteeg doch ik vrees hij velen nog al decourageert – die werkelijk iets beters verdienen. Wat zijn dat lamme kwesties.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Gisteren ontving ik een brief niet van Rappard doch van zijn vader<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> om me te zeggen R. ziek is. Wat hij mankeert weet ik niet – misschien<c type="kk">/</c> misschien wel wat gij en ik ook kennen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Ik kom op die gedachte door enkele expressies in zijn laatsten brief<c type="kk">/</c> toen hij me schreef dat ik door zou gaan met het nemen van proeven en dat hij zich zoo lam voelde dat hij niets doen kon<c type="kp">_</c> Jammer voor hem niet waar<c type="kk">/</c> het is zoo hard als men midden uit zijn werk moet om zoo'n lamme reden als ongesteldheid. Als ik berigt krijg dat het niet spoedig beter word zoo zou ik grooten lust hebben hem eens te gaan opzoeken. In den laatsten tijd heb ik nog al veel met hem gecorrespondeerd over het werk<c type="kk">/</c> hij heeft zeer veel liefhebberij gekregen in het verzamelen van houtsneden b.v. en ik acht het zeer wel mogelijk wij hoe langer hoe meer aan elkaar zullen krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Bij V.d. Weele zag ik een uitmuntende schets van Breitner<c type="kk">/</c> een teekening die niet af was – misschien ook niet af te maken – het stelde voor officieren die over een landkaart of plan de bataille zitten te delibereeren voor een open raam.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Breitner is werkelijk aan de Burgerschool te Rotterdam geplaatst.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Een uitkomst voor hem. Maar <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> men het uithouden? er niets anders bij te doen en al zijn tijd aan het werk geven dat is toch verkiesselijk mijns inziens. ’t Is of er iets fataals ligt in het er bij waarnemen van andere betrekkingen – misschien zijn juist de zorgen<c type="kk">/</c> juist de donkere schaduwkant van het artistenleven het beste er van – ’t is gewaagd dit te zeggen en er zijn momenten dat men anders spreekt – velen gaan door de zorg te gronde – maar die het doorworstelen – later winnen ze er bij.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Gij schrijft over de kwestie van teekeningen te maken in kleiner formaat – ik vind het mooi van U dat ge over die kwestie op een meer bedaarde wijs spreekt dan anderen die mij wel eens heel anders ’t zelfde gezegd hebben en tot me zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> als ge niet kleiner werkt dan zal dit gebeuren en dat gebeuren. Zóó er over te spreken vind ik voorbarig en oppervlakkig en kan niet gelooven het waar is wat ze zeggen. Weet ge hoe ik er over denk – alle formaten hebben hun vóór en hun tegen. in ’t algemeen voor mijn eigen studie heb ik bepaald behoefte ’t figuur tamelijk groot van proportie te nemen zoo dat kop<c type="kk">/</c> handen<c type="kk">/</c> voeten niet te klein worden en men ze stevig teekenen kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Voor eigen studie dus nam ik tot voorbeeld het formaat van de Exercices au fusain van Bargue<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> daar die grootte met een blik nog gemakkelijk te overzien is en toch de details niet al te klein worden. Maar de meesten nemen een kleiner formaat. Ik voor mij heb van ’t begin af ’t zóó gedaan voor mij zelf<c type="kk">/</c> nu eens iets kleiner<c type="kk">/</c> dan eens iets grooter<c type="kk">/</c> en voor eigen studie zou ik tegen mijn overtuiging handelen indien ik er van afweek.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Doch ofschoon dit dus voor mij het middelpunt is waarop mijn aandacht gevestigd is – het menschelijk figuur op een goede<c type="kk">/</c> flinke grootte in mijn magt te hebben – eene zaak die fameus moeielijk is – dat verzeker ik U – zoo neemt dit niet weg dat ik volstrekt niet absoluut daaraan gebonden ben. En dus<c type="kk">/</c> in 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>antwoord op ’t geen ge schrijft doe ik U de wedervraag<c type="kk">/</c> hebt gij een bepaald werk op ’t oog<c type="kk">/</c> heeft iemand U iets gezegd als b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> indien die figuren op de halve grootte waren zouden dergelijke bladen hier of daar voor te gebruiken zijn. En indien ge ’t een of ander dienaangaande weet zoo wil ik van mijn kant de moeite nemen om ’t zij figuren die ik reeds heb op halve grootte te reduceeren ’t zij geheel nieuwen in kleiner formaat te teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Zonder bepaalde reden zou ik van minder belang vinden dan met bepaalde reden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Is het dat gij<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik U eenige figuren b.v. ter halve grootte der vorigen zond<c type="kk">/</c> eens daarmede nieuwe proeven wilt nemen zonder dat ge nu reeds bepaald zeggen kunt bij wie of waarvoor<c type="kk">/</c> zoo is me dat reden genoeg om ze te maken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Wat ik daareven zeide is alleen om U er op te wijzen hoe ik van begin af aan een zekere orde in mijn werk heb trachten te houden<c type="kk">/</c> mij zelf een soort regel gesteld heb<c type="kk">/</c> niet om slaaf te worden van dien regel doch omdat men er helderder door denken kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Het reduceeren van een bepaald figuur op halve groote b.v. is volstrekt niet moeielijk – soms verliest men evenwel iets van het eigenaardige – soms ook wint het figuur er bij<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">In elk geval ik zal er U een paar sturen binnen kort – doch hebt ge iets bepaalds er mee op ’t oog zoo zeg me waarvoor het dienen moet<c type="kk">/</c> dan helpt mij dit in de keus van mijn figuren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Nogmaals dank voor het gezondene. Wat ik U in mijn vorigen brief schreef over een plan van bladen voor het volk te maken<c type="kk">/</c> is iets waarover ik hoop dat gij Uw gedachten eens zult laten gaan. Een vast plan heb ik zelf daaromtrent nog niet<c type="kk">/</c> in zoover dat om het helder in mijn hoofd te hebben ik en met betrekking tot de teekeningen zelf en met betrekking tot het procedé der reproductie dingen te doen heb<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Doch aan de mogelijkheid om zoo iets te doen twijfel ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> aan het nuttige der zaak ook niet<c type="kk">/</c> en dat er lui te vinden zouden zijn die er hart voor hebben zouden<c type="kk">/</c> daar kan ik ook niet aan twijfelen. Enfin 'k geloof dat het zoo te doen zou zijn dat niemand berouw zou hoeven te hebben er aan meegewerkt te hebben. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Terwijl ik U schrijf lees ik Uw laatsten brief nog eens over. Vooral ook wat gij zegt over formaat. Ik wil U eens een voorbeeld noemen van een teekenaar dien gij kent: Theophile Schuler die de werken van Erckmann Chatrian illustreerde.–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Aan die kleine illustraties ziet men duidelijk dat hij zeer goed in ’t klein werken kon<c type="kk">/</c> meer nog ziet men het aan dingen die hij in der tijd b.v. voor Ilustration &amp; magasin pittoresque<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> maakte – o.a. l’Album des Vosges waar ook Brion en Jundt aan meewerkten.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik geloof echter men zich zeer vergissen zou te meenen zulke dingen als b.v. het blad Le benedicité<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> (een familie houthakkers of boeren aan tafel) zoomaar in eens in zijn definitieven toestand ontstaan was<c type="kp">_</c> Neen – de soliditeit en pit van het kleine wordt in de meeste gevallen niet verkregen dan door veel serieuser studie dan zij die ligt over het werk van illustreeren denken<c type="kk">/</c> wel meenen. o Kerel<c type="kk">/</c> gij zijt een van de best ingelichten onder de kunsthandelaars die ik ken en gij spreekt er veel juister en gevoeliger over dan de meesten doch als ge wist wat al sjouwerij sommige dingen gekost hebben – als b.v. bladen uit Album des Vosges of die eerste dingen van de Graphic – ik geloof dat gij er door getroffen zoudt zijn. Mij althans gaat het dikwijls zoo dat als ik meer te weten kom omtrent het leven &amp; werken van lui als Schuler<c type="kk">/</c> Lancon<c type="kk">/</c> Renouard<c type="kk">/</c> zooveel anderen<c type="kk">/</c> ik bespeur dat wat men van hen ziet slechts het kleine rookwolkje is dat boven uit hun schoorsteen komt en binnen in hun hart en atelier een groot vuur is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">In de illustraties ondergaan zij een dergelijk iets als het kleine torentje in de verte dat heel klein lijkt en onbeteekenend en als men er digt bij komt een imposante massa is (ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> slechts een klein deel van hun werk wordt publiek gemaakt)<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Enfin met sommige schilderijen is het zoo dat zij in hun enorme lijsten veel lijken en men later zich verwondert dat zij eigentlijk zoo'n leeg en onvoldaan gevoel achterlaten; in tegenoverstelling daarvan<c type="kk">/</c> menig onaanzienlijk houtsnee of lith<c type="kp">_</c> of ets ziet men bij wijlen over ’t hoofd doch komt er op terug en wordt hoe langer hoe meer er aan gehecht en voelt er iets groots in<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik ken eene teekening van Teniel<c type="kk">/</c> voorstellende “twee dominés” (dit is de Engelsche titel niet natuurlijk doch wel het motief)<c type="kk">/</c> de eene is een stadsdominé<c type="kk">/</c> glorieus en breed en imposant – de andere is ietwat “shabby”<c type="kk">/</c> een onaanzienlijk dorpspredikantje blijkbaar<c type="kk">/</c> vader van een groot en arm gezin.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Dikwijls denk ik dat ook bij de schilders men die twee typen heeft en veel “illustrateurs” hooren tot die dorpspredikanten onder de schilders terwijl misschien personen als een Bouguereau of een Makart en nog meer anderen iets van eerstgenoemde type hebben.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Of nu ik voor mij in kleiner of grooter formaat moet werken is mij betrekkelijk onverschillig doch wat de illustraties vragen is slechts een deel van wat ik van mij zelf eisch<c type="kp">_</c>– Van mij zelf eisch ik gedecideerd dat ik het figuur op een grootte zoo dat kop<c type="kk">/</c> handen<c type="kk">/</c> voeten niet al te klein worden en de details er duidelijk in blijven<c type="kk">/</c> kunne maken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Dit heb ik nog bij lange na niet zóó als ik het van mij zelf vorder doch juist daarom<c type="kk">/</c> ik mag mijzelf niet loslaten op dat punt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Indien ik zulks vorder stel ik mijzelf geen anderen eisch dan zeer veel anderen zich zelven stelden. Zoo b.v. van die serie teekeningen die ik nu onder handen heb weet ik niet wat den definitieven vorm of grootte zal zijn. Ik heb ze gesteld<c type="kk">/</c> na er veel over gedacht te hebben<c type="kk">/</c> op de grootte ongeveer van het mannetje met het hoofd in de handen<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> doch van deze cartons<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> kan ik als het op drukken aankomt natuurlijk de grootte reduceeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">En dat het zijn raison d'être heeft in de praktijk de figuren tamelijk groot te teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> daarvoor spreken wel b.v. de Exercices au fusain<c type="kk">/</c> de Modèles d'après les maîtres<c type="kk">/</c> door G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> uitgegeven. Ik ben daarmee begonnen en heb tot heden geen beter leiddraad voor studies naar het levend model gevonden. Men wilde door de uitgaaf daarvan gezonde begrippen omtrent studie brengen en in de scholen en vooral ook zeker in de ateliers. Ik heb geluisterd naar wat Bargue in zijn voorbeelden zegt (ofschoon mijn werk niet op verre na zoo mooi is als het zijne) – ik geloof dat die een regten weg aanwijzen in overeenstemming met wat andere mannen<c type="kk">/</c> o.a. L. da Vinci<c type="kk">/</c> vroeger hebben geleerd – en in elk geval heb ik een zekere orde in mijn gedachten omtrent het teekenen er door gekregen die maakt dat het werken geregelder gaat dan wanneer men geen orde op zijn doen en laten stelt. Zie<c type="kk">/</c> dat is iets wat ik niet loslaten mag<c type="kk">/</c> doch nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ’t formaat van dit of dat figuur onder mijn studies kan ik<c type="kk">/</c> als men zulks wil<c type="kk">/</c> reduceeren. Ik verlang er wel erg naar dat gij alles weer eens bij elkaar ziet wat ik sedert dezen zomer maakte. Hoe is het toch met die teekeningen die gij schreeft per Rue Chaptal verzonden te hebben<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb ze nog niet ontvangen doch ik vermoed ze nog bij U berusten omdat gij toen juist kort daarop schreeft Buhot er van gezien had. Natuurlijk heb ik er geen direkten haast mee en schrijf ik er maar eens over voor ’t geval ze mogelijk ergens zijn blijven liggen. En is het gij het raadzaam rekent ze voor ’t geval ge den een of ander er over wilt spreken bij U te houden<c type="kk">/</c> zoo heb ik daar niets anders op tegen dan dat ik wou ge uit het geheel eens een nieuwe keus kondt maken voor dat doel misschien<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Accept my cordial thanks for your registered letter and for the roll. In it I found the paper from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs>. But I’d like to have some information to go with it, for example, <hi rend="italics">With what</hi> does one draw on this paper? Perhaps I’ll be told that later. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>’s Children in care<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> are wonderful, also his new drawing, The dock<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — although the latter is less important than his large prints of the Mazas prison, for example.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’m very pleased with them and thank you for them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You’ll have received an impression of a lithograph.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Actually it went wrong — but I sent it anyway because there are some bits in it that have turned out as I had intended the whole thing to be. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">This time the autographic ink ran badly and that had to be corrected later, but there were still black passages everywhere. But look, for example, at the left leg with the muddy boot. There one can see that fabrics can be rendered with this process and curious effects obtained. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Hands and head are poor, yet in the other old man<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> they’re the best part. Again I watched the transfer to stone and the printing carefully, and I must say that I believe a great deal can be done with this process. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Today I was at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>’s — he took considerable pleasure in the old man with his head in his hands and intends to try it himself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">He’s someone who makes truly splendid things sometimes. He gave me 4 etchings, a sheepfold, calves in a copse — two sand-carts and an ox-plough, and I hope to get more later when he has impressions made again.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">He doesn’t seem to like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> very much. At least, without my saying anything about him, and while we were talking about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der W.</rs>’s own studies, he said, all right, but if I do this or do that and I go to Tersteeg he makes such and such a remark. I believe he was speaking the truth and, honestly, I’m very sorry that things are like this. I would rather that I was mistaken in my 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> opinion of Tersteeg, but I fear he rather discourages many who truly deserve something better. How tiresome these matters are. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Yesterday I received a letter, not from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> but from his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_183">father</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> telling me that R. is ill. I don’t know what’s wrong with him — perhaps, perhaps what you and I are also familiar with.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> The thought occurred to me because of several expressions in his last letter, when he wrote that I should carry on doing experiments and that he felt so feeble that he could do nothing. What a pity for him, isn’t it? It’s so hard if one has to stop one’s work right in the middle for such a feeble reason as illness. I’ll very much want to look him up sometime, if I hear that he isn’t getting better quickly. I’ve corresponded with him quite a lot about work recently. He has taken very great pleasure in collecting woodcuts, for example, and I think it highly likely that with time we’ll be more and more help to each other. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">At <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>’s I saw an outstanding sketch by Breitner, a drawing that was unfinished, and perhaps couldn’t be finished. It was of officers deliberating over a map or battle-plan before an open window.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> does indeed have a position at the secondary school in Rotterdam.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">A solution for him. <hi rend="italics">Can</hi> one keep that up? Not doing anything else and devoting all one’s time to the work, that’s still preferable in my view. It’s as if there’s something fatal in holding other positions — perhaps it’s precisely the worries, precisely the dark side of the artistic life, that’s the best part of it. It’s risky to say this, and there are moments when one talks differently — many go under because of the worry — but those who struggle through benefit later. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">You write about the question of making drawings in a smaller format. I think it good of you that you speak about this question in a calmer manner than others, who have sometimes said the same thing to me in a very different way and told me, if you don’t work smaller then this will happen and that will happen. Talking about it like that seems to me premature and superficial, and I can’t believe that what they say is true. Do you know what I think — all formats have their pros and cons. In general, for my own study, I definitely need to have the figure in fairly large proportions, so that head, hands, feet aren’t too small and one can draw them robustly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">So for my own study I took as my example the format of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs>’s Exercices au fusain,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> because that size is easy to take in at a glance and yet the details don’t become too small. But most take a smaller format. For my part, from the beginning I’ve done it like this for myself, sometimes a little smaller, sometimes a little larger, and for my own study I would be going against my convictions if I deviated from that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Yet, so although this is for me the focus of my attention — to have the human figure in my power in a good, substantial size — an enormously difficult thing, I do assure you — it’s still the case that I’m by no means absolutely tied to it. And so in 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> reply to what you write I put to you a question in return: do you have a particular work in mind; has someone said something to you like, for instance, if those figures were half the size, sheets of this kind could be used for this or that? And if you know of anything like that, I, for my part, will take the trouble either to reduce figures I already have to half the size, or to draw completely new ones in a smaller format. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Without a specific reason I would think it less important than with a specific reason. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">If it’s so that, were I to send you some figures, say half the size of the last ones, you’d be willing to make new attempts without being able to say at this stage specifically where or what for, that would be reason enough for me to make them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">What I just said is only to point out to you how I’ve tried from the outset to maintain a certain order in my work, set a sort of rule for myself, not to be a slave to that rule but because it helps one to think more clearly. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Reducing a certain figure to half the size, for example, isn’t difficult at all — although sometimes one loses something of what makes it distinctive — but sometimes the figure gains by it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">At any rate, I’ll send you a few shortly, but if you have something particular in mind for them, tell me what they’re for — that will help me in the choice of my figures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Thank you again for what you sent. What I wrote to you in my last letter about a plan for making prints for the people is something to which I hope you’ll give some thought one day. I don’t have a fixed plan about this myself as yet, only in order to have it clear in my mind I’ll have things to do relating both to the drawings themselves and to the process of reproduction. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">But I don’t doubt the possibility of doing something like this, nor its usefulness. Nor can I doubt that people can be found whose heart would be in it. In short, I believe it could be done in such a way that no one would need regret having taken part. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I’m re-reading your last letter as I write to you. In particular what you say about format. I’d like to give you an example of a draughtsman you know: <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Théophile Schuler</rs>, who illustrated the works of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> One clearly sees from those small illustrations that he could work excellently on a small scale. One sees it even better in things he did at that time for L’Illustration and Magasin Pittoresque,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> for example, among them L’Album des Vosges, to which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1120">Jundt</rs> also contributed.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I believe, though, that it would be a great mistake to imagine that such things as, for instance, the print The grace<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> (a family of woodcutters or peasants at table) were created at a stroke in their final form. No, in most cases the solidity and pith of the small is only obtained through much more serious study than is imagined by those who think lightly of the task of illustrating. Oh, old chap, you’re one of the best-informed art dealers I know, and you speak about this much more accurately and sensitively than most, but if you knew how much hard graft some things have required — for instance, prints from Album des Vosges or those first things in The Graphic — I believe you would be struck by them. With me, at least, it’s often the case that as I learn more about the life and work of fellows like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Schuler</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1146">Lançon</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>, and so many others, I sense that what one sees of them is only the tiny puff of smoke that comes out of their chimney, and that within their heart and studio there’s a great fire. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">In the illustrated magazines they undergo something like the small tower in the distance that looks very small and insignificant, and when one gets up close proves to be an imposing mass (I mean, only a small part of their work is made public). </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Anyway, some paintings in their huge frames look very substantial, and later one is surprised when they actually leave behind such an empty and dissatisfied feeling. On the other hand, one overlooks many an unpretentious woodcut or lithograph or etching now and then, but comes back to it and becomes more and more attached to it with time, and senses something great in it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I know a drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1378">Tenniel</rs> of ‘two clergymen’ (this isn’t the English title, of course, but it’s the subject). One is a city vicar, splendid and broad and imposing; the other is slightly ‘shabby’, evidently a humble village curate, the father of a large and poor family.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> I often think that one finds these two types among painters as well, and many ‘illustrators’ belong to the village curates among the painters, while perhaps people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_890">Bouguereau</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1183">Makart</rs> and some others have something of the first type. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Now whether, for my part, I have to work in a smaller or larger format makes relatively little difference to me, but what the illustrated magazines ask is only part of what I demand of myself. Of myself I firmly demand that I can make the figure of a size such that head, hands and feet don’t become too small and the details remain clear. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">This is still very far from being what I require of myself, but for that very reason I must stand firm on that point. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">When I require this, I’m not making other demands of myself than very many others make of themselves. For example, with the series of drawings I’m working on now I don’t know what the final form or size will be. After a great deal of thought, I’ve made them about the size of the man with his head in his hands,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> but I can of course reduce the size of these designs if I wish when it comes to printing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">And that there are reasons for drawing the figures fairly large in practice is shown, for example, by Exercices au fusain, Modèles d’après les maîtres, published by G&amp;Cie. I began with them, and so far I haven’t found a better guide to studies from the live model. The book was intended to introduce sound ideas about study, both in the schools and certainly above all in the studios. I’ve listened to what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs> says in his examples (though my work is far from being as beautiful as his). I believe that they point to a correct way in accordance with what other men taught earlier, among them <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1414">L. da Vinci </rs>— and in any event through it I’ve brought a certain order to my ideas on drawing which results in work proceeding in a better-regulated way than if one imposes no order on one’s actions. You see, that’s something I may not let go of, but, again, if desired, I can reduce the format of this or that figure in my studies. I’d very much like you to see everything I’ve done since this summer all together again. What’s happened to those drawings that you wrote you had sent through rue Chaptal? I haven’t yet received them, but I suspect they’re still with you, since you wrote shortly afterwards that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs> had seen them. Of course I don’t need them in a hurry, and only mention them in case they may be lying around somewhere. And if you consider it advisable to keep them with you in case you want to talk to someone about them, I have nothing against that, except that I wish you could perhaps make a new selection from the whole lot for that purpose.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the money sent at the beginning of the month, which he had not yet received on Friday, 1 December <ref target="let289.xml">(289)</ref>; the letter follows <ref target="let289.xml">letter 289</ref> because he refers back to the plan to make prints for the people. Theo had not yet received <ref target="let289.xml">letter 289</ref>, for he had evidently not yet reacted to this plan <ref target="#l-135">(ll. 135-136)</ref>. Between the present letter and the one giving thanks for the <hi rend="italics">second</hi> remittance of December (<ref target="let293.xml">letter 293</ref>), which must date from on or about Monday, 11 December, Van Gogh also wrote <ref target="let291.xml">letter 291</ref> (of between 4 and 9 December) and <ref target="let292.xml">292</ref> (of 10 December), in which he again returns to the question. Thus the present letter must date from on or about Sunday, 3 December 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Consignment of lithographic paper from Buhot with explanatory information <ref target="let280.xml">(280)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Breitner is teaching at the Academy in Rotterdam <ref target="let277.xml">(277)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For the series <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1956 artwork.xml#ill_1957 artwork.xml#ill_1970 artwork.xml#ill_1959 artwork.xml#ill_396 artwork.xml#ill_395 artwork.xml#ill_1978"><hi rend="italics">The orphanage</hi></rs> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Paul Renouard</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let268.xml#n-6">see letter 268, n. 6.</ref> Van Gogh already had some sheets from the series; this explains why some occur more than once in the estate.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_380"><hi rend="italics">Banc des accusés</hi></rs> (The dock), which appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> in November, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let284.xml#n-11">see letter 284, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>’s series <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_397"><hi rend="italics">The prisons of Paris</hi></rs> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mazas</hi>), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let261.xml#n-8">see letter 261, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Workman sitting on a basket, cutting</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">bread </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2418">F 1663 / JH 272</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">‘At eternity’s gate’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2417">F 1662 / JH 268</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The first two works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Herman van der Weele</rs> could be: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Flock of sheep driven into a sheepfold</hi> (The Hague, Kunstmuseum) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Three cows in a landscape</hi> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_458">Ill. 458</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_451">Ill. 451</rs>. The other two etchings have not been identified.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_183">Frans Alexander Lodewijk, ridder (knight) van Rappard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh suggests that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had a venereal disease (in November 1882 Van Rappard fell seriously ill). Later he turned out to have a ‘nervous fever in the head’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let310.xml">letter 310</ref>), which usually meant encephalitis, but could also be a name for other fevers affecting the brain. Van Rappard spent July and August 1883 at the health resort Soden in northern Germany to recuperate. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 79, 83.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">George Hendrik Breitner</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Council of war at the time of the Batavian Republic</hi>, 1882 (present whereabouts unknown). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2037">Ill. 2037</rs>. See Hefting<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1970, cat. no. 139.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The sheets in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_851">Bargue</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_202"><hi rend="italics">Exercices au fusain</hi></ref> measure c. 61 x 47 cm on average; the illustrations themselves vary in size. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Théophile Schuler</rs> illustrated various books by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>. Those mentioned in the correspondence are: <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_52"><hi rend="italics">L’ami Fritz</hi></ref> (1867); <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_339"><hi rend="italics">Histoire d’un paysan</hi></ref> (1868); <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_292"><hi rend="italics">L’histoire d’un sous-maître</hi></ref> (1871) and <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_260"><hi rend="italics">Les deux frères</hi></ref> (1873). The others were: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Confidences d’un joueur de clarinette</hi> (1865); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La maison forestière</hi> (1866);<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Le blocus</hi> (1867); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’histoire du plébiscite</hi> (1871); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Une campagne en Kabylie</hi> (1873); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les années de collège</hi> (1874); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le brigadier Frédéric</hi> (1874); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’éducation d’un féodal</hi> (1876) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Maître Gaspard Fix</hi> (1876).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Schuler</rs> provided illustrations for the weeklies <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Magasin Pittoresque</hi> (1833-1875); the latter always had a full page illustration on the cover, and contained serials, popular science articles, news and pieces about art. There were several illustrations in each issue. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>For <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_543">L’Album des Vosges</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let267.xml#n-9">see letter 267, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Most probably Van Gogh means <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Schuler</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Repas de paysans dans une ferme d’Alsace</hi> (Peasant meal in a farm in Alsace), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration </hi>30 (12 December 1857), p. 393. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2014">Ill. 2014</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The description corresponds to the print <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Procedure</hi> in which a Parish Clerk is placed opposite the Rector of an adjoining village. It appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Punch, or The London Charivari</hi> 83 (15 July 1882), p. 23. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1367">Ill. 1367</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">‘Worn out’</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2416">F 997 / JH 267</rs>) measures 50 x 31 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘ontwerpen, ontwerpschetsen’ (designs, design sketches).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    