<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 10 December 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let292"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b264 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>292</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>242</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>282</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-10">Sunday, 10 December 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0264" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0264" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000323_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Zondags kom ik er telkens toe om U te schrijven en zoo ook heden. Dezer dagen las ik le Nabab van Daudet<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en vind het meesterlijk – – oa. die wandeling van le Nabab en Hemerlingue den bankier<c type="kk">/</c> op Père la chaise in de schemering terwijl de buste van Balzac<c type="kk">/</c> een donker silhouet<c type="kk">/</c> tegen de lucht uit ironisch op hen neerziet<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Dat is net een teekening van Daumier. Gij schreeft mij over Daumier hij gemaakt had la Révolution – Denis Dessoubs<c type="kp">_</c>– Toen ge zulks schreeft wist ik niet wie Denis Dessoubs was<c type="kk">/</c> nu las ik het in histoire d’un crime van Victor Hugo. Het is een nobel figuur – ik wou ik de teekening van D. kende.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik kan natuurlijkerwijs geen boek over Parijs lezen of ik denk direkt aan U. Ik kan ook geen boek over Parijs lezen of ik vind er eenigzins ook den Haag in terug<c type="kk">/</c> dat wel kleiner is dan Parijs doch toch ook een hofstad met bijbehoorende zeden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Als gij zegt in Uw laatsten brief “wat is er toch een raadsel in de natuur”<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zeg ik dat met U. Het leven in ’t abstracte is reeds een raadsel<c type="kk">/</c> de werkelijkheid maakt dat het een raadsel in een raadsel wordt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En wie zijn wij om het op te lossen<c type="kp">_</c>– Evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> we maken er zelf een stofdeeltje van uit<c type="kk">/</c> van die maatschappij waarvan we vragen<c type="kk">/</c> Waar heen gaat ze<c type="kk">/</c> naar den duivel of naar God.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Pourtant le soleil se lève<c type="kk">/</c> zegt V. Hugo.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Lang<c type="kk">/</c> lang geleden reeds las ik in l’ami Fritz van Erckmann Chatrian een woord van den ouden Rabbi dat dikwijls weer in mijn gedachten terug kwam<c type="kk">/</c> “nous ne sommes pas dans la vie pour être heureux mais nous devons tâcher de mériter le bonheur”.–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Op zich zelf genomen is er iets pedants in die gedachte<c type="kk">/</c> althans men zou het als iets pedants <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> opvatten maar in ’t verband waarin het woord voorkwam<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. in den mond van dat sympathieke figuur van den ouden Rabbi David Sechel<c type="kk">/</c> trof het mij diep en dikwijls denk ik er aan. Ook bij het teekenen – men moet niet er op rekenen dat men zijn teekeningen verkoopen zal doch het is pligt ze zoo te maken dat zij waarde hebben en serieus zijn. Men mag n.l. niet nonchalant of onverschillig worden al wordt men teleurgesteld in zijn omstandigheden.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Met betrekking tot mijn plan met de lithographies<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er nog veel over gedacht<c type="kk">/</c> was het dat alleen<c type="kk">/</c> ik was er niet mee gevorderd vrees ik want wat zal ik er over denken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dus bovendien heb ik er nog weer een paar teekeningen voor gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> eene vrouw met een zak kolen op ’t hoofd met een werf op den achtergrond<c type="kk">/</c> een silhouet van daken en schoorsteenen<c type="kk">/</c> en eene vrouw aan de waschtobbe.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Gij hoeft U niet ongerust te maken ik vooreerst andere demarches zal doen dan de teekeningen zelf – ik moet met het nemen van proeven met de lithographie een tijdje wachten tot ik eens weer bij kas ben om het voort te zetten<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik geloof het iets zou kunnen worden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Bij tijden kan ik erg verlangen eens weer in Londen te zijn. Ik zou zoo enorm graag meer van drukken en teekenen op hout weten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik voel eene kracht in mij die ik ontwikkelen moet, een vuur dat ik niet mag uitdooven maar moet aanwakkeren ofschoon ik niet weet tot welke uitkomst het mij leiden zal en over een sombere niet verwonderd zou zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">In een tijd als deze<c type="kk">/</c> wat moet men wenschen? Wat is het gelukkigste lot betrekkelijk?<ptr target="#note-t-a"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">In sommige toestanden is het beter overwonnene dan overwinnaar te zijn. b.v. liever Prometheus dan Jupiter<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Enfin – het is een oud woord<c type="kk">/</c> “laat maar gebeuren wat gebeuren moet”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Om van iets anders te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> weet gij wiens werk mij zeer getroffen heeft. Ik zag reproducties van Jul<hi rend="italics">ien</hi> Dupré (is dit een zoon van Jules Dupré???)<c type="kk">/</c> ’t eene stelde voor twee maaiers<c type="kk">/</c> ’t andere eene prachtige groote houtsnee uit Monde illustré<c type="kk">/</c> eene boerin die eene koe in de wei brengt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Het kwam mij voor uitmuntend te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> zeer energiek en zeer trouw<c type="kp">_</c> Het lijkt b.v. op Pierre Billet welligt of op Butin<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Dan zag ik ook nog verschillende figuren van Dagnan Bouveret<c type="kk">/</c> een bedelaar<c type="kk">/</c> eene trouwpartij<c type="kk">/</c> l’accident<c type="kk">/</c> le jardin des tuilleries<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Die twee zijn dunkt me kerels die corps à corps worstelen met de natuur<c type="kk">/</c> kerels die niet verflaauwen en een paar solide knuisten aan ’t lijf hebben. Over l’“accident” schreeft gij mij in der tijd<c type="kk">/</c> nu ken ik het en vind het zeer mooi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Het verhevene<c type="kk">/</c> de haast godsdienstige emotie van Millet hebben ze misschien niet<c type="kk">/</c> althans niet in die mate als Millet zelf<c type="kk">/</c> ze hebben misschien niet zijn volle warme liefde doch evenwel wat is het uitnemend goed. Nu ken ik wel is waar slechts reproducties doch mij dunkt daar kan niets in zijn wat niet in het oorspronkelijk werk zelf gelegd was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">à propos<c type="kk">/</c> het heeft bij mij lang geduurd eer ik Thomas Faed’s werk mooi vond maar tegenwoordig aarzel ik daaromtrent niet meer<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. de Sunday in the backwoods of Canada – Home &amp; the homeless – Worn out – The poor, the poor mans friend, enfin gij kent de serie aquatinten door Graves uitgegeven<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik heb vandaag nog gewerkt aan oude teekeningen uit Etten omdat ik de knotwilgen weer in dergelijken bladerloozen toestand hier terugzag in het veld en het geen ik verleden jaar zag mij weer voor den geest kwam.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik kan soms zoo verlangen naar landschap te maken<c type="kk">/</c> net als naar een verre wandeling om eens op te frisschen en ik zie in de heele natuur<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. in boomen<c type="kk">/</c> expressie en als ’t ware een ziel. Een rij knotwilgen heeft iets van een processie weesmannen soms.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Het jonge koren kan iets onuitsprekelijk reins en zachts hebben dat een dergelijke emotie opwekt als de expressie van een slapend kindje b.v.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Het platgetrapte gras aan den kant van een weg heeft iets vermoeids en bestovens als de bevolking van een achterbuurt. Toen het laatst gesneeuwd had zag ik een groepje savoye koolen die stonden te verkleumen<c type="kk">/</c> dat me herinnerde aan een groepje vrouwen die ik s’morgens vroeg in een water- en vuur kelder<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> had zien staan en hun dunne rokken en oude shawls<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Met betrekking tot die bewuste figuren die ik wel wilde lithographieeren geloof ik dat het moeielijkste is er een dertigtal te vinden die zamen een soort geheel vormen – men moet daarvoor er heel wat meer dan 30 teekenen<c type="kp">_</c>– Als ik die eerst heb dan is de stap van reproductie een tweede die welligt <hi rend="italics">dan</hi> gemakkelijker is dan wanneer men vóór men ’t geheel heeft al gaat reproduceeren. Misschien<c type="kk">/</c> of liever zeker zijt gij vóór ik zoover ben dat ik ze heb er wel weer eens geweest en kunnen wij er dan eens nader over spreken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Er is hier reeds iets dergelijks voor het lager onderwijs gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. 24 lith. door Schmidt Crans die ik onlangs zag<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Er zijn er een paar bij die goed zijn doch gij zult begrijpen aan den persoon die ze gemaakt heeft dat het wel wat flaauw<c type="shy">-</c>hartig is in ’t geheel genomen. <hi rend="italics">Die</hi> worden evenwel zeer gretig op de scholen gebruikt schijnt het – maar wat is het deplorable dat juist voor ’t onderwijs men met zoo iets reeds tevreden is. Enfin ’t is daarmee zooals met alles.</p>
    
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Doch kerel<c type="kk">/</c> lees vooral eens <hi rend="italics">le Nabab</hi><c type="kk">/</c> het is prachtig. Dat figuur zou men den <hi rend="italics">braven</hi> <hi rend="italics">schobbejak</hi> kunnen noemen<c type="kp">_</c> Zijn er zoo? Ik geloof het vast<c type="kp">_</c> Er is veel hart in die boeken van Daudet. Zoo in les Rois en exil dat figuur van de koningin “aux yeux d’aigue marine”.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Schrijf weer spoedig eens<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Wat kan het een mensch goed doen als men somber gestemd is aan ’t kale strand te wandelen en te kijken in de grijsgroene zee met de lange witte streepen der golven<c type="kp">_</c> Doch heeft men behoefte aan iets groots<c type="kk">/</c> iets oneindigs<c type="kk">/</c> iets waar men God in zien kan<c type="kk">/</c> men hoeft het niet ver te zoeken<c type="kk">/</c> mij dacht ik zag iets – dieper – oneindiger – eeuwiger dan een Oceaan in de expressie van de oogjes van een klein kindje – als het s’morgens wakker wordt en kraait – of lacht omdat het ’t zonnetje ziet schijnen in zijn wiegje<c type="kp">_</c> Als er een “rayon d’en haut”<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> is<c type="kk">/</c> welligt kan men die daar vinden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">adieu kerel, met een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I often get around to writing to you on Sundays, and likewise today. I’ve been reading Le Nabab by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> these past few days, and find it masterly — among other things that walk taken by the Nabab and Hemerlingue the banker at Père Lachaise in the twilight while the bust of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>, a dark silhouette against the sky, looks down on them ironically.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> It’s just like a drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>. You wrote to me about Daumier saying that he’d made The Revolution — Denis Dussoubs. When you wrote that, I didn’t know who <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_352">Denis Dussoubs</rs> was; now I’ve read it in Histoire d’un crime by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>. He’s a noble character — I wish I knew the drawing by D.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Of course I can’t read a book about Paris without instantly thinking of you. I also can’t read a book about Paris without to some extent also finding The Hague in it, which is admittedly smaller than Paris but still a court city with corresponding morals.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">When you say in your last letter ‘what a riddle there is in nature’, I echo your words. Life in the abstract is already a riddle, reality turns it into a riddle within a riddle. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And who are we to solve it? All the same, we ourselves form a particle of it, of the society of which we ask, Where is it going, to the devil or to God? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Yet the sun rises, says <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">V. Hugo</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Long, long ago, in L’ami Fritz by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>, I read a remark by the old rabbi that has often come to mind since: ‘We are not alive in order to be happy, but we must try to deserve happiness.’<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Taken in isolation, this thought seems a little pedantic, at least one <hi rend="italics">could</hi> interpret it as a little pedantic, but in the context in which the remark occurred, namely on the lips of the sympathetic figure of old Rabbi David Sechel, it struck me deeply and I often think of it. Also when drawing — one shouldn’t count on selling one’s drawings, but one has a duty to make them such that they have value and are serious. For one may not become nonchalant or indifferent, even if one is disappointed by one’s circumstances. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">As for my plan with the lithographs, I’ve thought about it a lot; if that had been all, I fear I wouldn’t have made any progress, for what is there to think about? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Thus in addition I’ve again made a few drawings for them, a woman with a sack of coal on her head with a yard in the background, a silhouette of roofs and chimneys, and a woman at the wash-tub.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">You needn’t worry that I’ll undertake anything else for the time being apart from the drawings themselves — I must wait a little before doing trials with lithography until I have some money to get on with them. But I believe it could come to something. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">From time to time I have a great longing to be in London again. I’d so very much like to know more about printing and drawing on wood. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I feel a power in me that I must develop, a fire that I may not put out but must fan, although I don’t know to what outcome it will lead me, and wouldn’t be surprised if it was a sombre one. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">In times like these, what should one wish for? What is the happiest lot in these circumstances? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">In some situations it’s better to be the vanquished than the victor, for example, better Prometheus than Jupiter.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Anyway, it’s an old saying, ‘what will be will be’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">To change the subject, do you know whose work has made a deep impression on me? I saw reproductions of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1006">Jul<hi rend="italics">ien</hi> Dupré</rs> (is this a son of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs>???). One was of two reapers, the other, a splendid large woodcut from Monde illustré, of a peasant woman taking a cow into the meadow.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> It seemed to me outstanding, very energetic and very true to life. It perhaps resembles <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_876">Pierre Billet</rs>, say, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_915">Butin</rs>. 
    <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Then I also saw various figures by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_959">Dagnan-Bouveret</rs>, a beggar, a wedding party, The accident, The Garden of the Tuileries.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Those two seem to me to be fellows who wrestle physically with nature, fellows who don’t weaken and aren’t afraid of dirtying their hands. You wrote to me about ‘The accident’ at the time, now I know it and find it very beautiful. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">They perhaps don’t have the lofty quality, the almost religious emotion of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, at least not to the same degree as Millet himself; they perhaps don’t have his full, warm love, but even so how outstandingly good it is. Now admittedly I only know reproductions, but it seems to me that they can’t contain anything that wasn’t put into the original work itself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">By the way, it took a long time before I found <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1011">Thomas Faed</rs>’s work beautiful, but these days I don’t hesitate about it any more, for instance, the Sunday in the backwoods of Canada — Home and the homeless — Worn out — The poor, the poor man’s friend, anyway, you know the series of aquatints published by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_437">Graves</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Today I worked on old drawings from Etten, because I saw the pollard willows again in a similar leafless state here in the field, and what I had seen last year came to mind again.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Sometimes I long so much to do landscape, just as one would for a long walk to refresh oneself, and in all of nature, in trees for instance, I see expression and a soul, as it were. A row of pollard willows sometimes resembles a procession of orphan men. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Young wheat can have something ineffably pure and gentle about it that evokes an emotion like that aroused by the expression of a sleeping child, for example. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">The grass trodden down at the side of a road looks tired and dusty like the inhabitants of a poor quarter. After it had snowed recently I saw a group of Savoy cabbages that were freezing, and that reminded me of a group of women I had seen early in the morning at a water and fire cellar<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> in their thin skirts and old shawls. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">As for those figures that I wanted to lithograph, I think the most difficult thing is to find thirty or so that together will form some sort of whole — for that one has to draw considerably more than 30. If I first have them, reproduction will be a second step which may <hi rend="italics">then</hi> be easier than if one had started reproducing before one had the whole. Perhaps, or rather certainly, you’ll have been here again before I’ve got as far as having them done, and then we can discuss this further. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Something similar for primary schools has already been made here, namely 24 lithographs by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_969">Schmidt Crans</rs> which I saw recently.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> A few of them are good, but you’ll understand, given the person who made them, that as a whole they’re rather faint-hearted. All the same, it seems that schools are keen to use <hi rend="italics">them</hi> — but how deplorable it is that people are satisfied with something like that, especially for schools. Well, it’s the same with this as with everything else. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Still, old chap, read <hi rend="italics">Le Nabab</hi> above all. It’s splendid. One could call that character the <hi rend="italics">good scoundrel</hi>. Are there such people? I’m sure there are. There’s a lot of heart in those books by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>. For example, in Les rois en exil the character of the queen ‘with eyes of aquamarine’.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Write again soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">How much good it does a person if one is in a gloomy mood to walk on the empty beach and look into the grey-green sea with the long white lines of the waves. Yet if one has a need for something great, something infinite, something in which one can see God, one needn’t look far. I thought I saw something — deeper, more infinite, more eternal than an ocean — in the expression in the eyes of a baby — when it wakes in the morning and crows — or laughs because it sees the sun shine into its cradle. If there is a ‘ray from on high’,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> it might be found there. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Adieu, old chap, with a handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 the letter is dated Sunday, 5 November. It is, however, unlikely that after <ref target="let280.xml">letter 280</ref>, which also has that date, Van Gogh wrote the present letter as well, because he says at the beginning ‘I often get round to writing to you on Sundays, and likewise today.’ </p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">Dorn has pointed out that it does not make sense for Van Gogh to be writing about <hi rend="italics">continuing</hi> to make lithographs when it is not until <ref target="let281.xml">letter 281</ref> that he refers to his first print. See exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 107 (n. 2). For this reason he dates the letter later, to 10 December 1882. There are other arguments that confirm that Dorn is right.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">In <ref target="#l-41">ll. 41-52</ref> Van Gogh says that he is going to give up making lithographs for the time being because of lack of money, but that he will continue to prepare for them by doing a lot of drawing. This is entirely in line with what he had already said in <ref target="let291.xml">letter 291</ref>, dated between Monday, 4 and Saturday, 9 December 1882. So the ‘plan with the lithographs’ <ref target="#l-41">(l. 41)</ref> is not the general introduction to the lithographic process in which he was engaged in early November, but the plan to use a society to publish a series of lithographs of 30 types of workman, as proposed in <ref target="let289.xml">letter 289</ref>. <ref target="let291.xml">Letter 291</ref> was the first resumption of Van Gogh’s explanation of that plan, and the remark about ‘those figures that I wanted to lithograph’ <ref target="#l-118">(l. 118)</ref> in the present letter is again entirely in line with this. Moreover, the remark that it had ‘recently’ snowed <ref target="#l-112">(l. 112)</ref> is borne out by meteorological observations (<hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi>). Thus the Sunday on which the letter was written was 10 December 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plan to make a series of 30 lithographs <ref target="let289.xml">(289)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Alphonse Daudet</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_306"><hi rend="italics">Le Nabab – Moeurs parisiennes</hi></ref> (1877) is a novel about the fall of Bernard Jansoulet, known as Le Nabab, who has amassed a fortune in Tunis. When this successful and honest businessman moves to Paris, he is swindled and rejected by this immoral and degenerate city. He later dies of despair.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The walk in the famous Parisian cemetery Père Lachaise is described in ‘Les funérailles’ (chapter 19); for the scene with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>’s bust, see Daudet 1986-1994, vol. 2. p. 761. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>As far as is known, there was only a painting of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1997"><hi rend="italics">Scene from the Revolution</hi></rs> (Scene from the Revolution), not a drawing, as Vincent had evidently understood from Theo; see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let280.xml#n-7">letter 280, n. 7.</ref></p>

<p rend="indent">Theo himself had probably drawn a link between <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_352">Denis Dussoubs</rs>, a republican activist, and the young revolutionary at the centre of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>’s painting, unless he was referring to a drawing (possibly unknown). </p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_307"><hi rend="italics">Histoire d’un crime</hi></ref> (1877-1878) recounts the events during the coup of December 1851 in Paris. The fourth volume, ‘Quatrième journée. La victoire’, chapter 3: ‘Les faits de la nuit – le Petit-Carreau’ describes at great length how <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_352">Dussoubs</rs> is killed while making a heroic attempt to mediate in a battle between soldiers and republicans. See Hugo 1987, pp. 374-383.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>A reference to the title of the last chapter of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Hugo</rs>’s historical novel <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_278"><hi rend="italics">Quatre-vingt-treize</hi></ref> (1874), ‘Cependant le soleil se lève’. See for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Quatre-vingt-treize</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let286.xml#n-9">letter 286, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>A reference to a dialogue between the humble Fritz Kobus and the rabbi David Sichel (not ‘Sechel’, as Van Gogh writes a little later) in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_52"><hi rend="italics">L’ami Fritz</hi></ref> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>. They discuss the question whether one should pursue happiness in life. The rabbi does not think so, because God did not intend it. He deduces this from the fact that God has not given man the means with which to be happy. On being asked what God does want from us in that case, he answers: ‘Il veut que nous méritions le bonheur, et cela fait une grande différence, Kobus’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’ami Fritz</hi>, edition bound with <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Histoire du plébiscite</hi>. Paris 1872, pp. 14-15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Strictly speaking, it is possible that three drawings are being described here, but given that with the lithographs Van Gogh was primarily concerned with the figures, we may assume that he is describing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">two</hi> drawings, the first including the background and the second only the central subject. These drawings are not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘naar omstandigheden’, ‘in dit verband’ (under the circumstances, in this connection).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This comparison, which was added as an afterthought, may come from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_198"><hi rend="italics">William Shakespeare</hi></ref>: ‘Prometheus was Right defeated. Jupiter, as always, perpetrated the usurpation of power by putting Right to the torture’ (Prométhée, c’est le droit vaincu. Jupiter a, comme toujours, consommé l’usurpation du pouvoir par le supplice du droit). See Hugo 1864, p. 307, and exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, pp. 33-34.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Cf. the saying ‘Aan wat gebeuren moet, is geen ontkomen’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The French landscape painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1006">Julien Dupré</rs> was a nephew of the artist <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs>. The work referred to with two reapers has not been identified – Dupré produced numerous scenes with ‘reapers’ and farm labourers, mostly undated. The second reproduction Van Gogh mentions is the print engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1556">Jules Louis Laurent Langeval</rs> after Dupré’s painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dans la prairie</hi> (In the meadow), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 26 (16 September 1882), pp. 184-185. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_794">Ill. 794</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>A ‘beggar’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_959">Dagnan-Bouveret</rs> is not known, but given that Van Gogh mentions several prints that appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi>, he must mean the engraving <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Un mendiant</hi> (A beggar), after the work with the same title by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_124">Jules Bastien-Lepage</rs>, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1512">Charles Baude</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 25 (25 June 1881), pp. 424-425. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_542">Ill. 542</rs>. A reduced reproduction of it was in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 77 (14 May 1881), p. 327; a lithograph in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Vie Moderne</hi> 3 (11 June 1881), p. 377.</p>

<p rend="indent">The ‘wedding party’ is Dagnan-Bouveret’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Une noce chez le photographe</hi> (A wedding party at the photographer’s), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1560">Auguste Louis Lepère</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 24 (7 February 1880), pp. 88-89. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_38">Ill. 38</rs>. There was also an engraving by Rouget in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Univers</hi> Illustré 23 (7 February 1880), p. 85, and a photogravure at Goupil, reproduced in Eugène Montrosier, Les artistes modernes, part 1. Paris 1881, p. 112.</p>

<p rend="indent">Auguste Louis Lepère also engraved <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Un accident</hi> (An accident) in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 24 (22 May 1880), p. 321. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_735">Ill. 735</rs>. A print by Charles Baude appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 77 (28 May 1881), between pp. 364 and 365; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Univers Illustré</hi> 23 (29 May 1880) p. 341 also had a print.</p>

<p rend="indent">For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_736"><hi rend="italics">A bird charmer in the Jardin des Tuileries</hi></rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let275.xml#n-40">see letter 275, n. 40.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>By ‘the series of aquatints published by Graves’ Van Gogh must mean the series of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">mezzotints</hi> (‘mixed mezzotint’) published by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_437">Henry Graves</rs> &amp; Co.</p>

<p rend="indent">The print after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1011">Thomas Faed</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunday in the backwoods of Canada</hi>, was engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1595">William Henry Simmons</rs> in 1863; it is also known as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Scottish emigrants’ Sunday in the backwoods</hi> (London, Victoria &amp; Albert Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_828">Ill. 828</rs>.</p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_50">Henry Cousins</rs> made a print after Faed’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Home and the homeless</hi> (Edinburgh, National Galleries of Scotland), <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_826">Ill. 826</rs>, (see The printsellers’ association catalogue of registered engravings. London 1912, no. 171). It has not been traced.</p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1597">Frederick Stacpoole</rs> made a mezzotint after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Worn out</hi> (1868) (London, British Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_829">Ill. 829</rs>.</p>

<p rend="indent">The print after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The poor, the poor man’s friend</hi>, 1867 (London, Victoria &amp; Albert Museum), <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_827">Ill. 827</rs>, was engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1595">William Henry Simmons</rs> (see The printsellers’ association catalogue of registered engravings. London 1912, no. 293). It has not been traced. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Three large drawings with pollard willows from the Etten period are known: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_320">F 1678 / JH 46</rs>; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_319">F 900 / JH 47</rs>; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_321">F 995 / JH 56</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>A cellar where hot water and glowing coals could be bought. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh probably means the four-volume publication <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_308"><hi rend="italics">Thieme’s teeken-cahiers door J.M. Schmidt Crans</hi></ref>. Arnhem, G.J. Thieme, 1866. The volumes cost 15 or 20 cents (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brinkman</hi>). As far as is known no copies are extant. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The ‘yeux d’aigue marine’ occur in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_264"><hi rend="italics">Les rois en exil – Roman parisien</hi></ref> (chapters 3 and 4). See Daudet 1986-1994, vol. 2, pp. 912, 940. Van Gogh is referring to the gentle and resigned Queen Frédérique of Illyria, one of the principal characters in the novel. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>For ‘un rayon d’en haut’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let143.xml#n-5">see letter 143, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    