<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 22 December 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let295"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b276 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>295</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>254</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>296</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-12-22">on or about Friday, 22 December 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0276" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000343_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000343_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0276" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000343_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000343_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000343_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw aanget. brief ontving ik in orde &amp; dank U hartelijk voor de toezending. Uit Uw brief zag ik ge het druk hebt met den inventaris. Heb er maar voorspoed mee<c type="kk">/</c> het zal een geduchte sjouwerij zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat wou ik we b.v. zoo’n paar kerstdagen eens zamen konden zijn – ik zou U zoo graag eens weer op ’t atelier hebben ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb in den laatsten tijd ook nog al er op gesjouwd<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat ik vol was van dat kerstmisgevoel<c type="kk">/</c> en te voelen is niet genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> men moet het in zijn werk brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Zoo ben ik nu bezig aan twee groote koppen van </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">een weesman<c type="kk">/</c> met zijn witten baard &amp; ouderwetschen<c type="kk">/</c> ouden hoogen hoed.–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Zoo’n soort oud geestig gezigt als men bij een gezellig kerstmisvuur zou wenschen heeft die kerel<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Bij gelegenheid van X<hi rend="super">mas</hi> is door Harper een blad uitgegeven<c type="kk">/</c> gemaakt door eenige schilders die zich <hi rend="italics">The tile club</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dus de “tegelschilders” noemen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Boughton heeft er een blad in<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> De mooisten die er bij zijn zijn teekeningen van Abbey – het zijn vooral scènes uit den ouden tijd toen de Hollanders New York stichtten onder den naam van Nieuw Amsterdam.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Deze teekeningen zijn gereproduceerd meen ik met dat procedé ’t welk ge beschreeft – op het papier waarvan Buhot een staaltje zond.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik moet deze amerikaansche teekeningen nog eens met de platen in Vie moderne vergelijken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik heb alle hoop dat ik dit wel leeren zou en wie weet of we ’t volgend jaar niet eens proeven kunnen nemen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Terwijl gij het zoo druk hebt als nu zal ik mijn uiterste best doen om teekeningen te maken met het oog daarop. Is dan Uw drukte eenigzins voorbij dan zal ik nog wel wat informatie van U te vragen hebben of van Buhot.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Maar ik zie duidelijk genoeg dat het procedé <hi rend="italics">dankbaar</hi> is<c type="kk">/</c> dat in geval de teekening goed is men haast zeker is van goede reproductie<c type="kp">_</c> Dus werken op de teekeningen is ’t voornaamste.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wat de lithographie betreft<c type="kk">/</c> doordat ik eenige malen het drukken &amp; al de preparatie van den steen heb bijgewoond zoo denk ik er zeer over om eens te gaan lithographieeren zonder eenige hulp van papier of iets anders<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. eenvoudig op den steen zelf teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Want hoe mooi of ik b.v. die bladen in Harpers X<hi rend="super">mas</hi> nommer of in Vie moderne ook vind<c type="kk">/</c> er is toch iets machinaals in<c type="kk">/</c> iets van eene photographie of photogravure<c type="kk">/</c> en nog liever zie ik een gewone lith<c type="kp">_</c> van Daumier of Gavarni of Lemud<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin voor ’t een zoowel als ’t ander is een vaste hand van teekenen noodig en daar hangt ’t meestendeels van af. Ik vrees dat het nieuwe procedé een van die dingen is dat niet ten volle iemand voldoen kan en dat eigentlijk wat te zoet is. Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> eene gewone ets<c type="kk">/</c> eene gewone houtgravure of eene gewone lithographie heeft een charme van oorspronkelijkheid die door niets machinaals te remplaceeren is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Zoo ook wat gravure aangaat – de reproductie met photogravure van de naaischool van Israels<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> b.v. of het sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van Blommers<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> of Artz<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> is superbe – zooals ze door G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> zijn uitgegeven<c type="kp">_</c> Maar als dit procedé geheel de eigentlijke gravure zou vervangen zou ik meenen, men de gewone gravures toch missen zou op den duur<c type="kk">/</c> met bezwaren en imperfecties en al.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Rappard is nog steeds ziek ofschoon de crisis voorbij is, is zeer zwak naar zijn vader schrijft. Wat het is? ik weet het niet – misschien hersenkoorts of -ontsteking? Daarover laat zijn vader zich niet uit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop ge aan Uw kerstmis nog wat hebben zult – nog eens een loop zult kunnen doen &amp; wat gezelligheid hebben zult<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Doch ik vrees ge zult diep in den inventaris zitten. Enfin er is in werken<c type="kk">/</c> ook in werk wat op zich zelf niet heel pleizierig is<c type="kk">/</c> altijd iets opwekkends<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Het beste U toegewenscht<c type="kp">_</c> als ge kunt schrijf nog eens maar hebt ge het te druk zoo begrijp ik daar alles van en dan moet ge Uw scha later maar eens inhalen door een paar beschrijvingen van Montmartre of zoo<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your registered letter in good order, and thank you warmly for sending it. From your letter I saw that you’re busy with the inventory. Good luck with it, no doubt it’s a fearsome grind. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">How I wish we could spend a couple of Christmas days together, for instance — I would also dearly like to have you in my studio once more. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I, too, have been toiling quite hard recently, precisely because I was full of the Christmas feeling, and feeling isn’t enough, one must bring it into one’s work. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">So I’m now occupied with two large heads of an orphan man, with his white beard and old-fashioned, old top hat.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> This chap has the sort of old, lively face that one would wish for beside a cosy Christmas fire. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Harper has published an issue for Xmas done by some painters calling themselves <hi rend="italics">The tile club</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs> has a print in it.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> The finest of them are drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> — they mainly show scenes from olden times when the Dutch founded New York under the name New Amsterdam.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I believe that these drawings are reproduced using that process you described — on the paper that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs> sent a sample of.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I must compare these American drawings with the prints in Vie Moderne. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I have every hope that I can learn this, and who knows, perhaps next year we’ll be able to do some experiments. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">As long as you’re as busy as you are now, I’ll do my very best to make drawings with that in mind. Then when you’re not so busy I’ll have some more information to ask from you or from Buhot. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But I see clearly enough that the process is <hi rend="italics">rewarding</hi>, that if the drawing is good one is virtually assured of good reproduction. So working on the drawings is the main thing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">As for lithography, because I’ve been present several times during the printing and the preparation of the stone, I’m seriously considering making a lithograph without the aid of paper or anything else, that is simply drawing straight onto the stone itself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">For however beautiful I find those sheets in Harper’s Xmas number, for example, or in Vie Moderne, there’s still something mechanical about them, something of a photograph or photogravure, and I would rather see an ordinary lithograph by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1167">Lemud</rs>. Anyway, a steady drawing hand is required for both the one and the other, and for the most part that’s what it depends on. I fear that the new process is one of those things that isn’t completely satisfactory, and is in fact a little too sweet. I mean, an ordinary etching, an ordinary wood engraving or an ordinary lithograph has a charm of originality that can’t be replaced by anything mechanical. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">So too with engraving — the reproduction through photogravure of the needlework school by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> say, or the painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> or the one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_33">Artz</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> is superb, as published by G&amp;Cie. But if this process were to completely replace true engraving I think the ordinary engravings would eventually be missed, with all their shortcomings and imperfections. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> is still ill, although the crisis is past; his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_183">father</rs> writes that he’s very weak. What is it? I don’t know — perhaps brain fever or infection? His father says nothing about that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Well, I hope that you’ll still be able to enjoy Christmas — still get to go for a walk and have a pleasant time. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But I fear you’ll be deep in the inventory. Still, there’s always something cheerful about working, even when the work itself isn’t that enjoyable. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">My best wishes to you. If you can, write again, but if you’re too busy I’ll understand completely, then you must make up for lost time later with a few descriptions of Montmartre or something like that.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter dates from after the receipt of the <hi rend="italics">third</hi> remittance in December, thus after about 20 December, and must have been written a few days before Christmas, because Vincent hopes that Theo will still enjoy the festive season <ref target="#l-72">(l. 72)</ref>. Accordingly, we date the letter on or about Friday, 22 December 1882. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Consignment of lithographic paper from Buhot with explanatory information <ref target="let280.xml">(280)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s illness <ref target="let290.xml">(290)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Two portraits of the orphan man with a top hat and a white beard are known from this period, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orphan man with top hat</hi>: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3027">F 954 / JH 287</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3028">F 954a / JH 288</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The special <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Christmas Pictures Paper. Christmas 1882. Done by The Tile Club &amp; its literary friends</hi>. The price of this 32-page special was 75 cents. We have consulted the copy in the Widener Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</p>

<p rend="indent">In 1877 a group of 31 celebrated New York City painters, sculptors, illustrators, architects, writers, and musicians formed the Tile Club. A social club established at the height of the aesthetic movement in America, the Tile Club influenced plein-air painting, the establishment of art colonies, and the development of American Impressionism. On them: Pisano 1999. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml#n-28">letter 333, n. 28.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">George Henry Boughton</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peter Stuyvesandt and the maiden</hi>, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1553">Francis Scott King</rs>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Christmas Pictures Paper</hi>, p. 16. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2018">Ill. 2018</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Edwin Austin Abbey</rs> supplied a total of six illustrations. Here Van Gogh would have meant two in particular that were printed next to the poem ‘The Dutch patrol’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1700">Edmund Clarence Stedman</rs>: beside the lines ‘In St. Mark’s church-yard – They see the shape arise’ (p. 8), and ‘From Maiden Lane to Corlear’s Hook – The Dutchmen’s pypen glow’ (p. 9) (engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1608">G.F. Williams</rs>) respectively. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2019">Ill. 2019</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2020">Ill. 2020</rs>.</p>

<p rend="indent">This special by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> also included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Winter</hi>, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1596">J.G. Smithwick</rs> (p. 17). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2021">Ill. 2021</rs>. Van Gogh later calls this engraving ‘Winter girl’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let302.xml">letters 302</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let309.xml">309</ref>). The prints <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mingo</hi>; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Miss Fraishy</hi> and<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">“Good-bye”</hi> illustrate the story ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_314">Mingo. A sketch of life in Middle Georgia</ref>’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1701">Joel Chandler Harris</rs> (pp. 24-25).</p>
      
<p rend="indent">
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> 26 (7 January 1882) also had prints about New Amsterdam, among them Abbey’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">New Amsterdam – The dinner</hi>, to accompany Charles G. Gray’s poem ‘New Amsterdam’ of 1655; p. 13. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_476">Ill. 476</rs></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo may have written about paniconography (a form of photozincography), which was invented as a replacement for the wood engraving and did have photographic applications. Cf. Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 19-20. He would also have provided information about working with transfer paper.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ecole de couture à Katwyk (Hollande) </hi>(The sewing school at Katwijk (Holland)), 1881. Photogravure Goupil, 1882 (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2022">Ill. 2022</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Bernardus Johannes Blommers</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Départ des pinken </hi>(Departure of the pinks). Photogravure Goupil, n.d. (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_593">Ill. 593</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_33">David Adolph Constant Artz</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’hospice des vieillards à Katwyk (Hollande) </hi>(Old people’s home at Katwijk (Holland)). Photogravure Goupil, 1882 (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_516">Ill. 516</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Theo had earlier sent descriptions of Montmartre, which Vincent greeted with enthusiasm on several occasions: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let260.xml">see letters 260</ref>-<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let262.xml">262</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let288.xml">letter 288</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    