<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Sunday, 4 March 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let324"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b295 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>324</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>272</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>326</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-03-04">on or about Sunday, 4 March 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0295" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0295" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000368_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Het is net donker geworden &amp; wilde U voor de aardigheid de teekening van heden sturen omdat ik er U over schreef.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Van morgen begon ik een aquarel van een jongen en een meisje aan een dergelijke soepuitdeeling met nog een vrouwen<c type="shy">-</c>figuurtje in den hoek.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Die aquarel werd te onfrisch<c type="kk">/</c> wat voor een deel wel aan ’t papier ligt dat er niet voor deugde. Toch zag ik hoe oneindig beter het atelier nu voor kleur geschikt is en zal het ook natuurlijkerwijs bij deze eerste proef niet laten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zoo ging echter den morgen voorbij en ik besteedde den middag aan een teek<c type="kp">_</c> met <hi>bergkrijt</hi><c type="kk">/</c> het ééne stukje dat ik nog had van dezen zomer. Die stuur ik U hierbij.– Ik vind het nog niet af genoeg maar als a sketch from life is er misschien iets in van het leven – en wat menschelijk sentiment. Hierna beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Deze teek. laat dus de kwestie aquarellen nog even ver doch geeft een <hi rend="italics">voorloopig</hi> antwoord op wat gij schreeft naar aanl. van een klein krabbeltje dat ik U stuurde om U een idee te geven van het effekt der ramen op ’t atelier.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wilt ge mij een <hi rend="italics">zeer groot</hi> pleizier doen – stuur me dan eenige stukken bergkrijt over de post.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Er zit in dat bergkrijt <hi rend="italics">een ziel</hi> en leven – in conté vind ik iets doods<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Al zien twee violen er van buiten ongeveer hetzelfde uit – bij het bespelen zit in de eene soms een mooien klank die in de andere niet zit<c type="kp">_</c> In het bergkrijt zit veel klank of toon. Het bergkrijt begrijpt wat men wil zou ik haast zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> luistert met intelligentie en gehoorzaamt<c type="kk">/</c> en het conté is onverschillig en werkt niet mee. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Het bergkrijt heeft een echte zigeunersziel<c type="kk">/</c> als ’t niet te veel van U gevergd is<c type="kk">/</c> stuur me er wat van.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wie weet of nu met het betere licht en het bergkrijt en lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt ’t me niet lukken zou voor illustraties iets te maken. <hi rend="italics">Actualiteiten</hi> – die vroeg men<c type="kk">/</c> als men daarmee bedoelde zulke dingen als bijvoorbeeld illuminaties bij gelegenheid van s’Konings verjaardag zou ik daarin bitter weinig pleizier hebben – doch indien het de heeren behaagde onder de actualiteiten te rangschikken scènes uit het alledaagsche volksleven zoo heb ik er niets op tegen mijn uiterste best daarop te doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Als ik weer bergkrijt heb zal ik daarmee eens weer een paar figuurtjes van weesmannen maken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">En van soepuitdeelingen<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als nu dit de eerste is<c type="kk">/</c> krijgt ge ook nog heel andere composities<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ge zult dit formaat ook wel wat groot vinden<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – doch ik geloof dat met nog een tijd werken met modellen ik er toe 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>komen zal de figuren zoo krachtig te maken dat de grootte er niet meer toe doet, en zelfs vereischte is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dat hoeft het kleine niet weg te nemen en kan ik altijd reduceeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Er is in deze ruwe schets veel wat me hindert maar ik weet zeker ik er nog in vorderen zal binnen kort.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Kunt gij U niet begrijpen als ge dit troepje luidjes zoo eens bij elkaar ziet<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik mij met hen ’t huis voel. Ik las onlangs het volgende gezegde in <hi rend="italics">Felix</hi> <hi rend="italics">Holt the Radical</hi> van Eliott.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">The people I live among have the same follies and vices as the rich – only they have <hi rend="italics">their own</hi> <hi rend="italics">forms</hi> of folly and vice – and they have <hi rend="italics">not</hi> what are called <hi rend="italics">the refinements</hi> of the rich to make their faults more bearable<c type="kp">_</c>– It does not much matter to me – I am not fond of those refinements but some people are and find it difficult to feel at home with such persons as have them not.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik zou het zelf niet in die woorden bedacht hebben doch ik heb dit zelfde wel eens gevoeld.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als schilder voel ik mij met hen volkomen t’huis en tevreden niet alleen<c type="kk">/</c> doch vind in hun een karakter dat mij aan zigeuners soms denken doet – althans iets even pittoresks.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Daar ik toch al zoo druk geschreven heb dezer dagen zal ik waarschijnlijk niet meer voor den tienden schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> als ge kunt stuur het gewone mij niet later want ik heb beloofd bij Leurs<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> wat te betalen tegen dien tijd<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik dien te doen voor ik weer een en ander halen kan wat ik noodig zal hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik heb namelijk plan verschillende dingen die hij al lang heeft staan en mij goedkoop laten<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> wil<c type="kk">/</c> zoogenaamd tegen inkoopsprijs over te nemen. Het is vooral een aantal vellen schilderpapier van een grof soort dat ze tegenwoordig niet meer vragen, maar mij beter aanstaat dan het gladde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Met het bergkrijt zoudt ge mij enorm pleizier doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">adieu, het beste met alle dingen U toegewenscht<c type="kk">/</c> vooral met Uw zieke. geloof me </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Darkness has just fallen and wanted to send you today’s drawing for the fun of it because I wrote to you about it.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> This morning I began a watercolour of a boy and a girl at a similar soup distribution with another female figure in the corner.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">That watercolour became too unclear, partly due to the paper, which wasn’t right for it. But I saw how the studio is now infinitely more suitable for colour and will of course not give up after this first trial.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">That was how the morning passed, though, and I devoted the afternoon to a drawing in <hi>natural chalk</hi>, the one piece I had left from this summer. I’m sending it herewith. I don’t consider it sufficiently finished yet, but as a sketch from life perhaps there’s something of life in it — and some human sentiment. Better from now on.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">This drawing therefore leaves the question of watercolour where it was, but gives a <hi rend="italics">provisional</hi> answer to what you wrote after I sent you a small scratch to give you an idea of the effect of the windows on the studio.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">If you want to do me a <hi rend="italics">very great</hi> favour, send me some pieces of natural chalk by post.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">That natural chalk has <hi rend="italics">a soul</hi> and life — I find something dead in conté. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Two violins may look more or less the same on the outside — when they’re played one sometimes turns out to have a beautiful sound that the other doesn’t have. Natural chalk has lots of sound or tone. I would almost say that natural chalk understands what one wants, listens with intelligence and obeys, while conté is indifferent and doesn’t cooperate. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> Natural chalk has a true gypsy soul. Send me some, if it isn’t asking too much of you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Who knows if now, with better light and natural chalk and lithographic crayon, I shan’t succeed in doing something for illustrated magazines. <hi rend="italics">Current events</hi> — that’s what they wanted. If by that they meant things like illuminations for the king’s birthday, say, that would give me precious little enjoyment. But if it pleased the gentlemen to include under current events scenes from the everyday life of the people, I’d have nothing against doing my very best for those.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">When I have some more natural chalk, I’ll again do a few figures of orphan men with it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And you’ll get completely different compositions of soup distributions, of which this is now the first.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">No doubt you’ll again think this format rather large<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — but I believe that after a period of working with models I’ll 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> be able to make the figures so forceful that the size makes no difference, and will even be necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">That needn’t rule out a smaller size, and I can always reduce them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">There’s much in this rough sketch that bothers me, but I know for sure that I’ll soon make progress.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Can you understand when you see this band of people together that I feel at home with them? Lately I read the following in <hi rend="italics">Felix Holt the Radical</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The people I live among have the same follies and vices as the rich — only they have <hi rend="italics">their own forms</hi> of folly and vice — and they have <hi rend="italics">not</hi> what are called the <hi rend="italics">refinements</hi> of the rich to make their faults more bearable. It doesn’t much matter to me — I’m not fond of those refinements but some people are and find it difficult to feel at home with such persons as have them not.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I wouldn’t have put it in those words myself, but I’ve sometimes felt the same. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">As a painter I feel completely at home with them and not just content, yet I find a character in them that sometimes makes me think of gypsies — at any rate something as picturesque. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Since I’ve been so busy writing letters of late, I’ll probably not write again before the tenth. Send the usual no later if you can, for I’ve promised <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_491">Leurs</rs><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> to pay something around that time. I must do that before I can get one or two things that I’ll be needing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">The fact is that I plan to buy various things which he’s had for a long time and which he’ll let me have cheap, supposedly at cost price. Above all, there are some sheets of painting paper of a coarse variety that’s no longer in demand but suits me better than the smooth kind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">You’d do me a huge favour with the natural chalk.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Adieu, best wishes with everything, especially with your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs>. Believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let323.xml">letter 323</ref> of on or about Saturday, 3 March Van Gogh says he is expecting several models ‘tomorrow’, among them a boy (<ref target="let323.xml#l-119">ll. 119-123</ref> and <ref target="let323.xml#l-129">ll. 129-131</ref>); the present letter says that he began work on a watercolour with these models ‘this morning’. He also says: ‘Since I’ve been so busy writing letters of late, I’ll probably not write again before the tenth’ <ref target="#l-104">(ll. 104-106)</ref>. On these grounds we have dated this letter to on or about Sunday, 4 March 1883. (Another point is that the children would have been most likely to pose on a Sunday.)</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
  <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Alterations to the studio windows <ref target="let317.xml">(317)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
  <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is working with natural chalk <ref target="let322.xml">(322)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
  <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let323.xml">See letter 323</ref> of the day before. The drawing sent would have been <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Soup distribution in a public soup kitchen </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2427">F 1020 a/ JH 330</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This watercolour, after which the letter sketch was done, is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Soup distribution in a public soup kitchen </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2428">F 1020 b/ JH 331</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This unknown scratch was sent with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let319.xml">letter 319</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The drawing measures 56.5 x 44.4 cm, and this is indeed exceptional for Van Gogh.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is not quoting literally; in particular the last sentence is different. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">George Eliot</rs> writes: ‘I don’t say more bearable to me – I’m not fond of those refinements; but you are’. Van Gogh paraphrases Eliot’s ‘but you are’. See Eliot 1980, chapter 51, p. 396.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_491">Wilhelmus Johannes Leurs</rs>. In 1881-1882 he was a frame-maker and seller of artists’ materials, Hofsingel 1; idem in 1883-1884, but at Practizijnshoek 1; and in 1884-1885 tradesman in artists’ materials and frame-maker, Molenstraat 5 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboeken 1881-1885</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘afstaan’ (let me have).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    