<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 6 March 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let326"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b296 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>326</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>273</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>328</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-03-06">on or about Tuesday, 6 March 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0296" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000369_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000369_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0296" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000369_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000369_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">’t was niet mijn plan zoo gaauw reeds weer te schrijven – doch ik ben aan ’t zoeken naar allerlei soort van teekeningen zoo als ge weet. En nu heden met de rest van dat stukje bergkrijt maakte ik nog weer eene schets<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – daarin heb ik vervolgens gewasschen met sepia. Ik meen in het bergkrijt allerlei eigenaardigheden te zien die het bij uitnemendheid een middel maken om sommige dingen uit de natuur weer te geven. Dezen morgen deed ik eene wandeling buiten de stad<c type="kk">/</c> in de weilanden achter den Zuid Buitencingel waar Maris ’t eerst gewoond heeft &amp; waar ook de asch<supplied>v</supplied>aalt is.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik stond daar lang te kijken voor eene rij der meest knoestige<c type="kk">/</c> verdraaide en gedesorienteerde knotwilgen die ik ooit gezien heb. Zij begrensden een stuk moestuin – versch omgespit – en spiegelden zich af<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> in een vuil slootje – zeer vuil – maar waar toch reeds sprieten lentegroen schitterden. Maar die bruine<c type="kk">/</c> ruwe schorsen – de omgespitte aarde – waar men de vruchtbaarheid in kon zien om zoo te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> dat alles had iets eigenaardig-warms in de donkere<c type="kk">/</c> krachtige toonen<c type="kk">/</c> die mij al weer op het bergkrijt bragten. Zoodat als ik weer wat er van heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik ook eens landschap er mee hoop aan te grijpen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ofschoon bijgaande schets zeer onaf is<c type="kk">/</c> zoo kwam het mij voor er dingen in konden zijn in overeen<c type="shy">-</c>stemming met uw bedoeling – en is het ook weer een sketch from life.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Meen niet dat ik het een kwaliteit reken als er geen uitvoerigheid genoeg in is<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat zij verre. Doch de uitvoerigheid die zoowel gij zelf als ik ook er in zouden willen zien<c type="kk">/</c> bestaat niet zoo zeer geloof ik in later er bij gebragte details<c type="kk">/</c> maar moest ineens er meer in zijn dan nu wel ’t geval is. Daar het frissche er niet bij verloren mag gaan en<c type="kk">/</c> mits de impressie juist zij<c type="kk">/</c> er soms ook in hetgeen betrekkelijk onaf is expressie zit. Ik zal er echter natuurlijkerwijs op werken meer variatie in de toonen te brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Y mettre des details is me betrekkelijk onverschillig doch meer “dégrossir” wel degelijk mijn streven. Namelijk serrer la forme de plus près<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ofschoon nu deze dat nog niet voldoende heeft – zoo is er toch zooveel onderscheid door dat beetje sepia in het algemeen effekt<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik dacht ge in verband met die van gisteren er eens uit zien kondt hoe dat bergkrijt op diverse wijzen kan gebruikt worden. Ik schreef gisteren aan Rappard over het bergkrijt 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>omdat ik hem toch over dingen betreffende lithographie moest schrijven. En daar ik hem eenige croquis er mee wou sturen teekende ik onzen zuigeling er in diverse posturen mee.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> voor croquis is het ook zeer geschikt merkte ik. Ook kan men er halve toonen in brengen door middel van broodkruim<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien zijn alleen de allerdiepste schaduwen er minder goed mee te krijgen doch dan kan men zich zeker in veel gevallen van het lithographisch krijt bedienen – dat ook warm is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">’k Geloof ge aan de figuren wel reeds merken kunt dat het atelier gewonnen heeft met betrekking tot het licht. Wat is alles mooi buiten – vindt gij niet – dezer dagen. Ik heb veel plannen – dat kunt ge wel begrijpen<c type="kp">_</c> Ge weet dat ik aan heel wat verschillende zaken bezig ben. maar ik zou ook zoo graag verschillende procedés kennen omdat zulks een opwekking is om veel te werken en men er meer gedachten door krijgt.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik wou wel ik eerder aan dit bergkrijt gedacht had want het is boven veel andere dingen te prefereeren. Het is ook niet zoo <hi rend="italics">hard</hi> als conté<c type="kk">/</c> dat wil zeggen het krast zoo niet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het is niet omdat ik anders niet kan werken dat ik graag wou ge me nog wat sturen kondt maar het is omdat ik er buiten het gewone werk om nog veel dingen mee zou kunnen doen dan<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik er over geschreven heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Schreef ik U reeds over die twee groote etsen van Israels<c type="kk">/</c> een man die zijn pijp aansteekt<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en een interieur van een arbeiderswoning.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Wat zijn die mooi<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik vind het zoo almagtig mooi van Israels dat hij doorzet met etsen<c type="kk">/</c> te meer omdat om zoo te zeggen al de anderen het hebben laten loopen ondanks de animo waarmee in der tijd de etsclub begonnen werd.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Althans de meesten hebben geen <hi rend="italics">vorderingen</hi> gemaakt in het etsen en als ze er nu een doen is ’t niet beter of compleeter dan wat ze jaren geleden maakten. Doch vader Israels is ondanks zijn grijze haren nog jong genoeg om vorderingen te maken en enorme nog wel – en dat vind ik de echte jeugd en altijd groene energie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Sapperloot<c type="kk">/</c> als de anderen hetzelfde gedaan hadden<c type="kk">/</c> wat zouden er mooie Hollandsche etsen in de wereld gekomen zijn. Ik heb 2 kleine etsjes van Israels<c type="kk">/</c> misschien wel zijn allereersten<c type="kk">/</c> een meisje met een schop in een tuintje en eene vrouw met een mand op den rug<c type="kk">/</c> kent gij die<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Is geloof ik uitgaaf der aquafortistes Belges.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Met dat èène stukje krijt heb ik dus reeds 2 schetsen gemaakt en heb nog over<c type="kk">/</c> en nog kleine croquis ook. Voortaan zal ik misschien voor ’t gewone werk weinig anders gebruiken. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I hadn’t intended to write again so soon, but I’m trying to make drawings of various kinds, as you know. And now today I did another sketch<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> with the rest of that piece of natural chalk, and then I gave it a sepia wash. I believe the natural chalk has various characteristics that make it an outstanding means of depicting some things from nature. This morning I went for a walk outside the city in the meadows beyond Zuid Buitensingel, where <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Maris</rs> first lived and where the rubbish dump is.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> For a long time I stood looking there, in front of a row of the most gnarled, twisted and disoriented pollard willows I’ve ever seen. They lined the edge of a vegetable garden — freshly dug — and were reflected in a small, dirty ditch — very dirty — but where blades of spring foliage were already glittering. But that brown, rough bark — the turned-over earth — in which one could see the fertility, so to speak — all that had something peculiarly warm in the dark, strong tones that again made me think of natural chalk. So that when I have some again I hope to tackle landscape with it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Although the accompanying sketch is very unfinished, it seemed to me that there could be things in it that corresponded with your intention — and again it’s a sketch from life.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Don’t think that I count it a quality if there isn’t enough fullness of detail. Far from it. But the fullness of detail that both you and I would like to see doesn’t consist in details added later, I believe, but should be more present at once than it is now. Because the freshness mustn’t be lost and, provided the impression is correct, there’s sometimes expression in what is relatively unfinished. However, I’ll naturally work at getting more variation in the tones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m relatively indifferent to putting in details, but removing more of the rough edges is definitely my aim. That’s to say, keeping closer to the form.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Although there isn’t enough of that in it yet, there’s still so much difference in the general effect through that little bit of sepia that I thought that, in combination with the one from yesterday, you’d be able to see how that natural chalk can be used in several ways. I wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> about natural chalk yesterday, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> because I had to write to him anyway about things to do with lithography. And since I wanted to send him some croquis done with it, I used it to draw our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">infant</rs> in various poses.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Well, I discovered that it’s also very suitable for croquis. One can also get half-tones in it by using breadcrumbs. Only the very deepest shadows are perhaps less easy to get, but then, certainly in many cases, one can use lithographic crayon — which is also warm.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I believe that you can already see from the figures that the studio is better now as regards the light. Isn’t everything outside beautiful at the moment, don’t you agree? I have many plans — you will understand that. You know that I’m busy with lots of different things. But I’d also like so much to learn different methods, because that’s a stimulus to work hard, and one gets more ideas as a result.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I wish I’d thought of this natural chalk before, because it’s preferable to many other things. It’s also not as <hi rend="italics">hard</hi> as conté, that’s to say that it doesn’t scratch as much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">It’s not that I would like you to send me some more because I wouldn’t be able to work otherwise; but I’ve written about it because I’d then be able to do many things with it in addition to the normal work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Have I already written to you about those two large etchings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, a man lighting his pipe<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and an interior of a labourer’s dwelling?<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> How beautiful they are. I think it mightily good of Israëls that he carries on etching, the more so since all the others, so to speak, have given it up, despite the enthusiasm with which the etching club was started at the time.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> At any rate, most haven’t made any <hi rend="italics">progress</hi> in etching, and when they make one now it’s no better or more complete than what they made years ago. Yet old Israëls is still young enough to make progress despite his grey hairs, and huge progress at that — and I think that is true youth and evergreen energy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">By Jove, if the others had done the same, what beautiful Dutch etchings would have come into the world. I have 2 small etchings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>, perhaps even his very first, a girl with a spade in a small garden and a woman with a basket on her back. Do you know them? I believe they were published by the Belgian etchers’ society.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">So with that <hi rend="italics">one</hi> piece of chalk I’ve already done 2 sketches and still have some left, and small croquis as well. In future I may use little else for ordinary work. Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written one day after the letter to Van Rappard <ref target="let325.xml">(325)</ref>, which dates from on or about 5 March; Van Gogh writes ‘I wrote to Rappard ... yesterday’ <ref target="#l-46">(l. 46)</ref>. The present letter thus dates from on or about Tuesday, 6 March 1883. When Vincent tells Theo he sent a drawing ‘yesterday’ <ref target="#l-44">(l. 44)</ref>, he must mean that he posted the letter with the drawing that he had written on Sunday, 4 March (<ref target="let324.xml">letter 324</ref>) on Monday, 5 March.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is working with natural chalk <ref target="let322.xml">(322)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Alterations to the studio windows <ref target="let317.xml">(317)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>The previous one was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Soup distribution in a public soup kitchen </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2427">F 1020 a/ JH 330</rs>), which was sent to Theo; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-3">n. 3</ref> below for the sketch.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jacob Maris</rs> lived from 1871 to 1878 on N.W. Binnensingel (now called ‘Bij de Westermolens’), and not, as Van Gogh says, on Zuid Buitensingel (now Houtzagerssingel). See exhib. cat. Laren 1991, p. 20 and exhib. cat. Mannheim 1987, p. 23.</p>

<p rend="indent">The ‘asvaalt’ – this rubbish dump is shown as ‘Aschlaat’ on an 1882 map – was in the neighbourhood of the gasworks, so just behind N.W. Binnensingel. Cf. exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 41, 177.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘weerspiegelden zich’ (were reflected).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      From <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let327.xml">letter 327</ref> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-210">ll. 210-215</ref>) it is clear that Theo commented on the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing, with a girl</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2434">F 1072 / JH 341</rs>), which is in natural chalk and ink. Although the descriptions ‘sketch’ and ‘very unfinished’ do not fit this large, fully worked-up sheet, this must be the one referred to. Vincent either sent the drawing seperately or enclosed the letter with the drawing.</p>
      
<p rend="indent"> It was previously thought to be <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Soup distribution in a public soup kitchen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_82">F 1020 / JH 333</rs>), but that is now placed with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let323.xml">letter 323</ref>. Van Heugten assumed that Van Gogh enclosed an – unknown – impression of a landscape with this letter, but the description ‘sketch from life’ does not seem to fit that. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 214 (n. 4).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>These three French phrases may be quotations; they are not found in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_922">Cassagne</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Traité d’aquarelle</hi> (1875).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Baby crawling (‘Adventurer sallying forth’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_88">F 872 / JH 334</rs>) was once in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s possession, so it could have been one of the works enclosed. The other drawings of the baby <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">Willem</rs> in natural chalk have not been identified. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man die zijn pijp aansteekt </hi>(<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De roker</hi>) (Man lighting his pipe (The smoker)), etching (1882), 40.4 x 27.7 cm (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_196">Ill. 196</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The likeliest candidate for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>’s ‘Interior of a labourer’s dwelling’ is the etching <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Binnenhuis</hi> or<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De moeder</hi>’ (Interior, or ‘The mother’), although at 15.9 x 23.9 cm it cannot be described as large (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_190">Ill. 190</rs>. See Hubert 1909, p. 37, no. 21.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1326">Félicien Rops</rs> co-founded the ‘Société Internationale des Aquafortistes’ in 1862. To promote interest in etching, in 1875 this Société published two albums with etchings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>, Auguste Danse and the Countess of Flanders, the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cahier d’études: eaux-fortes </hi>and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Album d’eaux-fortes</hi>. Brussels 1875. Cf. Stephen Goddard, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les Vingt en de avant-garde in België. Prenten, tekeningen en boeken c. 1890</hi>. Ghent 1992, pp. 53-54.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Meisje leunende op een schop</hi> (Girl leaning on a spade) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vrouw met een mand op de rug</hi> (Woman with a basket on her back), also known as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Huiswaarts</hi> (On the way home). Both etchings, 9.2 x 5.7 cm and 13.5 x 9.5 cm respectively, were published in March on one sheet in<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Album d’eaux-fortes</hi>. Brussels 1875, by the above Société (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_198">Ill. 198</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_205">Ill. 205</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    