<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 21 March 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let331"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b298 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>331</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>275</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>332</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-03-21">on or about Wednesday, 21 March 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0298 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0298 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000372_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0298 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0298 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000373_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Regt hartelijk dank voor Uw brief en het ingeslotene<c type="kp">_</c>– Het verheugde mij daarin meer uitvoerig eens weder iets omtrent Uw zieke te vernemen<c type="kk">/</c> te meer daar ’t mij voorkwam deze berigten zeer gunstig te noemen zijn. Dat wat men noemt tumeur blanche<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> is het niet iets dat bij anemie op zich zelf reeds wel eens voorkomt als zekere kwaadaardige bestanddeelen in het bloed zijn. Ik weet dit niet precies doch op zich zelf meen ik het bewuste abces iets niet ongewoons en bij goede behandeling volstrekt niet gevaarlijks is<c type="kp">_</c>– En overigens schrijft ge verscheiden goede dingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Erg aardig wat ge schrijft van haar invloed op anderen. Zulke dingen geloof ik – den invloed door een goed mensch te weeg gebragt strekt somtijds ver<c type="kp">_</c> Is wel aardig bij het zuurdeeg vergeleken<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Twee</hi> goede menschen – man en vrouw vereenigd – ’t zelfde willende &amp; bedoelende<c type="kk">/</c> met denzelfden ernst doortrokken<c type="kk">/</c> wat die niet zouden vermogen!– Daar heb ik dikwijls over gedacht<c type="kp">_</c>– Want door vereeniging wordt de kracht ten goede niet alleen verdubbeld maar veel malen verdubbeld – als door magtsverheffing om ’t zoo maar eens in rekenkundige woorden te zeggen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu – dan Uw beschrijving van ’t huis en van de omgeving van het huis – de cab stand is zeer goed<c type="kp">_</c>– Onderscheidt zich van andere stadsgezigten van U door – typiger stoffage – de cabstand is uitmuntend – kunt ge mij het personaadje met den rooden neus niet eens te poseeren bezorgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dat gij vriend Wisselingh hebt gesproken doet mij pleizier – dus is die weer terug gekomen in Parijs – <hi rend="italics">nog steeds in de zaak van Cottier</hi>?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Zoudt ge bij gelegenheid hem eens voor mij willen groeten – als hij eens naar Holland komt zou een bezoek van hem – dat hij me trouwens reeds toegezegd heeft eigentlijk – mij bijzonder genoegen doen. Ik wou wel ge hem animeeren kondt dit niet te vergeten<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou hem verscheiden dingen te vragen hebben nog over Londen. Heeft hij de lithographies nog gezien? Ik zou graag weer eens geheel op nieuw kennis met hem maken<c type="kk">/</c> ik vond altijd veel aantrekkelijks in hem en hij weet veel dingen en gevoelt juist in zaken van kunst<c type="kk">/</c> en oorspronkelijk<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin is iemand met een karakter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ommestaand krabbeltje is naar eene teekening die ik van morgen vroeg begon en den heelen dag op doorsjouwde.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Is misschien wel de beste die ik tot nog toe heb gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> althans van licht &amp; bruin<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik stuur U het krabbeltje (ofschoon ik onmogelijk op dit papier werken kan zoo<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> dat dezelfde krachten er in komen<c type="kk">/</c> het uit de proportie is – en de teek<c type="kp">_</c> meer voorgrond heeft) omdat ik denk gij er in zien zult wat ik door de verandering van ’t licht op ’t atelier win.– Dit figuur is geposeerd tegen ’t licht in en om het weer te geven komt iets anders nog kijken dan een contour<c type="kk">/</c> daar door licht uit een enkelen foyer de lumière het modelé karakter krijgt<c type="kk">/</c> en de krachten in harmonie met elkaar en in onderling rapport. En brengt deze opvatting mede primo wel de moeielijkheden van het weergeven van ’t geen men voor oogen heeft doch tevens nog iets anders waar men veel aan te blokken heeft<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk de kwestie eene figuur zóó te plaatsen en het licht zóó te doen vallen dat het karakter ’t best en meest volkomen uitkomt. ’t geen men buiten of binnen ziet moet men zoo geanalyseerd hebben ten opzigte van ’t licht dat men het terug kan vinden.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het doet me groot genoegen gij schrijft het bergkrijt te hebben. Het kwam echter heden niet per post ofschoon gij schreeft het afgezonden te hebben. Mogt gij ’t vergeten hebben zoo herinner ik er u nog eens aan en is het gij ’t reeds verzonden hebt zoo komt het zeker spoedig.– Ik heb weder een voorraad lithographisch krijt en wilde daarmede het bergkrijt combineeren<c type="kk">/</c> wat dunkt me gaan <hi rend="italics">moet</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Deze week teekende ik druk Kruiwagens<c type="kk">/</c> een kereltje op den rug gezien is nog al echt geworden, geloof ik.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> V.d. Weele was bij mij, wij hebben kunstbeschouwing van houtsneden gehouden<c type="kk">/</c> heel gezellig op een kruiwagen – want ik was juist met model bezig. Hij zou ze ook beginnen te verzamelen en demarches doen om uit de nalaten<c type="shy">-</c>schap van Stam den houtgraveur een aantal te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> door dezen bijeengebragt.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ik heb U nog niet geschreven dat ik zoo zoetjes aan haast de heele graphic compleet heb. van ’t begin 1870 af<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Natuurlijk niet alles<c type="kk">/</c> er is te veel ballast bij maar zoo de mooien er uit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Wanneer men die ziet<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. ’t werk van Herkomer er uit<c type="kk">/</c> gerangschikt bij elkaar in plaats van verspreid tusschen een massa onbeteekenende dingen<c type="kk">/</c> wordt het pleizieriger en gemakkelijker om te zien vooreerst doch tevens begint men dan meer de eigenaardigheden der diverse meesters te zien, en het groote verschil tusschen de teekenaars.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat zou ik toch graag eens iets van L’Hermitte zien.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik kan U niet genoeg zeggen hoe gelukkig ik mij voel door de verbetering van het atelier en hoezeer ik weer vervuld ben met allerlei figuren die ik maken moet.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">V.d. Weele zag de studies van koppen van dezen winter o.a. – ik weet zeker die mij nog tepas zullen komen – trouwens de andere studies ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Weet ge wat mij pleizier deed<c type="kp">_</c>– ge weet dezen winter was v.d. W. ook eens bij me<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – ’t is nu al maanden geleden – ik was toen doende aan studies van <hi rend="italics">Spitters</hi> – waarvan ik er nog een trachtte te lithographieeren<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Hij zag die toen doch ze schenen hem niet aan te trekken – bepaald niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu heeft hij voor zijn onder handen zijnd Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi><ptr target="#note-t-10"/><hi rend="super"> </hi>dezer dagen blijkbaar of spitters laten poseeren of het afgekeken terwijl ze ergens aan ’t werk waren – enfin hij heeft juist in de natuur spitters met aandacht bekeken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Bij het doorzien van mijn studies sprak hij er heel anders over toen we aan die spitters kwamen dan dezen winter – althans vooral zei hij zoo grif niet “dit of dat is anders”.– Ik zelf sprak er ditmaal geheel niet over. Maar hoe langer hoe meer begin ik zoowel in mij zelf als in anderen te zien hoe men zich vergissen kan dikwijls als men denkt dit of dat “<hi rend="italics">is niet zoo</hi>” of “<hi rend="italics">doet niet goed</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> vooral onwillekeurig zegt men het dikwijls waar het niet toepasselijk is<c type="kk">/</c> ik zelf niet minder dan anderen. Men meent het dan zeker te weten en moet er toch van terug komen wil men billijk zijn.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Uw beschrijving van den rijtuig stand en het eerwaardig urinoir en de aanplak<c type="shy">-</c>biljetten daarop is werkelijk erg best – t’is eeuwig jammer ge het niet teekent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Van aanplakbiljetten gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> de plaats alwaar zij aangeplakt zijn is soms een zonderlinge parodie op de aanplaksels of omgekeerd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Zoo om iets uit velen te noemen – tegen het poortje van den lommerd of bank v. leening zag ik aangeplakt in groote letters</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20"><hi>Prospectus</hi></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21"><hi>Eigen Haard</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">NB<c type="kp">_</c> Eigen haard is een tijdschrift<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ge misschien weet. Ik vond die nog al goed<c type="kk">/</c> als men er meer op lette zou men er nog beteren vinden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Gavarni heeft er eens iets op gemaakt, n.l. dit. de ingang van een huis waar staat geannonceerd “On prend des enfants en sevrage.” Op den stoep staat eene vrouw van zeer ongunstig uiterlijk en een kerel met een brûle gueule in den mond<c type="kk">/</c> de lui van de inrigting blijkbaar<c type="kp">_</c> Tegen den muur is aangeplakt eene reclame. <hi rend="italics">Perdu</hi> un enfant – tel et tel<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Zoo ook <hi rend="italics">au rendez vous de la fraternité</hi> is het uithangbord van een estaminet waar eenige dronken kerels aan ’t bakkeleijen zijn.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Rappard wil een groot schilderij sturen naar de Amsterd. tentoonstelling. Het stelt voor 4 tegelschilders rond eene tafel.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Ik hoorde indirekt er goeds van<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-7" facs="#zone-pb-2r-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ofschoon het niet nu in mijn plan ligt groote Schilderijen voor exposities te maken zoo zou ik toch niet minder werken willen dan Rappard b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik vind er zelfs iets animeerends in dat de een in deze<c type="kk">/</c> de ander in die rigting werke en men dan toch sympatiseere<c type="kp">_</c> Concurrentie die voort komt uit naijver is iets heel anders dan dat men <hi rend="italics">juist uit</hi> <hi rend="italics">respect</hi> voor elkaar zijn best doe het werk zoo goed mogelijk te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Les extrêmes se touchent<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> – in naijver zie ik niet het minste heil doch ik zou eene vriendschap verachten die niet meebragt dat men zich inspannen moest om elkaar bij te blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Hetgeen waarnaar ik soms zeer begin te verlangen is het werken met meer modellen te gelijk. Om teekeningen te maken die wat gecompliceerder zijn. Doch het verlangen daarnaar is niet onstuimig – ik heb toch genoeg te doen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik zag bij van der Weele de <hi>studies</hi> voor zijn groot schilderij<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Die studies waren uitmuntend – conscientieus – maar wie eenigzins begrijpt hoe men studies naar de natuur maakt en het verschil tusschen deze en een Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> of definitieve compositie<c type="kk">/</c> verwacht niet het schilderij te vinden in de studies – natuurlijkerwijs<c type="kp">_</c> De grootheid en eenheid van het schij ziet men in de studies niet – dat is geen wonder<c type="kp">_</c>– omdat de studies gedaan zijn voor de figuren<c type="kk">/</c> paarden of menschen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is hetzelfde – is de entourage verwaarloosd – is er nl<c type="kp">_</c> geen voorgrond<c type="kk">/</c> achtergrond &amp;c. genoeg. Doen zij niet voor en <hi rend="italics">staan niet op hun plaats zóó als</hi> <hi rend="italics">zij op ’t sch</hi><hi rend="super">  <hi rend="italics">ij</hi></hi><hi rend="italics"> doen</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Weet iedereen dat te begrijpen bij het zien van studies. Blijf gij er aan denken bij het zien van de mijnen – vooral ook als ge vroeger of later zien zult wat ik nog hier heb. Deze week voor de aardigheid zette ik er een paar in andere proportie op zóó dat ik er een geheel van kon aansmeeren<c type="kp">_</c>– Door een eenvoudige aangeving van enkele lijnen en enkele vlakke toonen van sepia er in te wasschen<c type="kk">/</c> kwam wat ik nu maar eens zal noemen het schilderijachtige er van zelf in.– ’k wil maar zeggen – meen niet dat ik anders kijk dan b.v. v.d. Weele ten opzigte van ruimte zien in de natuur. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf weer spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> het beste<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">t. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Vincent </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-8" facs="#zone-pb-1r-8"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">In dit krabbeltje ziet ge iets van ’t geen ik aan ’t eind van dezen brief zeide – hier is nu in ’t geheel geen voorgrond – wat nu op de eigentlijke studie althans toch iets meer is – maar als ik deze studie met bijvoorbeeld een van de spitters, laat ons zeggen die welke ik lithographieerde<c type="kk">/</c> combineer – dan hoort hier bij een groot<c type="kk">/</c> vlak stuk grond van voren en bijvoorbeeld een houtkant<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> er achter waar men heel boven aan <hi rend="italics">iets</hi> van de lucht zou zien<c type="kk">/</c> alleen om aan te geven waar het licht van daan komt<c type="kp">_</c> Dan wordt het dus misschien eene compositie in de breedte en komt het figuur in zijn entourage en op zijn plaats<c type="kp">_</c> Maakte ik op de studie zelf dat alles dan zou ’t figuur zoo klein worden dat als serieuse studie voor ’t figuur ik er niets aan hebben zou. Geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> het <hi rend="italics">aspect</hi> is geen heksenwerk<c type="kk">/</c> als mijn studies goed zijn ben ik heel kalm op dat punt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">En Ruimte<c type="kk">/</c> Lucht<c type="kk">/</c> breedheid – meen niet dat ik die wegredeneer – maar men moet daar niet mee <hi rend="italics">beginnen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> eerst het fondament – dan volgt het dak op zijn tijd<c type="kp">_</c>– </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many sincere thanks for your letter and the enclosure. I was pleased to learn about your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> in more detail from it, the more so since it seemed to me that these reports may be called highly favourable. Isn’t what they call a white tumour<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> something that sometimes occurs of its own accord in anaemia when certain malignant elements are in the blood? I don’t know for sure, but I believe that in itself the abscess in question isn’t something unusual and, given the proper treatment, not in the least dangerous. And otherwise you write various good things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">What you write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">her</rs> influence on others is very nice. I believe in things like that — the influence exercised by a good person sometimes extends a long way. The comparison with leaven is well taken. <hi rend="italics">Two</hi> good people — man and woman united — wanting and intending the same, steeped in the same earnestness, what couldn’t they achieve! I’ve thought about that often. For by uniting, the force for good is not only doubled but doubled many times — as if raised to a higher power, to put it in mathematical terms.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Well – then your description of the house and its surroundings — the cab-stand is very good. Stands out from other townscapes by you because of the more distinctive staffage — the cab-stand is excellent. Couldn’t you arrange for the figure with the red nose to pose for me sometime?
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’m pleased that you’ve spoken to friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs> — so he’s come back to Paris — <hi rend="italics">still in Cottier’s firm</hi>?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Would you give him my regards when you have an opportunity? If he ever comes to Holland, a visit from him — which he has actually promised me by the way — would give me great pleasure. I’d like you to encourage him not to forget this, I still have various things to ask him about London. Has he seen the lithographs? I’d like to make his acquaintance all over again, I always found much in him that was attractive, and he knows a great deal and has a true and original feeling in matters of art. In short, is someone with character.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The little scratch overleaf is after a drawing I began early this morning and toiled away at all day.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> It’s perhaps the best I’ve done so far, at least as regards light and shade. I’m sending you the scratch (although I can’t possibly work on this paper so that the same strengths come into it, it’s out of proportion — and the drawing has more foreground) because I believe you’ll see in it what I gain by the change in the light in the studio. This figure is posed against the light and something more than an outline is required in order to depict it, since light from a single source gives character to the form and brings the strengths into harmony and rapport with each other. And in the first place this approach entails the difficulties of depicting what one has before one’s eyes, but in addition something else that requires a lot of hard work, namely the question of how to position a figure and to have the light fall such that the character comes out at its best and most perfect. One must have analyzed what one sees inside or outside as regards the light in such a way that one can re-create it.</p><pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’m very pleased that you write that you have the natural chalk. It didn’t come in the post today, however, although you write that you’ve sent it. Should you have forgotten it, let me remind you about it again, and if you’ve already sent it, no doubt it will come soon. I again have a stock of lithographic crayon, and wanted to combine the natural chalk with that, which I believe<hi rend="italics"> must</hi> be possible.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">This week I was busy drawing Wheelbarrows; one chap seen from behind has turned out fairly real, I think.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> came by, we held a viewing of woodcuts, very cosily on a wheelbarrow, for I’d just been working with a model. He’s also going to start collecting them, and is to take steps to get some from the estate of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_204">Stam</rs> the wood engraver that he collected.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I hadn’t written before that little by little I have almost the whole Graphic complete, from the beginning in 1870.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Not everything, of course, there’s too much lumber for that, but the beauties from it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">When one sees it, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>’s work from it for example, arranged together instead of dispersed amid a mass of insignificant things, in the first place it becomes more enjoyable and easier to view, but then one also begins to see the peculiarities of the various masters better, and the great difference between the draughtsmen. 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">How much I would like to see something by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I can’t tell you how happy I feel because of the improvements to the studio, and how preoccupied I am once more with all manner of figures that I must do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> saw the studies of heads from this winter among others — I’m certain they’ll be of use to me — as, indeed, will the other studies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Do you know what pleased me? You remember that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der W.</rs> also came by one time this winter<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — it’s months ago now — I was working on studies of <hi rend="italics">Diggers</hi> at the time — one of which I tried to lithograph.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> He saw them but they didn’t seem to interest him, far from it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now he has evidently had diggers pose recently for the painting<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> he’s working on, or observed them at work somewhere — anyway, he has taken a close look at diggers in nature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">When we came to those diggers while looking through my studies, the way he spoke about them was very different from what it was this winter — at least he didn’t say so readily ‘this or that is different’. This time I myself said nothing at all about them. But more and more I begin to see both in myself and others how mistaken one can often be when one thinks this or that ‘<hi rend="italics">isn’t so</hi>’ or ‘<hi rend="italics">doesn’t look right</hi>’; above all, one often says it instinctively when it isn’t applicable, I myself no less than others. One imagines one knows for certain, but has to retract if one wants to be fair.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Your description of the cab-stand and the venerable urinal and the bills stuck on it is really very good — it’s a great pity you don’t draw it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Speaking of bills, the place where they’re put up is sometimes a curious parody of the bill, or the other way round.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">To mention just one of many — at the entrance to the Lombard or pawnshop I saw a bill with the following words in big letters</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"><hi>Prospectus</hi></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"><hi>Eigen Haard.</hi> <ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">NB. As you probably know, Eigen Haard is a magazine. I thought this one rather good; if one kept an eye out for them one would find even better ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> once came up with one, namely this. The entrance of a house with the announcement ‘Children weaned here’. Standing on the doorstep are a woman with a most unprepossessing appearance and a fellow with a short pipe in his mouth, evidently the people from the institution. A bill is posted on the wall. <hi rend="italics">Lost</hi> a child — so and so.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Similarly, <hi rend="italics">At the meeting-place of the brotherhood</hi> is the sign of an estaminet where several drunken fellows are squabbling.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> wants to send a large painting to the Amsterdam exhibition. It shows 4 tile painters around a table.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I’ve heard good things about it indirectly.
<pb f="2r" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-7" facs="#zone-pb-2r-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Although it isn’t part of my plan at present to do large paintings for exhibitions, I wouldn’t like to work less than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, say.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I even find something encouraging in the fact that one person can work in this direction and another in that, and yet still feel a sympathy. Rivalry stemming from envy is completely different from trying to do one’s best to make the work as good as possible <hi rend="italics">precisely out of respect</hi> for each other. Extremes meet<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> — I don’t see the slightest value at all in envy, but I would despise a friendship that didn’t entail making an effort to keep up with one another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">What I’m beginning to long for very much at times is to work with several models at once. To do drawings that are slightly more complicated. But this desire isn’t pressing — after all, I have enough to do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">At <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>’s I saw the <hi>studies</hi> for his big painting.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Those studies were outstanding — conscientious — but anyone with some understanding of how studies from nature are made, and the difference between them and a painting or definitive composition, won’t expect to find the painting in the studies — obviously. One doesn’t see the greatness and unity of the painting in the studies — that’s not surprising. Because the studies are done for the figures, horses or people, it doesn’t matter, the setting is ignored, there’s not enough foreground, background, &amp;c. They don’t look right, and <hi rend="italics">they’re not standing in their place as in the painting</hi>. Does everyone understand that when looking at studies? Bear that in mind when you’re looking at mine — especially when sooner or later you see what I still have here. This week, for the fun of it, I set down one or two in a different proportion so that I could merge them into a whole. Through a simple indication of a few lines and washing in a few flat tones of sepia, what for once I’ll call the painting-like quality came into it naturally. I just mean to say — don’t think that I look differently from, say, Van der Weele as regards seeing space in nature. Adieu, write again soon, best wishes.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">
<pb f="1r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-8" facs="#zone-pb-1r-8"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">In this scratch you see something of what I said at the end of this letter — here there’s now no foreground at all — at any rate in the actual study there’s a little more — but if I combine this study with, for instance, one of the diggers, say the one I lithographed — then belonging with this is a large, flat piece of land in front and, for example, a brushwood fence behind, and right at the top <hi rend="italics">something</hi> of the sky would be visible, just to indicate where the light comes from. Then perhaps it would become a composition breadthways, and the figure would be in its setting and in its place. If I did all that in the study itself, the figure would be so small that it would be of no use to me as a serious study for the figure. Believe me, the <hi rend="italics">appearance</hi> isn’t a tough job, if my studies are good I’m very calm about that point.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">And Space, Sky, breadth — don’t think that I rationalize them away — but one shouldn’t <hi rend="italics">begin</hi> with them, first the foundation — then the roof will follow in its own time.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the remittance <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, which must have been the <hi rend="italics">third</hi> of the month. He also writes about what he has been doing ‘this week’ <ref target="#l-86">(ll. 86-87)</ref>, which indicates that several days of the week have already passed. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Wednesday, 21 March 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Alterations to the studio windows <ref target="let317.xml">(317)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is working with natural chalk <ref target="let322.xml">(322)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s purchase of 21 volumes of <hi rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> <ref target="let302.xml">(302)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Arthritis, specifically in the knee. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo had probably said in his letter that he was considering marrying <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs>; in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let336.xml">letters 336</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let339.xml">339</ref> Van Gogh makes similar allusions.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Elbert Jan van Wisselingh</rs> worked with the art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_331">Daniel Cottier</rs> in London in 1874-1882. He left in the winter of 1882 and until the autumn of 1884 he was an independent dealer in Paris at 52 rue Laffitte. He lived at 52 rue Lepic. See Heijbroek and Wouthuysen 1999, pp. 29-30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
      
<p>This scratch is the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman digging</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_93">F - / JH 337</rs>); the drawing in question is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘zodanig’ (so that).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
      
<p>A drawing with a similar subject is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Scheveningen woman with a wheelbarrow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_633">F 1021 / JH 362</rs>); Meedendorp dates this to March 1883. See cat. Otterlo 2007, pp. 194-195.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
      
<p>Most probably the draughtsman, wood engraver and lithographer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_204">Willem Hendrik Stam</rs>, who had lived in The Hague. Between 1853 and 1872 his work was seen at exhibitions in The Hague in the form of woodcuts, wood engravings and drawings, as is evident from the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Kunstkronijk</hi>. No information about an auction of his estate has been found, but there is a detailed survey of his graphic work in a scrapbook with numerous prints after the work of various artists (Amsterdam, Library Rijksmuseum).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s interest in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> as a Black and White artist was prompted by what he had read about him in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let307.xml">see letters 307</ref>-<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let310.xml">310</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For this visit by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> in November 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let285.xml">see letter 285</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412">F 1656 / JH 262</rs>). The drawing for this is not known; two other studies are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2410">F 906 / JH 260</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2411">F 907 / JH 261</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> was working on the painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_499">A misty morning</rs></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let327.xml#n-1">see letter 327, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            
      
<p>This entrance gate at the back of the pawnshop was in Korte Lombardstraat. A year earlier Van Gogh had done the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The entrance to the Pawn Bank, The Hague </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3022">F - / JH 126</rs>) there; it shows how the walls on either side of the gate were covered with posters. One of them also bears the words: ‘Prospectus EIGEN HAARD geïllustreerd tijdschrift’ (Prospectus of the Eigen Haard illustrated periodical). See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 105-109, cat. no. 24.</p>

<p rend="indent">The poster would have been an announcement of the prospectus for this illustrated family magazine ‘Hearth and Home’, which also offered ‘art plates’. On this magazine: Hemels and Vegt 1993, pp. 146-150. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s description is not entirely accurate. This is one of the prints in the series ‘Bohèmes’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La mascarade humaine</hi> with the text ‘LOST / A LITTLE GIRL’; below it the words ‘Sevigne and his wife take children to be weaned’ (IL A ETE PERDU / UNE PETITE FILLE / Sevigne et son épouse prennent les enfants en sevrage) (Gavarni 1881, p. 129). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2087">Ill. 2087</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The print in question is found in the series ‘Les propos de Thomas Vireloque’, included in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_237">La mascarade humaine</ref></hi>. The sign reads ‘AT THE MEETING POINT / OF BROTHERR HOOD’; below the print the words ‘Brothers, perhaps! But, for cousins, not cousins!’ (AU RANDÉ VOU / DE LA / FRATAIRNITÉ / ‘Frères, possible! mais, pour cousins, pas cousins!’) (Gavarni 1881, p. 97). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2088">Ill. 2088</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Edmond and Jules de Goncourt</rs> discussed this work in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_224">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</ref></hi> (Goncourt 1873, pp. 355-356).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>At the International Exhibition, which opened in Amsterdam on 1 May 1883, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs> was represented by <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peintres en brique</hi> (no. 190): <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Tile painters</hi> (Middelburg, Zeeuws Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_332">Ill. 332</rs>. The painting both matches Van Gogh’s description and accords with his remark that it is ‘large’, since it measures 65.5 x 120.5 cm. But Van Rappard’s dating of the work, 1884, is a problem. It could mean that Van Rappard painted a second version of it (one in 1883 and one in 1884), or that he later made changes to the 1883 work and altered the date. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 82, cat. no. 93. The fact that Van Gogh knows of this painting leads to the conclusion that he must already have received Van Rappard’s letter, for which he thanks him in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let332.xml">letter 332</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>An expression, also quoted in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml">letter 333</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>These studies for the painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_499">A misty morning</rs></hi> are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘strook van kreupelhout die een veld begrenst’ (strip of undergrowth bordering a field).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    