<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Monday, 2 April 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let334"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b301 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>334</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>278</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>336</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-04-02">on or about Monday, 2 April 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000378_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Erg blij was ik met Uw brief &amp; regt hartelijk dank ik U voor het ingeslotene. Het spijt me alleen ge er waarschijnlijk zelf meer in ongelegenheid zijt geweest om ’t me toch te zenden dan ge wel schrijft. Ik hoop van harte ge sedert het bewuste hebt terugontvangen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dus is Hendrik ook weer uit Indie terug – was hij gezond en de zijnen? of is ongesteldheid oorzaak van hun retour.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> In der tijd maakte Hendrik op mij een veel minder gunstigen indruk dan zijn twee broers<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is dat uw indruk ook?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dezer dagen heb ik gewerkt met drukinkt – die wordt met terpentijn aangelengd &amp; met ’t penseel er op gezet. Geeft zeer diepe toonen van zwart. Gemengd met wat chineesch wit geeft het ook goede grijzen. Door bijvoeging van meer of minder terpentijn kan er zeer dun zelfs mee gewasschen worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Moet dunkt mij uitmuntend geschikt zijn om er mee te werken op dat papier dat Buhot U gaf.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als gij eens hier komt spreken we bepaald nog eens over die kwestie en zal ik U teekeningen wijzen die er op zouden kunnen worden gedaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Een jaar geleden was ’t me een raadsel hoe sommige zeer diepe toonen van zwart te verkrijgen waren, maar juist op de drukkerij heb ik er eenige gevonden. En juist daardoor kan ik wat verder doordringen in het zoeken naar modeleeren &amp; clair obscur.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dank voor Uw goede wenschen op mijn verjaardag,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ik had toevalligerwijs een erg prettigen dag daar ik net een voortreffelijk model had voor een spitter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dit kan ik U verzekeren<c type="kk">/</c> het werk gaat hoe langer hoe prettiger &amp; ik voel er om zoo te zeggen meer levenswarmte door &amp; ik denk daarbij steeds aan U<c type="kk">/</c> als zijnde het door U dat ik werken kan zonder fatale obstacles<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. zonder direkte handenbinders<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">De moeielijkheden prikkelen soms juist<c type="kp">_</c> Nu moet nog de tijd komen dat we er nog meer energie kunnen achterzetten. Mijn ideaal is te werken met hoe langer hoe meer modellen. een heele kudde arme luidjes voor wie ’t atelier een soort harbour of refuge<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> zou kunnen wezen in dagen van kou of als ze zonder werk zitten of behoefte hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Waar ze weten dat vuur<c type="kk">/</c> eten<c type="kk">/</c> drinken en een paar kwartjes voor hen te verdienen zijn. Dat is nu nog maar op heel kleine schaal<c type="kk">/</c> dat zal hoop ik zich uitbreiden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Voorloopig bepaal ik me juist tot eenige weinigen<c type="kk">/</c> zonder daar van af te gaan – ik kan er geen een van missen maar wel er nog bij 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>gebruiken. Gij schrijft over sommige liefhebbers die mogelijk te eeniger tijd mijn werk tel quel zullen nemen<c type="kk">/</c> zij ’t ook het niet bepaald een handelsartikel werd. Wel<c type="kk">/</c> dat geloof ik werkelijk ook. Als ’t mij lukken mag wat warmte en liefde in ’t werk te leggen dan zal het zijn vrienden vinden. Doorwerken is de kwestie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het verheugt me dat Uw zieke vooruitgaat<c type="kk">/</c> zij ’t ook langzaam. Hier is ’t heerlijk lenteweer geworden. de avonden zijn onbeschrijfelijk mooi. Als ’t bij U te lande zoo is<c type="kk">/</c> zal haar goed doen. Komt zij al op?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb den weesman<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> weer van daag &amp; moet mijn boeltje gaan klaarmaken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik sprak deze week v.d. Weele weer en verwacht hem dezer dagen weer eens bij mij ook.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Gij zult het druk hebben met den Salon ook waarschijnlijk.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Wanneer ge naar Holland zoudt komen kunt ge zeker nog onmogelijk ten naasten bij bepalen niet waar<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Heb het goed en als ge een oogenblikje heb schrijf weer eens<c type="kp">_</c> adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I was very glad to get your letter and I thank you sincerely for the enclosure. I’m only sorry that sending it to me probably got you into greater difficulties than you say in your letter. I do hope that you have since been repaid the sum in question.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">So <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">Hendrik</rs> is back from the East Indies — were he and his family well? Or was illness the reason for their return?<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> In the past Hendrik made a much less favourable impression on me than his two <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_406 bio.xml#_409">brothers</rs><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — is that your impression too? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve been working with printer’s ink lately — it’s thinned with turpentine and applied with a brush. Gives very deep tones of black. Mixed with some Chinese white, it also gives good greys. By adding more or less turpentine one can even wash very thinly with it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Ought to be extremely suitable, it seems to me, for use on that paper that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs> gave you.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">We must definitely discuss this question when you come here, and I’ll show you drawings that could be done on it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">A year ago it was a mystery to me how some very deep tones of black could be obtained, but it was at the printer’s that I found a few of them. And thanks to that I can go a little deeper in searching for modelling and chiaroscuro.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Thank you for your good wishes on my birthday.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> As it happened, I had a very pleasant day, because just then I had an excellent model for a digger. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I can assure you of this: the work is going better and better with time, and I feel more warmth of life, so to speak, as a result, and I think of you constantly during it, since it’s through you that I’m able to work without fatal obstacles, namely without direct restrictions. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">The difficulties are actually a stimulus sometimes. Now the time must come when we can put even more energy into it. My ideal is to work with ever more models, a whole flock of poor folk for whom the studio could be a kind of harbour of refuge<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> on cold days, or when they’re out of work or in need. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Where they know that there are fire, food, drink and a few quarters to be earned. At present that’s only on a very small scale, I hope it will grow. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">For now I limit myself to just a few, and keep to them — I can’t spare a single one and could use some 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> more. You write about some art lovers who might take my work such as it is sometime, without its becoming a commodity exactly. Well, I really believe that too. If I succeed in putting some warmth and love into the work, then it will find friends. Carrying on working is the thing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’m glad your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> is making progress, if only slowly. Here it’s delightful spring weather. The evenings are indescribably beautiful. It will do her good if it’s similar in your part of the world. Is she up already? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I have the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">orphan man</rs><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> again today, and must start getting my bits and pieces ready. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I spoke to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> again this week, and I expect to see him here again in the next few days.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">You’ll probably be busy with the Salon too.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I don’t suppose you can say roughly when you’ll be coming to Holland, can you? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I wish you well — write again when you have a moment. Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In his letter accompanying the remittance, Theo had sent Vincent good wishes on his birthday, which was on 30 March (<ref target="#l-32">see ll. 32-33</ref>). So this was the first remittance of April. Accordingly, we have dated the letter on or about Monday, 2 April 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This financial matter must have to do with a loan from Theo to his cousin <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">Hendrik Jacob Eerligh van Gogh</rs> (a son of Uncle Jan); this explains Vincent’s ‘much less favourable impression’ of this cousin in the following lines. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let336.xml">letters 336</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let342.xml">342</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">Hendrik van Gogh</rs> and his young bride <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_233">Maria Elisabeth Vos</rs> had left for the Dutch East Indies in September 1877; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let131.xml">letter 131</ref>. It is not known whether illness played a role in their return, but it is certain that about 18 months later Hendrik was suffering severe fits and was admitted to hospital (FR b2258 and FR b2261).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Hendrik’s brothers were <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_406">Vincent</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_409">Johannes van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo had sent Vincent a sample of paper for lithographing that had been given to him by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Félix Buhot</rs>. See e.g. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let290.xml">letters 290</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let295.xml">295</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was 30 on 30 March. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘beperkingen’ (restrictions).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
    
<p>Probably an allusion to the print <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1414">The harbour of refuge</rs></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1428">Frederick Walker</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let303.xml#n-12">see letters 303, n. 12</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let304.xml#n-16">304, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland</rs>, who often modelled for Van Gogh.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The Paris Salon opened on 1 May 1883. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    