<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 11 April 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let336"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b302 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>336</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>279</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>338</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-04-11">on or about Wednesday, 11 April 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0302" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0302" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000379_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw brief en ingesloten frs 50 die als altijd zeer welkom waren<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel eerstgenoemde als laatstgenoemden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat ge omtrent Uw zieke schrijft vernam ik met belangstelling. Ik begrijp ge tweestrijd hebt over de kwestie nu of later zekere vraag<c type="kk">/</c> die ik hier niet nader defineeren zal<c type="kk">/</c> te doen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">En de verandering van omstandigheden die haar herstel mede brengt heeft eene meer of minder kritieke zijde doordat, hetgeen waarop ge trouwens verdacht zijt (&amp; zelf zegt), er gemoederen in opstand zouden kunnen komen – mogelijk althans – laat ons hopen van niet.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wat is dat laatste toch eigentlijk erg vreemd. In zich zelf ziet men ’t geen men doet als iets eenvoudigs &amp; natuurlijks – iets van zelf sprekends – men is er min of meer over verwonderd waarom anderen de motieven welke iemand tot zoo iets dringen ook niet in zichzelven terugvinden. En zou haast tot de conclusie komen sommmige personen zekere gevoelszenuwen in zich gecauteriseerd<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> hebben.– met name die welke men gecombineerd het geweten noemt. Enfin – ik beklaag dezulken, zij reizen door ’t leven zonder kompas m.i.–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Menschenliefde is iets wat men in elk mensch zou meenen te mogen veronderstellen als zijnde de basis van zoo ongeveer alles. Maar sommigen meenen er betere fondamenten zijn. Ik ben er weinig nieuwsgierig naar. Dit oude fondament<c type="kk">/</c> beproefd &amp; goed gebleken zijnde zooveel eeuwen lang<c type="kk">/</c> is me genoeg. Vind gij dit niet aardig gezegd – ’t komt voor in les miserables:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Si César m’avait donné</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">La gloire &amp; la guerre,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Et qu’il me fallût quitter</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">L’amour de ma mère</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Je dirais au grand César</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Reprends ton sceptre &amp; ton char</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">J’aime mieux ma mère, o hé,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">J’aime mieux ma mère<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">In ’t verband waarin dit (een studentenliedje uit den tijd van de revolutie van 30) voorkomt<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> staat l’amour de ma mère voor l’amour de la république<c type="kk">/</c> of liever “l’amour de l’humanité”; anders gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> doodeenvoudig fraternité universelle.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Eene vrouw, hoe goed &amp; nobel zij ook van nature zij, indien zij zonder middelen is en door haar eigen familie niet beschermd wordt, staat m.i. in de tegenwoordige maatschappij in groot en onmiddelijk gevaar te verzinken in den maalstroom </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">der prostitutie. Wat spreekt meer van zelf dan dat men de zoodanige steune.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">En indien ’t niet anders te vinden is als ’t geval er toe leidt<c type="kk">/</c> welnu dan – il faut y mettre sa peau<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – en trouwen haar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Althans men moet dunkt mij zich tot principe stellen deze bescherming indien men ze begint<c type="kk">/</c> door te zetten tot definitieve redding en te dekken met eigen borst zoo noodig. Zelfs zonder bepaalde liefde? Misschien ja – alsdan is ’t een mariage de raison<c type="kk">/</c> que soit – doch niet in den zin van een huwelijk dat men uit eigenbaat aangaat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">En nu<c type="kk">/</c> Uw speciaal geval onderscheidt zich van meer alledaagsche – zooals ’t mijne b.v. – door de eigenaardigheid de persoon in kwestie een bijzonder charme heeft en er eene sympathie in gevoelens is naar ik meen<c type="kk">/</c> die maken dat ook al hadde de ontmoeting onder gansch andere en minder dramatische omstandigheden plaats gehad er kwestie konde zijn van tweestrijd over die vraag in kwestie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">In ’t bovenstaande vind ge mijn gedachte omtrent de kwestie: “hoe ver mag men gaan in het zich bemoeien met eene ongelukkige vrouw?” antwoord – “tot in ’t oneindige”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Evenwel op den voorgrond stellende dat trouw blijven de eerste en voornaamste is van alle liefde<c type="kk">/</c> zoo herinner ik U aan Uw eigen gezegde dat “het trouwen” (nl. het civiele) “zoo’n raar ding is”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Dit gezegde van U drukt precies uit hoe het is en op dat punt verklaar ik niet te weten wat beter of slechter is<c type="kk">/</c> er aan te tornen of niet. ’t is wat men noemt “<hi rend="italics">puzzling</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23"><hi rend="italics">it puzzles me too</hi> – en ik voor mij zou zoo zeer wenschen dat men daar niets mee te maken had. Ik vind het wel goed gezegd dat “als men trouwt men niet alleen de vrouw zelf trouwt doch de familie 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>bovendien”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> hetgeen soms iets min of meer fataals en beroerds is als het nare lui zijn.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Doch nu over de teekeningen – ’k heb er weer met drukinkt gemaakt en was deze week zoekende om de drukinkt te mengen met wit en vond ze<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> op twee wijzen te mengen is daarmee al vast – nl. met het wit uit de tubes olieverf – en waarschijnlijk nog beter met het gewone zinkwit in poeder dat men bij elken drogist zelfs krijgen kan – alsdan ’t aanlengende met terpentijn die op dit papier niet doortrekt en vlekken geeft<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> op den achterkant als olie – door dat ze zoo snel op droogt &amp; weg trekt.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">De drukinkt werkt veel pittiger dan O.I<c type="kp">_</c> inkt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Wat is ’t werk van Jules Dupré toch mooi<c type="kk">/</c> bij G&amp;C. voor ’t raam zag ik een kleine marine die ge zeker wel kent en die ik haast dagelijks s’avonds ben gaan kijken<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – maar ten opzigte van Dupré en dergelijke kunst – die te Parijs men zooveel meer te zien krijgt dan hier – zijt ge misschien wat verwend – en weet niet hoe almagtig mooi het hier doet waar men er zoo bitter weinig van ziet.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ben aan<ptr target="#note-t-d"/> ’t lezen van ’t laatste gedeelte van les misérables – ’t figuur van Fantine – eene prostituee – maakte diepe impressie op mij<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> – o ik weet net zoo goed als een ander dat men in de werkelijkheid niet precies eene Fantine vinden zal – doch evenwel dit figuur van Hugo – zooals trouwens al zijn figuren – is <hi rend="italics">waar</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zijnde eene essence van ’t geen men in werkelijkheid ziet. ’t is de <hi rend="italics">type</hi> – waarvan men slechts individus ontmoet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Mogt het zijn ge dezer dagen eens een graveur tegenkwaamt<c type="kk">/</c> n.l<c type="kp">_</c> een als b.v. Girardet of Eichens die aquatinten maken,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> zoudt ge me veel genoegen doen zoo ter loops eens te vragen: Waarmee maakt men gewoonlijk de <hi rend="italics">teekeningen</hi> die tot leiddraad moeten dienen voor de gravure<c type="kp">_</c>– Misschien zeggen ze dan: met drukinkt<c type="kp">_</c>– indien ze deze gebruiken – waarmede lengen zij die drukinkt aan – hoe gebruiken ze die?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">’t Komt mij voor dat als ge er den een of anderen graveur zoo ter loops eens over spraakt en mij verteldet wat hij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ik alligt in ’t geen hij zegt iets vinden zou 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>dat in sommige kwesties me licht zou geven<c type="kk">/</c> ook al was ’t geen direkt antwoord op waar de drukinkt mede gemengd wordt zóó dat men er <hi rend="italics">op papier</hi> op verschillende wijzen mee werken kan. Zeker is er ook nog andere drukinkt dan die welke ik nu op ’t oogenblik heb en lost het zich nog nader van zelf voor mij op.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Er komen in de teekeningen effekten door <hi rend="italics">dergelijk</hi> <hi rend="italics">als in aquatint gravures</hi> als men werkt met drukinkt en terpentijn zooals ik nu probeerde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ik heb in der tijd teekeningen gezien b.v. van Mottramb<c type="kk">/</c> de Engelsche graveur die de Boughtons gegraveerd heeft<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> en ik wou ik wist waar die mede werkte b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">’t Spreekt van zelf ik met deze informatie geen haast heb<c type="kk">/</c> alleen als ge zoo eens iets hoort van diverse procedes van teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> deel het mij vooral mede.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">De vrouw van Soek en haar moeder<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> (indien die nog met haar woont) ken ik ook – kwam er in der tijd – ik heb hen nog zeer duidelijk in mijn herinnering – en vind het twee sympathieke personen – die me denken doen aan mijn eigen huisgenooten – zoozeer zelfs dat onwillekeurig ik dikwijls aan hen als aan personen van dezelfde familie denk. ’t zijn net figuren uit Souvestre b.v. of van Ed. Frère. Men ziet er zoo meer te Parijs – trouwens overal<c type="kp">_</c> Zulke personen doen me altijd aan de vrouwenfiguren uit ’t Evangelie denken<c type="kk">/</c> misschien omdat ze soms in expressies iets hebben van b.v. de figuren in Delaroche<c type="kk">/</c> Vendredi Saint<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> of in Landelle<c type="kk">/</c> Bienheureux ceux qui pleurent.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Ik weet wel<c type="kk">/</c> deze zienswijs is niet compleet<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn andere aspecten – nog beter dan Delaroche – en dieper dan hij – b.v. die van <hi rend="italics">L’Hermitte</hi> en Herkomer<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dat vind ik er dus ook in maar ik kan mij toch begrijpen dat in de dagen van Souvestre<c type="kk">/</c> Delaroche<c type="kk">/</c> Frère<c type="kk">/</c> Landelle &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> deze rigting populair werd<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ze bij Millet en anderen vergeleken niet geheel juist en waar zij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Leeft ANKER nog<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> ik denk dikwijls aan zijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> ik vind dat zoo degelijk en zoo fijn gevoeld. Hij is nog een oude echte van de soort van Brion. Kerel wat kan ik soms verlangen ge weer eens op ’t atelier zijn zult<c type="kp">_</c>– Van harte hoop ik gij het geld van H.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> zult terugkrijgen. Bij mij moest er ditmaal veel direkt af en ik heb bitter weinig over. Enfin schrijf zoo spoedig ge kunt als het tegen den 20<hi rend="super">sten</hi> gaat. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you for your letter and the 50 francs enclosed, which were very welcome as always, both the former and the latter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I read what you write about your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> with interest. I understand that you’re in two minds over the matter of posing a certain question — which I shan’t further define here — now or later.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">And the change of circumstances brought about by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">her</rs> recovery has a more or less critical side because, and this is  what you are actually prepared for (and say so yourself), opposition may be aroused — possibly anyway — let’s hope not.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">How odd that last point really is. One sees what one does as simple and natural in itself — something self-evident — one is more or less puzzled as to why others don’t find the motives in themselves that compel someone to do such a thing. And would almost draw the conclusion that some people have cauterized certain sensory nerves in themselves — in particular those collectively known as the conscience. Anyway, I pity such people: in my view they travel through life without a compass.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Love of one’s fellow man is something one would expect to be able to take for granted in everyone as the basis of just about everything. But some believe there are better foundations. I feel little curiosity about them. This old foundation that has been tested and found good for so many centuries is enough for me. Don’t you find this nicely put? — it’s from Les misérables:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">If Caesar had given me</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Glory and war,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And if I was forced to forgo</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">My mother’s love,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">To great Caesar would I say,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Take back your sceptre and your chariot,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I love my mother more, hey!,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I love my mother more.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">In the context in which this (a student song from the time of the revolution of ’30) occurs,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> love of my mother stands for love of the Republic, or rather ‘love of mankind’; in other words, quite simply, universal brotherhood.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">A woman, however good and noble she may be by nature, in my view stands in great and immediate danger in today’s society of sinking into the maelstrom of prostitution if she has no means and isn’t protected by her own family. What is more natural than that one should support such a person?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">And if there’s no other solution when circumstances lead to it, well, then — you must put your heart and soul into it<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and marry her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">At least it seems to me that one must make it a principle to continue with this protection once offered until rescue is complete, and to protect with one’s own breast if necessary. Even without a particular love? Perhaps, yes — in that case it’s a marriage of convenience, so be it — but not in the sense of a marriage that one enters into for gain.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">And now, your particular case differs from the more everyday — such as mine, for instance — because of the singular circumstance that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">person</rs> in question has a special charm and that there is, I believe, a sympathy of feeling, so that even if the meeting had taken place under entirely different and less dramatic circumstances, you might have been in two minds over the question at issue.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">In the above you have my thoughts on the question: ‘How far may one go in becoming involved with an unfortunate woman?’ Answer — ‘ad infinitum’.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">While still emphasizing that staying loyal comes first and foremost in all love, I remind you of your own words that ‘marrying’ (i.e. civil marriage) ‘is such an odd thing’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> These words of yours express exactly how it is, and on that point I declare I don’t know which is better or worse, to meddle or not. It’s what they call ‘<hi rend="italics">puzzling</hi>’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"><hi rend="italics">It puzzles me too</hi> — and I for my part wish so much that one had nothing to do with that. I believe it’s well said that ‘when one marries, one marries not only the woman herself but the family 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> too’,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> which is sometimes more or less fatal and wretched if they’re nasty people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">But now about the drawings — I’ve done some more with printer’s ink, and this week I was investigating how to mix the printer’s ink with white, and found that it can be mixed in at least two ways — namely with the white from the tubes of oil paint — and probably even better with the ordinary zinc white in powder form that one can even get at any chemist — in that case diluting it with turpentine, which doesn’t soak through on this paper or leave marks on the reverse like oil — because it dries so quickly and disappears.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Printer’s ink has much livelier effects than indian ink.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">How beautiful <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs>’s work is. In the window at G&amp;C. I saw a small seascape which you no doubt know, and which I’ve been going to have a look at almost every evening<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> — but as regards Dupré and similar art — of which one sees so much more in Paris than here — you may be rather spoiled — and not know what an almightily beautiful impression it makes here, where one sees so precious little of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Have got round to reading the last part of Les misérables — the figure of Fantine — a prostitute — made a deep impression on me<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> — oh, I know as well as anyone that in reality one won’t find an exact Fantine — but all the same this character by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Hugo</rs> — like all his characters for that matter — is <hi rend="italics">true</hi>, being the essence of what one sees in reality. It is the <hi rend="italics">type</hi> — of which one encounters only individuals.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Should you happen to run into an engraver one of these days, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1049">Girardet</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1004">Eichens</rs>, for example, who make aquatints,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> you’d be doing me a great favour if you could ask in passing: what is normally used for the <hi rend="italics">drawings</hi> intended to serve as a guide for the engraving? Perhaps they’ll say: printer’s ink. If that’s what they use, what do they dilute that printer’s ink with? How do they use it?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">It seems to me that if you raised this with some engraver or other in passing and told me what he said, I would probably find something in what he said 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> that would throw light on some questions, even if it wasn’t a direct answer to what printer’s ink is mixed with to make it possible to work with it <hi rend="italics">on paper</hi> in various ways. No doubt there are other kinds of printer’s ink apart from the one I have at the moment, and the question may resolve itself in due course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Effects <hi rend="italics">like those in aquatint engravings</hi> are produced in the drawings when one works with printer’s ink and turpentine, as I tried now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I’ve seen drawings in the past by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1234">Mottram</rs>, say, the English engraver who engraved the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>s,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and I wish I knew what he worked with, for example.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">It goes without saying that I’m not in a rush to have this information, but if you happen to hear something about different methods of drawing, do let me know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I too know <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_758">Soek</rs>’s wife and her mother<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> (if she still lives with her) — went there in the past — they’re still very clear in my memory — and find them two sympathetic people — who remind me of the members of my own household — so much so indeed that instinctively I often think of them as members of the same family. They’re just like characters from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Souvestre</rs>, say, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1023">E. Frère</rs>. One sees more people like that in Paris — everywhere for that matter. Such people always remind me of the female figures in the gospel, perhaps because sometimes in their expressions there’s something of, for instance, the figures in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs>, Good Friday,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> or in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1153">Landelle</rs>, Blessed are they that mourn.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> I know, this view isn’t complete, there are other aspects — still better than Delaroche — and deeper than he — such as those of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs></hi> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>. Well, I find that in them too, but I can still understand that this movement became popular in the days of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Souvestre</rs>, Delaroche, Frère, Landelle &amp;c., even though compared with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and others it isn’t entirely correct and true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">ANKER</rs> still alive?<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> I think of his work often, I find it so sound and so delicately felt. He’s one of the genuine old sort, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs>. Old chap, how I sometimes long for you to be in the studio again. I sincerely hope you’ll get the money back from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">H.</rs><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> In my case a lot had to be spent right away this time, and I have precious little left. Anyway, write as soon as you can when it’s getting towards the 20th. Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter confirms receipt of the remittance of 10 April 1883, as is shown by <ref target="#l-2">ll. 1*-3</ref> and <ref target="#l-162">l. 162</ref>, and so dates from on or about Wednesday, 11 April 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo is expecting the repayment of a loan to Hendrik van Gogh <ref target="let334.xml">(334)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means a proposal of marriage; although part of the letter is unambiguously about that, he does not commit the words themselves to paper. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let331.xml">letters 331</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let339.xml">339</ref> Van Gogh also hints at a possible marriage between Theo and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘weggeschroeid’ (cauterized).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For the ‘conscience’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let133.xml#n-12">see letter 133, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The character Combeferre sings this song in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi>, part 3, book 4, chapter 5. It derives from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1735">Molière</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_336">Le misanthrope</ref></hi> (Act 1, scene 2). See Hugo 1951, pp. 690, 1615.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The Revolution of 1830 was the so-called July Revolution (27-29 July of that year), which was the beginning of the July monarchy. Louis-Philippe d’Orléans agreed to rule under a constitution that put political power in the hands of the propertied classes (1830-1848).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Immediately after the song in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi> the character Enjolars says that ‘l’amour de ma mère’ stands for ‘l’amour de la republique’. See Hugo 1951, pp. 690, 1615. It is Van Gogh who is responsible for equating mother love with ‘l’amour de l’humanité’ and with ‘fraternité universelle’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
    
<p>For this quotation from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238">La vie et l’oeuvre de J.F. Millet</ref></hi><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let210.xml#n-5">see letter 210, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh comes back to this remark at the end of <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let417.xml">letter 417</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Theo must have made this comment in 1882; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let301.xml">letter 301</ref>, where these words were also quoted.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Vincent is probably quoting from Theo’s letter here. The passage (‘and I for my part... nasty people’) was added later by Van Gogh.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘vond uit dat ze’ (discovered that they).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Read: ‘geen vlekken geeft’ (does not leave marks); ‘niet’ (not) before ‘doortrekt’ (soak through) is contracted.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>These drawings are not known. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 194.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>On 9 March 1883 Goupil’s branch in The Hague received a seascape by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs> from Paris. The painting – measuring 54 x 45 cm – was bought for 6000 francs. It was to be sold on to Goupil’s in London for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">£</hi> 250 on 27 November 1883 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RKD</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Goupil Ledgers</hi>).</p>

<p rend="indent">In a letter to Theo a few years later <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_125">A.H. Koning</rs> said of the effect of exhibiting in this window on the Plaats: ‘Here in The Hague that is an excellent thing, because in the afternoon the entire beau monde takes a turn before the big window on the Plaats.’ (FR b1080, 15 september 1888).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="d" xml:id="note-t-d">
                            

<p>Read: ‘toegekomen aan’ (got round to).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The prostitute Fantine has a boundless love for her illegitimate daughter Cosette, whom she hands over to an innkeeper’s family so that she is better able to earn the board and lodging. She works hard, even selling her hair and teeth, but encounters a great many setbacks. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1049">Paul Girardet</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1004">Philipp Hermann Eichens</rs> were engravers who made numerous aquatints for Goupil’s publications.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1234">Charles Mottram</rs> line-engraved different works after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">George Boughton</rs>, e.g. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_500">Pilgrim exiles</rs></hi> (1874), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_501">The belated traveller</rs></hi> (1875) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_502">The two farewells</rs></hi> (1875). Which drawings by Mottram Van Gogh saw – probably during his stay in London – is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>It is not known who the widow of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_758">Frans Soek</rs> and her mother were.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>For <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1730">Good Friday</rs></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Paul Delaroche</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let041.xml#n-7">see letter 41, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1153">Charles Landelle</rs>’s painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Bienheureux ceux qui pleurent parce qu’ils seront consolés</hi> (Blessed are they that mourn for they shall be comforted) was shown at the Salon of 1852. The reproduction of it, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1541">Alexis François Girard</rs> in 1857, appeared as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Beatitude (Bienheureux ceux qui pleurent car ils seront consolés)</hi> in the Goupil list (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1031">Ill. 1031</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_40">Albert Anker</rs> was to live until 1910.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>Cousin <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">Hendrik van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    