<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Saturday, 21 April 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let337"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b303 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>337</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>280</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>339</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-04-21">on or about Saturday, 21 April 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0303" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0303" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000380_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> dank voor het ingeslotene. Uw brief las ik met veel belangstelling. Ik ben blij dat gij juist inziet van welken kant waarschijnlijk moeielijkheden zullen komen. N.l. dat – zonder ’t expres te doen – vrouwen als bij S.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> (ge zegt teregt ze echter op zich zelf goed zijn) weinig voorzigtig zijn in wat ze zeggen enz. Als ge met een woord spreekt over eene relatie tusschen Uw patient &amp; hare eigene moeder<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> zoo is dat iets waar ik U ook niet mede feliciteer. Ik vrees aan die band zal zij menigmaal <hi rend="italics">achter</hi>uit getrokken worden als gij haar <hi rend="italics">vóóruit</hi>gang zoekt te bewerken. Alleen – het is niets ongewoons<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het is echter wel eene treurige gedachte dat iets als eene relatie tusschen moeder en dochter een donkeren kant kan hebben. Zoo dat een man die licht liefheeft en het zoekt er fataal door gedwarsboomd kan worden. Door den invloed van moeder en den omgang met vriendinnen – misschien meer dan door iets anders – komt er in de vrouwen soms iets wat men <hi rend="italics">retrograde</hi> noemt<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en hervormingen in denken en doen – soms noodig en dringend noodig – belemmerd. Ik ben er blij om dat gij met regt voorziet wat misschien U te wachten staat van dien kant maar ik ben er niet blij om dat dit U niet bespaard werd – was de vrouw <hi rend="italics">geheel</hi> van haar familie af<c type="kk">/</c> gij zoudt minder bezwaren in de toekomst te wachten hebben geloof ik. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>En de moeielijkheid ligt juist daarin dat men onmogelijk precies berekenen kan in welken vorm de bezwaren zullen komen en bij ’t nemen van voorzorgsmaatregelen soms denken moet<c type="kk">/</c> ja maar ’t kan best zijn ik precies tegenovergestelde manoeuvres zal moeten doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Er is ergens in eene voorrede van Zola een woord<c type="kk">/</c> ik meen in dezen vorm<c type="kk">/</c> “Ces femmes ne sont cependant pas mauvaises<c type="kk">/</c> l’impossibilité d’une vie droite dans les commérages et les médisances des faubourgs est la cause de leurs fautes &amp; de leurs chûtes”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Als er zooveel ontwikkeling in de vrouw is dat in gedachten en begrippen zij U volgen kan en dus in Uw gemoedsleven deelen kan<c type="kk">/</c> zoo wordt dat een sterke band die veel bezwaren neutraliseert. In het aanknoopen van relaties met haar familie zou ik meenen ’t bezwaar te voorzien was dat men daardoor soms in ’t officieele vervalt (de lui nemen ’t zóó op soms<c type="kk">/</c> zeer indiscreet) waar men meer privé en niet officieel ’t bedoeld had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Doen &amp; zwijgen zijn niet de bedoelingen van iedereen en sommige oudere &amp; wijzere familieleden vervallen zoo ligt in ’t lawaaimaken dat men er spijt van hebben kan hen gesproken te hebben. Juist ook omdat zij ’t niet laten kunnen te intrigueeren en enfin – <hi rend="italics">het zijn waarschijnlijk wolven</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik wou we niet zoo ver van elkaar waren<c type="kp">_</c> ik schreef U gisteren meer uitvoerig over sommige moeielijkheden waarmee misschien gij binnenkort te maken zult hebben maar het is ’t gevoel dat ik zelf ook niet weet soms hoe er door te komen dat me terughield van te schrijven<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Bovendien ik heb ’t vertrouwen dat liefde waar ze opregt is niet vergaat<c type="kk">/</c> althans dan niet waar tegelijk men met rede handelt. Toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou dat ook weer willen doorschrappen omdat het niet juist is. want liefde kan betrekkelijk wel degelijk vergaan – doch er is iets van een kracht van renaissance in de liefde<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7"><hi rend="italics">Ce que l’homme tue</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> Dieu le ressucite</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">V.d. Weele was weer eens bij me<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien kom ik door hem in kennnis met Piet vd<c type="kp">_</c> Velden dien ge zeker wel kent uit zijn boeren- en visschersfiguren.–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik heb v.d. V. ééns ontmoet en hij maakte toen een goede impressie op mij<c type="kk">/</c> ik dacht aan ’t figuur van Felix Holt de radicaal<c type="kk">/</c> van Eliott.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Er is iets breeds en ruws in hem dat mij zeer bevalt – iets van het ruwe van torchon. Een man die de beschaving blijkbaar niet zoekt in uiterlijke dingen doch inwendig veel verder is<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">veel veel veel</hi> verder dan de meesten. Enfin hij is een echt artist en ik wou ik hem kende want ik zou hem vertrouwen en ik weet zeker ik van hem zou leeren. En ook al komt het niet door v.d. Weele<c type="kk">/</c> zou ’t niet onmogelijk zijn ik hem eens tegen ’t lijf liep.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Rappard zou verl. Maandag bij me gekomen zijn<c type="kp">_</c> toen werd zijne zuster<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> ziek<c type="kk">/</c> schreef hij<c type="kk">/</c> en kon hij weer niet. Misschien komt hij deze week. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> tegenwoordig is er geen teekening meer waar ik niet met ’t penseel in werk met de drukinkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik moet U wel zeggen dat ik wel wat gegeneerd ben in mijn beurs<c type="kp">_</c> dit is zeer zeker niet Uw schuld – maar ’t is mijn schuld ook niet<c type="kp">_</c> hoe ik ook bereken<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan niet meer bezuinigen. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>en voor ’t uitvoeren van sommige plannen zou ik meer moeten hebben dan ik over beschikken kan. Begon ik er aan<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou moeten blijven steken. Maar ’t is wel eens iets melankolieks als men denkt<c type="kk">/</c> dit of dat zou ik zoo en zoo kunnen maken<c type="kk">/</c> en te stuiten op de kosten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Er blijft dan een onvoldane energie in iemand die men zou wenschen niet te behoeven in zich op te sluiten. Toch zeg ik het niet om te klagen – ik ben dankbaar ik<c type="kk">/</c> zij ’t niet zoo krachtig als ik zou willen<c type="kk">/</c> vorderen kan<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar de Engelschen zeggen wel eens<c type="kk">/</c> Time is money<c type="kk">/</c> en ik denk soms onwillekeurig het hard is tijd te zien voorbijgaan waarin dit of dat reeds had kunnen gedaan worden als ik de middelen gehad had. Gij zult begrijpen wat ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou meer willen kunnen besteden nog<c type="kk">/</c> en aan model en aan schilderbehoeften. Al verkoop ik geen een van mijn studies<c type="kk">/</c> toch zijn ze geloof ik waard wat zij aan verschotten<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> kosten. Het atelier is zoo veel beter en bruikbaarder geworden doch ik heb slechts stoom genoeg voor “half speed” en zou “full speed” willen gaan. Nog eens, ik zeg het niet om te klagen, ook niet omdat ik U tot grootere opofferingen zou willen dringen<c type="kk">/</c> gij zijt eigentlijk zelf ook boven uw kracht belast. Maar tot explicatie en om mijn hart eens lucht te geven. Want ge begrijpt dat ik soms zware zorg heb. Enfin roeien met die riemen die er zijn en de dingen die we niet vertillen kunnen met kracht ondermijnen door geduld. Deze week teekende ik een paar liggende figuren<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> ik zal wel eens figuren van lijken of zieken noodig hebben<c type="kk">/</c> zoowel mannen als vrouwen. Onlangs kwam ik ’t huis van Israels voorbij<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> – ik ben daar nooit binnen geweest – de voordeur stond open daar den gang geschrobd werd – ik zag dingen hangen in den gang en weet ge wat het waren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">de groote Herkomer<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Last muster Sunday at Chelsea</hi><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en eene phot. naar dat bewuste schij van <hi rend="italics">Roll</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Grève de</hi> <hi rend="italics">Charbonniers</hi><c type="kk">/</c> waarover ge U misschien herinnert ik U in der tijd schreef.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Ik wist niet dat er eene phot<c type="kp">_</c> van Last muster bestond. Ik heb de groote houtsnee van de twee hoofdfiguren en </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">de eerste ruwe schets<c type="kk">/</c> lang vóór ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> gemaakt.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> het beste met Uw patient<c type="kk">/</c> voorspoed met het werk.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter, thanks for the enclosure. I read your letter with great interest. I’m glad that you understand correctly from which quarter difficulties will probably come. Namely, that — without meaning to do so — women like S.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> (you rightly say that they, though, are good in themselves) aren’t very careful about what they say, etc. When, in short, you refer to a relationship between your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> and her own mother,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> that isn’t something on which I congratulate you. I fear that she’ll be drawn <hi rend="italics">back</hi>wards many times by that link when you’re trying to bring about <hi rend="italics">for</hi>ward movement. But — it’s nothing unusual.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It is, however, a sad thought that something like the relationship between mother and daughter can have a dark side. So that a man who loves light and seeks it can be fatally thwarted by it. Through the influence of the mother and mixing with girlfriends — perhaps more than through anything else — something called a <hi rend="italics">retrograde</hi><ptr target="#note-t-3"/><hi rend="italics"> </hi>gets into women sometimes and prevents reforms in their thinking and actions, which are sometimes needed, and urgently needed. I’m glad that you rightly foresee what may lie in store for you from that quarter, but I’m not glad that you weren’t spared this — if the woman had left her family <hi rend="italics">completely</hi>, you could expect fewer problems in the future, I believe. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And the difficulty is precisely that it’s impossible to calculate exactly what form the problems will take, and that when taking precautionary measures one must sometimes think: yes, but it may well be that I’ll have to perform diametrically opposite manoeuvres. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Somewhere in a preface by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> there are the following words, I believe in this form: ‘Yet these women are not bad, the impossibility of living a straight life in the midst of the gossip and calumny of the suburbs is the cause of their faults and their fall’.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> If the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">woman</rs> is sufficiently cultivated to be able to follow you in thoughts and concepts and thus share in your inner life, that will be a strong bond that will neutralize many problems. The problem to be expected in establishing relations with her family, I would think, is that one sometimes lapses into the official as a result (people take it like that sometimes, most indiscreetly), when one meant it to be more private and unofficial.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Act and be silent is not everyone’s aim, and some older and wiser family members lapse so easily into noise-making that one may regret having spoken to them. Especially because they can’t help intriguing, and anyway — <hi rend="italics">they’re probably wolves</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I wish we weren’t so far apart. I wrote to you yesterday at greater length about some difficulties you may encounter shortly, but I was prevented from writing<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> by the sense that I myself sometimes don’t know how to carry on. Moreover, I have faith that where love is true it doesn’t die, at least not when one acts with reason at the same time. Yet I would like to cross that out as well, because it’s not right. For love can indeed die, in a way — but there’s something like a power of renaissance in love. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><hi rend="italics">What man kills God restores to life</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> came to see me again. Perhaps through him I’ll make the acquaintance of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1400">Piet van der Velden</rs>, whom you certainly know from his figures of peasants and fishermen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I met <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1400">Van der V.</rs> once, and he made a good impression on me at the time. I was reminded of the character of Felix Holt the radical by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">Eliot</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> There’s something broad and rough in him that pleases me greatly — something like the roughness of torchon. A man who evidently doesn’t seek civilization in outward things but is much further inwardly, <hi rend="italics">much much much</hi> further than most people. In short, he’s a true artist, and I’d like to get to know him for I would trust him and I’m sure I would learn from him. And if it doesn’t happen through <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>, it isn’t impossible that I may bump into him at some point. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> was due to visit me last Monday, then his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1755">sister</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> fell ill, he wrote, and again he couldn’t come. Perhaps he’ll come this week. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Well, at present there are no drawings in which I don’t work in printer’s ink with a brush. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I have to say that I’m running a little short. This is certainly not your fault — but it’s not my fault either. Whatever calculations I make, I can’t economize any further. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> And to carry out some plans I would need to have more than I can command. I’d get stuck if I began them. But it’s sometimes a sad thing when one thinks, I could do one thing or another this way or that way, and to come up against the costs. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Then there remains undischarged energy in a person that one would prefer not to have to shut up inside oneself. Yet I don’t say this to complain — I’m grateful that I can make progress, albeit not as forcefully as I would like. But the English say sometimes: Time is money, and I can’t help thinking on occasion that it’s hard to see time passing in which this or that could have been done if I’d had the means. You will understand what I mean, I would like to be able to spend more, both on models and on painting materials. Even if I don’t sell a single one of my studies, I still believe they’re worth what they cost in outgoings. The studio is so much better and more practical, but I only have enough steam for ‘half speed’ and want to go ‘full speed’. Again, I don’t say this to complain, nor because I want to press you to make greater sacrifices — you’re already overburdened yourself. But in explanation and to open my heart for once. For you’ll understand that sometimes I’m burdened with cares. Still, we must make shift with what we have, and undermine with patience the things we can’t lift with strength. This week I drew a few recumbent figures,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I’ll need figures of corpses or sick people eventually, both men and women. I passed by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs>’s house lately<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> — I’ve never been inside it — the front door stood open because the hall was being scrubbed — I saw things hanging in the hall and do you know what they were?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">The large <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Last muster Sunday at Chelsea</hi><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and a photo<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> after that painting by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Roll</rs>, Miners’ strike</hi>, which you may remember I wrote to you about at the time.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I didn’t know there was a photo<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> of Last muster. I have the large woodcut of the two main figures and the first rough sketch, done long before the painting.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Well, adieu old chap, best wishes for your patient, good fortune with work.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter comes after <ref target="let336.xml">letter 336</ref> of on or about Wednesday, 11 April 1883 because Theo must have responded to Vincent’s remarks about the widow of Frans Soek and her mother in <ref target="let336.xml">letter 336</ref>. Since Vincent says thanks for the money received, it must be assumed that this was the next remittance, that of 20 April. We therefore date the letter on or about Saturday, 21 April 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Alterations to the studio windows <ref target="let317.xml">(317)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The widow Soek and her mother; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let336.xml#n-14">letter 336, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Neither <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs> nor her mother has been identified.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>. In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi> he wrote of the married woman: ‘she is almost always brought up by her mother to have reactionary ideas’ (presque toujours elle est élevée par sa mère dans les pensées rétrogrades) (Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, p. 167).</p>

<p rend="indent">There is a similar passage in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12">La femme</ref></hi> on the danger that a woman can lapse into a ‘reactionary past’ (passé rétrograde). She hinders the progress of her husband, who is stifled by ‘the old family home’ (le vieux foyer de famille) (Michelet 1863, pp. 12-13). Van Gogh expresses this view in similar phrasing in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let349.xml">letter 349</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to the following passage from the ‘Préface’ to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_255">L’assommoir</ref></hi>, dated 1 January 1877: ‘We must by no means conclude that the people in its entirety is bad, because my characters are not bad, they are merely ignorant, and ruined by the world of harsh toil and misery in which they live.’ (Il ne faut point conclure que le peuple tout entier est mauvais, car mes personnages ne sont pas mauvais, ils ne sont qu’ignorants et gâtés par le milieu de rude besogne et de misère où ils vivent). See Zola 1960-1967, vol. 2, p. 374. Also quoted in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let379.xml">letter 379</ref>. For the novel, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let338.xml#n-12">see letter 338, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Possibly an allusion to ‘Homo homini lupus’ (Man is like a wolf to his fellow man); after Plautus, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Asinaria</hi>, 495.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh appears – in view also of <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-62">ll. 62-63</ref> – to mean that he had started a letter but did not send it. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Borrowed from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi>, vol. 1, book 1, chapter 4: ‘He whom man kills, God brings back to life; he whom the brothers drive away, find the Father’ (Celui que l’homme tue, Dieu le ressuscite; celui que les frères chassent retrouve le Père). See Hugo 1951, p. 41.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1400">Pieter van der Velden</rs> worked in Wassenaar and The Hague between 1875 and 1888 (see Scheen 1981). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For the protagonist of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">George Eliot</rs>’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_57">Felix Holt, the radical</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let066.xml#n-1">see letter 66, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1755">Wilhelmina Elisabeth van Rappard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘onkosten’ (outgoings).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            
    
<p>Only one drawing of a recumbent figure is known: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman on her deathbed</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3035">F 841 / JH 359</rs>), which will have been one of them. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs> had lived since 1873 in an elegant building with a studio on Koninginnegracht 2 in The Hague. See exhib. cat. Groningen 1999, p. 358.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
    
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_171">The last muster (Sunday at Chelsea hospital</rs></hi> / <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Chelsea pensioners</hi>), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let199.xml#n-12">see letter 199, n. 12</ref> and cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let303.xml#n-6">letter 303, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
<p>Van Gogh wrote ‘phot.’ possibly meaning photogravure and not photograph.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            
    
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1329">Alfred Roll</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1950">A miners’ strike</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let263.xml#n-5">see letter 263, n. 5.</ref> Van Gogh discussed the print at length in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let272.xml">letter 272</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            
<p>Van Gogh wrote ‘phot.’ possibly meaning photogravure and not photograph.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh evidently means a photograph after the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">painting</hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs>. We have been unable to confirm that it was on sale at the time. When Herkomer’s painting won a gold medal of honour in 1878 at the International Exhibition in Paris, however, Arthur Turrell did make a mezzotint after the work (for Pilgeram and Lefevre). See Edward Morris, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Victorian and Edwardian paintings in the Lady Lever Art Gallery</hi>. London 1994, pp. 50-56, esp. 53. By ‘the large woodcut of the two main figures’ Van Gogh means <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1910">The last muster</rs></hi>; for ‘the first rough sketch’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let337.xml#n-13">see n. 13</ref>. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let199.xml#n-12">letter 199, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    