<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Wednesday, 2 or Thursday, 3 May 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let339"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b305 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>339</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>282</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>341</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-05-02">Wednesday, 2 or Thursday, 3 May 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0305" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0305" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000382_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
                <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                
<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>
                
<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief &amp; het ingeslotene was zeer welkom als altijd<c type="kp">_</c>– En als altijd wel bedankt er voor – en zoozeer begrijpende ge zelf heel wat te zorgen hebt waardeer ik het te meer<c type="kp">_</c></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Hetgeen ge schrijft betreffende Uw patient is betrekkelijk geen nieuws &amp; betrekkelijk wel<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat ge er over naar huis geschreven hebt<c type="kk">/</c> of schrijven zult liever<c type="kk">/</c> is iets wat U zelf rust zal geven en regt is. Natuurlijkerwijs heb ik nooit ’t minst over de zaak gerept en kunt ge er van verzekerd zijn ik ook niet t’huis of elders zal laten merken ik er reeds vroeger iets van wist of meer intieme details ken. En<c type="kk">/</c> dunkt me<c type="kk">/</c> doen als hoorde ik er zoo dezer dagen voor ’t eerst van, in ’t oppervlakkige. Doch ’t zal ook niet voorkomen iemand me er over spreekt.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wees dus hieromtrent gerust<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop van harte dat alles zoo van stapel zal loopen als ge beraamd hebt tegen October &amp; ben blij ’t zoo ver is, van harte blij<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">en</hi> voor U <hi rend="italics">en</hi> voor haar<c type="kp">_</c> Ik vind het zoo best – vooral juist <hi rend="italics">omdat</hi> ik details ken – als men zóó elkaar ontmoet dan moet men niet meer van elkaar gaan.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En hoop ik van harte het er van komen zal ge dezen zomer met haar eens naar Holland komt. Wie weet of niet juist nu sommige dingen met betrekking tot de vrouw voor mij ook zich zouden kunnen ophelderen.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En dus is de Salon geopend<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ge zult dezer dagen de heeren H.G.T<c type="kp">_</c> en C.M. wel weer over hebben. ’t Is nu al haast een jaar geleden dat ik met hem onaangenaamheden had (n.l. met HGT)<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik zal hem niet weer in den weg komen<c type="kk">/</c> dat heeft hij wel gezien ook dunkt mij en kan hij verzekerd zijn ik aan het gebeurde haast niet meer denk. Mij dunkt<c type="kk">/</c> mogt H.G.T<c type="kp">_</c> U soms een woord over mij spreken<c type="kk">/</c> coupeer het plus minus in dezer voege: Is V.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> U sedert in den weg geloopen of U tot last geweest – daar hij dit niet geweest is<c type="kk">/</c> maak gij het hem ook niet moeielijk. 
                    <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Het is mij min of meer onpleizierig dat ik om reden van die moeielijkheid met H<c type="kp">_</c>G.T<c type="kp">_</c> het huis G.&amp;C<c type="kp">_</c> steeds uit discretie moet mijden. Gij weet wat H.G.T. b.v. toen in der tijd aan Pa over mij schreef – welnu die opinie van dat ik het onmogelijk gemaakt had dat hij iets verder met mij te doen zou hebben heeft hij tot heden niet teruggenomen<c type="kp">_</c>– ’t Spreekt van zelf dat zoolang hij die opinie van mij heeft ik mijn voeten in de zaak op de Plaats niet zetten zal<c type="kp">_</c></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Niet omdat ik bang ben H.G.T<c type="kp">_</c> te ontmoeten evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> niet omdat ik mij voor hem verbergen wil of iets dergelijks<c type="kk">/</c> maar omdat ik hem geen aanstoot wil geven<c type="kp">_</c></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wil iemand niets met me te doen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> welnu ik zal zelf mee helpen en de enkele gelegenheden waar men soms elkaar ongezocht tegen ’t lijf zou loopen<c type="kk">/</c> trachten te vermijden. Overigens zoodanige opinie niet tegenspreken<c type="kp">_</c> van uit een zeker standpunt gezien heeft H.G.T<c type="kp">_</c> geen ongelijk – evenwel de zaken zouden van een anderen kant kunnen bezien worden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Men zou ’t anders hebben kunnen opgevat hebben dan ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> toen deed<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar dat moet hij zelf weten.– Waarom ik er met een woord even over schrijf is dat<c type="kk">/</c> gesteld hij sprak er U over<c type="kk">/</c> gij hem kunt zeggen dat ik aan ’t gebeurde niet meer denk anders dan dat ik om te vermijden wat hij indiscreet zou kunnen vinden (ten overstaan van zijn over mij duidelijk uitgesproken opinie) mij van het komen in de zaak op de Plaats onthoud en onthouden zal zoolang hij die opinie van me behoudt zóó als hij ze uitte tegenover Pa.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Van mijn kant heb ik mij toen over ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> uitgelaten tegenover U – maar overigens zoover ik weet ook niet tegenover anderen – geinfluenceerd door diverse omstandigheden die voor mij zeer onaangenaam waren (ongenoegen met Mauve<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c>)<c type="kp">_</c> Dat mijn oordeel over hem daardoor ook niet juist was geef ik gaarne toe en op conditie dat H.G.T. terugneemt wat hij over mij schreef aan Pa (dat ik het onmogelijk gemaakt had hij iets verder met me te doen zou hebben) neem ik terug mijn opinie dat H.G.T. schuld had aan onaangename dingen die me overkwamen. Indien ik me duidelijk genoeg uitdruk vindt ge in deze beschouwing mogelijk iets dat tot meer vrede of elkaar beter verstaan mogt kunnen leiden, ’t geen me verre van onverschillig zoude wezen.</p>
                <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Als ik reken van af Mei l.l. Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dan is ’t jaar voor mij niet precies makkelijk of zonder zorg geweest<c type="kk">/</c> he<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar dat’s niets<c type="kk">/</c> gemak of zonder zorgen wezen is ook mijn ideaal &amp; bedoeling niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Toch – er is heel wat komen kijken<c type="kp">_</c></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Hetgeen gij stuurt vind ik niet weinig doch veel maar ofschoon het veel was – meer zelfs dan gij zelf eigentlijk missen kondt – om voort te gaan en te vorderen met het werk en met het huishouden is een heksenwerk voor de vrouw en voor mij<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu is ’t soms voor mij erg naar als er zulke scheeve verhoudingen zijn dat ik b.v. juist zulke personen moet vermijden als men soms juist in verband tot ’t werk<c type="kk">/</c> direkt of indirekt<c type="kk">/</c> mee in aanraking zou dienen te komen. En wou ik ’t uit de wereld was.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Enfin – betrekkelijk heb ik ’t overgegeven<c type="kp">_</c></p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Op dit moment heb ik verschillend werk onder handen dat ik dien door te voeren – en werkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben wat gegeneerd. Ge schrijft over Rappard – ’t is zoo lam hij niet gekomen is toen hij schreef te zullen komen – als ik hem vraag me wat voor te schieten geloof ik bepaald hij dit me niet zal weigeren<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Want hij zelf heeft het me geproponeerd dezen winter<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> toen werd hij echter ziek en konden we niet correspon<c type="shy">-</c>deeren over de zaak waar ’t geld voor zou bestemd zijn<c type="kk">/</c> n<c type="kp">_</c>l. lithographies en teekeningen die daarmee in rapport stonden. Toen schreef zijn vader nog “mijn zoon is ziek doch ik weet er van<c type="kk">/</c> als gij soms in verlegenheid zijt zal ik U het bewuste voorschieten”. Dat vond ik zóó fijn van R. vader dat ik het grof van me zelf zou gevonden hebben indien ik toen het direkt hadde genomen<c type="kp">_</c> En schreef dus “neen<c type="kk">/</c> laat Uw zoon eerst beter zijn”<c type="kp">_</c> Nu werd R. beter maar ik hoorde daaromtrent niets direkts meer en was hij geabsorbeerd in ander werk<c type="kp">_</c> En zoo is dat nog steeds hangende en is er telkens iets dat in den weg komt van die zaak door te zetten. Maar ik van mijn kant ging er wel mede door<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. teekenen met drukinkt<c type="kk">/</c> lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt enz. en heb nog al kosten gehad ook. Daar is hij niet in ’t minst aansprakelijk voor maar ik wil maar zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> reden te meer hij me niet zal weigeren<c type="kk">/</c> denk ik<c type="kk">/</c> mij voor te schieten.</p>
                <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik zal ’t hem dus verzoeken – doch ben een brief van hem wachtende &amp; vóór ik de zaak beschreven &amp; antwoord heb<c type="kk">/</c> verstrijkt ligt een tijd want hij is slof in correspondentie soms. Toen ’t geld van U kwam van morgen was ik zonder geld – d.i. absoluut zonder een cent geweest ± een week. Ik was bovendien uitgeput in teekengerij<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik was in besprek met Smulders over eene partij teekenpapier &amp; heb dat gehaald ofschoon die uitgaaf nu niet convenieerde – maar ik moest het hebben met andere materialen als b.v. de drukinkt van de graveurs en lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt. En moest verscheiden dingen betalen en inslaan voor ’t huishouden. En moest modellen betalen die ik intusschen toch gehad had om door te blijven werken.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Het spijt me verschrikkelijk dat ik het dien te vragen maar als ge eenigzins kunt<c type="kk">/</c> stuur mij nog b.v. 10 francs<c type="kp">_</c> Er hangt een week werk van af want ik zal van Rappard niet direkt antwoord hebben kunnen, ben reeds à court en heb afspraak met modellen. Als Rappard me dan zendt is er ook weer een tijd dat alles geregeld zal gaan tot er eens weer ruimte komen kan. Kunt ge het zenden zoo loopt deze week werk grif van stapel en anders is er onaangename averij. Maar neem het me niet kwalijk<c type="kk">/</c> er was een combinatie van kosten (en allen onvermijdelijken) die ik niet precies kon schipperen. En hebt ge het niet – enfin – we zullen er niet van sterven daarom. De moeielijkheden in kleine zaken over kleine sommen zijn soms ook waarachtig hoofdbrekend en dit is zulk een geval. Ik hoop dat R. me wat mogt kunnen helpen want heb er behoefte aan<c type="kk">/</c> net als het veld naar<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> een regenbui als ’t lang droog geweest is.</p>
                
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> nogmaals wensch ik U allen voorspoed toe met betrekking tot uw patient<c type="kp">_</c> het weer is hier bij tijden heerlijk<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zal bij U te lande ook zeker mooi zijn &amp; zal haar goed doen. adieu.</p>
                <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                
<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">t. à. t.</p>
                
<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
                <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                </div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter and the enclosure were most welcome, as always. And as always, thank you for them — I appreciate it all the more knowing so well that you yourself have many cares.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">What you write concerning your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> is to some extent new and to some extent not. That you’ve written home about it, or rather will write, is something that will give you peace and is right. Naturally, I’ve never said a word about the matter, and you can rest assured that I won’t let on at home or elsewhere that I already knew something of it or am aware of more intimate details. And, I imagine, behave as if I first heard about it only recently, on a superficial level. But anyway, it’s unlikely that anyone will speak to me about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">So rest assured on this point.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well, I sincerely hope that everything happens as you have planned towards October, and am glad the time has come, sincerely glad <hi rend="italics">both</hi> for you <hi rend="italics">and</hi> for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">her</rs>. I think this is for the best — especially <hi rend="italics">because</hi> I know details — when one meets each other like that one should never again part.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And I sincerely hope that this summer it will be possible for you to come to Holland with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">her</rs>. Who knows if precisely now some things to do with the woman may become clear to me too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And so the Salon has opened.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> No doubt Messrs <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> will be paying you a visit one of these days. It’s now almost a year since I had the unpleasantness with him (i.e. with HGT).<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I shan’t cross his path again, I believe he realizes that too, and he can rest assured that I hardly ever think of what occurred. It seems to me, should H.G.T. say anything to you about me, that you should cut him off more or less in this manner: Has V.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> obstructed you since then or bothered you? — given that he hasn’t, you shouldn’t make things difficult for him. 
                    <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> It’s rather disagreeable to me that I always have to avoid the house of G.&amp;C. out of discretion, on account of that difficulty with H.G.T. You know what H.G.T. wrote about me to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> that time, for example — well, so far he hasn’t retracted his view that I’d made it impossible for him to have anything further to do with me. It goes without saying that as long as he holds that opinion of me I won’t set foot inside the premises on the Plaats.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Not, however, that I’m afraid of meeting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs>, not because I want to hide from him or anything like that, but because I don’t want to give him offence. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">If someone wants to have nothing to do with me, well I’ll help and try to avoid the few places where we might unintentionally bump into each other. Otherwise, don’t contradict such an opinion. From a certain point of view <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> isn’t wrong — nonetheless, things could be viewed from another angle.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It could have been taken differently from the way in which His Hon. took it then. But that’s up to him. The reason I’m writing just a word about it is so that, supposing he speaks to you on the subject, you can tell him I no longer think about what happened other than that, to avoid what he might find indiscreet (given his plainly pronounced opinion of me), I refrain from going into the premises on the Plaats and shall continue so to refrain as long as he holds the opinion of me that he expressed to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">For my part I gave my opinion of His Hon. to you then, but not as far as I remember to others, influenced by various circumstances that were most disagreeable for me (displeasure with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c.). I freely admit that as a result my judgement of him wasn’t correct either and, on condition that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs> takes back what he wrote about me to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> (that I had made it impossible for him to have anything further to do with me), I will take back my opinion that H.G.T. was to blame for disagreeable things that happened to me. If I express myself clearly enough, you may find in these thoughts something that could lead to more peace or better mutual understanding, which would be far from a matter of indifference to me.
                    <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">If I count from last May, Theo, this year hasn’t been exactly easy or free of care, eh. But that’s nothing; convenience or being without cares isn’t my ideal and goal either. Still, rather a lot has happened.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I find what you send not a little but a lot, yet although it was a lot — more even than you yourself could really go without — the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and I have the devil’s own job to keep going and to make progress with the work and with housekeeping. Now it’s sometimes very unpleasant for me if relations are so strained that, for example, I must avoid the very people that one ought to meet in connection with the work, directly or indirectly. And I wish it was all cleared up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Anyway, I’ve just about given up responsibility for that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">At the moment I have different kinds of work on my hands that I ought to carry through — and truly, I’m rather short. You write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> — it’s so tiresome that he didn’t come when he wrote that he would — if I asked him to advance me something I’m sure he wouldn’t refuse me.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> For he himself proposed that to me this winter,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but then he fell ill and we couldn’t correspond about the matter for which the money was to be intended, namely lithographs and drawings related to them. Then his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_183">father</rs> wrote, ‘my son is ill but I know about it, if you are hard up I shall advance you the amount in question’. I thought that was so good of R.’s father that I would have found it gross of myself if I had immediately taken it then. And so wrote, ‘no, let your son get better first’. Now R. did get better but I heard no more about it and he was absorbed in other work. And so that’s still pending and there’s always something that gets in the way of pursuing the matter. But I for one did carry on with it, namely drawing with printer’s ink, lithographic crayon, etc., and indeed incurred considerable costs. He isn’t in the least responsible for that, but I just mean that that’s all the more reason why he won’t refuse, I believe, to give me an advance.
                    <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">So I’ll ask him — but am expecting a letter from him and some time will probably pass before I’ve explained the matter and got a reply, for he’s sometimes a lazy correspondent. When the money from you arrived this morning I had no money — that is, had been absolutely without a single cent for about a week. Furthermore, I had run out of drawing materials. I was in discussions with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1482">Smulders</rs> about a batch of drawing paper and took it, although the expenditure was inconvenient now — but I had to have it and other materials such as the engravers’ printer’s ink and lithographic crayon. And had to pay various things and stock up for the housekeeping. And had to pay models whom I had had in the meantime so that I could carry on working.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’m terribly sorry to have to ask but if it’s at all possible send me another 10 francs, say. A week’s work depends on it, for I shan’t be able to get an immediate answer from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, am already short of cash, and have appointments with models. If Rappard then sends me some, there will again be a phase when everything goes smoothly until there can be a breathing space once more. If you can send some, work will come off the stocks rapidly this week, and otherwise there’ll be nasty damage to the vessel. But forgive me, there was a combination of costs (all unavoidable) that I couldn’t quite cope with. And if you haven’t got it — well — we won’t starve as a result. The difficulties in small matters about small sums are sometimes truly perplexing, and this is such a case. I hope R. will be able to help me a little, for I’m in need of it, just as the field needs a shower when it has long been dry. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Well, again I wish you all good fortune as regards your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs>. The weather here is delightful at times; no doubt it’s beautiful where you are too, and will do her good. Adieu.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
                    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
                    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for his (first) remittance <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, which arrived ‘this morning’ <ref target="#l-129">(l. 129)</ref>. He writes that ‘the Salon has opened’ <ref target="#l-27">(l. 27)</ref> – this took place on 1 May. Given that the letter must have been written after <ref target="let338.xml">letter 338</ref> of 30 April, we have dated it Wednesday, 2 or Thursday, 3 May 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
                        <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
                    
<p>Theo had plans to marry <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs>; see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let331.xml">letter 331</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
                    
<p>The Paris Salon opened on 1 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
                    
<p>For the worsening relations with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs>, which was the case from February 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let208.xml">see letters 208</ref> ff. Tersteeg’s disapproving attitude towards <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> and her <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs> during a visit in July 1882 (he also wrote about Vincent to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>) led to relations being broken off (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let247.xml">see letters 247</ref> ff.).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
                    
<p>Read: ‘Vincent’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
                    
<p>On the deteriorating relationship with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let209.xml">see letters 209</ref> ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
                    
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> was to lend Van Gogh 25 guilders; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let343.xml">see letter 343</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
                    
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s earlier offer to lend Van Gogh money, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let289.xml">see letter 289</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            
                    
<p>Read: ‘aan’ (of).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    