<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Thursday, 10 May 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let342"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b307 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>342</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>284</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>344</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-05-10">on or about Thursday, 10 May 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0307 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0307 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000384_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0307 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000385_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000385_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0307 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000385_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000385_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief heb ik in orde ontvangen met ingesl. frs 50. Die me eene verlossing waren<c type="kk">/</c> althans verademing zijn. Tevens heb ik eenig berigt van vriend Rappard – maar nog niets bepaalds.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Een brief die antwoord is op mijn schrijven en dat hij mij helpen zal en ook komen<c type="kk">/</c> doch<c type="kk">/</c> schrijft hij<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben weer aan ’t sukkelen met mijn gestel<c type="kp">_</c> Eindigt met: ik sluit het geld hierbij in<c type="kp">_</c>– Postscriptum<c type="kk">/</c> och ik zal maar direkt komen en ’t zelf mede brengen – ik kom morgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Daarop volgt den volgenden dag een telegram<c type="kp">_</c> Kom niet<c type="kk">/</c> brief volgt later<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dus ofschoon berigt hebbende<c type="kk">/</c> is het nog ’t zelfde op de wijs van ’t ganzebord<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> als ge U herinnert hoe men op een gans kan teregt komen<c type="kk">/</c> dus vooruitgaan doch ongelukkigerwijs dan juist teregt komen op eene nieuwe zoodanige gans dat den bek den anderen kant op wijst dan men heen wil en men weer terug moet tellen tot op zijn oorspronkelijke standplaats. Het is echter zijn schuld niet want hij is werkelijk zeer ernstig ziek geweest en heeft restes of naweeën daarvan behouden. Zijne zuster<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> heeft ongeveer eene dergelijke ziekte gehad als hij bovendien &amp; zijn ze daarover zeer in zorg geweest doch ook hersteld.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Evenwel geloof ik dit van vriend R.<c type="kk">/</c> dat hij dingen doet die hem veel energie en zenuwkracht kosten en ’t kruid<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> niet waard zijn dat hij er aan verschiet<c type="kp">_</c> zoo hoorde ik vóór zijn ziekte van decoraties voor een eeuwfeest van de Utrechtsche schildervereeniging<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en nu ditmaal van kerkornamenten. Toevalligerwijs 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>schreef ik hem van beiden ik dit minder goed vond en zoowel de vorige keer als nu deze keer is het dat hij ziek wordt. overwerkte hij zich aan gewone dingen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou het goed vinden<c type="kk">/</c> maar dit zooals gezegd vind ik ’t kruid niet waard dat men er aan verschiet<c type="kk">/</c> en schreef hem nog eens: ge zijt tirailleur en een van de weinigen die in den tegenwoordigen tijd patronen in hun tasch hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Verschiet ze niet dan in gevallen waar een schot onvermijdelijk is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik vrees – beste broer – dat het geld door U aan onzen lieven neef H<c type="kp">_</c> geleend – op dit moment den vorm van b.v. een kwaadaardigen jagthond of andere soortgelijke merkwaardigheid heeft aangenomen<c type="kk">/</c> aangezien ik meen hij zich nog al eens in dergelijke aankoopen fourvoyeert – en ’t hem dan later somtijds niet mogelijk is het uit dien vorm terug te brengen tot den toestand van bankpapier of te verzilveren<c type="kk">/</c> daar hij als meer andere paarden- of honden<c type="shy">-</c>liefhebbers in de strikken van een of anderen maquignon loopt. Ik ben onder degenen die hem den meest mogelijken voorspoed in deze negotiatieën toewenschen en niets liever zou zien dan dat zij een zoodanig resultaat mogen geven dat hij spoedig retourneere wat hij U debet is. In der tijd waren er groote plannen om de plantage<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> te bevolken met ontelbare honden. Deze veeteelt is wel zeer prijzenswaardig doch op dit moment wil ik er niet meer van zeggen dan dat ik hoop die buitengewoon rendeere.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Is Uw patient reeds uit het gasthuis geheel en al? Misschien echter zullen er nog wel eens dagen van zorg zijn<c type="kk">/</c> niet minder ernstig dan toen zij aldaar was<c type="kp">_</c>– Michelet zegt teregt – une femme est une malade<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Zij varieeren<c type="kk">/</c> Theo – zij varieeren als het weer. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> wie er oog op heeft ziet iets moois en goeds in <hi rend="italics">alle</hi> weer<c type="kk">/</c> vindt sneeuw mooi en brandende zon mooi en storm mooi en stilte mooi<c type="kk">/</c> koude goed en hitte<c type="kk">/</c> heeft alle saizoenen lief en wil geen dag missen uit het jaar en is in den grond tevreden en berustend de dingen zóó zijn als ze zijn – doch ook als men zóó ’t weer beschouwd en ’t veranderende jaar – en zóó de veranderende vrouwelijke natuur – in den grond ook van die geloovende er een <hi rend="italics">Raison</hi> zij<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t raadselachtige daarvan<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> – berustende waar men niet begrijpt – ook<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> als men ’t zóó zou opvatten is onze eigene natuur en zienswijs niet steeds en op ieder moment in harmonie en stemming met die der vrouw waaraan we verbonden zijn en voelt men individueel ’t zij zorg<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij onvoldaanheid<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij twijfelmoedigheid<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks ’t geloof en den goeden moed of sereniteit die men hebbe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">De radicale genezing van de vrouw van mij – daarmede zijn<c type="kk">/</c> werd me gezegd door den professor die haar heeft verlost<c type="kk">/</c> jaren gemoeid<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat is<c type="kk">/</c> steeds blijft het zenuwgestel enorm prikkelbaar b.v. en het variable van de vrouwen heeft zij zeer sterk. Het groote gevaar is – dat zult ge begrijpen – weer instorting in vroegere vergissingen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dit gevaar<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon van moreelen aard<c type="kk">/</c> heeft rapporten met het physiek gestel. En die wat ik zou willen noemen slingeringen tusschen beter worden en weer vervallen in vroegere verkeerde gewoonten<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er voortdurende en soms ernstige zorgen over. Zij kan zóó van humeur zijn dat het haast ondragelijk is zelfs voor mij, driftig<c type="kk">/</c> moedwillig verkeerd<c type="kk">/</c> enfin soms wanhoop ik. ’t Komt dan weer bij – en heeft ze me meermalen later gezegd – IK WEET DAN ZELF NIET WAT IK DOE.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Weet gij nog gij verl. jaar mij schreeft ge vreesdet ik de moeder tot mijn last zoude krijgen. Soms wou ik ’t dezen keer genomen had. De moeder is zóó flink als ze wil en zou zoo veel beter kunnen hebben doen dan ze gedaan heeft. Nu hindert ze soms meer dan ze helpt. Enfin – als de vrouw verkeerd doet is ’t soms de schuld van de moeder en als de moeder verkeerd doet is ’t soms weer de familie die achter de moeder zit. Dingen die op zich zelf zoo erg niet zijn maar den vooruitgang verhinderen en betere invloeden overdonderen of neutraliseeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">De vrouw van mij heeft bepaalde fouten en verkeerde dingen in haar manier van doen – dat kan niet anders<c type="kp">_</c>– DAAROM IS ZIJ NOG NIET SLECHT m.i. Toch<c type="kk">/</c> die verkeerdheden moeten er uit – gewoonten van slofheid<c type="kk">/</c> onverschilligheid<c type="kk">/</c> gebrek aan activiteit en handigheid<c type="kk">/</c> o, een massa zaken. Maar één zelfden wortel hebbende – verkeerde opvoeding<c type="kk">/</c> jaren van averegts verkeerde levensopvatting<c type="kk">/</c> fatale invloeden van slecht gezelschap. Dit zeg ik U in vertrouwen hoor – en niet uit wanhopigheid doch opdat ge ’t U begrijpen zoudt kunnen het voor mij niet eene liefde is van maneschijn en rozegeur doch iets dat prozaisch is als Maandagochtend.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Een klein sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van <hi rend="italics">Tissot</hi> stelde voor een vrouwenfiguurtje in de sneeuw tusschen verwelkte stengels.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> <hi rend="italics">Voie des fleurs</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">voie des pleurs</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> de vrouw van mij wandelt niet meer op een voie des fleurs als toen ze jonger was en deed haar eigen zin en volgde haar neiging<c type="kk">/</c> maar t’leven is doorniger geworden voor haar en geworden een Voie des pleurs<c type="kk">/</c> vooral verl. jaar – doch dit jaar heeft ook doornen en volgende jaren ook nog – evenwel met volhouden komt ze er bovenop.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Maar soms is er een crisis – bepaald dan wanneer ik het waag een of andere fout van haar die ik al lang stillekens in ’t oog heb gehad<c type="kk">/</c> attaqueer. Zoo b.v. om maar iets te noemen ’t verstellen van ’t goed en zelf de kleeren van de kinderen maken. Maar dat eindigt daarmee dat ze op een goeden dag er aantijgt en is reeds veel verbeterd in dit opzigt en in meer andere opzigten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik moet in mij zelf ook nog zooveel veranderen maar juist ik moet zorgen zij in mij een voorbeeld heeft van werken en van geduld en dat is verdomd moeielijk broer<c type="kk">/</c> om zoo te zijn dat men indirect een ander iets voordoen kan en ik schiet ook wel eens te kort, ik moet mij zelf opvoeren tot iets beters om in haar den lust wakker te maken.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het jongske vooral maakt het echter opperbest – ’t meisje is vroeger erg ziek geweest &amp; verwaarloosd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar het kleine ventje is een mirakel van levenslust<c type="kk">/</c> schijnt nu reeds tegen maatschappelijke instellingen en conventies zich te willen opponeeren. Zoo worden zoo ver ik weet <hi rend="italics">alle</hi> kinderen met een soort broodpap gevoerd. Maar dat heeft hij met de meeste vast<c type="shy">-</c>beradenheid geweigerd<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon nog geen tanden hebbende bijt hij flink in een stuk brood en krijgt allerlei eetwaren naar binnen steeds met veel lagchen en kraaien en geluiden maken doch voor pap &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> doet hij absoluut den mond digt. Hij zit dikwijls bij me op ’t atelier op den grond in een hoek op een paar zakken of zoo<c type="kk">/</c> hij kraait tegen de teekeningen en is altijd stil op ’t atelier omdat hij naar de dingen aan den muur kijkt. o het is zoo’n gezellig ventje.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Het aantal studies neemt telkens toe – als gij komt denk ik wel ge er wat bij zult vinden om in een portefeuille op Uw kamer te zetten misschien<c type="kk">/</c> enfin dat moet ge zelf weten<c type="kk">/</c> als ge maar goed begrijpt dat waar ge zin in hebt ge natuurlijkerwijs als Uw eigendom te beschouwen hebt<c type="kp">_</c> Er moeten echter uit de studies weer andere dingen voortspruiten en betere studies ook spruiten uit de ouden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik weet het zelf niet precies<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Maar verlang wel ge ze weer eens zien zult<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Met veel belangstelling zag ik eene uitgaaf le Salon 1883<c type="kk">/</c> een eerste afl. cahier illustraties<c type="kk">/</c> sommigen weergaasch goed. Met die nieuwe manier van reproductie gemaakt.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Ik heb er op ingeteekend<c type="kk">/</c> al heb ik uitgaven genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> juist met ’t oog op ’t geen ik zelf dezer dagen met de drukinkt en lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt aan ’t maken ben. Hoor eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof bepaald dat sommige dingen van mij goed zouden doen gereproduceerd op die wijs – bepaaldelijk zoodanigen waarin de meer intense zwarten<c type="kk">/</c> door lith. krijt en drukinkt verkregen<c type="kk">/</c> zitten; ’t bruinachtig lavis dat ik in bovengenoemde bladen dikwijls tegenkom kan ik ook krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> als ge komt kunnen we misschien dit een &amp; ander bedistelen.<ptr target="#note-t-c"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">En zal ik misschien eens uitvoerig opschrijven explicatie van verschillende zaken waaromtrent ik inlichting dien te hebben en zoudt ge eenige studies van me mee kunnen nemen met dat schrijven om b.v. aan <hi rend="italics">Buhot</hi> te laten zien die dan waarschijnlijk me wel licht zal geven in eenige dingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Heb dezer dagen gelezen Un mâle van Camille Lemonnier – erg flink gedaan in de manier van Zola. Alles naar de natuur geobserveerd en alles geanalyseerd<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Zag een groote Fromentin<c type="kk">/</c> een bataille van fellahs<c type="kk">/</c> in de vitrine van G&amp;C<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Zag ook de nouveautés<c type="kk">/</c> misschien niet allen. Julien Dupré over wien ik U schreef vond ik terug in twee dingen die ik minder mooi vond en meer conventioneel dan ’t geen ik van den winter van hem zag in een illustratie.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Weet ge reeds Rappards schilderij te Amsterdam ditmaal is geaccepteerd<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is reeds laat – dank voor Uw tijdige zending – ik hoop maar dat het “brief volgt” van R<c type="kp">_</c> niet al te lang duurt of H.v.G. voorspoed met zijn veeteelt zal mogen hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">adieu – voorspoed met alle dingen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral met de vrouw<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Fromentin is toch knap – en is een <hi rend="italics">zoeker</hi> en iemand die doorvoert en conscientieus ook.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter in good order with the 50 francs enclosed. Which were a deliverance for me, at any rate a respite. I’ve also heard from friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> — but nothing definite as yet. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">A letter that’s a reply to my letter, and that he will help me and come as well, but, he writes, my health is letting me down again. Ends with: I enclose the money herewith. Postscriptum: oh, I’ll come immediately and bring it myself — I’ll come tomorrow. This is followed by a telegram the next day. Not coming, letter follows later.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">So, despite having heard something, it’s still the same as with a game of goose,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> if you remember how one can land on a goose, thus go forward, but unfortunately just then land on a new goose with its beak pointing in a direction one doesn’t want to take, and so one must count back to one’s original position. Yet it isn’t his fault, for he’s been really very ill and is still feeling the remnants or after-effects of that. Moreover, his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1755">sister</rs><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> had a fairly similar illness, and they were most concerned about her, but she recovered too. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Nonetheless, I do believe this of friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, that he does things that cost him a great deal of energy and nervous tension and aren’t worth the powder he expends on them. Thus before his illness I heard about decorations for the centenary of the Utrecht painters’ society,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and now this time it was church ornaments. By chance 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I wrote to him that I thought they were both unwise, and he fell ill last time and now this time. I would approve if he overworked himself on normal things, but, as I said, this isn’t worth the powder expended on it, and I wrote again to him: you’re a soldier and one of the few who have cartridges in their box at the present time. Use them only in cases where a shot is unavoidable. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I fear — dear brother — that the money you loaned to our dear cousin <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">H.</rs> has currently taken the form of a vicious gun dog, for instance, or some similar curiosity, since I believe he’s quite often mistaken about such purchases — and then later it’s sometimes impossible for him to bring it back from that form to the state of banknotes or to cash it in because, like other lovers of horses and hounds, he’s caught in the snares of some crooked dealer. I’m one of those who wish him as much good fortune as possible in these negotiations, and would like to see nothing better than that their outcome is that he may speedily return what he owes you. At one time there were big plans to populate the plantation<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> with countless dogs. This livestock farming is highly commendable, but at present I want to say no more about it than that I hope it may prove exceedingly profitable.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Is your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs> already discharged from hospital? But there may still be worrying days, no less grave than when she was in there. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> says rightly: a woman is an illness.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> They are changeable, Theo — they are changeable like the weather. Now those with an eye for it see something beautiful and good in <hi rend="italics">all</hi> weathers, find snow beautiful and burning sun beautiful and storm beautiful and calm beautiful, cold good and heat, are fond of all seasons and don’t want to miss a single day of the year, and are fundamentally content and resigned to things being as they are — yet even if one looks at the weather and the changing year like this — and the changing female nature in the same way — believing that in the essence of that nature, in its mysteriousness, there is a <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> — accepting where one doesn’t understand — even, I say, if one should view it in that way, our own nature and vision isn’t always and at every moment in harmony and accord with that of the woman with whom we’re united, and individually one feels either concern or dissatisfaction or vacillation, despite the belief and the good spirits or serenity one may have. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I was told by the professor who delivered her that the complete cure of my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> would take years. That is, the nervous system remains tremendously sensitive, for example, and she has that changeableness of women very strongly. The great danger is — as you will understand — tumbling back into old mistakes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">This danger, although of a moral nature, has links with the physical constitution. And I have constant and sometimes serious concerns about what I would call these lurches between getting better and lapsing back into old bad habits. Her mood can be such that it’s almost unbearable, even for me, quick-tempered, wilfully wrong, in short, sometimes I despair. It passes — and more than once <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> has said to me later — I DON’T MYSELF KNOW WHAT I’M DOING THEN.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Do you remember writing to me last year that you feared that I would be burdened with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs>? Sometimes I wish things had taken that turn. The mother is very sturdy when she wants to be, and could have done so much better than she has. Now she sometimes obstructs more than she helps. Anyway, when the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> does something wrong it’s sometimes the mother’s fault, and when the mother does wrong it’s sometimes the family who are behind the mother. Things which aren’t so bad in themselves but which prevent progress and overwhelm or neutralize better influences. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">My <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> has certain faults and defects in the way she acts — that’s bound to be the case. THAT DOES NOT MAKE HER BAD in my view. Still, those defects must be eliminated — habits of laxity, indifference, lack of activity and deftness, oh, a mass of things. But all with the same root — wrong upbringing, years of an utterly wrong view of life, fatal influences of bad company. I tell you this in confidence, mind — and not out of desperation but so that you will understand that for me this love isn’t a bed of roses, but something as prosaic as Monday morning.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">A small painting by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1394">Tissot</rs></hi> showed a figure of a woman in the snow amid withered stalks.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> <hi rend="italics">Way of flowers, way of tears</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Well, my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> no longer walks on a way of flowers as she did when she was younger and pleased herself and followed her inclination, but life has become thornier for her and become a Way of tears, especially last year — yet this year has thorns too, and the following years as well — still, by persevering she will overcome them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But sometimes there’s a crisis — particularly when I venture to raise the matter of some fault of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">hers</rs> that I’ve been quietly observing for a long time. For example, just to mention one thing, mending the clothes and making the children’s clothes herself. But that ends with her getting down to it one day, and she’s already much improved in this respect and in other respects.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I must change so much in myself too, but I must ensure that in me <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> has an example of working and of patience, and that’s damned difficult, brother, to be so that one can indirectly show someone how to do something, and I too fall short sometimes, I must raise myself to something better in order to awaken her interest.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">boy</rs>, above all, is doing extremely well, though — the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_467">girl</rs> was very ill in the past and neglected. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">little lad</rs> is a miracle of high spirits, already appears inclined to oppose social institutions and conventions. For instance, as far as I know <hi rend="italics">all</hi> children are brought up on a kind of bread porridge. But he has refused that with the greatest determination. Although as yet without teeth, he bites firmly into a piece of bread and gets down all kinds of eatables while all the time smiling and crowing and making noises, but his mouth stays firmly shut for porridge &amp;c. &amp;c. He often sits with me in the studio on the floor in a corner on a couple of sacks or something, he crows at the drawings and is always quiet in the studio because he looks at the things on the wall. Oh, he’s such an agreeable little lad.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The number of studies keeps growing — when you come I think you’ll find some to put in a portfolio in your room perhaps, anyway that’s up to you, as long as you clearly understand that you may of course regard anything you take a liking to as your own. Other things must come forth from the studies, though, and better studies come from the old ones. I myself don’t know exactly how. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But I do long for you to see them again. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I saw with great interest a publication, Le Salon 1883, a first issue of a series of illustrations, some deuced good. Done with that new way of reproduction.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I’ve subscribed to it, although I have enough expenses, with a view to what I’m doing myself at present with the printer’s ink and lithographic crayon. Listen, I definitely believe that some of my things would do well if reproduced in that way — particularly those that have the more intense blacks obtained by lithographic crayon and printer’s ink; I can also get the brownish wash that I often come across in the above prints.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Well, when you come perhaps we can arrange one thing and another. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And perhaps I’ll write down a detailed statement of several matters about which I need information, and you could take some of my studies together with that to show to <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs></hi>, for instance, who would then probably shed light on a few things for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Recently read Un mâle by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_688">Camille Lemonnier</rs> — very strongly done in the manner of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>. Everything observed from nature and everything analyzed.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Saw a big <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1019">Fromentin</rs>, a battle of fellahs, in the window at G&amp;C.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Also saw the <hi rend="italics">nouveautés</hi>, perhaps not all of them. I again came across <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1006">Julien Dupré</rs>, whom I wrote to you about, in two things that I found less beautiful and more conventional than what I saw by him in an illustrated magazine in the winter.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Did you already know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s painting has been accepted this time in Amsterdam?<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Well, it’s late already — thanks for your timely dispatch — I just hope that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">R</rs>’s ‘letter follows’ doesn’t take too long, or that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">H. v. G</rs>.’s livestock farming may prosper. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Adieu — good fortune in all things, especially the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">woman</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Still, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1019">Fromentin</rs> is clever — and a <hi rend="italics">seeker</hi>, and someone who carries through, and conscientious too.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent, who is short of money, thanks Theo for his second, ‘timely consignment’ <ref target="#l-212">(ll. 212-213)</ref>. The letter must therefore date from on or about Thursday, 10 May 1883. This tallies with the report that he has seen a painting by Eugène Fromentin in Goupil’s window; it was displayed in the week of 8 May 1883 (<ref target="#n-12">see n. 12</ref>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s illness <ref target="let290.xml">(290)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo is expecting the repayment of a loan to Hendrik van Gogh <ref target="let334.xml">(334)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Conflict with Sien’s family <ref target="let338.xml">(338)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For the telegram, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let341.xml">see letter 341</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The board of the game <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ganzenbord</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1755">Wilhelmina Elisabeth van Rappard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘kruit’ (ammunition).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For this decoration <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_434">The muse of history</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let284.xml#n-6">see letter 284, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_404">Hendrik van Gogh</rs> was co-owner of Tjiseureuh (Tjiandjoer) Tea Plantation in the Dutch East Indies.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Chapter title in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi> (book 1, chapter 2), as is the comment (book 4, chapter 9): ‘“What is woman? Sickness (Hippocrates.) – What is man? The physician”’ (Qu’est-ce que la femme? la maladie. (Hippocrate.) – Qu’est-ce que l’homme? le médecin) (Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, pp. 52-58, 345).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘while one also believes that in the essence of the changeable female nature, in its mysteriousness, there is a rationale’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Earlier Van Gogh had talked of ‘Monday morning-like sobriety’; in that context it was probably an allusion to a passage in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_216">Shirley</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_534">Charlotte Brontë</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let274.xml#n-4">see letter 274, n. 4</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>No work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1394">Tissot</rs> with this subject is known. Van Gogh may have been thinking of Tissot’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1382">Walk in the snow</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let028.xml#n-8">see letter 28, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
    
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1394">James Tissot</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Voie des fleurs, voie des pleurs (The dance of Death)</hi> (Way of flowers, way of tears (The dance of Death)), 1860 (Providence, Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1384">Ill. 1384</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>What was ‘new’ about the reproduction technique was primarily the aquatint-like effects seen in some prints in this publication. The methods for photographing lithographs, engravings and etchings and transferring them to a printing plate became ever more advanced at the end of the century, and experiments were carried out with various techniques which cannot always be identified. For this first issue ‘Au Salon de 1883’, which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_585">F.-G. Dumas</rs> published via <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Paris Illustré</hi> and in which the ‘plusieurs tons’ in the printing process were emphasized, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let341.xml#n-12">see letter 341, n. 12.</ref> Cf. also what Van Gogh writes in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let309.xml">letter 309</ref> about the special paper on which ‘snow effects’ could be achieved.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Variant of ‘bedisselen’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The work of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_688">(Antoine Louis) Camille Lemonnier</rs>, including <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_337">Un mâle</ref> </hi>(Brussels 1881), is marked by extremely realistic descriptions of repellent scenes. This book tells the story of a brutal poacher, with bestial traits, who develops a crude passion for a country girl. She lets herself be caressed by this ‘fearful male’ (mâle terrible) and gives in to his urges. When she is exhausted and tries to wrest free of him, he is enraged. After he has attacked one of her admirers, he is hit by a police bullet and dies like a wild animal in the bushes. Van Gogh’s verdict contrasts with the widespread criticism of the work of this representative of Belgian naturalism, which encountered deep repugnance. The book was mocked as ‘vulgar, obscene and immoral’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Un mâle</hi>. Ed. Raymond Trousson. Paris 1996.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1019">Eugène Fromentin</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_504">Bataille de fellahs</rs></hi> (Battle of fellahs; present whereabouts unknown) was exhibited in Goupil’s middle window for a week under the title <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gevecht</hi> (Battle), as shown by a report in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het Vaderland</hi> of 8 May 1883. On 13 April 1883 the painting was bought as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Combat</hi> for 30,000 francs by the Hague branch of Goupil-Paris and sold back to Goupil-Paris on 23 May 1883 for the same amount (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RKD</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Goupil Ledgers</hi>). Not until 4 August 1885 would it be sold to Haseltine Galleries of Philadelphia, for 27,000 francs (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GRI</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Goupil Ledgers</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The catalogue <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Publications nouvelles de la Maison Goupil &amp; Cie</hi> of April 1883 lists two new photogravures after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1006">Julien Dupré</rs>: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_505">La récolte des foins</rs></hi> (Bringing in the hay) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_506">Le goûter des faneurs</rs> </hi>(The haymakers’ meal). They measure 47 x 59 cm (p. 3, nos. 30-31). </p>

<p rend="indent">The remark that Van Gogh saw ‘perhaps not all’ of the nouveautés implies that he went into the branch on De Plaats, now that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs> was in Paris for the Salon (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let339.xml">letter 339</ref>). What he saw in the winter ‘in an illustrated magazine’ was the print <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">In the meadow</hi> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let292.xml#n-9">see letter 292, n. 9</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_332">Tile painters</rs></hi>, exhibited at the International Exhibition in Amsterdam, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let331.xml#n-14">see letter 331, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    