<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Sunday, 20 May 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let343"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b308 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>343</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>285</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>345</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-05-20">on or about Sunday, 20 May 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0308" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0308" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000386_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Met een enkel woord wilde ik U mededeelen dat Rappard bij me is geweest en ik van hem f<c type="kp">_</c> 25 heb geleend, met belofte van teruggave in ’t najaar. Erg blij was ik met zijn bezoek – hij kwam s’morgens<c type="kk">/</c> bleef tot laatsten trein s’avonds &amp; waren we den heelen dag aan ’t kijken van een &amp; ander en heeft hij nog een schets gemaakt met de drukinkt en terpentijn om het eens te probeeren. Nu ga ik morgen naar hem toe om zijn werk te zien en zijn atelier<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">’t Was een regt gezelligen dag – hij was nog al veranderd &amp; in zijn voorkomen &amp; in zijn manier van doen – ik voor mij vind hem zòò veel beter dan vroeger. Hij is breeder geworden in zijn schouders en mij dunkt in zijn opvatting van veel zaken ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geld van hem heeft mij aan veel dingen geholpen die ik noodig had<c type="kk">/</c> het was hard noodig<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik heb er o.a. groote schetsblokken voor buiten van laten maken<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik moest er geld afnemen voor een broek echter en ik heb morgen reiskosten Utrecht. Maar het helpt toch<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Verder werd ik verrast door een zeer kort bezoek van Pa<c type="kp">_</c> Noch hij noch ik spraken over het nieuws van U betreffende de vrouw. Pa dacht waarschijnlijk ik ’t nog niet wist &amp; ik hield me aan afspraak met U<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Pa had geloof ik nog al schik in de werkmansfiguren die onder handen zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Bij de blokken die ik van ’t geld van R<c type="kp">_</c> liet maken is er ook een voor aquarellen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">ik heb daar reeds dadelijk weer eens mee geprobeerd, eene hut in de duinen met een kruiwagen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> op den voorgrond<c type="kk">/</c> een figuurtje van een spitter op den achtergrond.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Och Theo, het aquarelleeren zal ik wel vatten den eenen keer of den anderen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Dezer dagen of liever weken heb ik heel prettig gezelschap gehad buiten aan een jong landmeter<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> die zoo wat scharrelde met teekenen. Hij liet mij eens teekeningen zien die ik slecht vond en hem zeide waarom ik ze slecht vond. Ik had gedacht natuurlijk daarna nooit meer van hem iets te zullen hooren – doch op een goeden dag spreekt hij me er weer over aan<c type="kk">/</c> hij had tijd nu en mogt hij eens mee naar buiten gaan. Wel Theo<c type="kk">/</c> die kerel heeft het landschapteekenen zòò gevat dat hij tegenwoordig waarachtig alleraardigste schetsen uit weiland en bosch en duin meebrengt. Hij moet echter nog een examen doen in October en zijn vader<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> wil niet hij er zoo druk aan doet. Maar juist met zijn landmetersvak kan hij het teekenen heel best vereenigen m.i.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">’t Is zoo’n slag van jongen als Rappard toen we hem voor ’t eerst leerden kennen<c type="kp">_</c> ’t geen hij maakte voor ik hem kende waren horrible geknoeide schilderijtjes<c type="kk">/</c> afschuwelijk meestal. Ik heb begonnen met hem te zeggen dat hij eerst alleen teekenen moest een tijd – ik heb hem veel dingen moeten laten teekenen waar hij geen pleizier in had maar hij heeft mij daarin vertrouwd. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> van morgen vroeg hij of hij niet eens weer zou kunnen probeeren met schilderen en dat ging <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> zeer goed 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>en heeft hij al zijn oude dingen afgeschrapt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ben naar brief van U verlangend.– gij moet van Rappard veel groeten hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Gaat het U goed en gaat het Uw patient goed. Pa zei wel ge ook hun geschreven had van komen dezen zomer. Hoe ik daarnaar verlang kan ik U moeielijk zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zag in geill. catalogus Salon la moisson van L’Hermitte<c type="kk">/</c> dat ziet er mooi uit<c type="kk">/</c> wat zit het echte van ’t werk en van het boerenfiguur er in<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop uw brief spoedig komt want ik heb ’t weer noodig. Ik zag Arnold in stad met iemand anders<c type="kk">/</c> misschien Trip<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – zij liepen met Mauve<c type="kp">_</c> Maar zag hen heel in de verte. Daar Mauve in ’t midden liep dacht ik aan le X<hi rend="super">st</hi> entre deux larrons<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> of had de groep<c type="kk">/</c> als silhouet in toon tegen een muur met zon<c type="kk">/</c> iets van iemand die door twee gendarmen wordt opgebragt<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin dat zijn zoo van die imaginaties<c type="kk">/</c> things as they <hi rend="italics">might be</hi> seen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Heb het goed kerel, met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I wanted to let you know in just a word or two that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> has been to see me and that I’ve borrowed 25 guilders from him, with the promise of repayment in the autumn. I was delighted by his visit — he came in the morning and stayed until the last train in the evening, and we spent the whole day looking at one thing and another, and he did a sketch using printer’s ink and turpentine to try it out. Now I’m going to him tomorrow to see his work and his studio.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It was a truly enjoyable day — he was rather changed in both  his appearance and his manner — for my part I find him much better like this than before. He’s broader in the shoulders, and in his views on many matters as well, I believe. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Well, the money from him has helped me to get many things I needed; it was badly needed. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I used it, among other things, to have large sketchpads made for outdoors.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I had to keep back some money for a pair of trousers, though, and tomorrow there’s the cost of travelling to Utrecht. But it still helps. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">In addition, I was surprised by a very brief visit from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>. Neither he nor I mentioned your news about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">woman</rs>. Pa probably thought I didn’t know yet, and I kept to our agreement.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was rather taken by the figures of workmen I’m working on. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Among the pads I’d made with the money from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">R.</rs> there’s one for watercolours too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I tried it out straightaway, a hut in the dunes with a wheelbarrow &amp;c. in the foreground, a figure of a digger in the background.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Ah, Theo. I’ll get the hang of watercolour one day or another.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">In the last few days, or rather weeks, I’ve had the very pleasant company outdoors of a young <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">surveyor</rs><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> who was trying his hand at drawing. He showed me drawings which I thought poor, and I told him why I thought they were poor. After that I naturally expected to hear no more from him — but one fine day he approached me again, he had time now and might he come with me outdoors? Well, Theo, that chap has got the hang of landscape drawing so well that these days he brings along truly attractive sketches of meadows and woods and dunes. He has to take an examination in October, however, and his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_370">father</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> doesn’t want him to spend so much time on it. But in my view he can easily combine his profession of surveyor with drawing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">He’s the same sort of young chap as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> when we first met him. What he did before I knew him were horribly botched paintings, generally atrocious. I began by telling him that first he should only draw for a while — I had to make him draw lots of things, which he didn’t enjoy but he trusted me in that. Well, this morning he asked if he might have another go at painting, and that went extremely well <hi rend="italics">now</hi> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> and he has scraped off all his old things. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Am longing for a letter from you. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> sends his regards. Are things going well for you, and for your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">patient</rs>? <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> did say that you’d written to them about coming this summer. I can hardly tell you how I long for that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Saw The harvest by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> in the Salon illustrated catalogue. It looks beautiful; how it captures the truth of the work and of the peasant figure.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Well, adieu, I hope your letter comes soon for I have need of it again. I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_255">Arnold</rs> in town with someone else, perhaps <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_256">Tripp</rs><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — they were walking with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>. But saw them in the far distance. Because Mauve was in the middle I thought of Christ between two thieves,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> or else the group, in dark silhouette against a sunlit wall, looked like someone being taken in by two gendarmes. Anyway, those are figments of one’s imagination, things as they <hi rend="italics">might be</hi> seen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I wish you well, old chap, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent hopes that Theo’s following remittance will come quickly ‘for I have need of it again’ <ref target="#l-94">(ll. 94-95)</ref>. The remittance of 20 May has evidently not arrived yet. In the meantime Van Rappard has paid him a visit, so the letter dates from after about 10 May, when this had yet to take place. Moreover, the letter was written one day before <ref target="let344.xml">letter 344</ref>: in the present letter it is said that Van Gogh is going to Utrecht ‘tomorrow’; <ref target="let344.xml">letter 344</ref> says that he has ‘just’ got back from Utrecht and found Theo’s letter with an enclosure. Since that letter is dated on or about Monday, 21 May, this one dates from on or about Sunday, 20 May 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On this agreement not to mention Theo’s relationship, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let339.xml">see letter 339</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This watercolour of a hut in the dunes is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">Antoine Philippe Furnée</rs>, who was training to become a surveyor; he took his exams at the end of 1883. See Op de Coul and Tellegen 1995.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_370">Hendrik Jan Furnée</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>A simplified reproduction of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La moisson</hi> (The harvest) (Saint Louis (USA), Washington University Gallery of Art), <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_217">Ill. 217</rs>, appeared in the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Catalogue illustré du Salon</hi>. Publié sous la direction de F.-G. Dumas. Paris 1883, p. 189. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_214">Ill. 214</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The art dealers <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_255">Arnoldus Petrus Eversteijn</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_256">Richard Howard Tripp</rs> (or Trip; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let033.xml#n-4">letter 33, n. 4</ref>) were the owners of Maison Arnold et Tripp, located at 8 rue Saint-Georges. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Almanach du commerce de Paris</hi> 1885. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> had dealings with them in the 1880s. See Stolwijk 1998, pp. 214-215 (n. 96). From time to time Arnold visited <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>’s studio in The Hague. Tripp replaced Van Gogh at Goupil in London in 1875 (FR b2338). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s use of French here may indicate that he was thinking of a work of art depicting Christ between the two thieves.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Possibly a quotation (cf. Matt. 13:17).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    