<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, on or about Friday, 25 May 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let346"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8368 V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>346</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R36</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>348</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-05-25">on or about Friday, 25 May 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8368" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8368" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001622_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">’t is me behoefte U nog eens opnieuw te zeggen dat ’t bezoek bij U mij zeer heeft geanimeerd. Ik ben voornemens ook eenige grootere composities op touw te zetten en een daarvan heb ik reeds op touw.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dat zijn n<c type="kp">_</c>l. <hi rend="italics">turfspitters</hi> in het duin. 1 meter bij 1/2 meter ongeveer.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Herinnert ge U ik U vertelde van dat het daar in ’t duin zoo’n mooi geval was. Het heeft iets van ’t opwerpen van een barricade. Zoodra ’k bij U vandaan kwam ben ik ook begonnen want in mijn hoofd was het reeds rijp betrekkelijk. Zoo als over eenige andere composities ik reeds veel heb gedacht en studies voor heb ook reeds.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Als ik echter ’t geld van U niet gehad had zoo zoude ik dit b.v. niet hebben kunnen doen op ’t moment.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik heb een houten passepartout laten maken op de wijs van de Uwe doch geen lijst. Ik denk er over die passepartout<c type="kk">/</c> nu nog ongeverfd<c type="kk">/</c> de kleur van notenhout te geven<c type="kp">_</c> Zòò als Uw <hi rend="italics">lijst</hi> is. Het werkt prettig als men de teekening afsluit en zoodra ik Uw teekeningen zag besloot ik ook zoo’n passepartout te nemen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">In Harpers Weekly vond ik een illustr. van Reinhardt<c type="kk">/</c> verreweg ’t beste wat ik tot heden van hem zag<c type="kk">/</c> “Washed ashore”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Een lijk is aangespoeld<c type="kk">/</c> een man is er naast geknield om te zien wie het is<c type="kk">/</c> eenige visschers &amp; vrouwen geven renseignementen omtrent den schipbreukeling aan een gendarme<c type="kp">_</c> Dus lijkt het wel wat op une épave<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> die gij hebt<c type="kk">/</c> maar er is in de teekening van R. iets van Regamey<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is een erg mooi blad.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wat is er veel moois te vinden niet waar<c type="kp">_</c>– De teek. Turfspitters heb ik nu geschetst met fusain<c type="kk">/</c> bergkrijt en autographische inkt. De grootste krachten van drukinkt heb ik er nog niet in gebezigd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Zoo is ’t aspect er van nog niet zoo krachtig als ik mij voorstel het zou kunnen worden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb op fusain alleen tegen dat het zoo ligt uitwischt, men dingen verliest die men gevonden heeft door dit uitwisschen als men niet zeer voorzigtig werkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">En ik heb behoefte niet al te voorzigtig te behoeven te zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik heb een paar plannen voor groote teekeningen amice<c type="kk">/</c> waar ge misschien wel sympathie voor zoudt hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik wou dat gij les miserables<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> reeds gelezen hadt<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik er U beter over kunnen spreken want misschien zoudt gij door de zelfde dingen die mij telkens in de gedachten komen getroffen worden. dat zou me niet verwonderen<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Ik kende dat boek vroeger reeds maar sedert ik het nu weer heb gelezen komt veel er uit mij telkens in de gedachten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Zoowel gij als ik hebben op school zoowat geschiedenis geleerd maar als ’t U gaat als mij zoo is U dat niet genoeg en is het te droog en te conventioneel<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij zoude wenschen het tijdvak 1770 b.v. tot nu toe duidelijk te kunnen overzien vooral. De fransche revolutie is het allergrootste modern evenement waar alles om draait<c type="kk">/</c> ook van den tegenwoordigen tijd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Als ik lees iets als de Londen en Parijs van Dickens (Tale of two cities)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en daar over denk zoo vind ik men uit dat tijdvak van de revolutie zulke prachtige motieven kan nemen voor teekeningen<c type="kp">_</c> Niet direkt op de eigentlijke geschiedenis betrekking hebbende zoozeer<c type="kk">/</c> als wel incidenten van het gewone leven en het aspect der dingen zoo als ze vroeger waren. Neem de teekening van Howard Pyle en die andere van Abbey die ik onlangs U liet zien<c type="kk">/</c> X<hi rend="super">mas</hi> in old New york<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> X<hi rend="super">mas</hi> in old Virginia.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> in die dagen beginnende en zijne gedachten latende gaan tot heden<c type="kk">/</c> overziet men een tijdvak waarin alles veranderd is<c type="kp">_</c> En verschillende momenten zijn bijzonder interessant. En vind men in verschillende fransche en Engelsche boeken zoo aangrijpend en zoo degelijk beschreven<c type="kk">/</c> zóó dat het mogelijk wordt zich de dingen van vroeger duidelijk voor te stellen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Dickens<c type="kk">/</c> die meestal zijn eigen tijd beschreef<c type="kk">/</c> kon het niet laten de Tale of two cities te schrijven<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en telkens in zijn werk ziet men hij beschrijvingen uit vroeger dagen tusschen in lascht. b.v. een beschrijving van de Londensche straten vóór er lantaarns waren.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vrage<c type="kk">/</c> zou men hollandsche motieven kunnen vinden b.v. uit den tijd dat de eerste lantaarns werden geplaatst of vóór dat ze er waren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Stel U eens voor een kerkbank of iets van een begrafenis zoo uit den tijd van 1815<c type="kp">_</c> Eene verhuizing<c type="kk">/</c> een wandelplaats<c type="kk">/</c> een straat op winterdag uit die tijdsperiode of iets later<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">In les miserables<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon een later tijdvak behandelende<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> vind ik wat ik zoek<c type="kk">/</c> aspecten van vroeger die mij opwekken om te verzinnen hoe ’t er uitzag in den tijd van mijn overgrootvader of niet later terug dan mijn grootvader zelfs. Quatre vingt treize van Hugo was ’t geen door alle teekenaars van de Graphic zamen geillustreerd werd.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Caldecott doet het ook zoo echt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik wou wel eens de impressie zien die Quatre vingt treize en les miserables op U maken zouden. Dat ge ’t mooi zoudt vinden weet ik vast en zeker. Ik zag toen ik bij U was een paar brokken van de stad<c type="kk">/</c> die ik mij voorstelde geanimeerd door figuren uit den ouden tijd. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> we spreken waarschijnlijk nog wel eens over teekeningen uit een vroegere periode. Ik hoop ’t er van komt ge zoo als ge zeidet dezen zomer nog eens naar hier komt<c type="kp">_</c> onmogelijk is het niet mijn broer uit Parijs U ook eens bezoekt dezen zomer<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou hij Uw werk weer eens zag en ik wou we als hij hier was zamen eens weer naar U toe gingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Met een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I need to tell you again that the visit to you raised my spirits enormously. I intend to make a start on some larger compositions too, and I’ve already started on one of them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">That is <hi rend="italics">peat diggers</hi> in the dunes. About 1 metre by 1/2 metre.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Do you recall my telling you that there was such a beautiful sight there in the dunes? It looks a little like the raising of a barricade. As soon as I left you I started work, for it was already fairly ripe in my head. Just as I’ve already thought a lot about some other compositions, and already have studies for them too. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">If I hadn’t had the money from you, however, I wouldn’t have been able to do this, for example, at this time. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ve had a wooden passe-partout made like yours but no frame. I’m thinking of giving the passe-partout, unpainted as yet, the colour of walnut. Like your <hi rend="italics">frame</hi>. The effect is pleasing when one encloses the drawing and as soon as I saw your drawings I decided to have a similar passe-partout.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">In Harper’s Weekly I found an illustration by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1297">Reinhart</rs>, by far the best I’ve seen by him up to now, ‘Washed ashore’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">A body has been washed up, a man is kneeling beside it to see who it is, a few fishermen and women give information about the shipwreck victim to a gendarme. So it looks somewhat like Victim of a shipwreck<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> that you have, but the drawing by R. has something of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1302">Régamey</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> for example. It’s a very fine print. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">What beautiful things there are to be found, don’t you think? I’ve now sketched the drawing Peat diggers in charcoal, natural chalk and autographic ink. I haven’t yet used the strongest strengths of printer’s ink on it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So it doesn’t yet look as forceful as I imagine it could be. The only thing I have against charcoal is that it wipes off so easily; one loses things one has found because of this wiping off unless one works very carefully. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And I feel a need not to have to be all that careful. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I have a few plans for large drawings, my dear friend, for which you might perhaps have some sympathy. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I wish you had read Les misérables,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> then I would be better able to discuss it with you, for you might perhaps be struck by the same things that keep coming into my mind. That wouldn’t surprise me. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I knew that book long ago, but many things from it keep coming to mind now that I’ve read it again. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Both you and I learned some history at school, but if you’re like me that’s not enough for you, as well as being too dry and too conventional. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Now for my part I’d wish to have a clear view of the period from 1770, say, to the present. The French Revolution is the greatest modern event on which everything turns, in the present age too. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">When I read something like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs>’s London and Paris (Tale of two cities)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and reflect on it, I believe one could choose such splendid subjects for drawings from that period of the Revolution. Not directly related to actual history so much as to incidents of ordinary life and the look of things as they were in the past. Take the drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1285">Howard Pyle</rs> and that other one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> that I showed you recently, Xmas in old New York,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Xmas in old Virginia.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now, starting in those days and letting one’s thoughts wander up to today, one surveys a period in which everything has changed. And several moments are particularly interesting. And one finds them described so compellingly and so thoroughly in various French and English books that it becomes possible to picture the things of the past clearly.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs>, who usually described his own times, couldn’t help writing the Tale of two cities,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and one sees repeatedly in his work that he inserts descriptions from earlier days, for instance a description of the London streets before there were street-lamps.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Question: could one find Dutch subjects from, say, the time when the first street-lamps were put up or from before they existed? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Just imagine a pew or a funeral, say, from the year 1815. A removal, a promenade, a street on a winter’s day from that period or a little later. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">In Les misérables, although it deals with a later period,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I find what I am seeking, aspects of the past that stimulate me to imagine how things looked in the age of my great-grandfather, or no further back than my grandfather even. Quatre-vingt-treize by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Hugo</rs> was the one that was illustrated by all The Graphic draughtsmen together.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_924">Caldecott</rs> also does it so truly. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I’d like to see what impression Quatre-vingt-treize and Les misérables made on you. I don’t doubt for a moment that you’d find them beautiful. When I visited you I saw a few parts of the city which I imagined to myself enlivened by figures from ancient times. Well, we’ll probably talk about drawings from an earlier era another time. I hope it turns out that, as you said, you come here again this summer. It isn’t impossible that my brother from Paris may also visit you this summer. I would like him to see your work again and I would like us to come to you together while he’s here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">With a handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes to Van Rappard ‘again’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref> about his visit to his studio in Utrecht, which took place on or about Monday, 21 May 1883. Inspired by that visit, Van Gogh is now working on a large drawing, and has had a wooden passepartout made, so that a few days must have passed. For this reason the letter is dated on or about Friday, 25 May 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s visit to Van Rappard’s studio <ref target="let344.xml">(344)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>This may be <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>), which is only known from the photograph Van Gogh had made of it (see <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let362.xml">letter 362</ref>). Later on in the letter he says that the drawing has been done ‘in fusain, natural chalk and autographic ink’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1297">Charles Stanley Reinhart</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Washed</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">ashore</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> 27 (20 January 1883), pp. 40-41. The engraving was also in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 27 (20 January 1883), Supplement, between pp. 58 and 59. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1258">Ill. 1258</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_873">Fernand Blayn</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Une épave</hi> (Victim of a shipwreck), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 74 (15 November 1879), pp. 312-313. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_591">Ill. 591</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>In this context <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1302">Félix Régamey</rs> is more likely to be meant than his brother <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1301">Guillaume</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml#n-12">see letter 333, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Charles Dickens</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_164">A tale of two cities</ref></hi> is set in London and Paris during the French Revolution.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1285">Howard Pyle</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1224">Christmas morning in Old New York</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let279.xml#n-8">see letter 279, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Edwin Austin Abbey</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_473">Christmas in old Virginia</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let304.xml#n-37">see letter 304, n. 37.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh may have based this remark on the ‘Preface’ to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_164">A tale of two cities</ref></hi>, which reveals <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs>’s powerful compulsion to write the novel: ‘A strong desire was upon me then, to embody it [= the story] in my own person ... Throughout its execution, it has had complete possession of me; I have so far verified what is done and suffered in these pages, as that I have certainly done and suffered it all myself’. Dickens hoped that his book would contribute towards a better understanding of ‘that terrible time’. See Dickens 1859, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">v</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A tale of two cities</hi> there are frequent references to the dark streets and to extra lighting from candles, candlesticks and torches. See e.g. book 1, chapters 1 and 3. In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_324">Barnaby Rudge. A tale of the riots of ‘Eighty’</ref></hi>, which is set in London in 1775-1780, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_580">Dickens</rs> writes: ‘the streets of London ... were, one and all, from the broadest and best to the narrowest and least frequented, very dark. The oil and cotton lamps, though regularly trimmed twice or trice in the long winter nights, burnt feebly at the best; and at a late hour, when they were unassisted by the lamps and candles in the shops, cast but a narrow track of doubtful light upon the footway, leaving the projecting doors and house-fronts in the deepest gloom.’ Ed. London [1874], p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi> begins in 1815 and is set in the time of the Restoration, the July Revolution and the Workers Uprisings in Paris in 1832-1834.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_278">Quatre-vingt-treize</ref></hi>, which is set shortly after the French Revolution, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let286.xml#n-9;">see letter 286, n. 9;</ref> for the illustrations in this novel, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let304.xml#n-75">see letter 304, n. 75.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    