<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 30 May 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let347"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b310 V/1962 (sheet 1) and d328 V/1969 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>347</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>287</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>349</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-05-30">on or about Wednesday, 30 May 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0310" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0310" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000388_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="d 0328" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001679_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001679_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="d 0328 V/1969" xml:id="surf-extra-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001679_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001679_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Deze week heb ik druk gewerkt aan een groote teekening<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> waar ik U eens een krabbeltje van stuur<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Toen ik met Rappard sprak zei hij “die allereerste teekeningen van je waren toch goed<c type="kk">/</c> je moest in dat zelfde genre toch weer eens iets maken”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Weet gij nog dat heel in ’t begin ik U eens een soort schetsen stuurde<c type="kk">/</c> “Winter Tale”<c type="kk">/</c> Shadows passing<c type="kk">/</c> enz<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <hi rend="italics">Gij</hi> zeidet toen ter tijde gij vondt de actie der figuren niet genoeg was uitgedrukt – herinnert ge U wel. Dit nu was volkomen waar, maar nu heb ik sedert een paar jaar uitsluitend gesjouwd op ’t figuur om er wat actie en ook wat structuur in te krijgen. En juist door dat sjouwen was de animo om te composeeren en de imaginatie eens weer te laten werken me wat vergaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Toen Rappard met een zekere warmte over dien allereersten tijd sprak<c type="kk">/</c> werd het weer wakker. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> hoe oppervlakkig dit schetsje ook zij<c type="kk">/</c> zoo geloof ik ge er in terug zult vinden iets van dat allereerste maar juist met meer actie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dit zijn <hi rend="italics">Turfspitters in ’t duin</hi> – de eigentlijke teekening is nu geworden 1 meter bij 1/2 meter ongeveer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">’t Is een almagtig mooi geval in de natuur<c type="kk">/</c> waar een oneindig aantal motieven uit te halen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik was er deze laatste weken veel en heb er allerlei studies van. Rappard zag studies er van maar toen hij hier was wisten we nog niet hoe het zamen te brengen. Maar deze compositie is sedert ontstaan. En toen ik ’t eenmaal zoowat bijeen gevonden had vlotte het nogal en zat ik s’morgens 4 uur er al aan te werken op den zolder.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu is ’t mijn plan<c type="kk">/</c> eenmaal weer begonnen zijnde aan het composeeren<c type="kk">/</c> er meer uit te voeren die ik in ’t hoofd heb en reeds studies voor heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En heb er me voor ingerigt met ramen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> te laten maken en ook een groote houten lijst om in de lijst te kunnen werken en het af te sluiten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik denk dat misschien gij er niet op tegen zult hebben deze als ze af is eens mee te nemen om aan de lui van de illustraties te laten kijken. En meer pleizier zult hebben van iets dergelijks dan van de losse studies<c type="kp">_</c> Ik weet het echter niet vooruit &amp; kunnen we zien als ge komt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Maar kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben blij dat ik vóór ge komt deze nog heb kunnen opzetten en kunnen we beter over de toekomst eens praten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb zoo zeer behoefte iets gezelligs te maken<c type="kk">/</c> iets dat te denken geeft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ge weet het dat een van de schilderijen die ik van al wat bestaat ’t allermooiste vind is la promenade sur les remparts van Leys<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>’t Is niet die rigting echter die tegenwoordig aan de orde van den dag is maar het sentiment dat daarin is<c type="kk">/</c> is iets eeuwigs en men kan de werkelijkheid<c type="kk">/</c> de natuur op verschillende wijzen opvatten en ook nu terugvinden wat in de dagen van Leys meer algemeen misschien gezocht en gevoeld werd dan wel nu.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het kost echter een aanhoudende studie om ’t geen men voelt uit te drukken en den vorm uit te drukken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik kan U niet zeggen hoe het mij geanimeerd heeft Rappard weer eens te zien, zijn werk vind ik toch zoo goed, en toen ik bij hem was zei hij me ook dat het hem opgefrischt had bij mij te zijn. Door met elkaar te praten hebben we nieuwe gedachten gekregen. Ik wenschte wel dat als gij hier in Holland kwaamt gij ook Rappard weer eens ontmoetet<c type="kp">_</c> Zoowel op zijn atelier als het mijne zoudt ge geloof ik een indruk krijgen die meer heeft van ’t geen men vroeger op de ateliers zag dan wel van tegenwoordig<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik geloof toch dat het in Uw geest zou zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Rappard heeft op dit moment een soort smidse<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en dezen winter maakte hij het blindengesticht<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en de tegelschilders.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> In allen is stijl en het is leuk en degelijk dunkt me<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ge begrijpt dat ik met een en ander nog al verschotten<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> heb. Als ik ’t geld van R. niet gehad had zou ik dit niet hebben kunnen ondernemen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">En al heb ik er studies voor, toch voor dit en voor anderen heb ik voortdurend model noodig en hangt het vorderen er van af of ik geld heb om ze te nemen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik heb nog een paar anderen in t’hoofd maar ik begin weer en gêne te zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ge ziet dat als ik eens een buitenkansje heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik er ook gebruik van maak om iets te doen dat anders een miskraam zou worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Dus als het eens kan<c type="kk">/</c> stuur nog eens iets buitengewoons.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20"><hi rend="italics">Dit</hi><c type="kk">/</c> n.l. de turfspitters<c type="kk">/</c> is een ander landschap dan precies “le paradou”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> En wilt ge gelooven dat ik toch ook voor le paradou gevoel heb. Wie weet of ik op een goeden dag zoo’n paradou geval nog niet eens opvat<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Schrijf spoedig als ge nog niet reeds geschreven hebt<c type="kp">_</c> Als ge de teek. zien zult<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik niet gij die <hi rend="italics">te groot</hi> zult vinden. De proportie die alzoo de figuren krijgen is zòò dat men er wat kracht op doen kan en ze vereischen men ze ieder afzonderlijk bestudeere. Ik heb studies voor alle figuren die er op voorkomen.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ik heb deze teek. gemaakt met fusain en bergkrijt en drukinkt. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> heb het goed en schrijf spoedig. Ik ben laatst met v.d. Weele in ’t duin geweest. We vonden daar een plek waar de duinen afgegraven worden voor zand<c type="kk">/</c> een mooi ding met kerels en kruiwagens.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>

</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">This week I’ve been busy working on a large drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> a scratch of which I’m sending.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> When I talked to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, he said ‘those very first drawings of yours were good after all, you should do something in that genre again’. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Do you remember that in the very beginning I once sent you sketches of a sort, ‘Winter Tale’, Shadows passing, etc.?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <hi rend="italics">You</hi> said at the time that you thought the action of the figures was insufficiently expressed — do you remember? Now that was entirely true, but for a few years now I’ve been toiling solely on the figure in order to get some action and also some structure into it. And precisely because of that toil, I had rather lost my enthusiasm for composing and for making my imagination work once more. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">It was reawakened when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> talked about those early days with a certain warmth. Now, however superficial this little sketch may be, I believe you’ll find something of the earliest time in it, but just with more action. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">This is <hi rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> — the drawing itself is now about 1 metre by 1/2 metre. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It’s a wonderfully beautiful sight in nature, from which an infinite number of subjects can be taken. I went there often these last few weeks and have all kinds of studies of it. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> saw studies of it, but when he was here we didn’t know how to bring it together. This composition came about later. And once I’d finally got it all just about together, it went quite smoothly, and at 4 o’clock in the morning I was already working on it in the attic.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Now that I’ve begun composing again, my plan is to execute more things which I have in my mind and for which I already have studies. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And have made arrangements for that by having stretching frames &amp;c. made, and also a big wooden frame so that I can work in the frame and enclose the drawing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I believe you may not be opposed to taking this one when it’s finished to show to the people at the illustrated magazines. And will take greater pleasure from something like this than from separate studies. I don’t know in advance, though, and we can see when you come. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But, old chap, I’m glad that I’ve been able to start work on this before you come, and we’ll be better able to talk about the future.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I feel such a need to make something pleasing, something that makes one think.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You know that one of the paintings I think the finest of all in existence is The walk on the ramparts by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Leys</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> It isn’t that movement, though, that’s the order of the day at present, but the sentiment in it is something eternal, and one can conceive reality, nature, in different ways, and even now recognize what was perhaps sought and felt more generally in Leys’s time than it is today. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But it takes constant study to express what one feels and to capture the form.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I can’t tell you how much it raised my spirits to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> again, I think his work is really so good, and when I was at his place he also told me that it had refreshed him to visit me. Through talking to each other we’ve got new ideas. I would like you to see Rappard again when you’re here in Holland. Both in his studio and mine I believe you would get an impression based more on what one saw in the studios in the past than on what there is at present. Yet I believe it would still be in your spirit. At the moment Rappard has a sort of forge,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and this winter he did the institute for the blind<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and the tile painters.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> They all have style, and are pleasing and solid, it seems to me.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">You’ll understand that, what with one thing and another, I’ve had quite a few outgoings. If I hadn’t had the money from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">R.</rs>, I wouldn’t have been able to undertake this.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And although I have studies for it, I need models continually for this and for others, and progress depends on whether I have the money to take them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I have a few others in my mind, but I’m beginning to run short again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">As you see, when I have a windfall, I make use of it to do something that would otherwise miscarry.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">So if at all possible, send something extra as well. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"><hi rend="italics">This</hi>, namely the peat diggers, is a different kind of landscape from ‘le paradou’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> And please believe that I also feel something for le paradou. Who knows, one fine day I might just tackle such a paradou.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Write soon if you haven’t written already. When you see the drawing, I don’t think you’ll think it <hi rend="italics">too big</hi>. The proportions the figures acquire in this way are such that one can do them with some force, and they demand to be studied separately. I have studies for all the figures in it.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I did this drawing in charcoal and natural chalk and printer’s ink. Well, I wish you well and write soon. I went into the dunes with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> recently. There we found a place where the dunes are being levelled for sand, a fine sight with fellows and wheelbarrows. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref> of Sunday, 3 June Van Gogh writes that he has been working furiously over the past week. The present letter says that ‘this week’ he has been working hard (namely on his drawing <hi rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi>), which places this letter in the week from 28 May to 2 June 1883. The plea ‘Write soon if you haven’t  written already’ <ref target="#l-117">(l. 117)</ref> indicates a date shortly before an expected remittance (for which Theo was thanked on 3 June). Accordingly, we have dated the letter on or about Wednesday, 30 May 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s visit to Van Rappard’s studio <ref target="let344.xml">(344)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Possibly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>): <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let346.xml#n-1">see letter 346, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The enclosed sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_94">F 1030 / JH 364</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>It is not certain which sketches Van Gogh means here; they are probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">On the road</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_15">F - / JH Juv. 15</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">In front of the embers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_14">F - / JH Juv. 16</rs>), which were enclosed with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let162.xml">letter 162</ref> in January 1881. He wrote then that he had also drawn ‘a man sweeping snow’ and ‘a walk in the snow’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let162.xml#l-14">letter 162, l. 14</ref>). ‘Etc.’ may refer to these. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Henri Leys</rs>, ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1055">The walk in the snow</rs>’, which is part of a decoration of 1855 in the dining room of his home in Antwerp, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let354.xml#n-3">see letter 354, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s drawings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_508">Silversmith workshop</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-6">see letter 344, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For the subject, cf. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_507">Ward in the Institute for the Blind in Utrecht</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-5">letter 344, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
      
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_332">Tile painters</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let331.xml#n-14">see letters 331, n. 14</ref> and  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-7">344, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘uitgaven’ (outgoings).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            
      
<p>For the reference to ‘Le Paradou’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_253">La faute de l’abbé Mouret</ref></hi> (1875) , <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-1">see letter 344, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
      
<p>These studies are not known. Cf. for the poses of several figures in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> the drawings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2410">F 906 / JH 260</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_429">F 908 / JH 258</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Scheveningen woman with a wheelbarrow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_633">F 1021 / JH 362</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man breaking up the soil</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_982">F 1307 / JH 853</rs>) and the lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Digger</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2412">F 1656 / JH 262</rs>) among others.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    