<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Thursday, 7 June 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let351"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b314 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>351</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>291</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>353</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-06-07">on or about Thursday, 7 June 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0314" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0314" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000395_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Vandaag ontving ik een brief van t’huis en ik wilde<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon in dien brief Pa over U niet sprak<c type="kk">/</c> U er toch over spreken omdat in de gegevenen gij misschien wel iets zoudt willen weten omtrent de stemming waarin zij zijn<c type="kk">/</c> buiten en behalve wat zij direkt aan U zouden schrijven. En is ’t mijn impressie ge voorloopig daaromtrent heel kalm kunt zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Den brief in kwestie is Pa’s eerste schrijven sedert zijn bezoek<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en is zeer gemoedelijk en hartelijk en ging vergezeld van een pakje waarin een jas<c type="kk">/</c> een hoed<c type="kk">/</c> een pakje sigaren<c type="kk">/</c> een koek<c type="kk">/</c> een couponnetje.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">In den brief stond het plan van een preek waarvan ik den tekst<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> verreweg het mooiste vond en die me minder trof dan later een enkel woordje over eene begrafenis van een boerenarbeider.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En verder dat Moe te Prinsenhage<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> was en huiselijke bijzonderheden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wel<c type="kk">/</c> waarom ik U dit nu zoo uitvoerig mededeel is dat gij er uit ziet dat er geen bepaalde overspanning is of iets abnormaals<c type="kk">/</c> maar wel kreeg ik den indruk Pa veeleer in passieve of lijdelijke stemming was<c type="kk">/</c> den gemoedelijk melankolieken kant uit<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan men veronderstellen zoude als men alleen zou af gaan op de expressies van bezwaren maken die ge me geschreven hebt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik denk dus dat die woorden meer bedoeld zijn als raad of waarschuwing (m.i<c type="kp">_</c> après tout een raad die niet op een soliden grond rust en geen steek houdt) maar niet zoo zeer een blijk van bepaalde tegenkanting of oppositie tegen een vast besluit van U.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Denkende zij misschien ge nog niet vast besloten zijt of meenende zij dat gij zelf er niet genoeg over gedacht hebt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Omdat in vorig schrijven ik zoo sterk afkeurde wat Pa gezegd had<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – en dat ook nu afkeur<c type="kk">/</c> bepaald van tegenovergestelde meening zijnde in zooverre ik ’t niet àpropos reken in dit geval bezwaren in zake van geld en godsdienst te opperen – zoo wilde ik toch in dit opzigt mijn woorden verzachten dat ik zoude meenen dat hier kwestie is van eene fout (m<c type="kp">_</c>i<c type="kp">_</c> altans een fout) die meer in Pa’s woorden dan in zijn hart en stemming zit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En heb ik op ’t hart er eens met U over te praten dat Pa een oud man is en zoo innig gehecht aan U en gij geloof ik bevinden zult dat hij zich schikken zal naar Uw opvatting als ’t niet anders kan<c type="kk">/</c> ook al strijdt die met de zijne<c type="kk">/</c> doch zich onmogelijk zou kunnen schikken naar vervreemding van U of vermindering van omgang enz<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">En uit een humaan oogpunt bekeken neem ik terug mijn opinie: “door zóó te spreken hebben zij getoond Uw vertrouwen niet waard te zijn en hoeft ge m.i<c type="kp">_</c> hen er niet verder in te kennen” of iets dergelijks dat ik toen geschreven heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet het niet precies.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Maar begrijp me wel<c type="kk">/</c> niet omdat ik ’t geen zij zeiden minder afkeur doch omdat ik meen men ’t in dit geval zoo zwaar niet tillen moet en er geen urgentie is er tegen te velde te trekken zoolang het woorden blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het coupeeren door iets te zeggen als b.v<c type="kp">_</c>: “ge ziet de toekomst wel wat somber in” en “kunt toch van me niet vergen dat ik handele als of de wereld op vergaan stond” is in dezen geloof ik wel zoo wijs als hun woorden zwaar te tillen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">’t Komt mij voor Pa echter ietwat melankoliek is en misschien wat tobt over U en zich sombere dingen voorstelt – maar nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> Pa schrijft er geen syllabe direkt over en sprak er geen woord over bij gelegenheid van zijn bezoek. Maar dat <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> er over spreken is ook ietwat abnormaal juist. Enfin – ik ken Pa ook zoo min of meer en meen indices van ietwat melankolie te zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Wilt ge dit verhelpen<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf zoowat luchtig en opgewekt en schrijf over Uw bezoek van dezen zomer als zijnde ’t zeker ge hun weldra zien zult (al is ’t dat ge ’t zelf nog niet weet hoe ge Uw komst schipperen zult wat den tijd betreft)<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Want misschien<c type="kk">/</c> misschien heeft Pa zelf de bewustheid van wat te ver gegaan te zijn of onrust er over hoe ge ’t op zult nemen of vreest ge niet komen zult.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik weet natuurlijk het regte niet en gis er maar naar, en alleen ik denk zoo<c type="kk">/</c> Pa is een oud man en verdient dat men hem wat opvroolijke als ’t kan.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Dat m.i. ge de vrouw trouw behoort te zijn weet ge genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> er is geen sprake ik daaromtrent iets minder zoude zeggen dan ik deed maar doe gij wat regt is en neem Pa als hij zich vergist ’t niet kwalijk. Dat wou ik zeggen. Spreek er niet eens over dat hij zich vergist tenzij hij er op doorga<c type="kk">/</c> misschien komt hij van zelf er van terug<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> nog een woordje over ’t werk<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">ik heb vandaag permissie aangevraagd om schetsen te mogen maken in het oude mannen- &amp; vrouwengesticht<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> n.l. van de mannenzaal<c type="kk">/</c> van de vrouwenzaal en van den tuin<c type="kp">_</c> Ik was er van daag. Ik schetste uit het raam een oud tuinmannetje bij een krommen appelboom en de werkplaats van den timmerman van het huis<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> waar ik thee dronk met twee weesmannen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">In de mannenzaal kan ik komen als bezoeker<c type="kk">/</c> ’t was erg echt<c type="kk">/</c> onbeschrijfelijk echt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Een kereltje met langen mageren hals in een stoel op rolletjes o.a. was onbetaalbaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">In die timmermanswerkplaats<c type="kk">/</c> met kijkje op koelen<c type="kk">/</c> groenen tuin met die twee oudjes<c type="kk">/</c> was ’t net een geval als b.v. die phot<c type="kp">_</c> van Bingham naar dat kleine schilderijtje van Meissonier<c type="kk">/</c> die twee pastoors die zitten te drinken.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Misschien weet ge wat ik bedoel. Of ik nu echter permissie zal krijgen is niet geheel zeker en moet worden aangevraagd aan den advokaat diaken<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik gedaan heb en antwoord moet halen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Overigens ben ik aan ’t zoeken van de teekening van den mestvaalt.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> ’k schreef U ik hoop had een scheveningschen schoermantel<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb dien ook en een ouden hoed op den koop toe maar die is niet bijzonder mooi<c type="kk">/</c> maar de mantel is superbe en ben ik dadelijk mee begonnen te werken. Ben daar even blij mee als in der tijd met den zuidwester.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">En met die schets van de mestvaalt ben ik zóó ver dat ik ’t schapenhok achtige effekt van binnen tegen buiten – ’t licht onder de sombere loodsen – er zoowat in heb<c type="kk">/</c> en de groep vrouwen die hun aschbakken leegen begint zich te ontwikkelen en vorm te krijgen.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ’t op en neer gaan van de kruiwagens en de chiffonniers met mestvorken<c type="kk">/</c> dat gescharrel onder de loodsen<c type="kk">/</c> moet nog uitgedrukt worden zonder dat het effekt van licht en bruin van ’t geheel verloren ga<c type="kp">_</c>– Integendeel moet het er door versterkt worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">’k Denk ge uit Uw eigen ook wel soortgelijke opvatting van Pa’s woorden zult hebben en ik U dus niets nieuws zeg<c type="kk">/</c> maar wegens ik er zoo scherp over sprak wilde ik ge tegelijk weten zoudt ik zulks niet uit pleizier doe maar met leedwezen<c type="kk">/</c> en blij zoude zijn als met wat bonhomie den vrede kon behouden worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Dezen winter was Pa evenzeer als nu er op tegen betrekkelijk ik met de vrouw was<c type="kk">/</c> toch stuurde hij een warmen soort mantel<c type="kk">/</c> “of die mij soms te pas kon komen”<c type="kk">/</c> niet preciseerende waarvoor maar blijkbaar met de gedachte “ze mogt eens kou hebben”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> dat is toch het regte en voor één zoo’n daad zou ik met pleizier 3 mud<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> woorden over mijn kant laten gaan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Want zelf hoor ik ook niet tot hen die in woorden niet falen – dezulken zouden volmaakt zijn – en heb niet de minste pretentie op volmaaktheden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">En wilde dus U daarop wijzen<c type="kk">/</c> in elk geval heeft Pa<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> tegen mijn zijn met de vrouw bezwaar<c type="kk">/</c> zeker NOG VEEL MEER dan wat U betreft<c type="kk">/</c> en ondanks dat dacht hij toch van den winter zeker iets als: “dat beroerde wijf – maar ze moet toch geen kou hebben”<c type="kp">_</c> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> zoo alligt in Uw geval: “dat arme roomsche wijf moet toch niet alleen zijn” of zoo iets. Maak U dus niet ongerust<c type="kk">/</c> heb goeden moed en stel hen gerust.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Vincent </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Today I received a letter from home and I wanted to talk to you about it, although <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> doesn’t mention you in the letter, because in the circumstances you might perhaps like to know something about their state of mind, above and beyond what they may write to you directly. And my impression is that for the present you may be entirely at ease on that score. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The letter in question is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s first since his visit<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and is very amiable and cordial and was accompanied by a package containing a coat, a hat, a packet of cigars, a cake, a money order.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">In the letter was the outline of a sermon, by far the best part of which I thought was the biblical text,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and which made less of an impression on me than a few words about the funeral of a farm labourer later on. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And otherwise that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> was at Princenhage<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and domestic details. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Well, the reason I’m telling you this at such length is so that you’ll see from it that there’s no particular tension or anything abnormal; rather, I got the impression that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s mood was more passive or resigned, tending towards good-natured melancholy, more so than one would expect if one were to go only by the expressions of objections you wrote to me about. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">So I think those words were intended more as advice or warning (advice that in the end has no solid grounds in my view, and doesn’t hold water) and less as a sign of definite resistance or opposition to your firm decision. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">They may think that you haven’t yet made up your mind, or they may believe that you haven’t given it enough thought. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Because in my last letter I disapproved so strongly of what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> had said<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — and still disapprove of it now, being decidedly of the opposite opinion inasmuch as I don’t consider it appropriate in this case to raise objections to do with money and religion — I wanted to soften my words, in the sense that I believe that it’s a question here of a fault (at any rate a fault in my view) that lies more in Pa’s words than in his heart and mood. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And I have in mind to talk to you about how <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> is an old man and so deeply fond of you, and you’ll find, I believe, that he’ll accept your view if there’s no alternative, even if it conflicts with his own, yet couldn’t possibly accept estrangement from you or having less contact, etc.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And adopting a humane point of view, I take back my opinion: ‘by saying that, they have shown they are unworthy of your trust and in my eyes you needn’t confide in them any further’, or something similar that I wrote then, I don’t remember exactly.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> But don’t misunderstand me, not because I disapprove less of what they said, but because I believe that in this case one shouldn’t take it too seriously, and there’s no pressing need to take up arms against it as long as it remains only words. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Cutting it short by saying something like, for example, ‘You take a rather gloomy view of the future’ and ‘can hardly demand from me that I act as if the end of the world were imminent’ is wiser in this case, I believe, than taking their words very seriously.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">It seems to me that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s a little melancholy, though, and is perhaps fretting a little about you and imagining gloomy things — but again Pa writes not a syllable about it directly, and said not a word about it at the time of his visit. But <hi rend="italics">not</hi> talking about it is in fact also rather abnormal. Anyway — I, too, know Pa quite well, and believe I can see signs of some melancholy. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">If you want to help him, write quite lightly and cheerfully, and write about your visit this summer as though it’s certain you’ll see them again soon (even though you may not know yourself yet how you’ll fit your visit in as regards the time). </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">For perhaps, perhaps <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> himself is conscious of having gone a little too far, or worried about how you’ll take it, or afraid that you won’t come. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Of course I don’t know how matters stand and am only guessing, but I do think this, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> is an old man and deserves to have people cheer him up if they can.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">You know well enough that in my view you ought to be loyal to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">woman</rs>; there’s no question of my saying anything less about that than I did, but do what’s right and don’t blame <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> if he’s mistaken. That’s what I wanted to say. Don’t even refer to the fact that he’s mistaken unless he keeps going on, perhaps he’ll retract of his own accord.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Now a word about the work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Today I asked for permission to draw sketches in the old men’s and old women’s home,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> namely the men’s ward, the women’s ward and the garden. I was there today. From the window I sketched an old gardener by a crooked apple tree, and the workshop of the home’s carpenter,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> where I drank tea with two orphan men. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I can go into the men’s ward as a visitor. It was very real, inexpressibly real. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">A small chap with a long, thin neck in a chair on rollers, among others, was priceless. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">In the carpenter’s workshop, with a view of the cool, green garden with those two old boys, it was just like the scene in, for example, that photo by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_877">Bingham</rs> after that small painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs>, the two priests sitting drinking.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Perhaps you know the one I mean. Whether I’ll get permission isn’t, however, entirely certain, and has to be applied for from the assistant deacon, which I’ve done and have to go back for the answer. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Apart from that, I’m working out how to draw the dung-heap. I wrote to you that I had hopes of getting a Scheveningen cape,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> well, I’ve got it, and an old hat thrown in which isn’t particularly beautiful, but the cape is superb and I immediately started working with it. Am just as pleased with it as I was with the sou’wester before.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And I’ve got as far with the sketch of the dung-heap as more or less getting into it that sheep-shed effect of inside against outside — the light under the dark sheds — and the group of women emptying their dustbins is beginning to develop and take shape.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Now the wheelbarrows going up and down and the rag-pickers with dung forks, that grubbing about under the sheds, has still to be expressed without losing the effect of light and shade of the whole. On the contrary, it must be strengthened as a result.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I believe you’ll have your own, similar view of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s words, and so I’m not telling you anything new, but because I spoke so sharply about it I wanted you to know at the same time that I don’t do such a thing with pleasure but with regret, and would be glad if peace could be kept with a little geniality. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">This winter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was pretty much against my being with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> just as much as now, yet he sent a warm coat ‘in case I could make use of it’, not specifying what for but obviously with the idea ‘she may be cold’.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Well, you see, that is right after all, and for one such deed I would gladly put up with a deluge of words.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Because I myself am not one of those who don’t fail in words either — such people would be perfect — and don’t make the slightest claim to perfection. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">And wanted to point out to you that in any case <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> objects to my being with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>, MUCH MORE SO indeed than with you, and despite that last winter he still no doubt thought something like: ‘that wretched woman — but she shouldn’t suffer from the cold’. Now, probably the same in your case: ‘that poor papist woman shouldn’t be alone even so’, or something like that. So don’t be concerned, be of good heart, and put their minds at ease. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Adieu, old chap, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter dates from a few days before <ref target="let352.xml">letter 352</ref>, which was written after Theo had reacted to the present letter. We therefore date it on or about Thursday, 7 June 1883. Cf. also <ref target="let350.xml">letter 350</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie (<ref target="let300.xml">300</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> visited him in the middle of May; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let343.xml">see letter 343</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The biblical text on which the sermon was based. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Aunt Cornelie</rs> lived in Princenhage.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>‘My last letter’ means <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote: ‘You’ve fulfilled your duty to inform <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526 bio.xml#_524">Pa and Ma</rs>, but now that they talk like this they give you the right, it seems to me, to exclude them from further confidences and to consult them less than you would if they were more reasonable. They’re mistaken in the sense that they’re not humble and humane enough in this case’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml#l-88">letter 348, ll. 88-92</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The Nederlands Hervormd Oude-mannen-en-vrouwenhuis on Z. Buitensingel 1; at the time this street was also known as ‘Om en Bij’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
    
<p>The drawing of a gardener by an apple tree and that of a carpenter’s workshop are not known. Van Gogh later did a letter sketch from memory after the first (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let362.xml">see letter 362</ref>) and the lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gardener near a gnarled apple tree </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3030">F 1659 / JH 379</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>A photograph after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le vin du curé </hi>(The priest’s wine), 1860 (Reims, Musée des Beaux-Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_253">Ill. 253</rs>. Cf. exhib. cat. Lyon 1993, pp. 96, 122, cat. nos. 16-b, 43. For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_877">Bingham</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml">see letter 156</ref>. The photograph would have been on sale at Goupil’s at the time. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Otherwise I am searching for the right way to draw the dung-heap’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘schoudermantel’ (cape).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote about his hopes of getting a cape in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let350.xml">letter 350</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had had a sou’wester for his models since the end of January; see e.g. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let301.xml">letters 301</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let305.xml">305</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>This is the drawing after which Van Gogh had done a small sketch in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let350.xml">letter 350</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> had sent this lady’s coat at the beginning of October 1882; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let271.xml">see letter 271</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh used the word ‘mud’, a Dutch measure of capacity equivalent to 100 litres and applied chiefly to potatoes and coal.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>After this Van Gogh crossed a word out; it may have been ‘teregt’ (rightly).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    