<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 15 June 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let353"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b316 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>353</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>293</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>355</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-06-15">on or about Friday, 15 June 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0316" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0316" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000397_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Weet ge nog ik een tijdje geleden U schreef “ik zit voor twee groote blanke ramen en weet nog niet hoe ik er wat op zal krijgen”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> sedert<c type="kk">/</c> weet ge<c type="kk">/</c> is op t’eene de mestvaalt gekomen<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> maar nu deze laatste dagen ben ik ook nog al gevorderd met de tweede. Dat moet worden een steenkolenboel zoo als ik ’t uit het raam van ’t atelier zie op het terrein van den Rijnspoor.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Er zijn daar hoopen steenkool &amp; daar werken kerels in en er komen luidjes met kruiwagentjes om een zak kolen te koopen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen sommige dagen zeer druk gaat en vooral van den winter met de sneeuw aardig was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dacht er al lang over en onlangs zag ik het zoo mooi op een avond en maakte mijne schets zóó dat ik sedert weinig veranderd heb aan wat ik er toen van opzette wat betreft de compositie in groote lijnen. Ik heb toen op de plaats zelf een kerel gehad die boven op die hoopen is geklouterd en hier &amp; daar gaan staan zoo dat ik de proportie van ’t figuur op diverse plaatsen zien kon. Maar ik heb er sedert verscheiden figuurstudies voor gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon de figuurtjes maar klein worden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Juist onder het maken van deze studies begint zich een plan voor een nog grootere teekening bij me vast te zetten<c type="kk">/</c> van het aardappelrooien namelijk. en heb ik het zóó in mijn gedachten dat ge er wel iets in zoudt vinden misschien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">’t landschap zou ik willen hebben een vlak terrein en een lijntje duinen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">De figuren zoowat een voet van hoogte<c type="kk">/</c> de compositie in de breedte<c type="kk">/</c> 1 tegen 2<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Vlak van voren in een hoek knielende figuren van vrouwen die de aardappels oprapen als repoussoir<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Een rij spitters<c type="kk">/</c> mannen en vrouwen<c type="kk">/</c> op het tweede plan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En de perspectief van ’t terrein zóó nemen dat aan den anderen hoek van de teekening dan waar de oprapers zitten ik de plek krijg waar de kruiwagentjes komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wel<c type="kk">/</c> behalve de knielende vrouwenfiguren zou ik U al de andere figuren reeds in groote studies kunnen laten zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ja<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou nu dezer dagen aan die teekening beginnen<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb de terreinen ook wel zoowat in ’t hoofd en zal op mijn gemak een mooi aardappelveld zoeken en er studies van maken voor de lijnen van het landschap<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Tegen den herfst als wanneer het rooien plaats heeft zou de teekening af moeten zijn<c type="kk">/</c> als doorwerkte schets althans<c type="kk">/</c> en zoude ik den toon en het acheveeren dan slechts te doen hebben.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb het verl. jaar hier gezien<c type="kk">/</c> vóór verl. jaar op ’t Heike waar het prachtig was en vóór dat jaar in de Borinage waar het geschiedde door de mijnwerkers<c type="kp">_</c> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> zoo heb ik het rijp in mijn geest<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">De figuren zouden zóó moeten zijn dat het waar was voor overal<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan een costuumstudie. Wel<c type="kk">/</c> dat blanke doek preoccupeert mij door alles heen en onder de anderen door zoek ik er steeds nieuwe studies bij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">De rij spitters zou eene rij donkere gedaanten moeten zijn slechts op ’t eerste aspect of van verre<c type="kk">/</c> maar zeer doorwerkt en gevarieerd van beweging en type.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">b.v. een jonge<c type="kk">/</c> eenvoudige kerel tegenover een van die echt typige oude scheveningers in een wit &amp; bruin gelapt pak met ouden<c type="kk">/</c> hoogen hoed<c type="kk">/</c> zoo’n dof zwarte die ze in den nek zetten<c type="kp">_</c> b.v<c type="kp">_</c> een kort<c type="kk">/</c> stevig vrouwenfiguur<c type="kk">/</c> stemmig in ’t zwart met wit kapje tegenover een langen hannikenmaaier<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> in witte broek<c type="kk">/</c> lichtblaauwen kiel en stroohoed – een kale kruin naast een jonge vrouw<c type="kp">_</c> Deze gedachten komen bij me op juist door de studies die ik reeds heb tegen elkaar te stellen<c type="kp">_</c> We zullen zien. Maar wat er ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een groot raam gekocht (een oud schilderij raam) bij Laarman en het bespannen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">En met den dag meer wordt het me duidelijker maar het is weergaasch moeielijk om figuren te vinden die als oppositie goed doen tegen elkaar en toch in een zelfde zeer beperkte ruimte kunnen plaats vinden. En moet men elk misschien 3 of meer malen nog maken voor het uitkomt. Maar ik zal het opzetten en er mee doen als met de mestvaalt<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. het later op een ander raam opnieuw beginnen als het eerste niet teregt komt zoo als ik wil. Maar wilde het betrekkelijk klaar hebben tegen den eigentlijken tijd van het aardappelrooien<c type="kk">/</c> al is het dat ik dan het op nieuw geheel om moet werken weer op een nieuw papier.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">’t Is goed geweest dat ik toen eens naar Rappard ben geweest want ik heb bij hem eigentlijk de gedachte opgedaan om die grootere teekeningen te beginnen en juist heb ik gemerkt dat terwijl men composeert men meer precies voelt wat voor studies men te maken heeft. Ik werk dezer dagen met erg veel pleizier en betrekkelijk zonder moe worden<c type="kk">/</c> door den lust die ik er in heb<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik had mijn eigen lang ingehouden om te composeeren zooals gij weet en in dat opzigt is er nu een revolutie in me ontstaan omdat het den tijd was dat die kwame<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en haal ik wat vrijer adem nu ik den teugel die ik me zelf had aangedaan wat heb laten schieten. Maar ik geloof toch dat het goed was ik zoo’n langen tijd maar op de studies heb gesjouwd<c type="kk">/</c> want is het met alles zoo<c type="kk">/</c> met ’t figuur toch in ’t bijzonder moet men er veel bepaald voor studeeren en niet denken dat men het kan. Ik vind het zoo’n mooi woord van Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> dat met al zijn werken en ondervinding hij nog zegt “soms weet ik nog niet waar de <hi rend="italics">knobbels</hi> in een koe zitten”.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik voor mij doe dikwijls zóó tegenwoordig dat als ik een spitter teeken die zijn ééne been voor ’t andere heeft of zijn eenen arm vòòr de andere of zijn hoofd voorover<c type="kk">/</c> ik het been<c type="kk">/</c> den arm of den nek &amp; achterhoofd dat achter ’t voorste komt &amp; gevolgelijk buiten ’t gezigt<c type="kk">/</c> toch eerst en en detail er op teeken &amp; dan eerst ’t geen in ’t gezicht komt er over heen om zoo mogelijk het raak te krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik hoop dat ’t me lukken zal de schim of het spook van de aardappelteekening er reeds op te hebben tegen den tijd dat gij komt. Ik verlang erg naar U. Weet ge nog niets meer bepaalds omtrent Uw komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet weer aan mijn steenkolenwerkers<c type="kp">_</c> Mijn bezitting in contant geld bestaat op dit oogenblik in een couponnetje van f 1.23 1/2 dat door<c type="shy">-</c>midden gescheurd is en men me al eens geweigerd heeft. Dus hoef ik U niets meer te zeggen van dat ik nog al zal zitten uitkijken naar Uw brief<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb het groote raam maar bespannen om afleiding te hebben en in de dagen vóór ik weer ontvang toch te kunnen werken als ik misschien geen model zal kunnen krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien kan ik het toch nog wel krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Mijn Scheveningschen mantel is een prachtige bezitting<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ik heb drie uitvoerige studies er mee<c type="kk">/</c> een vrouw met een aschbak<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en twee met kruiwagens.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Als ge weer stuurt hoop ik een visschersbuis met staanden kraag en korte mouwen te nemen en een vrouwenhoed. De vrouwenhoeden zijn duur en moeielijk te krijgen schijnt het. Enfin ik heb er een voor desnoods.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25"><hi rend="italics">Er moeten Scheveningsche</hi> <hi rend="italics">Teekeningen komen ook</hi> <hi rend="italics">en binnen kort</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Verl. jaar om dezen tijd was ik in ’t gasthuis<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – de geschilderde studies van verl. zomer vind ik slecht en verkeerd – ik kom hierop omdat ik juist een oude geschilderde studie van dien kolenboel heb opgezocht<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> om te zien hoe ze verleden jaar lagen<c type="kk">/</c> ik vind ze nu te slordig<c type="kk">/</c> te gejaagd gemaakt<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin ik heb me sedert op nieuw geconcentreerd op het figuurteekenen en ik denk niet dan zeer indirekt aan het schilderen. Nu adieu<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf zoodra het kan en heb voorspoed met alles. met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Do you remember that not long ago I wrote to you ‘I’m sitting in front of two big blank stretching frames and don’t yet know how I’ll get anything onto them’?<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Well since then, you know, the dung-heap has come on one,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and in the past few days I’ve made good progress with the second. It’s to be a coal-yard on the Rijnspoor site as I see it from the window of the studio.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> There are heaps of coal and fellows working in them, and people come with small wheelbarrows to buy a sack of coal; trade is very busy some days, and especially in the winter, with the snow it was a charming scene.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Had been thinking about it for a long time and recently I saw it looking so beautiful one evening and did my sketch in such a way that I’ve since changed little of what I put down then as regards the broad outlines of the composition. At the place itself I had a fellow who scrambled up the heaps and stood here and there so that I could see the proportion of the figure at various places. But I’ve since done various figure studies for it, although the figures come out small. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Just while I’m doing these studies, a plan for an even larger drawing, namely of the potato-digging, begins to take root in me. And the way I have it in my mind, you might perhaps see something in it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I would like the landscape to be a flat area and a small line of dunes.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The figures just about one foot high, the composition breadthways, 1 to 2. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">In a corner in the foreground kneeling figures of women gathering up the potatoes as a <hi rend="italics">repoussoir</hi>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">A row of diggers, men and women, in the background.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And take the perspective of the area so that in the other corner of the drawing from where the women are gathering up, I get the spot where the wheelbarrows come. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Now, apart from the figures of the kneeling women, I could already show you the other figures in large studies. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Yes, I want to start on these drawings in the next few days, I have the sites pretty well in my head, and shall seek out a fine potato field at my convenience and do studies of it for the lines of the landscape. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The drawing ought to be complete, as a worked-up sketch at any rate, towards the autumn, when the lifting takes place, and I’d only have the tone and the finishing to do.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I saw it here last year, and the year before last at Het Heike, where it was splendid, and the year before that in the Borinage, where it was done by miners. Anyway, this is how it has ripened in my mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">The figures ought to be such that it’s true everywhere, and more than a costume study. Well, that blank canvas preoccupies me in spite of everything else, and while making studies I’m always looking for new ones to add.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">The row of diggers should be just a row of dark shapes at first sight or from a distance, but highly finished and varied in movement and type.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">For instance, a young, plain fellow opposite one of those really typical old Scheveningers in a white and brown patched suit with an old top hat, one of those matt black ones that they wear low in the neck. For instance, a short, stocky figure of a woman in sober black with a white cap opposite a tall grass-mower<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> in white trousers, light blue smock and straw hat — a bald crown next to a young woman. These ideas come to me precisely by putting the studies I already have opposite each other. We’ll see. But be that as it may, I’ve bought a large stretching frame (an old painting frame) from Laarman and covered it.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">And it’s becoming clearer to me day by day, but it’s devilishly difficult to find figures that look right as opposites and can still find a place in the same, very confined space. And one has to do each one perhaps 3 or more times before it works out. But I’ll make a start on it and do the same as with the dung-heap, that is, begin again later on another stretching frame if the first doesn’t come out as I want. But wanted to have it relatively finished towards the time for potato digging, even though I’ll then have to go over it again completely on another piece of paper. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">It’s good that I went to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> that time, for it was actually there that I got the idea of starting on the larger drawings, and I’ve noticed that while one composes one feels more exactly what studies one must make. These days I’m working with a great deal of pleasure and without getting especially tired, because of the enjoyment I feel. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I had long restrained myself from composing, as you know, and in that respect a revolution has now come about in me because it was time it came,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and I breathe more freely now that I’ve slightly slackened the rein I had imposed on myself. But I still believe it was a good thing that I toiled away just at studies for such a long time, for it’s the same with everything, and particularly with the figure: one must study a great deal and not imagine that one can do it. I find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s words very fine: after all his work and experience he still says ‘sometimes I still don’t know where the <hi rend="italics">knobbles</hi> are on a cow’.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">For my part, what I often do these days is that if I’m drawing a digger who has one leg in front of the other, or his one arm in front of the other, or his head leaning forwards, I first draw in detail the leg, the arm or the neck and back of the head that’s behind the one in front and hence out of view, and only afterwards on top of that what’s in sight, to get it as accurate as possible. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I hope I’ll succeed in getting down the shadow or the ghost of the potato drawing by the time you come. I long for you. Don’t you know anything more definite about when you’ll be coming?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Well, I must get back to my coal workers. All the cash I have at the moment is a money order for 1.23  1/2  guilders which is torn in two and has already been refused once. So I don’t need to tell you that I’ll be looking forward to your letter keenly. I’ve covered the big stretching frame so that I have a distraction and can still work in the days before receipt again if perhaps I can’t get a model. But perhaps I can get one after all. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">My Scheveningen cape is a splendid possession,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I have three detailed studies with it, a woman with a dustbin<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and two with wheelbarrows.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> When you send again I hope to take a fisherman’s jacket with a stand-up collar and short sleeves and a woman’s hat. The women’s hats are expensive and hard to obtain, it seems. Still, I have one if need be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25"><hi rend="italics">There must be Scheveningen Drawings as well, and soon</hi>. This time last year I was in the hospital<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> — I think the painted studies from last summer are poor and wrong — I thought of this because I’ve just looked up an old painted study of that coal-yard<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> to see how they were done last year. Now I consider them too carelessly and hastily done. In short, I’ve since concentrated on figure drawing again, and I think of painting only very indirectly. Well, adieu, write as soon as you can and good luck with everything. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written a few days after <ref target="let352.xml">letter 352</ref>, because ‘in recent days’ Van Gogh has worked on a drawing of a ‘coal yard’ of which there is not yet any mention in <ref target="let352.xml">letter 352</ref>. The exact date cannot be determined, but in <ref target="let355.xml">letter 355</ref> Vincent asks Theo to send money earlier (than 20 June) if possible, and consequently it dates from on or about 16 June (see also <hi rend="italics">Date</hi> there), so we date the present letter on or about Friday, 15 June 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s visit to Van Rappard’s studio <ref target="let344.xml">(344)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml">See letter 348</ref>: ‘Well, in front of me I have two blank sheets for new compositions and must set to work on them’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For the first and second versions of the drawing of the dung-heap, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let352.xml">see letter 352</ref>. Both versions are unknown. Here Van Gogh is referring to the revised, second version.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This drawing of the coal yard at Rijnspoor station is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Soon afterwards Van Gogh made several studies of figures lifting potatoes: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2442">F 1034 / JH 372</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2444">F 9 / JH 385</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let357.xml">See letters 357</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let362.xml">362</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>A ‘hannekemaaier’ is a grass-mower, an agricultural labourer of German origin.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh would have bought his stretching frame from one of the two carpenters called Laarman in The Hague in 1883: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_481">Dirk Laarman</rs>, located at Paveljoensgracht 27a, or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_482">Cornelis Johan Laarman</rs>, at Visschersdijk 41 (close to the Grote kerk, now Torenstraat). Paveljoensgracht was nearest to Schenkweg, where Van Gogh lived (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">SAAm</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboeken</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">1882-1883</hi>).</p>

<p rend="indent">For the nature and purpose of the stretching frames, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let346.xml">see letters 346</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml">348</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This phrasing is derived from a quotation from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Hugo</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi> that Van Gogh cited in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let397.xml#n-4">letter 397, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had had a cape at his disposal since the beginning of June; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let351.xml">see letter 351</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This drawing of a woman in a cape with a dustbin is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The two studies of a woman in a Scheveningen cape with a wheelbarrow are not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For Van Gogh’s stay in the Municipal Hospital in June 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let237.xml">see letters 237</ref> ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>This painted study of the coal yard at Rijnspoor station (of 1882) is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    