<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, on or about Friday, 15 June 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let354"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8369 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>354</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R37</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>356</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-06-15">on or about Friday, 15 June 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8369 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8369 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001623_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8369 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001624_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001624_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8369 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001624_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001624_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001624_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Was bezig aan een brief aan U toen zooeven de post Uw zeer welkom schrijven me brengt<c type="kp">_</c> ’t doet me pleizier ge met Uw teekening gevorderd zijt<c type="kk">/</c> ik twijfelde er niet aan of zulks zoudt ge doen trouwens want ge hadt het mannelijk aangezet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ’k begin met U te zeggen ik wat gij zegt over de Engelsche teekenaars volkomen juist en volkomen goed vind<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zag het in Uw werk<c type="kk">/</c> precies wat ge zegt. Nu ik denk ook zoo er over<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Over de stoute contours bepaaldelijk<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Neem de ets van <hi rend="italics">Millet</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">les bêcheurs</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> neem een gravure van Albert Durer<c type="kk">/</c> neem bovenal de groote houtsnee door <hi rend="italics">Millet</hi> zelf<c type="kk">/</c> la bergère<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en dan ziet men ten volle wat er door zoo’n contour vermag uitgedrukt worden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En zoo als ge zegt<c type="kk">/</c> men voelt dan “zoo heb ik ’t altijd willen doen als ik altijd mijn eigen weg had gevolgd” &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> Dat is mooi gezegd van U kerel en mannelijk gesproken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik ook een exempel vindt van eigenaardig stoere<c type="kk">/</c> krachtige teekening zijn de schilderijen van Leys<c type="kk">/</c> bepaaldelijk de serie decoraties voor zijn eetkamer. la promenade dans la neige<c type="kk">/</c> les patineurs<c type="kk">/</c> la reception<c type="kk">/</c> la table<c type="kk">/</c> la servante<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En de Groux heeft het ook en Daumier heeft het ook<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Israels zelf en soms<c type="kk">/</c> soms Mauve &amp; Maris<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> ook kunnen zich van een krachtigen contour niet onthouden maar doen het niet zóó als Leys en niet zóó als Herkomer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">En als men hen hoort vooral willen ze er eigentlijk niet van weten en spreken ze meest over toon en kleur. Toch<c type="kk">/</c> Israels in sommige fusains heeft ook lijnen gebruikt die aan Millet doen denken. Ik voor mij verklaar U ronduit dat bij alle liefde &amp; respect die ik voor die meesters heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik vooral van Mauve &amp; Maris het jammer vindt zij als zij tot anderen spreken niet meer wijzen op ’t geen men door den contour doen kan<c type="kk">/</c> en aanraden voorzigtig en zachtjes te teekenen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En zoo is het dat heden ten dage het aquarelleeren aan de orde van den dag is en als ’t meest expressieve middel wordt beschouwd<c type="kk">/</c> en wordt er m.i<c type="kp">_</c> te weinig werk gemaakt van Black &amp; White<c type="kk">/</c> zóó zeer zelfs dat er een zekere antipathie tegen is. In aquarel is om zoo te zeggen geen zwart en baseert men zich daarop om te zeggen “die zwarte dingen”<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Is nu evenwel niet noodig dezen brief daarover vol te schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wilde U mededeelen ik op ’t moment 4 teekeningen op ’t ezel heb. <hi rend="italics">Turfspitters</hi><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – <hi rend="italics">Zandgroeve</hi><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – <hi rend="italics">Mestvaalt</hi><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – <hi rend="italics">Kolenladen</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Mestvaalt maakte ik zelfs tweemaal<c type="kk">/</c> de eerste werd te gefatigueerd om er op door te gaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik heb ook niet veel met terpentijn &amp; drukinkt durven werken er in<c type="kk">/</c> heb fusain<c type="kk">/</c> lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt en autographische inkt gebruikt tot nog toe<c type="kp">_</c> Behalve in de schets voor de mestvaalt die te gefatigueerd werd<c type="kk">/</c> die heb ik er mee geattaqueerd en niet met ongunstig gevolg. Werd wel zwart maar toch kwam de frischheid er weer wat in en zie ik nu kans opnieuw er nog in te werken<c type="kk">/</c> terwijl vòòr de drukinkt er op kwam ik daar geen kans meer toe zag.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb hard gewerkt sedert ik U bezocht<c type="kk">/</c> ik had in zoo lang niet gecomposeerd en veel studies gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> zoo toen ik er eenmaal aan begon werd ik er fel op<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Verscheiden morgens was ik om 4 uur al aan den gang<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wou verbazend graag dat gij ze eens zaagt want ik kan geen touw vast maken aan wat v.d. Weele<c type="kk">/</c> de eenige die ze gezien heeft<c type="kk">/</c> er van zeide.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">v.d. Weeles oordeel was nog al sympathiek maar van de Zandgroeve zei hij er stonden te veel figuren op. de compositie was niet eenvoudig<c type="kp">_</c> hij zei<c type="kk">/</c> kijk eens<c type="kk">/</c> teeken dat èène kereltje met dien kruiwagen op een dijkje s’avonds tegen de lichte lucht in<c type="kk">/</c> wat zou dat b.v. mooi zijn, en nu rammelde het.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> toen wees ik hem de teek<c type="kp">_</c> v. <hi rend="italics">Caldecott</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Brighton Highroad</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en zei<c type="kk">/</c> is Uw bedoeling persé ’t niet gepermitteerd is veel figuren in een compositie te brengen en die zeer te compliceeren? laat mijn teekening daar en zeg eens wat ge van deze compositie vindt? Wel<c type="kk">/</c> zei hij<c type="kk">/</c> dat vind ik ook niet mooi<c type="kk">/</c> maar<c type="kk">/</c> voegde hij er bij<c type="kk">/</c> ik spreek persoonlijk en kan niet anders spreken dan persoonlijk. en dat is niet hetgeen waar ik van houd en waar ik naar kijk. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dat vond ik goed gezegd betrekkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> maar begrijpt ge ik niet precies in hem vond dat op de hoogte zijn van de kwestie daar ik verlangen naar had. Maar hij is anders wel een solide kerel &amp; ging ik heel prettig met hem uit en wees hij me verduiveld mooie dingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De zandgroef zag ik ook op een wandeling met hem maar toen die keer had hij er naauwelijks naar gekeken en ging ik den volgenden dag er alleen naar terug. Die zandgroef heb ik daarom met veel figuren geteekend omdat in die zandgravingen soms werkelijk zeer veel kerels aan ’t sjouwen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. verschaft men s’winters en in ’t najaar van wege de stad werk aldaar aan personen die zonder werk loopen<c type="kp">_</c> En is ’t er dan almagtig aardig<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">’k heb eenige mooie modellen gehad in den laatsten tijd<c type="kp">_</c>– Een superbe hannikemaaier<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/> een prachtigen boerenjongen<c type="kk">/</c> geheel als een van die figuren van Millet<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">een kerel met een kruiwagen<c type="kk">/</c> denzelfden van wien ge U misschien herinnert ik den kop teekende op zijn Zondagsch met een Zondagschen lap voor zijn blinde oog<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Nu heb ik hem in zijn daagsche pak en zou ’t moeielijk te gelooven zijn ’t denzelfden man was die voor die twee figuren poseerde misschien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Deze vier groote teekeningen zijn 1 meter bij 1/2 meter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik bevind me goed bij ’t gebruik van een bruinen passepartout met zeer diep zwarten binnenrand<c type="kp">_</c> Dan lijken veel zwarten grijs die te zwart zouden doen in een witten passepartout en blijft ’t geheel helder.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Sapperloot ik wou ge ze eens zien kondt<c type="kk">/</c> niet omdat ik ze zelf goed vind maar ik wou ofschoon ik er nog niet over tevreden ben wel eens Uw gedachten er omtrent weten. Het zijn nog niet genoeg bepaalde figuurteekeningen<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> naar mijn zin ofschoon het toch figuurteekeningen zijn maar ik wou nog vierkanter en brutaler de teekening van acties en structuur uitdrukken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Wat gij schrijft dat ge gevoelt ge nu op een <hi rend="italics">weg</hi> zijt en niet op bijpaadjes en zijweegjes<c type="kk">/</c> vindt ik zeer juist<c type="kp">_</c> Heb zelf een soortgelijk gevoel omdat ik dit laatste jaar meer nog dan vroeger me heb geconcentreerd op ’t figuur<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Wees er van verzekerd, als ge gelooft dat ik oogen heb om te kijken, dat er terdeeg sentiment in Uw figuren is<c type="kk">/</c> het is gezond en mannelijk wat ge maakt<c type="kk">/</c> twijfel niet aan Uw zelf in dat opzigt en juist omdat ge niet twijfelt<c type="kk">/</c> zet het er zonder aarzelen op<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">De studiekoppen voor de blinde kerels vind ik superbe<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Wou U nog vertellen van een soort potlooden van Faber<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> die ik gevonden heb. Ziehier de dikte van de doorsnee<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Zij zijn zacht en beter kwaliteit dan de timmermans<c type="shy">-</c>potlooden<c type="kk">/</c> geven een fameus zwart en werken zeer prettig voor groote studies<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik teekende eene naaister er mee op grijs papier sans fin en kreeg een effekt als van lith. krijt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Deze potlooden zijn in zacht hout gevat<c type="kk">/</c> van buiten donker groen geverfd<c type="kk">/</c> kosten 20 cents per stuk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Voor ik ’t vergeet – ik wilde U te leen vragen de afleveringen Harpers magazine die ge hebt<c type="kk">/</c> om de artikels over Holland te lezen die Boughton en Abbey hebben geïllustreerd<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Ik zal U een pakje zenden met de oude losse afleveringen die ik heb met ill. v. Howard Pyle &amp;c. om ze eens door te kijken op Uw gemak<c type="kp">_</c> En zal er bij voegen Erckmann Chatrian<c type="kk">/</c> histoire d’un paysan geillustreerd door Schüler<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> en er bijvoegen enkele illustraties van Green die ge U herinneren zult ik U beloofd heb. Als gij nog dubbelen hebt<c type="kk">/</c> voeg ze bij de Harpers (als ge die laatsten ten minste missen kunt voor een dag of 14 dat ik ze lezen kan) en als ge ’t uit hebt ’t boekje van Zola over Manet<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">’t doet me leed dat Uw gezondheid nog niet in orde is en toch denk ik dat het meer dan de baden<c type="kk">/</c> of wat ze daar te Soden uitvoeren<c type="kk">/</c> U zal op monteren dat ge flink vordert met Uw teekeningen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Ik denk ge naar Uw atelier terug zult verlangen zoodra ge er uit zijt. Ik weet nog van Mauve hoe die eens vreesselijk melankoliek geworden is op zoo’n togt naar een soortgelijke fabriek<c type="kk">/</c> met alle respect er van gesproken<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Ik ben zoo als ge weet zeer ongeloovig in die soort van zaken en kan met <hi rend="italics">Bräsig</hi> uit Reuters gedroogde kruiden sympathiseeren aangaande wat die authoriteit noemt “de waterkunst” geloof ik.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Wat is het werk van Fritz Reuter mooi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Ik denk wel gij de Erckmann Chatrian mooi zult vinden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Moet U nog vertellen ik onlangs een prachtigen ouden Scheveningschen vrouwemantel ben magtig geworden en een hoed<c type="kk">/</c> maar de hoed is niet mooi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> En ik krijg ook nog een schippersbuis met staanden kraag &amp; korte mouwen. Ik zou Uw fusain almagtig graag eens zien<c type="kk">/</c> misschien als mijn broer komt – wanneer weet ik niet precies – zou ik met hem mee gaan naar Brabant &amp; dan Utrecht passeerende komen kijken<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien als ik ’t hem lappen kan kom ik ook zonder dat eens want ik zou ’t graag zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Van Uw kant<c type="kk">/</c> zie ’t er op te houden ge nog eens in den Haag komt<c type="kk">/</c> immers voor die <supplied>tr</supplied>ouwpartij zeidet ge toen. Als ’t me zoo blijft vlotten met ’t vinden van modellen als dezen laatsten tijd maak ik zeker nog een &amp; ander dezen zomer in groote teekeningen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Ik wou nu met die ik onderhanden heb wat doorwerken om zoo mogelijk ze op een hoogte te krijgen tegen dat mijn broer komt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">In Harpers weekly zie ik daar een heel echt ding naar Smedley – een zwart mannenfiguur op een witten zandweg. Hij noemt het “a generation ago”<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is een figuur van een soort dominé misschien<c type="kk">/</c> maakt op mij de impressie<c type="kk">/</c> ja zoo was mijn grootvader wel.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Ik wou dat ik ’t gemaakt had. In zelfde nummer naar Abbey twee meisjes die staan te hengelen aan een slootkant met knotwilgen<c type="kp">_</c> Beide zijn in de Harper maar croquis in een compte rendu van een tentoonstelling<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">Ik wou U wel croquis sturen van de teekeningen maar ik heb niet veel tijd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Ik heb permissie gevraagd om in het oude mannen- &amp; vrouwenhuis hier te teekenen maar is me dat weer geweigerd<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Enfin er zijn meer gestichten op de dorpen in de buurt. Maar hier kende ik een paar lui voor modellen. Ik was er echter om eens te kijken en zag o.a. een tuinmannetje bij een ouden<c type="kk">/</c> krommen appelboom dat zeer echt was<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> daar komt model. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> zend de Harpers als ge ze missen kunt<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.42" n="42">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.43" n="43">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Was writing a letter to you when the post brought your most welcome letter just a moment ago. I’m pleased you’ve made progress with your drawing, I didn’t doubt that you would, by the way, for you’d made a manly start. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Well, let me begin by saying that I think what you say about the English draughtsmen is entirely correct and entirely right. I saw it in your work, exactly what you say. Well, I take the same view.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">On the bold outlines in particular.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Take the etching by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, The diggers</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> take an engraving by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_990">Albrecht Dürer</rs>, take above all the large woodcut by <hi rend="italics">Millet</hi> himself, The shepherdess,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and then one sees fully what can be expressed by such an outline. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And as you say, one then has the feeling ‘that’s how I’d always have wanted to do it if I’d always gone my own way’ &amp;c. That’s well said, old chap, and spoken like a man. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Now, what I also find an example of singularly robust, forceful drawing is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Leys</rs>’s paintings, particularly the series of decorations for his dining room. The walk in the snow, the skaters, the reception, the table, the servant.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> has it as well and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> has it as well. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> himself and sometimes, sometimes <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Maris</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> too, cannot resist forceful outline, but don’t do it like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Leys</rs> or like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And when one hears them, they really don’t want to know, and talk most about tone and colour. Yet in some charcoal drawings <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> used lines reminiscent of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>. I for one declare to you frankly that, with all the love and respect I have for these masters, I find it a pity that they, especially <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Maris</rs>, don’t point out what can be done with the outline more often when talking to others, and recommend drawing carefully and softly.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And so it is that these days watercolour is the order of the day and considered to be the most expressive medium, and in my view too little effort goes into Black and White, to the point even that there’s a certain antipathy to it. In watercolour there’s no black, so to speak, and that’s the basis for people talking about ‘those black things’. All the same, there’s no need to spend the whole of this letter writing about that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Wanted to inform you that at present I have 4 drawings on the easel. <hi rend="italics">Peat diggers</hi><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> — <hi rend="italics">Sand quarry</hi><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — <hi rend="italics">Dung-heap</hi><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — <hi rend="italics">Loading coal</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I even did the dung-heap twice; the first became too worn to continue working on. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I didn’t dare work on them much with turpentine and printer’s ink, have used charcoal, lithographic crayon and autographic ink so far. Except in the sketch for the dung-heap that got too worn — I tackled that with them, with not unfavourable results. It became black, but still some of the freshness came back into it, and now I see possibilities for working in it again, whereas before the printer’s ink came on it I saw no possibility of that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I’ve worked hard since I visited you, I hadn’t composed for so long and had done a great many studies, so once I began I went at it furiously. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Several mornings I was already at work at 4 o’clock. I would like it immensely if you saw them sometime, for I can make no sense of what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> said about them, the only one to have seen them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Van der Weele’s judgement was rather sympathetic, but he said of the Sand quarry that there were too many figures in it. The composition wasn’t simple. He said, look, draw that one little fellow with his wheelbarrow on a dyke in the evening set against the light sky, how beautiful that would be, for instance, and now it lacked cohesion. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Well, then I showed him the drawing by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_924">Caldecott</rs>,</hi> <hi rend="italics">Brighton Highroad</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and said, do you mean that it’s absolutely not permitted to put many figures in a composition and to make it highly complicated? Leaving aside my drawing, tell me what you think of this composition. Well, he said, I don’t find that beautiful either but, he added, I’m speaking personally and can only speak personally. And that’s not what I like or what I look at. Well, I thought that was rather well said, but you understand that I didn’t find in him that awareness of the question that I sought. But for the rest he’s a solid fellow, and I had some very pleasant excursions with him and he showed me some devilishly beautiful things. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">It was also during a walk with him that I saw the sand quarry, but that time he hardly looked at it and I went back alone the next day. I drew the sand quarry with a lot of figures, because sometimes there really are a great many fellows toiling away in those sandpits, for example in the winter and the autumn they provide work there in the name of the city for those who have no work. And then it’s wonderfully pleasing there.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I’ve had several fine models of late. A superb grass-mower, a splendid country lad, exactly like one of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s figures. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">A fellow with a wheelbarrow — you may remember me drawing his head in Sunday clothes with a Sunday patch over his blind eye.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Now I have him in his everyday suit, and it’s perhaps hard to believe that it’s the same man who posed for the two figures. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">These four big drawings are 1 metre by 1/2 metre. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I feel happy using a brown passe-partout with a very deep black inside edge. Then many blacks that would appear too black in a white passe-partout look grey and the whole remains clear. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">By Jove, I wish you could see them, not because I myself think they are good, but I would like to hear your thoughts about them, even though I’m not yet satisfied with them. To my taste they aren’t yet figure drawings in the true sense of the term, although they are still figure drawings, but I wanted to express the outlines of actions and structure even more squarely and boldly. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">What you write about feeling that you’re now on a <hi rend="italics">road</hi> and not on byways or side roads seems to me absolutely right. Have a similar feeling myself, because this last year I’ve concentrated more on the figure than in the past. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Be assured, if you believe I have eyes to see, that there is certainly sentiment in your figures; what you make is healthy and manly, do not doubt yourself in that respect and, precisely because you do not doubt, dash it on without hesitating. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The studies of heads for the blind fellows seem superb to me.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Wanted to tell you about a type of pencil by Faber<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> that I’ve found. Here you see the thickness of the cross-section.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">They’re soft and better quality than the carpenter’s pencils, produce a marvellous black and are very agreeable to work with for large studies. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I used it to draw a woman sewing on grey <hi rend="italics">papier sans fin</hi> and got an effect like lithographic crayon.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> These pencils are made of soft wood, dyed green on the outside, cost 20 cents apiece. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Before I forget — I wanted to borrow the issues of Harper’s Magazine you have to read the articles about Holland that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> illustrated.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I’ll send you a package with the old loose issues that I have with illustrations by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1285">Howard Pyle</rs> &amp;c. so that you can look through them at your leisure. And shall add <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>, Histoire d’un paysan illustrated by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Schuler</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and enclose several illustrations by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1058 bio.xml#_1059">Green</rs> that you will remember I promised. If you still have duplicates, add them to the Harpers (at least if you can do without the latter for about a fortnight so that I can read them), and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s book about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> if you’ve finished it.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I’m sorry that your health isn’t yet in order, but I think that what will cheer you up more than the baths or whatever it is they do there in Soden is to make solid progress with your drawings.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> I reckon you’ll be longing for your studio as soon as you’re out of it. I know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> became terribly melancholy during a journey to a similar kind of factory, speaking with all due respect.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">As you know, I’m very unbelieving in matters of this kind, and can sympathize with <hi rend="italics">Bräsig</hi> in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_728">Reuter</rs>’s Gedroogde kruiden as regards what I think that authority calls ‘the water art’.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">How beautiful <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_728">Fritz Reuter</rs>’s work is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">I do think you’ll find the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs> beautiful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Must also tell you that I recently got hold of a splendid old Scheveningen woman’s cape and a hat, but the hat isn’t beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> And I’m also to get a skipper’s jacket with a stand-up collar and short sleeves. I’d dearly like to see your charcoal drawing, perhaps when my brother comes — I don’t know exactly when yet — I could go with him to Brabant and then come for a look while passing Utrecht. Perhaps if I can manage it I’ll come anyway sometime, for I would like to see it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">For your part, make sure you come to The Hague again, for the wedding you spoke of then. If I carry on having such success as just recently in finding models, I’ll certainly do one or two things in large drawings this summer. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Now I want to continue with those I’m working on to get them to the same level, if possible, by the time my brother comes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">In Harper’s Weekly I see a very true thing after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1360">Smedley</rs> — a black figure of a man on a white sandy road. He calls it ‘a generation ago’. It’s the figure of a kind of minister perhaps; the impression it made on me was: yes, my grandfather was like that.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> I wish I had done it. In the same number after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> two girls fishing on the bank of a ditch with pollard willows. In Harper’s they’re both just croquis in a review of an exhibition.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">I would send you croquis of the drawings but I haven’t got much time. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">I asked permission to draw in the old men’s and women’s home here but that has been refused me.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Still, there are more homes in the villages around here. But here I knew a few people whom I could use as models. I was there, though, to have a look, and saw among others a gardener next to an old, crooked apple tree that was very real.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">Well, there’s my model. Adieu, send the Harpers if you can do without them, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In earlier editions this letter was printed with a section between <ref target="#l-152">ll. 152-153</ref> that cannot originally have been part of it. This sheet must have been written in the Nuenen period: there are references to recent ‘winter gardens’ Van Gogh had drawn and to people who lived in Nuenen. This erroneous arrangement was spotted by Dorn; see exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 162 (n. 3). We have added the sheet to <ref target="let437.xml">letter 437</ref>. See also under <hi rend="italics">Additional details</hi> there. </p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s visit to Van Rappard’s studio <ref target="let344.xml">(344)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For the etching after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1876">The two diggers</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let142.xml#n-18">see letter 142, n. 18.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_267">The large shepherdess seated</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let216.xml#n-2">see letter 216, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Henri Leys</rs>’s paintings of 1855 were part of the dining room in his home, now Leysstraat 12 in Antwerp. After Leys’s death in 1869 the so-called ‘Hotel Leys’ was opened to visitors. The decoration, a frieze 6.5 metres long, has been in ‘the small Leys room’ of Antwerp town hall since 1897 and bears the title <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_510">Een kerstfeest in de zestiende eeuw</rs></hi> (A Christmas celebration in the sixteenth century). See N. de Poorter, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Inventaris van de kunstwerken in het stadhuis van Antwerpen. Schilderijen – grafiek – beeldhouwkunst</hi>. Antwerp 1988; and Todts 1988, pp. 104-105.</p>

<p rend="indent">
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La promenade dans la neige</hi> (La promenade sur les remparts) (The walk in the snow (The walk on the ramparts) is part of Vrolijk gezelschap (Merry Company) (153 x 644 cm). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1055">Ill. 1055</rs>. ‘The skaters’ is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het oversteken van de brug</hi> (Crossing the bridge) (153 x 504 cm) – part of the work was lost as a result of alterations to the room (Van Gogh comes back to that in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let544.xml">letter 544</ref>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1056">Ill. 1056</rs>. ‘The reception’ is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het welkom</hi> (The welcome) (137 x 222 cm). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1057">Ill. 1057</rs>. ‘The table’ and ‘The servant’ are part of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De feesttafel</hi> (The festive table) (153 x 220 cm). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1059">Ill. 1059</rs>. </p>

<p rend="indent">It seems that Van Gogh first saw the decorations in situ in November 1885 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let544.xml">letter 544</ref>). His remark in the present letter about the outlines indicates that he had seen reproductions previously. Photographs of the decorations (by Fierlants among others) were available, and there were etchings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs> (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml">letter 542</ref>); Leys and a pupil had also made smaller copies. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jacob Maris</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The drawing of the sand quarry, first mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref>, (‘team of workmen labouring’), is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh did two drawings of the dung-heap, which are both unknown; they are first mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let350.xml">letters 350</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let352.xml">352</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This drawing of ‘loading coal’ is not known; it is the same drawing as the one said in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let353.xml">letter 353</ref> to have been done at Rijnspoor station. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brighton Highroad</hi> is probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_924">Caldecott</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_669">Afternoon in King’s road</rs></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let276.xml#n-9">see letter 276, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘Landarbeider’ (farm labourer).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Old man in his Sunday best with an eye patch</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2423">F 1003 / JH 285</rs>). Drawings from the sessions mentioned here are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘figuurtekeningen die die naam werkelijk verdienen’, ‘figuurtekeningen in de ware zin van het woord’ (figure drawings truly worthy of the name, figure drawings in the true sense of the term).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s drawings in the Institute for the Blind, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let345.xml#n-3">see letter 345, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Faber is a German manufacturer of pencils and other artists’ materials. The type of pencil Van Gogh is referring to is known as a Försterstift in German (forester’s pencil). It is a thick pencil sturdy enough to mark wet wood. Although there are no known drawings from the Hague period that were made with this kind of pencil, it may have been used for letter 362 and the associated sketch, F - / JH 380, as well as for the Drenthe drawing, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ploughman and three women</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_538">F 1096r / JH 411</rs>). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Van Gogh’s studio practice</hi>, ed. Marije Vellekoop <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al.</hi>. Brussels 2013, pp. 392, 405.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>This pencil drawing of a woman sewing on grey paper is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>For these contributions to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">Abbey</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let348.xml#n-11">see letter 348, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>For this edition of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_339">Histoire d’un paysan</ref></hi> illustrated by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1356">Schuler</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let345.xml#n-5">see letter 345, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_340">Ed. Manet, étude biographique et critique</ref></hi>. This study of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Edouard Manet</rs> in several dozen pages appeared in January 1867 in the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Revue du XIXe Siècle</hi> and was published separately in the same year. It was a defence of the artist, a ‘statement’ (procès-verbal) that Zola wrote ‘in honour of truth’ (pour l’honneur de la vérité). See Zola 1966-1970, vol. 12, p. 824.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> was taken ill in November 1882 and recovered slowly (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let290.xml">letters 290</ref> ff.). This is why in the summer of 1883 he took the waters at Soden in Germany; see exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>In 1873 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs> had spent some time at a rest home in Godesberg in Germany; see Engel 1967, pp. 53-54.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            
      
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_728">Fritz Reuter</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_321">Gedroogde kruiden</ref></hi> and the figure of Bräsig, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let306.xml#n-6">see letters 306, n. 6</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let317.xml#n-3">317, n. 3</ref> respectively. The ‘water art’ passage is in Reuter’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_330">Herinneringen uit mijne leerjaren op het land</ref></hi>, in which Bräsig disappears to a spa for some time. ‘When Easter came round, Bräsig travelled to his water art’. He undergoes all manner of water cures and diets to get rid of his gout, but finally loses faith in the treatment. Ed. Leiden 1883, pp. 138-152 (part 1, chapter 8).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>For this cape and hat, see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1360">William Thomas Smedley</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A generation ago</hi>, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> 27 (3 February 1883), pp. 72-73. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1347">Ill. 1347</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>The print meant, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Along the shore of the silver streaming Thames</hi>, after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_838">E.A. Abbey</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_175">Alfred Parsons</rs>, was on p. 72 of the same issue of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_470">Ill. 470</rs>. The exhibition meant was ‘The Sixteenth Annual Exhibition of the American Watercolor Society’ at the National Academy of Design, reviewed on p. 71 of the magazine. The illustrations are a selection from the catalogue of the exhibition. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2101">Ill. 2101</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>For this request to be allowed to work in the Nederlands Hervormd Oude-mannen-en-vrouwenhuis, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let351.xml">see letters 351</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let352.xml">352</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    