<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh, The Hague, on or about Friday, 13 July 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let362"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b323 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b1036 V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>362</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>300</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>365</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-07-13">on or about Friday, 13 July 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0323" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0323" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000408_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1036" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1036" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001205_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Voor ik naar Schevening ga wou ik nog even een woordje met U praten. Ik heb ’t maar eens doorgezet met de Bock dat ik bij hem een pied à terre krijg<c type="kp">_</c> Misschien zal ik nu &amp; dan bij Blommers eens aangaan ook.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> En dan is mijn plan een tijd lang Schevening geheel &amp; al als hoofdzaak te beschouwen<c type="kk">/</c> s’morgens er heen te gaan en den dag te blijven<c type="kk">/</c> of anders als ik t’huis <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> zijn dat t’huis zijn in ’t middaguur te stellen als ’t te warm is en dan s’avonds er weer heen. Dit zou me nieuwe idees geven vertrouw ik<c type="kk">/</c> en rust<c type="kk">/</c> niet door stilzitten maar door verandering van omgeving en bezigheid. Ik zit anders hier wel nog diep in ’t werk. Vandaag nog eens den Weesman<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> gehad en wel voor iets dat me plotseling in ’t hoofd kwam ik nog eens door wou zetten voor ik aan iets anders begin. Ge moet weten ik toch nog eens in ’t weeshuis ben geweest op een bezoekdag.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Toen had ik daar het tuinmannetje gezien en geteekend uit het raam<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dat wou ik niet laten schieten en staat er nu op in dezen vorm zoo ongeveer<c type="kk">/</c> voor zoover ’k me uit t’hoofd herrinner.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gisteren avond heb ik een cadeau gekregen dat mij enorm pleizier deed (van die twee landmeters – want er is een tweede nog bijgekomen sedert)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> namelijk een zeer echt Scheveningsch buis met staanden kraag<c type="kk">/</c> pittoresk verkleurd en gelapt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb voor zoo veel me doenlijk was mijn schildergerij in orde gebragt &amp; aangevuld wat ik mankeerde en me van tramkaartjes voorzien &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Van morgen heb ik de negatieven gezien van drie photos<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Ik ben verlangend naar de drukken en heb wel hoop zij alzoo in ’t klein iets zijn zullen waarmede wij bij de illustraties zullen kunnen 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>demarches doen. Ik denk er over het tuinmannetje van heden ook te laten doen want dat figuur is veel<c type="kk">/</c> veel uitvoeriger dan in dezen krabbel<c type="kk">/</c> en entourage ook minder tam dan hier. Ik hoop U volgende week drukken van photos te kunnen zenden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6"> Maar kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou U wel vragen Uw uiterste best te doen om als ’t eenigzins kan mij nog iets te sturen want ik ben reeds à sec door een &amp; ander ik absoluut noodig had om Schevening te kunnen beginnen<c type="kp">_</c> Het hoeft niet veel te zijn maar iets om den tijd door te komen en in ’t duin niet absoluut op een droogje te zitten.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">De photos zijn Zaaier<c type="kk">/</c> aardappel wroeters en Turfstekers<c type="kk">/</c> laatstgenoemde kwam mij voor ’t best te doen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Vindt ge dat niet aardig van die landmeters<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zijn aardige<c type="kk">/</c> vroolijke lui die me veel gezelligheid al hebben bezorgd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ze beginnen werkelijk wel aardige schetsen te maken maar zitten beiden voor hun 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>eindexamen<c type="kk">/</c> een voor dat van landmeter en den ander voor ingenieur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Als ik me wat georienteerd heb op Schev. dan zal ik de vrouw nu en dan meenemen om te poseeren of ten minste plaats &amp; grootte van figuren aan te kunnen geven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik verlang erg naar U kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop er bij ’t werk iets zijn zal waar ge eenig pleizier in hebt en dat ge wat gevorderd vindt<c type="kp">_</c> Bock zag nog sommige geschilderde studies van verl. jaar en vond er iets in maar mij bevallen ze hoe langer hoe minder<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop er beteren te maken dit jaar<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Zondag krijg ik den photograaf<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> op ’t atelier om eens met hem te praten wat ’t best voor photos zou zijn onder de figuren die ik heb<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik zou niet weinig in moeielijkheid zijn als gij absoluut niets extras zenden kondt<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb enkel het bepaald onmisbare genomen voor de schilderdoos maar heb toch zoo goed als niets kunnen overhouden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Het Scheveningsch buis is me een meevallertje<c type="kp">_</c> Ik schreef U eens dat ’t me misschien gaan zou als toen ik jaren geleden ook te s’Hage woonde<c type="kk">/</c> dat het eerst een beroerden tijd zou zijn maar later prettiger worden.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> ’t is in menig opzigt dezen laatsten tijd gezelliger en prettiger geworden al. Nu adieu, doe wat ge kunt en geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Iets wat ik U nog wou zeggen is dat de figuurstudies voor de groote teekeningen in mijn oog veel beter zijn dan de teekeningen zelf.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Dat een vrij groot aantal van die figuren iets is wat ik al vast op ’t atelier heb en ik meen me van een blijvend nut zullen zijn in ’t jaar dat voor de borst staat<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Is niet dat ik moedeloos ben over ’t afgeloopen jaar sedert Uw laatste bezoek en nu<c type="kk">/</c> maar hadden de inkomsten iets ruimer geweest kunnen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> we waren met ’t schilderen verder gevorderd.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Het is een kwestie van den moed niet opgeven en niet verslappen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Tegen dat ge komt zal ik alles op orde zetten zoo dat we het makkelijk en geregeld doorkijken kunnen.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Maar zie ge wat lang bij me blijft<c type="kk">/</c> broer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Als de tijden moeielijk zijn moeten we zien elkaar althans zedelijken moed te geven zoo dat we het niet opgeven als epreuves komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">En als we onze sereniteit bewaren kunnen zoo is er hoop om tot iets goeds te geraken dat vast staat op zijn pooten.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Tegenover andere schilders tracht ik mij wat kort af en als geen oogenblik twijfelend te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Als we ’t volgend jaar geschilderde studies konden hebben<c type="kk">/</c> even vast geschilderd als de tegenwoordigen vast geteekend zijn<c type="kk">/</c> zoo meen ik dat we de bataille voorloopig gewonnen konden rekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Vóór dien tijd zal het er nog spannen en als we wat kracht kunnen vernieuwen zullen we die tot het uiterste moeten inspannen en in geen geval er te veel van hebben kunnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik denk dat vriend Rappard niet ongenegen zal zijn ons nog een handje te helpen nu en dan<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Hij heeft me onlangs gezegd dat hij met vernieuwde gedachten van mijn atelier was gekomen – en ik van ’t zijne ook<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> – maar de kracht waarover ik momenteel beschikken kan is niet veel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ofschoon ik van C.M. geen syllabe antwoord ontving op mijn schrijven<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en croquis van Turfspitters<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> en zandgroef<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> zoo geef ik hem niet geheel op.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Verleden jaar was hij over de laatste zending teekeningen niet in zijn humeur en schreef me een onaangenaam briefje.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> ik repliceerde daarop dat Rappard die zelfde teekeningen had gezien en in plaats van ze minder te vinden dan mijn vorigen ze gedecideerd beter had gevonden. Ik was toen al ziek en kreeg C.M<c type="kp">_</c>’s antwoord in het gasthuis<c type="kk">/</c> hij had ze nog eens nagezien<c type="kk">/</c> ja er waren goede dingen in en als ik eens iets anders had zouden we verder zien. Ik heb echter niet direkt er op willen doorgaan<c type="kk">/</c> tot nu pas<c type="kp">_</c> Dat hij geen relaties wilde aanknoopen nu moet hem zitten in dingen die hij over “wangedrag”<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik met eene vrouw woon en kinderen zonder reeds getrouwd te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> hoorde. Met Francken<c type="kk">/</c> zijn eigen zwager<c type="kk">/</c> wilde C.M. ook een tijdlang weinig te doen hebben om soortgelijke reden weet ik<c type="kk">/</c> omdat ik met C.M<c type="kp">_</c> eens te Parijs geloopen heb zelf en hij me zeide “daar woont mijn zwager maar ik kan er niet naar toe gaan om reden dat hij met ‘een gemeen wijf’ woont”.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Nu echter heb ik expres C.M. betrekkelijk voor den uitersten nood in petto gehouden en ik denk er over dat het goed zou kunnen zijn als gij eenige van de beste studies hem eens liet zien en ronduit tot hem spraakt dat er hoop is op overwinning als we het maar uit kunnen vieren en volhouden en dat ik hem niet vraag om geld zoo maar doch overeenkomstig onze eerste afspraak van verl. jaar zou wenschen hij me geld gaf voor studies die ik zelf heel graag later weer zoude terug koopen van hem of ruilen voor aquarel of schilderij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ik heb eigentlijk van Oom Cent ook nog een bepaalde belofte dat hij teekeningen van me nemen zou doch ik heb hem er nooit meer over gesproken, sedert twee jaar geleden.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Before going to Scheveningen I wanted to have a brief word with you. I’ve confirmed with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> that I’ll have a pied-à-terre at his place. I may also drop in on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs> now and again.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> And then my plan is to regard Scheveningen as absolutely the main thing for a while, going there in the morning and staying there for the day, or otherwise, if I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be at home, allocating that being at home to the afternoon when it’s too hot and then going back there in the evening. I’m sure this will give me new ideas, and rest, not through sitting still but through a change of surroundings and activity. Otherwise, I’m still deeply absorbed in work here. Had the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Orphan man</rs><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> again today for something that suddenly occurred to me and that I wanted to press ahead with before beginning on something else. I must tell you that I’ve been to the orphanage again after all on a visiting day.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> That was when I saw the gardener and drew him from the window.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Well, I didn’t want to let that go, and now I’ve got it down in roughly this form, as far as I can remember.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Yesterday evening I received a present that gave me enormous pleasure (from those two surveyors — for a second one has since joined in),<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> namely a highly authentic Scheveningen jacket with a standing collar, picturesquely faded and patched. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ve sorted out my painting materials as far as was practicable, and replaced what I lacked and equipped myself with tram tickets &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">This morning I saw the negatives of three photos.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I’m looking forward to the prints, and have hopes that in this small form they’ll be something with which we’ll be able to make approaches to 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> the illustrated magazines. I’m also considering having today’s gardener done as well, for that figure is much, much more detailed than in this scratch, and the setting isn’t as dull as here. I hope to be able to send you prints of the photos next week. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But, old chap, I would ask you to do your utmost to send me a little more, if at all possible, for I’m already broke because of one thing and another I absolutely had to have to be able to start in Scheveningen. It needn’t be very much, but just something to tide me over so that I’m not absolutely without a thing to drink in the dunes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The photos are Sower, potato grubbers and Peat diggers; the last seemed to me to come out the best. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Don’t you think that was kind of the surveyors? They’re kind, cheerful fellows who’ve given me a lot of companionship. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">They’re beginning to make really charming sketches, but are both about to take their 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> final examinations, one to be a surveyor and the other an engineer. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">When I’ve got my bearings in Scheveningen I’ll bring the woman along now and then to pose, or at least to indicate the position and size of figures. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I long for you dearly, old chap, I hope there’ll be something in the work that will give you some pleasure and which you think shows some progress. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">Bock</rs> saw some painted studies from last year and thought they had something, but they please me less and less, I hope to do better ones this year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">On Sunday the photographer<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> is coming to the studio to talk about which of the figures I have would be best for photos. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ll be in no little difficulty if you absolutely cannot send anything extra. I’ve only taken what was definitely indispensable for the painting box, but have nonetheless been left with next to nothing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">The Scheveningen jacket is a nice surprise. I once wrote to you that things might turn out as they did years ago when I was also living in The Hague — that at first it would be a miserable time but become more agreeable later on.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> In many respects it has already become more pleasant and agreeable of late. Well, adieu, do what you can, and believe me, with a handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Something I also wanted to say to you is that the figure studies for the large drawings are, in my view, much better than the drawings themselves. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">That quite a large number of those figures are something that I at least have in my studio and, I believe, will continue to be of use in the year ahead. It isn’t that I’m dejected about the past year between your last visit and now, but if the income could have been a little more, we’d have made more progress with painting. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">It’s a question of not losing heart and not weakening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I’ll have everything in order by the time you come so that we can regularly look through it easily.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">But make sure you spend a long time with me, brother. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">When times are difficult we must give each other moral courage at the least, so that we don’t give up when trials come.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">And if we can preserve our serenity, there’s hope of achieving something good that stands firmly on its feet.
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">In the company of other painters I try to appear offhand and not doubting for a moment. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">If next year we can have painted studies, painted as steadily as the present ones are drawn steadily, then I think we can consider the battle won for the time being. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Until then it will be a close thing, and if we can muster some strength we’ll have to exert it to the utmost, and in no case can we have too much of it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I think friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> won’t be disinclined to give us a helping hand now and then.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">He told me recently that he had come back from my studio with new ideas — and I too from his<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> — but the strength I can muster at the moment doesn’t amount to much. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Although I haven’t heard a syllable from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> in reply to my letter<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and croquis of Peat diggers<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and sand quarry,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> I’m not giving him up completely.
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Last year he was in a bad mood about the last consignment of drawings and wrote me a disagreeable note.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> To that I replied that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> had seen the same drawings and instead of thinking them inferior to my earlier ones he found them decidedly better. I was already ill at the time, and received <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>’s reply in the hospital. He had looked at them again, yes, there were good things in them and when I had something else we would see. But I didn’t want to take him up on that right away, until now. His not wanting to have any contact now must be due to things he has heard about ‘misconduct’, that I live with a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs> without being married. For a time C.M. also wanted little to do with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_362">Franken</rs>, his own brother-in-law, for similar reasons; I know because I was once walking in Paris with C.M. and he said to me ‘that’s where my brother-in-law lives but I can’t go there because he lives with “a low woman”.’<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> However, I’ve deliberately kept <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> in reserve for just such an emergency, and I think it might be good if you were to show him some of the best studies and say to him plainly that there’s hope of victory if we can only get some more rope and persevere, and that I’m not just asking for money but, in accordance with our first agreement last year, would like him to give me money for studies which I myself would be very glad to buy back from him later, or exchange for a watercolour or painting. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">In fact, I also have a certain promise from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Cent</rs> that he would take drawings from me, but I’ve never spoken to him about it again, and it’s two years ago now.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent asks Theo to send a little extra, because he is already broke as a result of spending money in order to be able to start painting in Scheveningen (<ref target="#l-49">l. 49</ref> and <ref target="#l-82">ll. 82-85</ref>). That places this letter after <ref target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref> of on or about 11 July 1883, since there he wrote that he wanted to work in Scheveningen. It must also have been written before the coming Sunday, when he is expecting a photographer (<ref target="#l-79">l. 79</ref>; in <ref target="let363.xml">letter 363</ref> this photographer indeed turns out to have come). We therefore date the letter on or about Friday, 13 July 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The second sheet was not a separate letter (although it was treated as such in <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990, as 364 [-]). It must have been a postscript to one of the letters of mid-July 1883; cf. ‘something I also wanted to say to you’ <ref target="#l-93">(l. 93)</ref>. In this fragment Vincent writes about his progress in the past year, by which he must mean the period since Theo last visited the studio, namely the beginning of August 1882 <ref target="#l-103">(ll. 103-105)</ref>. Theo’s visit in 1883 was planned for ‘the beginning of August’ (<ref target="let361.xml">see letter 361</ref>). It is less likely that this fragment was a postscript to <ref target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref> of on or about 11 July 1883: that letter already has a postscript, and Van Gogh would then have had to have used the same phrasing twice in relation to Uncle Cor, from whom he had not received ‘a syllable in reply’ <ref target="#l-59">(l. 59)</ref>. Furthermore, the present postscript contains a reference to renewing acquaintance with a number of painters in The Hague (cf. <ref target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref>), in front of whom he says he tries ‘to appear offhand’ <ref target="#l-38">(l. 38)</ref>. On these grounds we have placed this postscript with <ref target="let362.xml">letter 362</ref>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Storage of painting materials at De Bock’s <ref target="let360.xml">(360)</ref> </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo (<ref target="let361.xml">361</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs>’s studio was at Van Stolkweg 20; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs> lived at Van Stolkweg 17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s model was the orphan man <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let267.xml">see letter 267</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The Nederlands Hervormd Oude-mannen-en-vrouwenhuis at Z. Buitensingel 1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This was the beginning of June (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let351.xml">see letter 351</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The drawing on which the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gardener near a gnarled apple tree </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_103">F - / JH 380</rs>) is based is not known. The lithograph with the same title, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3030">(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3030">F 1659 / JH 379</rs>)</rs>, has, however, survived.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>It is not known who this ‘second’ surveyor – in addition to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">Antoine Philippe Furnée</rs> – was. As becomes apparent later in the letter, like the 21-year-old Furnée, he was an examination candidate. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The photographs are specified later in the letter. The three photographs have survived from the estate of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">L.W.R. Wenckebach</rs>. They belonged to the collection of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs>, who must have been given them by Van Gogh. The drawings after which the photographs were made have been lost. They are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Potato grubbers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2442">F 1034 / JH 372</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2443">F 1035 / JH 374</rs>). There are prints in the RKD in The Hague and the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam (inv. nos. p 628-630). See exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, pp. 146-147, cat. nos. 43-45.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For this photographer, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let361.xml#n-34">see letter 361, n. 34.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Which particular letter fragment Van Gogh has in mind here has not been established. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written the same before, in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>A reference to the earlier loan of 25 guilders from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let339.xml">see letter 339</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had visited Van Gogh in mid-May; Van Gogh returned the courtesy on or about 21 May: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let343.xml">see letters 343</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let345.xml">345</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Vincent reported to Theo on 3 June 1883 that he had written to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let349.xml">see letter 349</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>An unknown sketch after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>It is not certain whether this sketch was made after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The sandpit at Dekkersduin near The Hague</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2439">F 1029 / JH 366</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The question Van Gogh mentions relates to what took place in June 1882 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml">see letters 235</ref>-<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let237.xml">237</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_362">Daniël Franken Dzn</rs> was the brother of C.M. van Gogh’s second wife <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_74">Johanna Franken</rs>. From 1871 he lived in Paris. It is not known who was meant by the ‘low’ (working class) woman.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let204.xml">letter 204</ref> Van Gogh had also written that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs> had said this in the summer of 1881; around that time he had received a paintbox from him (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let173.xml">letter 173</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    