<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh, The Hague, Sunday, 22 July 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let364"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b325 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>364</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>302</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>367</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-07-22">Sunday, 22 July 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0325 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0325 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000412_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0325 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000413_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000413_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0325 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000413_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000413_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Zondagavond.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Beste broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Of het koortsachtigheid is of zenuwen of iets anders weet ik niet – maar ik voel mij niet wel. Ik denk aan die expressie in Uw brief<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in verband met verschillende dingen<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan noodig is hoop ik<c type="kk">/</c> en heb een onrustig gevoel dat ik niet van me af kan zetten ofschoon ik het heb getracht af te leiden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Er is immers niets<c type="kk">/</c> of is er wel wat? als er wat is<c type="kk">/</c> spreek dan ronduit wat voor soort van obstacles er zouden in den wind zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Schrijf in elk geval eens<c type="kk">/</c> als ’t kan per ommegaande<c type="kk">/</c> of er iets is of niet<c type="kp">_</c> Ik kan ’t niet helpen als het zonder oorzaak is maar ik ben in eens beroerd geworden<c type="kk">/</c> het kan reactie zijn van dat ik me overspannen heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Schrijf me eens in elk geval kerel<c type="kp">_</c> hebt ge de photos gekregen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik ga nog een eind loopen om te zien of het wegtrekt<c type="kp">_</c> Gegroet en</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik heb eigentlijk geen vriend behalve U en als ik beroerd ben zijt gij me altijd in de gedachten. Ik wou ge maar eens hier waart en we toch nog eens overleggen <supplied>k</supplied>onden over een verhuizing naar buiten. </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Behalve wat ik U reeds schreef is er anders niets bijzonders met mij en gaan de dingen wel – maar ik kan wel wat binnenkoorts<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> gekregen hebben of zoo en ben beroerd gewor<supplied>d</supplied>en ineens<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb weer moeten betalen regts en links<c type="kk">/</c> huisheer<c type="kk">/</c> verf<c type="kk">/</c> bakker<c type="kk">/</c> kruidenier<c type="kk">/</c> schoenmaker<c type="kk">/</c> weet ik wat<c type="kk">/</c> en het overschotje is weinig<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin<c type="kk">/</c> maar ’t beroerdste is dat men na veel zoodanige weken soms de krachten wat verminderd voelt om de dingen te dragen en een algemeene vermoeienis begint te voelen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Al hebt ge niet om direkt te sturen broer<c type="kk">/</c> zie dat in elk geval ge mij eens zoo ge kunt per ommegaande schrijft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En met betrekking tot die bewuste toekomst<c type="kk">/</c> als er onraad zou wezen<c type="kk">/</c> zeg het maar gerust<c type="kk">/</c> homme avisé en vaut deux<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is beter te weten precies waar men mee zou te strijden hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb nog zitten werken van daag maar er overviel me in eens een malaise door merg en been die ik niet precies weet waaraan toe te schrijven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het is op zulke momenten dat men van ijzer zou willen zijn en het land kan hebben maar vleesch en been te zijn. Ik had aan U geschreven van morgen vroeg<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> maar toen ik mijn brief had weggebragt was het net of in eens al de moeite die ik al gehad had met een en ander zich zamen pakten en het werd mij te sterk omdat ik de toekomst niet begreep meer.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Anders kan ik het niet zeggen – niet begrijpen het waarom van dat het niet vlotten zou met het werk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Mijn gansche hart heb ik er op gezet en dat kwam me als een vergissing voor<c type="kk">/</c> momenteel althans.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Toch kerel gij weet het zelf<c type="kk">/</c> waarop (in de praktijk<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t werkelijke leven)<c type="kk">/</c> waar zal men zijn kracht en zijn denken en geestesinspanning aan geven. Men moet er maar een slag in slaan en zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal wat doen en het doorzetten. Nu en dan kan het verkeerd uit komen en kan men stuiten op een muur als de lui het niet hebben willen<c type="kk">/</c> maar toch<c type="kk">/</c> men hoeft niet het zich aan te trekken<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar. Ik geloof niet dat men er zich over beroerd maken moet maar het wordt iemand soms te sterk en men wordt beroerd<c type="kk">/</c> al wil men anders. Nu dacht ik dat ik spijt had dat ik in der tijd maar niet in de Borinage ergens ziek geworden en kapot gegaan was in plaats van het schilderen. Want ik ben U maar tot last en ik kan het toch niet helpen<c type="kk">/</c> want om goed te worden zou men veel periodes door moeten en intusschen is hetgeen men maakt daarom niet slecht als men zijn best er op doet maar er zouden lui moeten zijn die het beschouwden in zijn verband en rigting en streven<c type="kk">/</c> en niet eischten<c type="kp">_</c> ik weet niet wat ze eigentlijk willen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik zie nu de dingen zwart in. Als ik ’t nog alleen was<c type="kk">/</c> maar het is de gedachte aan de vrouw en aan de kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> die arme schapen<c type="kk">/</c> die men veilig zou willen houden en zich voor aansprakelijk voelt. Het gaat goed met de vrouw in den laatsten tijd<c type="kp">_</c> Ik kan met hun er niet over spreken maar voor mijzelf werd het me al te bang vandaag<c type="kp">_</c> Werken is ’t eenige wat men doen kan<c type="kk">/</c> als dat niets helpt is men ten einde raad<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">En ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> het zit hem daarin dat de mogelijkheid om te werken afhangt van het plaatsen van ’t werk want men heeft onkosten – hoe meer men werkt hoe meer onkosten (ofschoon dit laatste niet in <hi rend="italics">alle</hi> opzigten)<c type="kp">_</c> Het niet plaatsen – als er anders geen inkomsten zijn – maakt vorderingen onmogelijk die anders van zelf zouden volgen. Enfin kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben er benaauwd over geworden meer dan ik dragen kan<c type="kk">/</c> over den algemeenen stand van zaken<c type="kk">/</c> en ik zeg U mijn gedachten. Ik wou dat gij maar eens spoedig kwaamt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Enfin en vooral schrijf eens spoedig want ik heb er behoefte aan. Natuurlijk kan ik met niemand anders zoo over de dingen spreken als met U want anderen hebben er niet mee te maken en zijn er buiten.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Alles en alles zamen genomen zal ’t er op aan komen dat we goed elkaar blijven verstaan en de vriendschap goed warm houden. Komt er dan ongeluk<c type="kk">/</c> we zullen ’t braveeren<c type="kk">/</c> maar broer laat ons elkaar trouw blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Ik win alles daarbij want zonder U zou ik ’t niet hebben kunnen houden tot zoover we nu zijn<c type="kk">/</c> gij wint er niets bij dan toch alleen het gevoel van iemand een carriere te geven die anders geen carriere zou hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">En later<c type="kk">/</c> wie weet wat we zoodoende nog zamen maken. Het schilderen om ’t goed te krijgen zal nog wel een periode van eenig scharrelen kosten maar als ge de studies ziet zult ge geloof ik toch zien dat het geen malligheid is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Dat ik U nu zoo dikwijls schrijf over geldgebrek<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is omdat de nood aan den man is. Men moet ligchamelijk niet te zwak worden en in zijn gevoel niet al te veel gekrenkt<c type="kp">_</c> En wordt het te erg en ’t vuur wat na aan de scheenen<c type="kk">/</c> is het pligt rond te kijken of men de omstandigheden niet wat bedaren kan.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik zou minder bezwaar in de toekomst zien als ik minder onhandig was om met de lui om te gaan. ’t vinden van koopers is als ik zonder U ben onmogelijk om zoo te zeggen en met U is het langzamerhand mogelijk. En als we ons uiterste best doen zal het op zijn pooten blijven en niet te gronde gaan maar we moeten zamen blijven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik nu heb er behoefte aan we weer eens elkaar zien en zamen nagaan welken kant ’t werk uit moet. Met de Bock en andere schilders<c type="kk">/</c> ik praat eens met hen maar ik spreek niet over de dingen als of ik ten volle hen vertrouwde en hoeven zij veel zaken niet te weten. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> zulke dingen als dat kleine incident van van morgen tel ik natuurlijk niet maar het contact met een boel onaangenaamheden van buiten af maakt dat men behoefte heeft alles eens te vergeten door te praten met iemand die ten volle de dingen begrijpt en sympathie heeft. Het alledaagsche is voor mij de dingen voor me zelf te houden en kort af me er door te slaan. Maar als men wat gevoel heeft zoo is dat alledaagsche niet voldoende en zoekt men naar waarachtige vriendschap en vertrouwen<c type="kp">_</c> Het is juist omdat bij tijden mijn gestel begint te bezwijken en ik de kracht om de dingen te verdragen voel verminderen dat ik het U ronduit zeg dat ik eens behoefte heb om rustig met U te zijn en elkaar eens te zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik heb dit jaar strijd gehad om het atelier vol te houden<c type="kk">/</c> vreesselijk moeielijk is het soms geweest aan den gang te blijven<c type="kp">_</c> En ik moet mijn kracht eens vernieuwen<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">En schrijf nu eens als ’t eenigzins kan – en dat kan toch wel – een keer meer in den tusschentijd die nog zou moeten verloopen tot we elkaar zien. Ik moet doorwerken en er is een gevoel van afgematheid dat me telkens overdondert, een algemeene flaauwheid die reactie is van inspannen en telkens terugkomt maar waar ik iets aan doen moet anders wordt het erger. Ik zou dit niet tegen de Bock of zoo iemand zeggen – maar U vertrouw ik genoeg om het te zeggen. Het is geen kwestie van moed verliezen of iets opgeven maar van meer kracht te hebben gespendeerd dan men missen kan en min of meer épuisé te zijn in krachten.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Sunday evening.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Whether it’s fever or nerves or something else I don’t know — but I don’t feel well. I think of that remark in your letter<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in connection with various things, more than necessary I hope, and have an uneasy feeling I can’t shake off, although I’ve tried to distract myself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">There’s nothing wrong, or is there? If there is something, say frankly what kind of obstacles are in the offing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Write in any case, if possible by return of post, and say whether or not there is something. I can’t help it if it has no cause, but I’ve suddenly fallen ill; it may be a reaction to my having over-exerted myself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Write to me in any case, old chap. Did you get the photos?<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’m going for a walk to see if it clears up. Regards and</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I don’t really have any friends except for you, and when I’m ill you’re always in my thoughts. I wish you were here and we could confer again about a move to the country. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Apart from what I’ve already written, there’s nothing particular wrong with me and things carry on as normal — but I may have caught a chronic fever or something, and have suddenly fallen ill.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’ve had to pay out left and right again: landlord, paint, baker, grocer, cobbler, I don’t know what else, and what’s left isn’t much. Anyway, the worst thing is that after many weeks like that one sometimes feels the strength to bear things diminishing, and begins to feel a general fatigue. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Even if you have nothing to send immediately, brother, make sure in any event that you write to me, if you can, by return of post.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And as for that future, if there’s something wrong, don’t be afraid to say so, forewarned is forearmed, it’s better to know exactly what one will be fighting against. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I did do some work today, but I was overcome all at once by a malaise in my very marrow, and I don’t exactly know what to attribute it to. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">At such moments one would like to be made of iron and hates being only flesh and blood. I wrote to you early this morning,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> but when I had posted my letter it was just as if suddenly all the trouble I had had with one thing and another gathered itself together and it was too much for me, because I could no longer comprehend the future.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Otherwise I cannot say — cannot understand — why the work shouldn’t be making progress. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I’ve set my whole heart on it, and that seemed to me a mistake, at least for the moment. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Still, old chap, you know yourself, on what (in practice, in real life), to what should one give one’s strength and one’s thoughts and mental powers? One must have a stab at it and say, I’ll do something and carry it through. Now and then it may turn out wrong and one may come up against a wall if people don’t want to have it, but still one needn’t take it to heart, need one? I don’t believe that one should make oneself ill over it, but sometimes it becomes too much for someone and one falls ill, even though one would rather not. Now I thought that I was sorry that I didn’t get ill and give up the ghost somewhere in the Borinage years ago instead of painting. For I’m just a burden to you and I can’t help it, for one must go through many periods to become good, and in the meantime what one produces isn’t bad because of that if one does one’s best, but there ought to be people who viewed it in its context and direction and aim, and didn’t make demands. I don’t know what they really want.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Things look black to me now. If only I was alone, but it’s the thought of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, those poor lambs, whom one would like to keep safe and for whom one feels responsible. The woman has been doing well recently. I can’t discuss it with them, but I myself found it too frightening today. All one can do is work; if that doesn’t help one is at one’s wits’ end. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And you see, the thing is that the possibility of working depends on getting the work placed, for one has expenses — the more one works the more the expenses (although not in <hi rend="italics">all</hi> respects). Not getting it placed — if there’s no other income — makes progress impossible that would otherwise follow naturally. In short, old chap, I’m more anxious about it than I can bear, about the general state of affairs, and I’m letting you know my thoughts. I wish you would come soon. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Anyway, above all write soon, for I have need of it. Naturally, I can’t talk about things with anyone else as I do with you, for others have no involvement and are outsiders.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">All things considered, what it will come down to is that we continue to understand each other well and keep our friendship warm. Then if misfortune comes, we’ll defy it but, brother, let’s remain true to each other. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I gain everything, for without you I wouldn’t have been able to carry on to where we are now; you gain nothing except for the feeling of giving a career to someone who would have had no career otherwise. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">And later, who knows what we can produce together in this way? A period of some struggling on will be required to get the painting right, but when you see the studies I believe you’ll see that it isn’t foolishness. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The reason I write to you so often now about the shortage of money is that the situation is desperate. One mustn’t become too weak physically and not have been too emotionally hurt. And if things get too bad and too hot to bear, it’s one’s duty to look around and see if one can alleviate the circumstances somewhat.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I would see less of a problem in the future if I were less awkward in dealing with people. Finding buyers if I’m without you is impossible, so to speak, and with you it’s gradually becoming possible. And if we do our absolute best it will stay on its feet and not founder, but we must stay together. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">I feel a need for us to see each other again and together see which way the work should go. I talk to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> and other painters sometimes, but I don’t talk about things as if I trusted them completely, and there are many things they don’t need to know. Of course I don’t talk about things like that small incident this morning, but encountering a lot of unpleasantness from outside makes one feel a need to forget everything for once by talking to someone who understands things fully and is sympathetic. The everyday reality for me is to keep things to myself and get by through being offhand. But the everyday isn’t enough if one has some feeling, and one seeks true friendship and trust. It’s precisely because my constitution begins to give way at times and I feel the strength to bear things diminishing that I say to you frankly that I sometimes have a need to be with you quietly and to see each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">This year I had a battle to carry on in the studio; sometimes it was terribly difficult to go on working. And I must renew my strength. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">And write now if at all possible — and that must be possible — one more time in the interval that must pass before we see each other again. I must keep on working, and there’s a feeling of weariness that overwhelms me time and again, a general weakness that’s a reaction to exertion and keeps recurring, but which I must do something about or it will get worse. I wouldn’t say this to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs> or someone like that — but I trust you enough to say it. It’s not a question of losing heart or giving something up, but of having expended more strength than one should and of having more or less exhausted one’s powers.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Since this letter follows on directly from <ref target="let363.xml">letter 363</ref> – which must have been written on the morning of Sunday, 22 July – and since it is headed ‘Sunday evening’, it must also date from Sunday, 22 July 1883; see also the dating of <ref target="let363.xml">letter 363</ref>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The order of pp. 5 and 6 has been reversed as compared to <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1990. The effect is to make the handwriting more compressed on the last page. </p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
 <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo (<ref target="let361.xml">361</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo had written: ‘as for the future, I can give you little hope’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let363.xml#l-5">letter 363, l. 5</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>These are three photographs of the drawings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Potato grubbers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2442">F 1034 / JH 372</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2443">F 1035 / JH 374</rs>): <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let362.xml#n-7">see letter 362, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘een aanhoudende koorts die het gestel langzaam ondermijnt’ (a persistent fever that slowly undermines the constitution). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This letter was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let363.xml">363</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    