<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh, The Hague, on or about Friday, 27 July 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let368"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b329 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>368</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>306</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>371</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-07-27">on or about Friday, 27 July 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0329" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0329" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000417_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Tot mijn verrassing kwam gisteren nog een brief van U met ingesloten bankbiljet. Ik behoef U niet te zeggen ik er blij om was en regt hartelijk er U voor dank. Maar het biljet heeft men geweigerd te wisselen wegens te veel gescheurd te zijn. Ik heb er echter f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 op gekregen en is ’t opgestuurd naar Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> wordt het aan de bank geweigerd zoo moet ik de f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 waarvoor ik kwitantie teekenen moest retourneeren<c type="kk">/</c> doch wordt ’t gewisseld aan de bank zoo krijg ik de rest later.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat gij schrijft in Uw brief omtrent dien strijd die men hebben kan over de kwestie of men aansprakelijk is voor de ongelukkige gevolgen eener goede daad – of men niet beter deed zoo te handelen dat men weet het niet goed is doch tevens men er toch zonder ongelukken mee uit zal komen – dien strijd<c type="kk">/</c> ik ken hem ook wel<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Als men het geweten volgt – ’t geweten is voor mij de allerhoogste rede – de rede in de rede – zoo komt men in verzoeking te denken men verkeerd of dwaas gehandeld heeft<c type="kk">/</c> vooral raakt men van streek als meer oppervlakkige menschen er zich over vroolijk maken dat ze zoo veel wijzer zijn en er zoo veel beter komen. Ja het is dan soms moeielijk<c type="kk">/</c> en als er toestanden komen waarin de moeielijkheden tot een springvloed stijgen<c type="kk">/</c> kan men er toe komen spijt te hebben men is zoo als men is en wenschen minder conscientieus te zijn geweest<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik hoop dat gij u van mij geen andere voorstelling maakt dan als hebbende ook voortdurend dienzelfden inwendigen strijd en dikwijls ook vermoeide hersens en als in veel gevallen ook niet wetende te beslissen over kwesties van of men beter of slechter deed met dit of dat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Terwijl ik aan ’t werk ben voel ik een onbepaald vertrouwen in de kunst en dat ik er komen zal<c type="kk">/</c> maar in dagen van physieke oververmoeidheid of als er finantieele hinderpalen zijn voel ik dat geloof minder en overkomt me twijfel die ik tracht te overwinnen door dan maar weer direkt de handen uit den mouw te steken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En zoo is ’t ook met de vrouw en de kinderen. als ik bij hen ben en het kleine mannetje komt op handen en voeten naar me toe kruipen<c type="kk">/</c> kraaijend van pleizier<c type="kk">/</c> twijfel ik niet in ’t minst of ’t is in den haak.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Al heel dikwijls heeft dat kind mij gecalmeerd<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Als ik t’huis ben dan is hij van mij niet af te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> zit ik te werken<c type="kk">/</c> hij komt aan mijn jas trekken of werkt zich tegen mijn been op totdat ik hem op mijn schoot neem. Op het atelier kraait hij tegen alles<c type="kk">/</c> zit uren stil te spelen met een stuk papier<c type="kk">/</c> een eind touw of een oud penseel<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is een kind dat bijna voortdurend vroolijk is<c type="kk">/</c> als hij dat humeur volhoudt zijn leven lang dan zal hij knapper zijn dan ik.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> wat zullen we zeggen over die kwesties van dat er tijden zijn dat men voelt er een zekere fataliteit is die ’t goede verkeerd<c type="kk">/</c> ’t verkeerde goed doet uitkomen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik geloof men het regt heeft die gedachten te beschouwen als voor een deel uitvloeisel van overspanning en als men ze heeft zich niet tot pligt moet stellen te meenen de dingen inderdaad zóó zwart zijn als men ze dan inziet maar<c type="kk">/</c> omdat men als men er over zou gaan malen krankzinnig zou worden<c type="kk">/</c> is het integendeel raisonable zich physiek te sterken alsdan<c type="kk">/</c> en als dat gebeurd is eens flink de handen uit den mouw te steken<c type="kk">/</c> en helpt dat dan nog niet<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">steeds toch</hi> <hi rend="italics">die twee middelen te blijven volhouden</hi> en het als iets fataals te beschouwen als die melankolie blijft. Op den duur zal men dan in geestkracht toenemen en het leven volhouden<c type="kp">_</c> Er blijven onpeilbaarheden<c type="kk">/</c> er blijft <hi rend="italics">sorrow</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> of melankolie maar tegenover dat eeuwigdurende negatieve staat positief het werk dat men zoodoende toch gedaan krijgt. Als het leven zòò eenvoudig was en de dingen zoo in elkaar zaten als de geschiedenis van den braven Hendrik<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> of een gewone<c type="kk">/</c> alledaagsche dominéspreek<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zou zoo heel moeielijk niet zijn zich een weg te banen. Maar nu is dat eenmaal zoo niet en ze zijn tot in ’t oneindige gecompliceerder<c type="kk">/</c> en goed en kwaad komen op zich zelf even min voor als zwart en wit in de natuur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu moet men zorgen niet te vervallen in opaque zwart – in bepaalde slechtheid – en nog 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>meer moet men ’t wit als van een gewitten muur vermijden<c type="kk">/</c> dat de schijnheiligheid is en het eeuwige phariseeisme<c type="kp">_</c> Wie de rede en vooral ’t geweten<c type="kk">/</c> de allerhoogste rede – de sublieme reden – moedig tracht te volgen en door te voeren eerlijk te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> hij zal moeielijk geheel en al verdwalen geloof ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon men niet zonder fouten en hoofdstooten en zwakheden ’t er afbrengen zal en de volmaaktheid niet bereiken<c type="kp">_</c> En er zal een diep gevoel van medelijden en van bonhomie door ontstaan geloof ik<c type="kk">/</c> breeder dan dat afgepaste dat den dominés eigen is als specialiteit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Men moge zoodoende nog door de eene nog door de andere partij als iets beteekenend beschouwd worden en onder de mediocreteiten gerekend<c type="kk">/</c> en zich zelf door en door niets anders dan een gewoon mensch onder de menschen voelen<c type="kk">/</c> men zal komen met dat al tot een betrekkelijk vaste sereniteit in ’t eind.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Men zal er toe komen zijn geweten tot een staat van ontwikkeling op te voeren zoo dat het de stem van een beter en hooger ik wordt die ’t gewone ik tot zijn knecht heeft<c type="kp">_</c> En men zal niet in scepticisme of in ’t cynieke vervallen<c type="kk">/</c> niet onder de rotte spotters hooren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Niet in eens. Ik vind het prachtig gezegd van Michelet en dat eene woord van M<c type="kp">_</c> zegt al wat ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> “Socrate naquit un vrai satyre mais par le devouement<c type="kk">/</c> le travail<c type="kk">/</c> le renoncement des choses frivoles<c type="kk">/</c> il se changea si complètement qu’au dernier jour devant ses juges et devant sa mort il y avait en lui je ne sais quoi d’un dieu, un rayon d’en haut dont s’illumina le Parthenon”.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> datzelfde verschijnsel ziet men in Jezus ook<c type="kk">/</c> die eerst maar een gewoon werkman was en zich opwerkte tot iets anders<c type="kk">/</c> wat het dan ook geweest zij<c type="kk">/</c> eene persoonlijkheid zóó vol medelijden<c type="kk">/</c> liefde<c type="kk">/</c> goedheid<c type="kk">/</c> ernst<c type="kk">/</c> dat men er nog door getrokken wordt. Een timmermansjongen word in veel gevallen een timmermans<c type="shy">-</c>baas<c type="kk">/</c> kleingeestig<c type="kk">/</c> droog<c type="kk">/</c> gierig<c type="kk">/</c> ijdel<c type="kk">/</c> en wat er ook van Jezus zij<c type="kk">/</c> hij heeft de dingen anders opgevat dan mijn vriend de timmerman van de werf hierachter<c type="kk">/</c> die zich opgewerkt heeft tot huisjesmelker<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en toch heel wat pedanter is en meer over zich zelf maalt dan Jezus.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik moet echter niet te veel in ’t afgetrokkene vervallen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Mijn plan is vooreerst te zien mijn krachten te vernieuwen en ik denk dat als die weer wat boven ’t laagwater<c type="shy">-</c>peil komen ik weer nieuwe gedachten voor het werk zal krijgen om mijn manier van doen een anderen kant dan dat drooge uit te sturen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Als gij komt zullen we hier nog eens over praten ook – ik geloof niet dat het een kwestie is van een paar dagen. In eenige dagen als ik wat eten naar binnen krijg<c type="kk">/</c> krachtiger dan den laatsten tijd<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik wel mijn <hi rend="italics">ergste</hi> <hi rend="italics">malaise</hi> kwijt zijn denk ik doch <hi rend="italics">het zit nog dieper</hi> dan dat en ik wou ik doorzetten kon tot ik eens overvloed van gezondheid en kracht had<c type="kk">/</c> wat niet tot de onmogelijk<c type="shy">-</c>heden behoort om te bereiken bij veel buiten zijn en iets hebben waar men met lust aan werkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Want het is eene daadzaak dat nu AL mijn werk TE MAGER EN TE DROOG is. Dat is me in den laatsten tijd zoo klaar als den dag geworden en ik twijfel niet in ’t minst of er is een algemeene<c type="kk">/</c> grondige verandering noodig<c type="kp">_</c> Het is mijn plan er U nog eens over te raadplegen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">als gij het werk van dit jaar gezien zult hebben</hi><c type="kk">/</c> of gij het met me zoudt eens zijn omtrent een paar maatregelen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en zijt ge het eens dan denk ik wij er wel in slagen zullen er boven op te komen. Wij zullen niet moeten twijfelen maar <hi rend="italics">avoir la foi de charbonnier</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik mag lijden het biljet gewisseld wordt. Ik ben enorm blij dat gij het hebt gelapt om wat te sturen want ik geloof dat het me een ziekte coupeert. Ik zal het U schrijven hoe ’t met ’t biljet afloopt. En als ge toch den eersten Aug<c type="kp">_</c> kondt zenden zou goed zijn. Ik geloof dat het altijd nog mogelijk is dat we bij ’t doorzien van het werk tot een ander plan komen voor ’t vervolg – wat<c type="kk">/</c> weet ik nu ook niet – maar er moet ergens werk zijn dat toch gedaan moet worden en ik net zoo goed kan doen als een ander<c type="kp">_</c> Als Londen wat digter bij was zoo zou ik althans het niet maar overlaten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Weet steeds goed dat het mij een enorm pleizier zou zijn als wij een artikel maken konden dat op ging<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">ik zou dan minder strijd hebben over het geld van U dat gij zelf eigentlijk best gebruiken kondt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Nogmaals dank en gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">To my surprise another letter from you arrived yesterday with a banknote enclosed. I don’t need to tell you that I was glad of it, and truly thank you for it. They refused to change the note, though, on the grounds that it was too torn. But I got 10 guilders on it and it has been sent to Paris. If the bank refuses it, I’ll have to return the 10 guilders, for which I had to sign a receipt, but if the bank changes it I’ll get the rest later.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">What you write in your letter about the conflict one can have over the question of whether one is accountable for the unfortunate consequences of a good deed — whether one wouldn’t do better to act in a way which one knows isn’t good but which will allow one to come out of it without mishaps — that conflict is familiar to me too. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">If one follows one’s conscience — for me conscience is the very highest form of reason — the reason within the reason — one is tempted to think one has acted wrongly or foolishly, one gets particularly upset if more superficial people are amused by thinking they’re so much wiser and are so much better at getting where they want. Yes, then it’s sometimes difficult, and if conditions are such that the difficulties rise to a spring flood, one can be led to regret that one is as one is and wish one had been less conscientious.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I hope that you don’t picture me in any other way than as constantly waging the same inner battle, and also often having tired brains, and in many cases also being unable to decide questions of whether it would be better or worse to do this or that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">While I’m working I feel an unlimited confidence in art and that I’ll succeed, but on days of physical exhaustion or when there are financial obstacles I feel that faith less and am overcome by doubt, which I try to get over by immediately setting to work. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And it’s just like that with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>. When I’m with them and the little fellow comes crawling towards me on hands and knees, crowing with delight, I haven’t the slightest doubt that it’s all right.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs> has very often calmed me down. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">When I’m at home he can’t be kept away from me; if I’m working he comes up to tug at my jacket or works his way up my leg until I take him on my lap. In the studio he crows at everything, sits playing silently with a piece of paper for hours, a bit of string or an old brush. He’s a child who is almost always cheerful; if he manages to keep that up all his life he’ll be cleverer than I am. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Well, what to say about such matters as that there are times when one feels that there’s a certain fatality that makes the good work out wrong and the wrong good? I believe one has the right to regard those thoughts as the consequence, in part, of stress and if one has them one shouldn’t make it a duty to believe things are indeed as black as one then thinks but, because if one were to worry about it one would go mad, on the contrary, it’s reasonable to strengthen oneself physically in that case, and really set to work when that has been done, and if that doesn’t help <hi rend="italics">continue nonetheless with these two remedies</hi> and regard it as something fatal if that melancholy persists. In time one will gain in strength of mind and carry on with life. There remain imponderables, there remains <hi rend="italics">sorrow</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> or melancholy, but against that eternally negative there’s the positive of the work that one nonetheless gets done in this way. If life were as simple and things actually worked as in the story of dutiful Hendrik<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> or an ordinary, routine sermon by a minister, it wouldn’t be all that hard to find one’s way. But the fact is they aren’t like that, they’re infinitely more complicated, and good and evil no more occur by themselves than black and white do in nature. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Now one must take care not to relapse into opaque black — into definite badness — and still more 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> must one avoid the white of a whitewashed wall, which is hypocrisy and the eternal Pharisaism. Whoever bravely tries to follow reason and above all conscience, the very highest reason, the sublime reason, and tries to put being honest into practice, is unlikely to go completely astray, I believe, although one won’t succeed without mistakes and banging one’s head and weaknesses, and won’t achieve perfection. And this will give rise to a deep sense of compassion and courtesy, I believe, broader than that measured quality that the ministers have made their speciality. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">So one may not be regarded as of any significance by either one side or the other, and be accounted one of the mediocrities, and feel oneself at heart to be nothing other than an ordinary person among ordinary people, yet despite all that one will arrive at a relatively fixed serenity in the end. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">One will be able to raise one’s conscience to a level of development such that it will become the voice of a better and higher I that is the master of the ordinary I. And one won’t relapse into scepticism or cynicism, not become one of the vile mockers. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">  Not at once. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> puts it beautifully, and those few words by M. say everything I mean, ‘<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs> was born a real satyr, but through devotion, work, renunciation of frivolous things, he changed himself so completely that on his last day, before his judges and facing death, there was in him something of a god, a ray from on high, with which the Parthenon was illuminated’.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Well, one sees the same thing in Jesus too, who began as an ordinary labourer and worked his way up to be something else, whatever it may have been, a personality so full of compassion, love, goodness, seriousness, that one is still drawn to it. In many cases a carpenter’s boy becomes a carpenter’s boss, small-minded, dry, mean, vain, and whatever one thinks of Jesus his approach to things was different from my friend the carpenter’s from the yard behind here, who has worked his way up to become a slum landlord<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and is a lot more complacent and much more preoccupied with himself than Jesus.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">But I mustn’t lapse into the abstract too much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">My plan is first of all to regain my strength, and I think that when that’s once more above the low-water mark I’ll get new ideas to steer my way of working in a different direction from that dry one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">We’ll talk about this again when you come — I don’t believe it’s a matter of a few days. If I get down some food, more nourishing than of late, in a couple of days I’ll be rid of my <hi rend="italics">worst malaise</hi>, I believe, but <hi rend="italics">it lies still deeper</hi> than that, and I wish I could carry on until I have an abundance of health and strength, which isn’t impossible to achieve if one is outside a good deal and has something one enjoys working on.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">For it’s a fact that at present ALL my work is TOO MEAGRE AND TOO DRY. That has become crystal clear to me recently, and I don’t doubt for a moment that a general, thorough change is needed. I plan to consult you again, <hi rend="italics">when you’ve seen this year’s work</hi>, as to whether you agree with me about a few measures,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and if you do then I think we’ll succeed in getting back on our feet. We mustn’t doubt but <hi rend="italics">have collier’s faith</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I hope the note is changed. I’m hugely glad you managed to send something, for I believe it spared me an illness. I’ll let you know what happens with the note. And it would be good if you could send on the first of Aug. I believe it’s still always possible that on looking through the work we may decide on another plan for the future — I don’t know what as yet — but somewhere there must be work that has to be done and that I can do as well as someone else. If London were a little closer, I for one wouldn’t leave it to others.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Be assured as ever that it would give me enormous pleasure if we could make an article that would find buyers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I would then feel less conflict about the money from you that you could really do with yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Thanks again, and regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">We have dated the letter on or about Friday, 27 July 1883; see <hi rend="italics">Date </hi>at <ref target="let366.xml">letter 366</ref>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo (361)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo sent Vincent a 50-franc note, as <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let369.xml">letter 369</ref> shows.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh gave one of his drawings the title <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sorrow</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let216.xml">see letter 216</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1738">Nicolaas Anslijn Nz.</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_351">De brave Hendrik. Een leesboekje voor jonge kinderen</ref></hi> (Leiden 1810) was an extremely popular children’s book. It is about a boy who surpasses everyone everywhere in virtuousness. Hendrik is god-fearing, helpful and orderly, always ready to listen to wise lessons.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This very approximate quotation is taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi> (‘Les aspirations de l’automne’): ‘Socrates was born a real satyr; and through his deep thinking, through the sculpting of reason, virtue, devotion, he remade his face so thoroughly, that on the last day, a God was to be seen there, by whom the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Phaedo</hi> was illuminated’ (Socrate naquit un vrai satyre; et par sa profonde pensée, par la sculpture de raison, de vertu, de dévouement, il refit si bien son visage, qu’au dernier jour un Dieu s’y vit, dont s’illumina le <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Phédon</hi>) (Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, p. 393). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let738.xml#n-7">letter 738, n. 7</ref> and A. Verkade-Bruining, ‘More about Michelet’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vincent. Bulletin of the Rijksmuseum Vincent van Gogh</hi> 4-3 (1975), pp. 22-23.</p>

<p rend="indent">In one of the poetry albums Van Gogh transcribed this passage correctly. See Pabst 1988, p. 30. Also quoted, with a few slight differences, in Jules Michelet’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12">La femme</ref></hi> (Michelet 1863, p. 175). Incidentally, in this book the Parthenon is mentioned (on p. 227).</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh may have borrowed the phrase ‘rayon d’en haut’ from the foreword to Michelet’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_162">Histoire de la Révolution</ref></hi> (1847). There he says he wrote the book with ‘just such a ray from above, so luminous a beam from the sky’ (un tel rayon d’en haut, une si lumineuse échappée du ciel). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Oeuvres de J. Michelet. Histoire de la Révolution</hi>. Paris 1888, vol. 1, p. 32. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let143.xml#n-5">letter 143, n. 5</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The carpenter’s yard was owned by the builder <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_813">P.W. de Zwart</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>‘A few measures’ may be an indirect reference to the question of net prices (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let366.xml#n-8">letter 366, n. 8</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For ‘collier’s faith’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let286.xml#n-17">see letter 286, n. 17.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘waar belangstelling voor zou zijn’ (for which there would be a demand).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    