<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 3 August 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let370"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b331 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>370</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>308</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>373</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-08-03">on or about Friday, 3 August 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0331 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0331 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000420_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0331 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000421_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000421_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0331 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000421_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000421_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw brief van gisteren en voor het ingeslotene. Gelukkig is ook het andere biljet gewisseld geworden tegen f<c type="kp">_</c> 23<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb de meest verontrustende dingen zoodoende kunnen dempen<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon niet alles want er moest veel af voor verf direkt<c type="kk">/</c> die ik intusschen had gehad.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zeer verlangend ben ik te weten of gij weer zoo van plan zijt te doen als verl. jaar<c type="kk">/</c> eerst een paar dagen naar t’huis en dan direkt naar hier.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Laat ons afspreken ge t’huis maar niet praat over bezwaren in de toekomst of weinig kans tot plaatsing van het werk.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Althans niet direkt<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons eerst eens zamen praten en kijken wat er nog is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Theo ik verlang vreesselijk om de aardappel<c type="shy">-</c>wroeters te schilderen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ik geloof dat het goed zou doen. En zelfs al werd het niet verkocht<c type="kk">/</c> het zou toch ons helpen om te vorderen<c type="kk">/</c> daar sommige personen soms veranderen als ze eens iets gezien hebben dat ze niet verwachten<c type="kp">_</c> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een paar studies er voor reeds gemaakt maar ik heb er nog niet genoeg model voor kunnen nemen en ik zie kans ze nu direkt nog veel beter te maken als ik maar eens een beetje bij kas mogt blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het is nu net de tijd en daarom van vacantie nemen kan betrekkelijk niets inkomen want zoo goed en zoo kwaad als ik vorderen kan blijf ik aan den gang. Toch<c type="kk">/</c> Uw idee van doen zooals Weissenbruch is ook het mijne<c type="kk">/</c> maar letterlijk <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ik het niet uitvoeren omdat 14 dagen naar de polders gaan me meer zou kosten dan 14 dagen t’huis blijven en ik al niet weet hoe ik t’huis de eerste 14 dagen door zal scharrelen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar anders<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als ik U met een woord schreef reeds<c type="kk">/</c> ik zit toch veel in ’t groen te kijken en maak landschapstudies of marinestudies om eens afleiding te hebben van ’t figuur en bevind me daar goed bij.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar het figuur roept me eigentlijk weer en wel zoo sterk dat ik tracht te doen wat de omstandigheden maar eenigzins toelaten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Als ik grif kon doorzetten zoo zoude de herfst niet passeeren zonder dat de bewuste aardappel<c type="shy">-</c>wroeters tot stand kwam.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik weet niet in hoever de studies die ik schilder met de teekeningen voldoende zullen zijn in de gegevenen maar quand bien meme zal ik zien er iets van te maken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Model is niet heel makkelijk te krijgen tegenwoordig omdat er veel werk op ’t veld is en ik wou dat ik er wat meer aan geven kon want dan was het te overkomen. Enfin ik zal – nu is ’t me nog absoluut onmogelijk – maar zoodra ik het er met mogelijkheid kan afnemen<c type="kk">/</c> eens een paar kerels een heelen dag zien te krijgen buiten in ’t duin<c type="kk">/</c> voor de aardappelwroeters.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dat zou de korte en bondige weg zijn en ik zal er mijn best op doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik hoop in de dagen die verloopen zullen tusschen nu en uw komst nog een en ander te schilderen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik voel me nog niet in orde maar gelukkig animeert het werk mij zoo dat als ik bezig ben ik de zwakte zoo zeer niet voel<c type="kk">/</c> maar wel blijft het me in de tusschenpoozingen<c type="kk">/</c> als ik niet voor de natuur zit<c type="kk">/</c> overvallen. Een soort duizeling soms en hoofdpijn ook bij tijden<c type="kk">/</c> enfin het is wat verzwakking. Ik heb het al uitgesteld en uitgesteld om me wat te versterken<c type="kk">/</c> daar er dingen waren die voorgingen en dat heeft wat te lang geduurd.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar gij zult U wel kunnen begrijpen dat het werk er nog al op aan komt en juist omdat ik er al veel aan gedaan heb zou ik er niet af kunnen<c type="kp">_</c> Gij zult het wel zien als gij komt<c type="kk">/</c> dat het zaak is wij ferm doorzetten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ge zegt het wel teregt<c type="kk">/</c> dat wat ik U schreef over de finantieele zaken zorg geeft<c type="kk">/</c> maar er staat tegenover dat wij er niet verre van af kunnen zijn ’t een of ander te maken dat<c type="kk">/</c> al is het tegen betrekkelijk weinig<c type="kk">/</c> verkocht kan worden. Het werk wordt mij veel klaarder.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">En als ik er over denk is het een kwestie van bespoedigen of vertragen alleen en dat wij later zelfs inhalen zullen<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs het verleden<c type="kk">/</c> maar het is een weergaasch doornigen<c type="kk">/</c> moeielijken<c type="kk">/</c> zorgvollen tijd waar we in zijn met dat al.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Als het me mogelijk was genoeg te krijgen om geheel en al voldoende verf en model te hebben dit saizoen<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zou er wel wat opklaren en veel ook geloof ik.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Enfin in elk geval is het erg best dat gij spoedig komt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Een heel zware zorg is mij dezer dagen grootendeels van de schouders gevallen. Verl. jaar beproefde ik herhaaldelijk figuurstudies te schilderen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> nu<c type="kk">/</c> ze werden toen zóó dat ik er desperaat over was. Ik heb het nu weer begonnen en ik heb nu niet iets wat me direkt hindert in de uitvoering meer<c type="kk">/</c> omdat ik veel gemakkelijker teeken dan verl. jaar. Toen raakte ik telkens in de war als ik mijn geteekende schets onder ’t schilderen kwijt raakte. en moest er lang op zitten om die schets te maken<c type="kk">/</c> zoo dat<c type="kk">/</c> als ik ’t model maar kort hebben kon<c type="kk">/</c> er absoluut niets van teregt kwam.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Maar ik heb er nu de grootst mogelijke maling aan als de teekening uitwisscht en maak ze 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>alleen direkt met ’t penseel<c type="kk">/</c> en den vorm komt er toch genoeg in om van de studie nut te hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Daarom zeg ik dat ik nu mijn weg klaarder zie<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet wel dat ik veel studies zal noodig hebben doch die zullen mij niet moeielijker vallen dan ze te teekenen. en daarom dit jaar veel schilderen en we zullen wel licht krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Dat hoop ik vast en zeker.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Zoo voor den winter heb ik het plan soortgelijke studies van koppen als ik U geteekenden een paar van stuurde<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> te schilderen. Ik zou dat zelfs direkt doen als het niet zaak was de figuurtjes op ’t land na te loopen terwijl ’t saizoen er is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">V.d. Weele is nu op reis gedurende de vacantie – ik hoorde hij heeft de zilveren medaille te Amsterdam voor zijn Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van de zandopladers.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Als hij terug komt in stad hoop ik wel nog veel aan hem te hebben omdat ik geloof dat die aardappel<c type="shy">-</c>wroeters in zijn geest zullen vallen en hij me bij het uitvoeren van mijn plan er mee nog nuttige dingen zal kunnen zeggen<c type="kp">_</c> En Rappard ook als hij terug komt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">De twee eerste figuren die ik nu dit jaar schilderde deed ik nog net als ik verl. jaar probeerde – eerst teekenen en dan den contour invullen.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Dat is wat ik de drooge manier zou willen noemen<c type="kp">_</c> De andere manier is dat men eigentlijk de teekening ’t laatst doet en te werk gaat door eerst de toonen te zoeken zonder er zich veel over te bekommeren<c type="kk">/</c> over de teekening<c type="kk">/</c> alleen trachtende de toonen in eens ten naastenbij op hun plaats te zetten en langzamerhand den vorm te preciseeren en de onderverdeeling der kleurtjes. Dan krijgt men meer dat het figuur als door de lucht omgeven er op komt<c type="kk">/</c> en komt er iets zachters in<c type="kp">_</c> Terwijl de kleuren fijner worden juist omdat men er dikwijls over heen gaat en de eene kleur door de andere veegt. Ge zult<c type="kk">/</c> als de twee eersten die ik nu maakte in hun tegenwoordigen toestand blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ’t verschil wel zien. Er is een tentoonstelling van teekeningen, die verl. jaar in de Gothische zaal was, maar ik vind het nog al bijzonder dun dit maal en weinig er bij dat men van dezelfden niet reeds gezien had<c type="kk">/</c> en meestal beter.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Er zijn een paar teekeningen van J<c type="kp">_</c> v<c type="kp">_</c> Berg<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> die ik al mee van de besten vind van wat er is<c type="kp">_</c> Meestal is het zoo dat Schipperus<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en zulken al van de besten zijn.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Betreffende het maken van die aardappelwroeters<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb gedeeltelijk de wording gezien van het groote Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van v<c type="kp">_</c> d. Weele nu pas<c type="kk">/</c> en bij Rappard al de studies voor de schilderijen die hij maakte verl. jaar. Zoo dat wat er zou komen kijken voor het definitieve schilderij ik wel zoo wat me vooruit kan voorstellen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Als het me eenigzins mogelijk is zal ik nog vóór dat ge komt eens in het duin een paar studies maken er voor. n<c type="kp">_</c>l. met model naar die velden achter Loosduinen gaan<c type="kk">/</c> s’morgens vroeg of s’avonds tegen de schemering<c type="kp">_</c> Ik geloof dat het iets zou kunnen worden. De compositie van de teekening zou nog wel wat aan veranderd worden en vooral het effekt meer bestudeerd<c type="kp">_</c> toch zou ik het ongeveer zòò houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik geloof dat de figuren krachtig zouden moeten worden en al de rest in een lila achtig grijs waas<c type="kp">_</c> In de teekening vind ik de verdeeling van donkere vlakken en lichtere niet eenvoudig genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> de figuren gedeeltelijk licht en gedeeltelijk donker zijnde en de grond eveneens. Of de grond en de figuren moeten meer tot elkaar gebragt worden en een donker silhouet tegen een lichte lucht vormen – of lucht en grond moeten meer een grijs dampig geheel vormen waartegen de tooniger vlakken der figuren uitkomen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Die beide effekten bestaan doch dat van de teekening is niet goed zoo als ’t nu is want het is te droog en te mager. en omdat de figuren met den grond te veel toonen gemeen hebben komen ze er niet af en de lucht hoort er niet bij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Enfin de toon moet gansch anders worden maar de compositie kan betrekkelijk blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Het is me een zekere rust te denken dat we elkaar eens spoedig zien zullen en eens zamen kijken hoe we ’t werk zullen voortzetten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Voorloopig zal ik zien er nog wat bij te maken en met het oog daarop zou ik erg graag het geld van den tienden een paar dagen vroeger hebben als het kon<c type="kp">_</c> Dan zou ik nog voor gij komt willen trachten die 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>studies in het duin te maken. Het kan er nu nog niet af daar ik zooveel heb moeten betalen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Gij weet wat gij schreeft betreffende de mogelijkheid eener teleurstelling met de percenten van de zaak.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Wel<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop die catastrophe geen plaats zal hebben doch we moeten het beschouwen als zijnde een meevaller als het dan goed uitkomt en van den tijd dien we nog hebben geen snipper laten verloren gaan<c type="kp">_</c> Er is dan geloof ik kans tegen dien tijd het werk zoo ver te krijgen dat er wat mee te doen is maar het zal er op aan komen door te sabelen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Het zou mij zeer verwonderen als ten langen laatsten sommigen niet begonnen terug te komen van gedachten dat ik iets absurds bedoelde of deed<c type="kp">_</c> Gij zult wel zien wat ik bedoel in de studies en<c type="kk">/</c> denk ik<c type="kk">/</c> U sommige onzer vroegere gesprekken over kunst wel herinneren<c type="kp">_</c> Wij moeten het hart maar trachten opgeruimd te houden en goed doorzetten<c type="kp">_</c> Wat mij dezer dagen een zekere mate van goeden moed geeft is dat ofschoon ik in verscheiden maanden niet schilderde<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof dat er toch vooruitgang is in de <hi rend="italics">geschilderde</hi> studies van verl. jaar en nu. ’t Geen komt omdat dingen van ’t teekenen en proportie meten die mij toen veel moeite kostten<c type="kk">/</c> nu betrekkelijk wegvallen en ik dus voor de natuur zittende<c type="kk">/</c> in plaats van als ’t ware om twee dingen te gelijk te denken te hebben<c type="kk">/</c> teekenen en schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> alleen aan het schilderen hoef te denken<c type="kp">_</c> Bij ’t opvoeren komt men wel weer in beiden te gelijk maar ook dat is anders.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal dezer dagen leven op hoop van Uw komst. Als ik wat voorspoed mag hebben met het schilderen dan worden misschien de tijden wat makkelijker<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">De 14 dagen tusschen nu en dat ge komt zullen echter niet heel makkelijk zijn om door te komen<c type="kp">_</c> Als het kan denk dan aan wat ik U vroeg van zoo mogelijk een paar dagen voor den tienden zelfs nog wat te ontvangen want dan zou ik zien die figuurstudies in ’t duin nog te maken vóór gij komt. à dieu en nogmaals dank voor Uw brief &amp; voorspoed in alle opzigten U toegewenscht. en geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you for your letter of yesterday and for the enclosure. Fortunately the other note has also been changed for 23 guilders.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">As a result I’ve been able to keep the most worrying things within bounds, although not everything, because a lot went off straightaway for paint that I’d had in the meantime. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m most eager to know if you’re planning to do the same as last year, first a few days at home and then straight to here.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Let’s agree that at home you won’t talk about problems in the future or the limited chances of placing the work.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> At least not right away, let’s have a talk together first and see what there still is. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Theo, I yearn desperately to paint the potato grubbers.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I believe it would come out well. And even if it isn’t sold it will still help us to make progress, since people sometimes change once they see something they weren’t expecting. Well, I’ve already done a few studies for it, but I haven’t been able to take enough models, and now I see a chance to do them much better right away if only I could have enough cash. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">This is just the right time, and for that reason there can be no question of taking a holiday, for I’ll keep at it as best I can. Still, your idea of doing the same as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Weissenbruch</rs> would be mine too, but I literally <hi rend="italics">can’t</hi> put it into practice, because going to the polders for a fortnight would cost me more than staying at home for a fortnight, and I don’t even know how I’ll scrape by at home for the next fortnight.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But otherwise, as I’ve already written to you briefly, I’m outdoors a great deal, looking and doing landscape studies or seascape studies to have a distraction from the figure for once, and feel fine doing that.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But in fact the figure calls to me again, and so strongly that I try to do what circumstances to some extent permit. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">If I could press ahead resolutely, the autumn wouldn’t pass without the potato grubbers being done. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I don’t know to what extent the studies I’m painting from the drawings will be satisfactory in the circumstances, but all the same I’ll see to it that I make something of them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It isn’t very easy to get models at present, because there’s plenty of work in the fields, and I wish I could spend a little more, because that would overcome the problem. Anyway I shall — it’s absolutely impossible for me at present — but as soon as I can spare it I’ll see to it that I have a couple of chaps out in the dunes for a whole day for the potato grubbers. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">That would be the most direct route, and I’ll do my best. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I hope to paint one or two things in the days to come between now and your arrival.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I don’t yet feel in good health, but fortunately the work is so stimulating that while I’m busy I don’t feel the weakness so much, but it continues to overcome me in the intervals, when I’m not sitting before nature. A sort of dizziness sometimes, and headache too now and again, in short it’s a degree of weakening. I have postponed and postponed getting my strength back because there were more important things, and that has gone on for rather too long.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But you’ll understand that the work is rather important, and precisely because I’ve already done a lot to it I couldn’t let it go. You’ll see when you come that the thing is for us to carry on resolutely.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">You rightly say that what I wrote to you about financial matters is worrying, but on the other hand we can’t be far from making a thing or two that can be sold, even if for relatively little. The work is becoming much clearer to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">And when I think about it, it’s only a question of accelerating or delaying, and later we’ll even catch up, even with the past, but it’s a devilishly thorny, difficult, anxious age we’re in, all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">If it was possible for me to get enough to have sufficient paint and models this season, I believe there would be a brightening up, and a big one at that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Well, in any case, it’s very good that you’re coming soon. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">A very heavy burden has largely fallen from my shoulders of late. Last year I repeatedly tried to paint figure studies.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Well, I was driven to desperation by the way they turned out. Now I’ve started again and I no longer have anything directly hindering me in the execution, because I draw much more easily than last year. Then I got confused every time I lost my drawn sketch while painting. And had to work a long time to do that sketch, so that if I could only have the model for a short time absolutely nothing turned out well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">But now I don’t give a rap if the drawing is erased, and I always do them 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> directly with the brush, and enough form comes into it to make the study useful. This is why I say that I see my way more clearly now; I know that I’ll need many studies, but they won’t be more difficult for me than drawing them. And so plenty of painting this year and we’ll have light. That’s certainly my hope. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">This winter I plan to paint studies of heads like the few drawn ones I sent you.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I would do that right away were it not that the figures have to be followed in the fields while the season lasts.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> is now travelling during the holidays — I heard that he has got the silver medal at Amsterdam for his painting of the sand loaders.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> When he’s back in town I hope that he’ll be a great help to me because I believe the potato grubbers will be to his liking and that he’ll be able to give me useful tips when I carry out my plan for it. And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> too, when he returns. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I did the first two figures that I painted this year just the same way as I tried last year — drawing first and then filling in the outline.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> That’s what I would call the dry manner. In the other manner one in fact does the drawing last and begins work by first seeking the tones without worrying much about it, about the drawing, just trying to put the tones roughly in their place in one go and to gradually define the form and the subdivision of the colours. Then one gets more of that effect of the figure coming out as if it’s surrounded by air, and it takes on a softer quality. While the colours become more delicate, because one goes over them often and sweeps one colour through another. You will surely see the difference if the first two I’ve done now stay in their present state. There’s an exhibition of drawings, which was in the Gothic Room last year, but I find it particularly thin this time, and there’s little that one hasn’t already seen by the same artists, and generally better.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> There are a few drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_14">J. van Berg</rs><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> which I think are among the best of what there is. Usually <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1476">Schipperus</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and suchlike are among the best.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">As to doing the potato grubbers, I’ve just now seen the making of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>’s large painting in part, and at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s all the studies for the paintings he did last year. So that I can just about imagine what would be involved for the definitive painting. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">If it’s at all possible, I’ll do a few studies for it in the dunes before you come, namely going with a model to those fields behind Loosduinen, in the early morning or in the evening towards dusk. I believe that could be something. The composition of the drawing would have to be altered a little, and the effect in particular given more study, but I would keep it roughly as it is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">I believe the figures should be forceful and all the rest in a lilac-like grey haze. I find the division into darker and lighter areas in the drawing not simple enough, the figures being partly light and partly dark, and the ground too. Either the ground and the figures must be brought closer to each other and form a dark silhouette against a light sky — or sky and ground must form more of a grey, misty whole against which the more toned areas of the figures stand out. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Both these effects exist, but that of the drawing isn’t right as it is now, for it’s too dry and too meagre. And because the figures have too many tones in common with the ground, they don’t stand out and the sky doesn’t belong to it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">In short, the tone must be completely different but the composition can stay, more or less.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">It gives me a certain calm to think that we’ll see each other soon, and together look at how to continue with the work. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">For the time being I’ll try to do a few more, and with that in mind I’d very much like to have the money of the tenth a few days earlier if possible. Then I could try to do those 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> studies in the dunes before you come. There isn’t the money for them now, because I’ve had to pay out so much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">You remember what you wrote about the possibility of a disappointment with the percentage from the business.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Well, I hope that that catastrophe doesn’t happen, but we must regard it as a pleasant surprise if it does turn out all right, and not lose a fraction of the time we have left. I believe there’ll be a chance by that time to get the work to the point where something can be done with it, but it will come down to steadily hacking a way through. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">It would greatly surprise me if some didn’t finally begin to give up the idea that I intend or am doing something absurd. You will see what I mean in the studies and, I think, remember some of our earlier discussions about art. We must try to keep our spirits up and press ahead. What has given me a degree of encouragement of late is that, although I haven’t painted for several months, I believe there’s progress nonetheless in the <hi rend="italics">painted</hi> studies done last year and now. This is because things like drawing and measuring proportions, with which I had a lot of trouble then, now fall into place more or less, and so as I sit before nature I need only think about painting, instead of thinking about two things at once, as it were, drawing and painting. When working it up, one again has to deal with both at once, but that’s different again. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Well, in the coming days I’ll live on the hope of your coming. If I manage to have some success with painting, times may become a little easier. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">The fortnight between now and when you come won’t, however, be very easy to get through. If possible, remember what I asked you about receiving a little more a few days before the tenth, because then I could try to do those figure studies in the dunes before you come. Adieu, and thank you again for your letter, and wishing you good fortune in every respect. And believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent is awaiting Theo’s visit and must have received the remittance of 1 August (‘your letter of yesterday’, l. 1*), because he says he would like to have the money for the 10th a few days earlier than normal <ref target="#l-189">(ll. 189-190)</ref>. On the assumption that ‘yesterday’ refers to the <hi rend="italics">receipt</hi> of Theo’s remittance, the present letter is dated on or about Friday, 3 August 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo <ref target="let361.xml">(361)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard was taking the waters in Soden in Germany in July-August 1883 <ref target="let354.xml">(354)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>There had been problems about exchanging a 50-franc note Theo had sent; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let368.xml">see letters 368</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let369.xml">369</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For Theo’s previous visit to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> and to Vincent in the summer of 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let252.xml">see letters 252</ref> ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh evidently did not want to add to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526 bio.xml#_524">parents</rs>’ concern about his future or cause friction. On 2 August 1883 Mr van Gogh wrote to Theo: ‘O, we think of him so much, and in my heart I pity him so. What a difficult life he has chosen’ (FR b2244).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means that he wanted to do a painted version of the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Potato grubbers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2442">F 1034 / JH 372</rs>), of which he had done a sketch for Theo in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let357.xml">letter 357</ref>. The result was the painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Potato grubbers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2444">F 9 / JH 385</rs>); see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let373.xml">letter 373</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo must have suggested to Vincent that he should work somewhere else for a while, following the example of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1443">Jan Hendrik Weissenbruch</rs>, who regularly spent time in the picturesque polder landscape and lake area near Nieuwkoop and Noorden in the middle of the Netherlands.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let369.xml">letter 369</ref> Van Gogh described what he had seen in nature in the country.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This was around the end of August 1882; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let259.xml">letter 259</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Vincent means the drawn heads which he sent to Theo in January 1883 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let300.xml">see letter 300</ref>) and to which he referred several times in later letters, such as <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let301.xml">301</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let305.xml">305</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let318.xml">318</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>’s painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_499">A misty morning</rs></hi> and the silver medal, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let327.xml#n-1">see letter 327, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fisherman on the beach</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2391">F 5 / JH 188</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Scheveningen woman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2392">F 6 / JH 189</rs>). See cat. Otterlo 2003, pp. 34-38.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh went to the second exhibition of the Koninklijk Genootschap van Nederlandsche Aquarellisten (Royal Society of Dutch Watercolourists), which was held in Fluweelen Burgwal in The Hague. For the exhibition mentioned at the Gothic Room in the summer of 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let265.xml#n-5">see letter 265, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Among those exhibiting were ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_861">Joan F[rans] Berg</rs>’ and ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_14">J. van den Berghe</rs>’; the latter, who showed only one work, was probably Willem Jan van den Berghe. Van Gogh speaks of ‘a few drawings’, so he must mean the former, who showed <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_516">De zeeoogst</rs></hi> (Sea harvest) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_517">Strand bij winter</rs></hi> (Beach in winter). These drawings have not been traced. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1883, cat. nos. 8-9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Two drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1476">Pieter Adrianus Schipperus</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_518">Herfst</rs></hi> (Autumn) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_519">Winter</rs></hi> (Winter), were exhibited. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1883, cat. nos. 80-81.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Theo’s salary was made up of a fixed amount of 4,000 francs per year (payable in 12 instalments) and a bonus of 7.5% of the net annual profit of the boulevard Montmartre branch, where he was the manager. He was waiting for his bonus for 1882, which would amount to 7,242 francs. This was about 10% lower than the average bonus he would receive for the years 1882 to 1890. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 195 (n. 91), 33 (ill. 30); for the bonuses Theo received from 1882 to 1890, see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book</hi> 2002.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    