<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 12 or Monday, 13 August 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let372"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b333 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>372</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>310</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>375</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-08-12">Sunday, 12 or Monday, 13 August 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0333" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000424_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000424_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0333" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000424_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000424_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000424_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">’t berigt dat ge reeds op reis zijt bij dezen was me regt aangenaam<c type="kp">_</c> Dank voor Uw schrijven en het ingeslotene.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dat ik verlangend naar U uitzie behoef ik U niet te zeggen – ik ben deze laatste dagen ver van wel geweest – altijd hetzelfde – bij tijden hartklopping ook – waar het ten lange laatste bij mij wel op neer kan draaien dat het hart aangedaan wordt<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin ik weet daar zelf niet alles precies van doch wel weet ik dat ge t’huis of tegen wie ook er niet van spreken moet uit vrees van misconstructie in hun voorstellingen betreffende mijn omstandigheden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Waarvan ik alleen dit bedoel dat ik wat goeds maken wil quand bien même en er kans is zulks te bewerkstelligen als we onze sereniteit behouden, toekomst donker of niet donker.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Als ik wist wanneer<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. met welken trein ge kwaamt zoo zou ik U afhalen<c type="kp">_</c> En gesteld ge mogt bij mij komen terwijl ik uit ben zoo kan de vrouw U zeggen waar ik ben want om U niet te missen ga ik niet verder van huis dan hier achter op den Binkhorst<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> een paar studies schilderen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Zeer nieuwsgierig ben ik naar wat ge van ’t werk vinden zult<c type="kk">/</c> of er iets bij zal zijn waar ge iets in vinden zult of niet. Enfin we zullen zien<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ben wel steeds denkende er over de aardappelwroeters te ondernemen als groot schilderij<c type="kk">/</c> al zou het zijn dat het niet voor volgend jaar af kwam en dit saizoen slechts half af kwam. Mij dunkt de compositie zou zoo kunnen blijven<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en vast begonnen worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik ben niet competent te onderscheiden in hoeverre mijn onwel me gevoelen een physieke oorzaak zou hebben of voor rekening van overspannen zenuwen komt<c type="kp">_</c> Het is me wel eens als of ik U in den tusschentijd eens had moeten spreken kunnen en praten over ’t werk maar nu zijt ge toch eindelijk gekomen en dat ons zamenzijn in elk geval me calmeeren zal geloof ik vast<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Ik hoop we zamen eens een flink eind zullen loopen ook<c type="kp">_</c> Schreef ik U ik te Loosduinen doornstruiken heb gevonden precies als le Buisson van Ruysdael.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">’t Is in die buurt dat ik me voorstel studies voor aardappelwroeters te gaan maken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik mag lijden ik spoedig weer geheel normaal zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal er mijn best voor doen want ik heb er gruwelijk het land aan dat ik niet zoo voort kan als ’t zou kunnen zijn als ik mijn volle kracht had. Betreffende wat ik aan Rappard schreef<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik meende niet in de wereld te zijn om mijn gestel te conserveeren<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> zoo is dit een kwestie dat er omstandigheden zijn waarin men moet kiezen of deelen tusschen werken en niet eten of eten maar het werk laten waaien (dan n.l. als ’t werk onkosten vordert en voorloopig niet rendeert). Nu koos ik in sommige gevallen het eerstgenoemde en geloof niet zulks een vergissing is<c type="kk">/</c> daar ons werk blijft doch wij zelf toch in geen geval<c type="kk">/</c> en iets te doen leven is<c type="kk">/</c> en ik liever een paar jaar daarvan heb dan veel jaren van er maar over suffen en uitstellen. En ik zei toen tegen Rappard er bij dat ik voor mij meende er waarheid was in het mysterieuse woord<c type="kk">/</c> wie zijn leven zal zoeken te behouden die zal het verliezen doch zoo wie het verliezen zal ter wille van iets hoogers die zal het vinden.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> tot ziens<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">The news that you’re already on the way by now gave me great pleasure. Thanks for your letter and the enclosure. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I don’t need to tell you that I’m eagerly looking forward to seeing you — I’ve been far from well in the last few days — always the same thing — heart palpitations as well at times — in the end, with me it may come down to the heart being affected. Well, I don’t know all about it in detail, but I do know that you mustn’t mention it at home or to anyone else for fear of it being misconstrued in their ideas of my circumstances. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">By which I mean only that I want to do something good, come what may, and there’s a chance of bringing that about if we keep our serenity, dark future or no dark future. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I could meet you if I knew when, that’s to say on which train, you were coming. And supposing you come to see me while I’m out, the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> can tell you where I am because, so as not to miss you, I’m not going further from home than the Binkhorst<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> behind here, to paint some studies.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’m very curious to know what you’ll think of the work, whether there’ll be anything which you think has something or not. Well, we’ll see. I keep thinking about undertaking the potato grubbers as a large painting, although it wouldn’t be finished before next year, and only half finished this season. It seems to me that the composition could stay as it is<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and a start could be made on it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’m not competent to determine the extent to which my feeling unwell has a physical cause or is due to nervous tension. It seems to me as if I ought to have been able to talk to you in the meantime and discuss the work, but now you’ve come at last and I firmly believe that our being together will calm me down at any rate. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I hope we’ll also go for a long walk together. Did I write to you that I had found thorn-bushes at Loosduinen exactly like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>’s Bush?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">That’s the area in which I propose to do studies for the potato grubbers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I hope I’ll soon be completely normal again, I’ll do my best at that, for I thoroughly detest not being able to make headway as I could if I had my full strength. As regards what I wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, that I didn’t think I was put into the world to conserve my constitution,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> this is a question of there being circumstances in which one must choose between working and not eating, or eating and letting the work go hang (namely when the work leads to expenses and for the time being produces no return). Well, in some cases I chose the former, and I don’t believe that was a mistake, since our work remains but we ourselves defnitely do not, and having something to do is life, and I would rather have a few years of that than many years of just daydreaming about it and procrastinating. And I also said then to Rappard that I, for one, thought there was truth in the mysterious words, whosoever shall seek to save his life shall lose it and whosoever shall lose his life for the sake of something higher shall find it.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Adieu, old chap, goodbye for now, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for his remittance, which must have been that of the 10th; in the meantime Theo is on his way to Nuenen <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>. It is unlikely that he began his journey on Saturday because that was a normal working day for him. Moreover, it is clear from <ref target="let373.xml">letter 373</ref> of 14 August that Theo must have arrived in Nuenen the day before since his father had been able to pass on by letter the time of the train Theo was going to take to The Hague. This means that Theo must have arrived on Sunday, 12 or Monday, 13 August and that Mr van Gogh wrote his letter on the 13th. It must have crossed with the present letter, which therefore dates from Sunday, 12 or Monday, 13 August 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was sent with a letter to his parents, whom Theo was visiting. Vincent sealed the letter and wrote on the outside: ‘Monsieur Th. van Gogh Jnr’.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Planned visit by Theo <ref target="let361.xml">(361)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>De Binkhorst was a polder near to Van Gogh’s house and to the south-west of The Hague in the direction of Rijswijk and Voorburg.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means that the composition of the proposed painting would stay the same as in the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Potato grubbers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2442">F 1034 / JH 372</rs>), of which Theo had an idea from a letter sketch in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let357.xml">letter 357</ref>. In fact the painting (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2444">F 9 / JH 385</rs>) was to have not four figures, but five. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written about discovering this spot in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let369.xml">letter 369</ref>. For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Jacob van Ruisdael</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1707">The bush</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let034.xml#n-4">see letter 34, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh had written to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> about this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let341.xml">letter 341</ref>. The phrasing here – from which it could be concluded that Vincent is reacting to a comment on the subject by Theo – may indicate that Van Rappard had written to Theo about Vincent’s remark. It is also possible that Van Rappard referred to it in his letter to Vincent, which the latter had sent on to Theo (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let355.xml">see letter 355</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This biblical reference (Matt. 16:25) was indeed included – in a slightly shorter form – in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let341.xml">letter 341</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    