<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Tuesday, 21 August 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let378"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b339 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>378</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>316</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>381</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-08-21">Tuesday, 21 August 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0339" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0339" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000434_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief kwam heden en gaf mij in veel opzigten ruimte.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ontvang mijn dank voor de demarche bij C.M<c type="kp">_</c> gedaan – ik zal C.M. bedanken<c type="kk">/</c> hem eenige studies sturen<c type="kk">/</c> verder<c type="kk">/</c> over de vrouw vooral – <hi rend="italics">niets</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Toch nog één ding<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik zal U dezer dagen een brief schrijven die ik op mijn gemak schrijven zal en mijn best zal doen kort te schrijven en toch er datgene in te zeggen wat ik meen noodig te zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dien brief zoudt ge dan kunnen houden om – als gij staat of zult staan tegenover iemand die misschien te bewegen ware studies van me te nemen – zoo iemand precies mijn eigen gedachte en bedoeling te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Mijn gedachte vooral deze zijnde – één teekening van me op zich zelf zal <hi rend="italics">ook in vervolg van tijd</hi> niet ten volle voldoen. een aantal studies zullen<c type="kk">/</c> hoe uiteenloopend overigens<c type="kk">/</c> toch elkaar aanvullen. Kortom voor de liefhebbers zelf is het m.i. beter zij er een aantal nemen dan een enkele<c type="kp">_</c> En als ’t op ’t geld neer komt heb ik liever te doen met een liefhebber die goedkoop voortdurend zou nemen dan een enkelen keer slechts<c type="kk">/</c> al betaalde hij dan goed.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Misschien als gij b.v. C.M<c type="kp">_</c> in Uw of in mijn woorden nog eens datgene voorstelt waarvan verleden jaar kwestie was<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> zoo komt ’t er misschien op neer<c type="kk">/</c> ik me duidelijker uitdrukkende<c type="kk">/</c> hij meer in mijn idee zal treden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Enfin hierover later.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu kan ik U nog vertellen ik een bezoek heb gehad van Rappard en hij de grootere teekeningen zag en in zijn spreken er over hartelijk was. Toen ik hem zei ik mij wat slap voelde en dacht het komen kon wegens het maken er van niet van zelf gaat<c type="kk">/</c> scheen hij er niet aan te twijfelen of dit hoorde onder de begrijpelijke zaken.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Wij zamen spraken over Drenthe<c type="kp">_</c> Hij gaat dezer dagen daar weer heen<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en hij gaat ook nog verder<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk naar de visschersdorpen op Terschelling.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ik voor mij nu<c type="kk">/</c> vooral na ’t bezoek van Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> zou erg graag naar Drenthe gaan. Zoo zeer zelfs dat ik onderzocht heb of het verhuizen van het heele boeltje makkelijker of bezwaarlijker te doen zou zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Door intermediair van Gend en Loos<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> kan men de meubels (de kagchel en bed) zelfs meenemen door een halven goederen wagon te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> wanneer zelfs weinig of geen pakkisten noodig zouden zijn. Natuurlijk denk ik daarover wegens<c type="kk">/</c> al zijn die dingen die ik heb niet heel veel waard<c type="kk">/</c> het toch een groote uitgaaf is als men weer van voren af aan zich zou moeten installeeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Mijn voornemen zou dan echter zijn<c type="kk">/</c> gaan met vrouw en kinderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wij zouden staan voor de kosten van die verhuizing en reiskosten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Eenmaal daar geloof ik<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor vast in die heidestreek en veenderijen zoude blijven<c type="kk">/</c> waar hoe langer hoe meer schilders komen en met der tijd welligt een soort kolonie van schilders zou kunnen ontstaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het leven is daar zoo veel goedkooper dan hier dat ik geloof het mij f<c type="kp">_</c> 150 of f<c type="kp">_</c> 200 per jaar in elk geval reeds zoude bezuinigen<c type="kk">/</c> op woning vooral in elk geval.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En van het geld van C.M<c type="kp">_</c> mijn schuld betaald hebbende<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ware ’t misschien wenschelijk snel te zijn in die beweging. Eene reis derwaarts om poolshoogte te nemen zoude mij voorkomen als eigentlijk overbodig<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik heb voor mij liggen een kaartje van Drenthe<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zie daarop een groot wit vak zonder tittels van dorpen<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Wordt doorsneden door de Hoogeveensche vaart<c type="kk">/</c> die plotseling eindigt<c type="kk">/</c> en ik zie ’t woord <hi rend="italics">Veenen</hi> op de kaart dwars door ’t blanke vak geschreven<c type="kp">_</c> Rondom dat blanke vak een aantal zwarte stipjes met dorpsnamen<c type="kk">/</c> een roode stip voor het stadje Hoogeveen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Aan de grens een meer – ’t zwarte meer – een naam die te denken geeft – allerlei baggerlui stel ik me op de oevers voor.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Enkele dorpsnamen als Oosterheuvelen<c type="kk">/</c> Erica<c type="kk">/</c> hebben ook iets dat te denken geeft.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Enfin deel mij eens mede wat gij zoudt denken van de mogelijkheid eener snelle beweging van verhuizen naar die streek. Als er van kwam<c type="kk">/</c> ik zoude beginnen met op gegevens van Rappards ondervinding daar af te gaan<c type="kp">_</c> Dan zijn raad volgen van meer in dien achterhoek te gaan waarvan ik u beschrijf hoe ’t zich op de kaart voordoet. Ik zie dezer dagen een uitvoerige kaart van Drenthe te krijgen met de aanduiding der terreinen er op.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Wel zouden we staan voor eene onmiddelijke uitgave maar op den duur zouden we veel uithalen<ptr target="#note-t-"/> geloof ik<c type="kp">_</c> Meer dan dat reken ik van belang ik zoude zijn in een streek zeker zeer opwekkend<c type="kk">/</c> zeker van zelf stemmende tot al wat serieus is<c type="kk">/</c> en mijn werk er niet anders dan op verbeteren kan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Hoe groot zoude die uitgave zijn? ik zal U dat dezer dagen eens uitrekenen meer naauwkeurig<c type="kp">_</c> Ik veronderstel de heele familie doorgaat voor 2 1/2 (men <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> echter eisschen voor 3) persoon<c type="kp">_</c> De reiskosten staan in mijn spoorboekje niet maar zullen veronderstel ik onder de f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 per persoon blijven.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> 1/2 wagon tot Assen werd geschat door Gend &amp; Loos op f<c type="kp">_</c> 20<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Men zoude evenwel zich eenigzins moeten prepareeren op eenige dagen verblijf in de herberg<c type="kk">/</c> wat ± f<c type="kp">_</c> 1 per persoon per dag bedraagt<c type="kp">_</c> Hier is de huishuur vooral en bovendien de duurte van alles voor mij assommant<c type="kp">_</c> En de allerzwaarste uitgaaf<c type="kk">/</c> die van model<c type="kk">/</c> zou ginder zeer zeker in dit opzigt verschillen dat ik met ’t zelfde meer en beter model zou hebben of met minder geld evenveel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik zoude wel denken dat indien ik ergens daar me zou vestigen<c type="kk">/</c> Rappard in die zelfde streek nog meer zou komen dan nu en wij eenige gezelligheid aan elkaar zouden hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Zooals ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> vooral sedert zijn bezoek en wat wij zamen bespraken omtrent het werk<c type="kk">/</c> fixeerde zich mijn idee op Drenthe. Overigens ik kan ook desnoods hier zoeken naar goedkoopere woning en ik vind het hier ook mooi<c type="kp">_</c> Maar toch – ik wou wel eens met de natuur alleen zijn – zonder stad<c type="kp">_</c>– Hoeveel genoegen ’t geen ge omtrent het werk zegt mij geeft<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik U moeielijk zeggen – ik ben blij gij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> er iets bij doen is eigentlijk verkeerde politiek<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Men vervalt daardoor in halve maatregelen die een half mensch van iemand maken<c type="kp">_</c> Dat waar wij op werken moeten is dat het quelque chose de mâle<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> er <hi rend="italics">nog meer</hi> in komt<c type="kp">_</c> Dat gij iets daarvan nu reeds ziet geloof ik niet ge zult hoeven terug te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral niet als ik mijn kracht terug heb. Het is nu wel lastig dat mijn maag zelfs het gewone niet verdragen kan<c type="kk">/</c> en mijn <hi rend="italics">trek</hi> zou wezen als ik er aan toegaf – alleen zure appelen. Ik geef daar <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> aan toe<c type="kk">/</c> doch genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> er <hi rend="italics">is</hi> verslapping<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan regt is. Ik verwacht nog een brief van Rappard over Drenthe ook. In elk geval schrijf ik U spoedig nog ook over een plan van eenvoudig hier blijven als ik van mijn huisbaas<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> informatie hebben zal over een woning te Voorburg die hij zegt ik misschien goedkoop zou kunnen krijgen. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> nogmaals hartelijk dank<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter arrived today and gave me leeway in many respects.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Accept my thanks for the step taken with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> — I’ll thank C.M., send him some studies, otherwise, especially about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>, <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> But just one more thing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ll write you a letter in the next few days which I’ll write at my leisure, and I’ll do my best to write briefly and still say what I believe is necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You could then keep this letter so that — when you’re with someone who might be persuaded to take studies by me — you can explain to them my precise idea and intention.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> My idea being this above all — a single drawing by me won’t be entirely satisfactory in itself, <hi rend="italics">even in the future</hi>. A number of studies, no matter how diverse, will still complement each other. In short, in my view it would be better for the art lovers themselves if they took several rather than just one. And if it comes down to a question of money, I would rather have an art lover who bought regularly at a low price than one who only bought occasionally, even if he paid well. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Perhaps if you again proposed to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.,</rs> say, in your words or mine, what was raised last year,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> the outcome might be that he might see more in my idea if I expressed myself more clearly. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Anyway, more about this later.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I can also tell you that I’ve had a visit from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> and that he saw the larger drawings and spoke warmly of them. When I told him that I felt a little weak and thought this might be because doing them isn’t easy, he seemed not to doubt that this was one of the understandable matters.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">We talked about Drenthe. He’s going there again shortly,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and he’s going still further, namely to the fishing villages on Terschelling.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> For my part I’d very much like to go to Drenthe, especially after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s visit. So much so, indeed, that I’ve looked into whether moving all the things would be easy or difficult. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Through Van Gend &amp; Loos<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> one could even take along the furniture (the stove and bed) by taking half a goods wagon, in which case hardly any packing cases would be needed. Of course I’m considering that because, although the things I have aren’t worth very much, it would still be a big outlay if one had to set up house all over again. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But my intention would then be to go with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">We’d be faced with the costs of moving and the travel costs. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Once there, I believe I would stay for good in the heathland and the peat districts, where more and more painters are coming, and in time a kind of painters’ colony might develop.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Life there is so much cheaper than here that I believe it would save me 150 or 200 guilders a year in any case, on housing especially in any case.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And having paid my debt with the money from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> it might be desirable to make the move quickly. A journey there to assess the situation would seem to me unnecessary, really. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I have a map of Drenthe in front of me. On it I see a large white area with no names of villages. It’s crossed by the Hoogeveen waterway, which ends suddenly, and I see the words <hi rend="italics">Peat moors</hi> written on the map straight across the blank area. Around that blank area a number of black dots with the names of villages, a red dot for the small town of Hoogeveen. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">On the boundary a lake — the black lake — a name that gives pause for thought — I imagine various dredging workers on the banks. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Several village names, like Oosterheuvelen, Erica, also make one think.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Anyway, let me know what you think of the possibility of a rapid move to that region. If it were to happen, I’d begin by going by information from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s experiences there. Then follow his advice to go further into the remoter part whose appearance on the map I’ve described. One of these days I’ll try to get hold of a detailed map of Drenthe showing the types of terrain.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">We’d be faced by immediate expenditure, but in the end I believe we’d gain a great deal by it. More than that, I consider it important that I’d be in a region that’s sure to be very stimulating and sure to incline one naturally towards everything serious, and my work can only be improved by it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">How much would the expenditure be? I’ll work it out more precisely for you in the next few days. I assume the whole family counts as 2  1/2  people (but they <hi rend="italics">may</hi> insist on 3). The travel costs aren’t given in my timetable, but will be less than 10 guilders per person, I assume.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Gend &amp; Loos estimated that a  1/2 wagon to Assen would be 20 guilders. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">One would have to be prepared, though, to stay at the inn for a few days, which costs around 1 guilder per person per day. Here the rent above all, and moreover the cost of everything, is nerve-racking. And the heaviest expense, the cost of models, would most certainly be different over there in the sense that for the same amount I could get more and better models or the same number for less money. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I think that if I were to settle somewhere there, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> would come even more often to that area than now, and we’d be company for each other. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">As I say, my thoughts have become fixed on Drenthe, particularly since his visit and what we discussed in connection with the work. For that matter I can also look for a cheaper house here if need be, and I do find it beautiful here too. But still, I would like to be alone with nature for once — without the city. I can hardly tell you how much pleasure what you say about the work gives me — I’m glad you say that doing something else as well would really be the wrong policy.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> One would then lapse into the half measures that make someone a half person. What we must work at is getting <hi rend="italics">yet more</hi> of a manly element<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> into it. I don’t think you’ll have to retract your view that you already see something of that, particularly not when I have my strength back. It’s a nuisance that my stomach can’t take even normal things, or what I’d have an <hi rend="italics">appetite</hi> for if I gave in to it — only sour apples. I <hi rend="italics">don’t </hi>give in, but enough, there <hi rend="italics">is</hi> more weakening than is right. I’m also expecting a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> about Drenthe. In any case, I’ll write to you again soon about a plan to simply stay here when I have information from my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">landlord</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> about a place in Voorburg that he says I may be able to get cheaply. Adieu, many thanks again.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter is a reaction to a letter from Theo, which Vincent received ‘today’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-3</ref>). By saying that Theo’s letter gave him ‘leeway in many respects’, Van Gogh indicated that both its contents (such as the steps taken with Uncle Cor, <ref target="#l-3">ll. 3-4</ref>) and the enclosed third remittance of August offered him a solution. We assume that Theo passed on the result of his conversation with Uncle Cor as soon as he returned to Nuenen, thus on Monday, 20 August; so we date the present letter to Tuesday, 21 August 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This should be read as confirmation of the receipt of the third remittance for August. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
    
<p>In accordance with what had been discussed during his visit, Theo must have asked <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> to help support Vincent. Given the course of events in the following months, it seems that Uncle Cor took more than 20 drawings on consignment and was to send Theo an advance on them; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let380.xml">see letters 380</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let384.xml#l-50">384, l. 50</ref>. Uncle Cor also had ‘with the right to swap them later’, as <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let388.xml">letter 388</ref> shows. It is not known which studies Van Gogh sent.</p>

<p rend="indent">In connection with the remark about ‘the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>’: in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let376.xml">letter 376</ref> Vincent had written to Theo, ‘If perhaps you said something to C.M. about me possibly leaving the woman, then please take it back immediately’. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>No such letter is known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>In the spring of 1882 Van Gogh had twice made a series of drawings for his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> for payment (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let210.xml">see letter 210</ref> ff.). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had also spent time in Drenthe in the summer of 1882; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let256.xml">see letter 256</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Terschelling is a small island in the North Sea to the north of the Netherlands. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> visited the island three times: in August-September 1883 (when he stayed in West-Terschelling; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let388.xml#n-3">see letter 388, n. 3</ref>), July-September 1884 and in August-September 1885.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For the transport company Van Gend &amp; Loos, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let135.xml#n-19">see letter 135, n. 19.</ref> The branch in The Hague was at that time located close to Rijnspoor station. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>By ‘having paid’ Van Gogh means: as soon as I shall have paid, namely after receiving the advance from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let384.xml">Letter 384</ref> shows that Van Gogh received the money and did indeed act as proposed here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>No map that exactly matches Van Gogh’s description has been traced; Erica has existed since 1863, so the map must date from between 1863 and 1883. Presumably it was a map of the province of Drenthe similar to that of J. Kuijper, published by H. Suringar of Leeuwarden in 1882. This measures 18 x 26.5 cm (Assen, Drents Archief). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2115">Ill. 2115</rs>. By ‘Oosterheuvelen’ Van Gogh must mean the village of ‘Oosterhesselen’.</p>

<p rend="indent">It is also possible that it was the sixth edition (1883) of the map of Drenthe by J.J. Jaeger, published by W.J.F. Tjeenk Willink of Zwolle. Only the fifth edition of 1875 is known. See Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 72-74. For Zwartemeer (the black lake), see <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let385.xml#n-5">letter 385, n. 5</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-">
                            
<p>‘uithalen’: ‘besparen’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s estimate was a little too high. The cost of a single ticket to Assen via Deventer was 6.20 guilders for an adult. Children below the age of four – and thus Sien’s youngest <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">son</rs> – travelled free, while in the case of the six-year-old <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_467">daughter</rs> the reduction of 50% for children aged between six and ten applied (Information from the Nederlands Spoorwegmuseum, Utrecht).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>By ‘doing something else as well’ Van Gogh means spending time on activities other than drawing and painting for the sake of the money. He set out his views on this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let376.xml">letter 376</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>This term ‘a manly element’ came from Theo, as <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let379.xml">letter 379</ref> shows.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">M.A. de Zwart</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    