<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 2 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let380"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b341 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>380</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>318</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>383</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-02">Sunday, 2 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0341" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0341" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000437_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Heb dank voor Uw brief en het ingeslotene<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik wil er reeds heden op antwoorden. Het kan waar zijn wat gij schrijft – wat we ook reeds bespraken – wat ik en voor en na dien tijd zelf ook meermalen over heb gedacht – dat indien de vrouw verpligt was van mij af te zijn – op eigen beenen te staan – zij een regter koers zou beginnen. Wegens ze 2 kinderen heeft is het echter een zeer moeielijk geval maar wat zal ik er van zeggen – in de gegevenen is het iets waar zij zelf toe noodzaakt en <hi rend="italics">de omstandigheden nog veel meer echter toe</hi> <hi rend="italics">noodzaken</hi>. Ik onderstreep dit laatste<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Weet ge wat ik heb gedaan – ik heb van daag met haar een rustigen dag gehad – met haar er over gesproken lang en breed – haar uitgelegd ten volle hoe het met mij stond en dat ik weg <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> voor mijn werk en een jaar <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> hebben van weinig uitgeven en wat verdienen om ’t gepasseerde<c type="kk">/</c> dat me wat te zwaar was<c type="kk">/</c> in te halen. Dat ik voorzag dat als ik met haar bleef ik haar toch niet zou kunnen helpen meer over korten tijd<c type="kk">/</c> en dan alweer in schuld raken hier waar het duur is<c type="kk">/</c> en er niet meer uit kunnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zoo dat kortom zij en ik wijs moesten zijn en van elkaar gaan als vrienden. Dat zij van haar familie moet gedaan krijgen die de kinderen opnemen en dat zij moet gaan dienen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> het is zoo duidelijk dat ik het hier moeielijk zou kunnen houden<c type="kk">/</c> dat zij het ook wel begrijpt. En zoo is onze afspraak wij<c type="kk">/</c> op dit moment beiden in den brand zittende en het erger makende door bij elkaar te blijven<c type="kk">/</c> zullen scheiden voor een tijd of voor altijd<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als het loopt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik zeg er bij “of voor altijd” omdat zij voor haar kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mijn werk een reden hebben om te <hi rend="italics">moeten</hi> leven quand bien même en dingen zullen moeten doen tegen onzen zin en – misschien niet zoo goed zullen <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> zijn als we zouden willen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik heb tot haar gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> gij zult er wel niet kunnen komen geheel regt maar ga zoo regt mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal ook zoo regt mogelijk gaan maar weet vooruit ik verre van geheel goed het er af zal brengen in ’t leven. Dus zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> zoolang ik maar wete dat gij Uw best doet en niet <hi rend="italics">alles</hi> loslaat en goed zijt voor de kinderen zoo als gij weet ik er ook goed voor ben geweest – als ge maar zòò doet dat de kinderen bij U<c type="kk">/</c> al zijt ge maar een arme dienstmeid<c type="kk">/</c> al zijt ge maar een arme hoer<c type="kk">/</c> toch een <hi>Moeder</hi> vinden – zijt en blijft ge met al den bliksemschen troep fouten in mijn oog <hi rend="italics">goed</hi>. En ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik geen oogenblik twijfel of heb soortgelijke agrementen<c type="kk">/</c> zal niet anders worden hoop ik dan zoo als ik was<c type="kk">/</c> in zoover dat ik geen vrouw met een dikken buik of in de rats zal zien<c type="kk">/</c> of ik zal er ’t mijne van denken en doen wat ik er in doen kan als ’t in mijn weg komt.– Als het met U, zeg ik, zoo gesteld was als toen ik U vond<c type="kk">/</c> wel ge zoudt bij mij een t’huis hebben – een schuilplaats voor den storm – zoolang ik een stuk brood en een dak heb<c type="kk">/</c> maar nu is ’t zoo niet en de storm voorbij<c type="kk">/</c> ge kunt geloof ik een regten weg maken voor Uw voeten<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> zonder mij<c type="kp">_</c>– Welnu ge moet dat probeeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik voor mij zal me ook een regten weg voor de voeten zien te maken<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet hard werken en doe gij dat ook. Zoo op die manier heb ik er over gesproken<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Och broer gij ziet het wel<c type="kk">/</c> wij zouden niet van elkaar gaan als we niet moesten. Ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> we zouden niet van elkaar gaan als we niet moesten<c type="kp">_</c>– Hebben we elkaars fouten niet telkens vergeven en weer opgemaakt. Wij kennen elkaar zóó dat wij elkaar niet slecht meer kunnen vinden<c type="kp">_</c> Of het liefde is weet ik niet maar wat er tusschen ons is<c type="kk">/</c> is er tusschen ons<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Betreffende ’t moeten<c type="kp">_</c>–  Ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil ook niet in scharrelen vervallen<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil doorwerken<c type="kk">/</c> regt door – krachtig – doen wat gedaan moet worden in zake schilderen<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat<c type="kk">/</c> weet ik<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik niet verkeerd aan doen – dat wil zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet niet <hi rend="italics">hoe</hi> het zal uitkomen voor haar of voor mij als ik flink doorzet maar zeker zal het <hi rend="italics">beter</hi> uitkomen als ik desnoods alleen mij een eind verder sabel dan dat wij beiden in <hi rend="italics">stagnatie</hi> zouden vervallen door te blijven bij elkaar als we in elkaars wielen rijden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu kom ik terug op wat Drenthe betreft. Denk er eens over of gij een weg ziet voor mij om geld te krijgen voor mij alleen er heen te gaan. Desnoods kan ik, stel ik me voor, de meubels hier laten<c type="kk">/</c> ergens een hoek zolder huren van mijn huisbaas<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Maar ik wil af hoe eer hoe liever van mijn zware huishuur vooreerst<c type="kk">/</c> begrijpt ge<c type="kk">/</c> en ik wil naar ginder hoe eer hoe liever. Ik heb het noodig om te vorderen<c type="kk">/</c> Drenthe<c type="kk">/</c> Katwijk<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Brabant<c type="kk">/</c> ’t kan me niet schelen<c type="kk">/</c> een tijd te zijn bij een boer of zoo<c type="kk">/</c> geheel<c type="kk">/</c> geheel wijd weg buiten<c type="kk">/</c> wijd weg in zoover de natuur echt moet zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En dan moet ik veel schilderen en iets meer aan schilderbehoeften kunnen besteden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb met v.d. Weele alles nog eens besproken<c type="kk">/</c> hij is een middag op ’t atelier geweest<c type="kk">/</c> heeft mijn studies een voor een gezien<c type="kk">/</c> wij hebben toen verscheidenen er van verschilderd zamen om mij dingen te wijzen van techniek<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin hij heeft me nuttige dingen gewezen. Verder<c type="kk">/</c> voor ik ga<c type="kk">/</c> dezer dagen dus<c type="kk">/</c> zal hij nog wat van zijn tijd geven om me een &amp; ander te zeggen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Wisselingh is ook een morgen bij me geweest<c type="kp">_</c> Heel gezellig – hij zeide ik was verder dan hij gedacht had<c type="kp">_</c>– We hebben zamen koffij gedronken en over oude tijden gepraat<c type="kp">_</c> Hij gaf me veel moed en v.d. Weele ook<c type="kp">_</c> Maar het schilderen kan niet ontweken worden<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet – laat ik het nu maar eens ronduit zeggen – zien dat ik een honderttal flinke studies schilder. Ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">doorzetten</hi> er mee<c type="kp">_</c> En die studies moeten praktische motieven zijn ook. brokken natuur met karakter. Wisselingh zal wel eens wat van mij nemen<c type="kk">/</c> misschien reeds spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> en ik heb met hem afgesproken ik dezen herfst reeds of tegen den winter<c type="kk">/</c> enfin als ik een poosje geheel buiten zal zijn geweest<c type="kk">/</c> hem wat hoop te zenden. en daarmee voort te gaan<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo dat hij op de hoogte blijft van wat ik uitvoer<c type="kk">/</c> of hij er al dan niet van neemt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik heb hem gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf me over wat ik U zenden zal en dan zal ik in dat genre doorzetten waar gij denkt iets mee te kunnen doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Betreffende C.M.<c type="kk">/</c> ik stuurde hem meer dan 20 studies<c type="kk">/</c> zoo geloof ik hij – bovendien later kunnende inruilen – niet malcontent zal zijn.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Daar gij zelf niet over hebt zoo wilde ik U in bedenking geven hem eens de zaak bloot te leggen dat het goed zou zijn ik naar buiten kon en eens flink doorschilderen<c type="kp">_</c> Dat wij zullen zien het zonder zijn hulp er af te brengen<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat als het eens moest het zooveel helpen zoude als hij niet geheel zich er buiten hield in ’t vervolg. Gij ziet<c type="kk">/</c> er is wel mogelijkheid op wij er nu toe raken toe te komen met het gewone en toch te doen wat het werk vordert<c type="kk">/</c> ook wat schilderen betreft. Bij een boer in Drenthe betaalt men iets van f<c type="kp">_</c> 1 per dag voor logies en kost. De vrouw wou ik wel  aanvankelijk een oogje op houden zooveel ik kan met wat bij te passen<c type="kk">/</c> maar toch de zorg zal verminderen en het atelier moet dan een tijd opgegeven worden. Den boel geborgen in een hoek zolder tot betere tijden. En dan zonder baggage<c type="kk">/</c> zonder gezelschap op reis voor studie. Schrijf mij nu eens spoedig hoe gij denkt over een en ander<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou gij dadelijk eens schreeft als ge dezen gelezen hebt hoe gij denkt over een en ander. Ik voor mij ga morgen mijn huur opzeggen en afspreken ik desnoods mijn boeltje hier ergens bergen kan. De vrouw gaat op een dienst uit. En ondertusschen werk ik wat ik kan<c type="kp">_</c> Betreffende een plan om ergens heen te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> ik wacht Uw schrijven af en wij zullen zien wat we doen kunnen daarna<c type="kp">_</c> Ik hoop het een weg is om er boven op te komen. adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> heb ’t zoo goed mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> heb wat voorspoed met de zaken. geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Accept my thanks for your letter and the enclosure. I want to answer it today. What you write may be true — as we’ve already discussed — as I’ve thought to myself more than once, both before and since then — that if the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> were obliged to do without me — to stand on her own feet — she would follow a straighter course. Since she has 2 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, however, it’s a very difficult case, but what can I say? In the given situation it’s something that she herself makes necessary, and <hi rend="italics">the circumstances make much more necessary</hi>. I underline this last.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Do you know what I’ve done? Today I had a quiet day with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> — talked with her about it at great length — explained fully what my position was and how I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> go for my work and <hi rend="italics">must</hi> have a year with few outgoings and earn something to make up for what had passed, which had been rather too much for me. That I foresaw that if I stayed with her, I soon wouldn’t be able to help her any more and would then get into debt again here, where it’s expensive, and be unable to get out of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">So in short <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> and I must be sensible and part as friends. That she’d have to get her family to take the children in, and that she must go into service.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well, it’s so clear that it’s impossible for me to carry on here that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> too understands. And so our agreement is that, both of us being in a fix at the moment, and making it worse by staying together, we’ll separate for a while or forever, depending on how things turn out.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I say ‘or forever’ because we have reasons for <hi rend="italics">having</hi> to live nonetheless, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> in her children and I in my work, and shall have to do things we don’t like — and shall perhaps not be <hi rend="italics">able</hi> to be as good as we would wish.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I said to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, you may not be able to manage by going entirely straight, but go as straight as possible, I too shall go as straight as possible, but be assured in advance that I’ll do far from well in life. So I say, as long as I know that you’re doing your best and not letting <hi rend="italics">everything</hi> go and are good to the children, just as you know I too have been good to them — as long as you behave in a way that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs> still find a <hi>Mother</hi> in you, even if you’re only a poor maidservant, even if you’re only a poor whore — in my eyes you are and will remain <hi rend="italics">good</hi>, with the whole damned host of faults. And I, though I don’t doubt for a moment that I have similarly attractive points, will be no different, I hope, from how I was, in that I won’t be able to see a woman with a big belly or in a stew without drawing my own conclusions about it and doing what I can if she crosses my path. If you were in the same state, I say, as when I found you, you would have a home with me — a shelter from the storm — as long as I had a crust of bread and a roof, but it isn’t like that now and the storm has passed, I believe you can now make a straight path for your feet<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> without me. Well, you must try.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For my part I’ll also make a straight path for my feet, I must work hard, and you should too. That’s how I talked about it.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Ah, brother, you see that we wouldn’t have parted if we didn’t have to. I repeat, we wouldn’t have parted if we didn’t have to. Haven’t we forgiven each other’s faults time after time and made up again? We know each other so well that we can’t think each other bad. I don’t know whether it’s love, but what there is between us is between us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">As regards having to. You see, I don’t want to lapse into scraping by, I want to keep on working, straight ahead — vigorously — do what must be done by way of painting. I know that it can’t be wrong to do that — that’s to say, I don’t know <hi rend="italics">how</hi> it will turn out for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> or for me if I keep on working hard, but it will certainly turn out <hi rend="italics">better</hi> if I keep hewing away on my own, if need be, than if we both lapse into <hi rend="italics">stagnation</hi> by staying together when we get in each other’s way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I come back now to Drenthe. Think about whether you see a way for me to get money to go there on my own. If need be, I imagine, I can leave the furniture here, and rent a corner of an attic somewhere from my landlord.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">But first I want to be rid of the burden of my house rent, the sooner the better, you understand, and I want to go over there, the sooner the better. I need it to make progress. Drenthe, Katwijk,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Brabant, I don’t mind. To stay for a time with a farmer or someone, far, far away in the country, far enough away for nature there to be real.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And then I must paint a lot and be able to spend a little more on painting materials.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I discussed everything again with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs>. He spent an afternoon at the studio and saw my studies one by one. Together we repainted several of them to show me some things to do with technique. Anyway, he showed me some useful things. Also, before I go, in the next few days in other words, he’ll give some more of his time to tell me a thing or two.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs>, too, came for a morning. Very pleasant — he said I had got further than he expected. We had coffee together and talked about old times. He gave me great encouragement, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> did too. But there’s no getting away from painting. I must — let me say it plainly for once — try to paint about a hundred substantial studies. You see, <hi rend="italics">persevering </hi>with them. And these studies must be practical subjects too. Fragments of nature with character. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs> will take something from me now and again, perhaps soon, and I’ve agreed with him that as early as this autumn or towards the winter, anyway when I’ve been in the country for a while, I hope to send him something. And to continue doing that. So that he’ll be abreast of what I’m doing, whether or not he takes anything.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I said to him, write to me about what I send you, and then I’ll continue in the genre that you think you can do something with.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">As for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>, I sent him more than 20 studies, so I don’t think he’ll be dissatisfied — moreover, he can exchange them later.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Given that you have nothing to spare, I would ask you to consider putting the case to him — that it would be good if I could go to the country and do a lot of painting. That we’ll try to manage without his aid, but that when necessary it would be such a help if he didn’t stay out of it completely in future. You see, there’s a possibility that we’ll now be able to manage with the usual and still be able to do what the work demands, in painting as well. At a farmer’s in Drenthe one pays about 1 guilder a day for board and lodging. I would like to keep an eye on the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> in the beginning as far as I can, and contribute something, but still the care will be reduced, and the studio will have to be given up for a time. The things stored in a corner of an attic until better times. And then without baggage, without company, off on an excursion to study. Write to me soon and tell me what you think about one thing and another, I want you to write immediately when you’ve read this and say what you think about one thing and another. For my part, I’m going to give my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">landlord</rs> notice tomorrow and arrange to store my things somewhere here, if need be. The woman is going to look for a position in service. And meanwhile I do what work I can. As for a plan of where to go, I’ll wait for your letter, and after that we’ll see what we can do. I hope it will be a way of getting back on my feet. Adieu, old chap, I wish you the very best, I hope the business prospers. Believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent writes immediately after receiving Theo’s letter with the money (‘today’, <ref target="#l-2">ll. 2-3</ref>), which must have been the first remittance of September, because he continues to work on his plans for moving to Drenthe. Moreover, he says he has spoken to Sien ‘today’ <ref target="#l-14">(l. 14)</ref>; it turns out later that this was on a Sunday, the same Sunday on which Theo also went on a walk (<ref target="let381.xml#l-7">see letter 381, ll. 7-15</ref>). This means that the present letter must date from Sunday, 2 September 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s plan to go to Drenthe <ref target="let379.xml">(379)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Drawings on consignment with Uncle Cor <ref target="let378.xml">(378)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Cf. Heb. 12:13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>As well as the two provinces mentioned, the coastal town of Katwijk was popular with painters. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Theo had mediated to put <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> and Vincent back in touch; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let378.xml">see letter 378</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    