<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 5 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let381"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b342 V/1962 and b343 b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>381</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>319</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>384</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-05">on or about Wednesday, 5 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0342" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0342" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000438_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0343" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000440_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000440_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0343" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000440_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000440_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief ontvang ik daareven toen ik t’huiskom vanuit de duinen achter Loosduinen<c type="kk">/</c> doornat want een uur of 3 had ik in den regen gezeten op een plek waar alles <hi rend="italics">Ruysdael</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Daubigny</hi> of <hi rend="italics">Jules Dupré</hi> was<c type="kp">_</c> Ik kwam terug met een studie van kromme<c type="kk">/</c> verwaaide boompjes<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en een tweede van een boerderij<c type="kk">/</c> na den regen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Alles is reeds brons<c type="kk">/</c> alles is dat wat men buiten in de natuur zien kan slechts op dit moment van ’t jaar<c type="kk">/</c> of als men voor een van die schilderijen staat als Dupré b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> en zoo mooi is men in zijn verbeelding altijd er onder blijft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ge schrijft over Uw wandeling op dien zondag te Ville d’Avray<c type="kk">/</c> op dat zelfde moment van dien zelfden dag wandelde ik ook alleen en wil U van die wandeling ook iets zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> als wanneer waarschijnlijk wederom onze gedachten eenigermate zich kruisten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik had gesproken met de vrouw zoo als ik U schreef – we voelden dat de toekomst ons gesloten was om zamen te blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ja dat wij elkaar ongelukkig zouden maken<c type="kk">/</c> toch voelden we van weerskanten hoe sterk wij gehecht waren aan elkaar. En toen was ik naar buiten gegaan<c type="kk">/</c> wijd weg<c type="kk">/</c> om eens met de natuur te praten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik kwam te Voorburg en van daar tot Leidschendam.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ge kent die natuur daar<c type="kk">/</c> superbe boomen vol majesteit en sereniteit naast groene<c type="kk">/</c> afschuwelijke speelgoeddoos koepeltjes en al wat de logge verbeeldingskracht der rentenierende Hollanders voor absurditeit weet te verzinnen in zake van bloemperkjes<c type="kk">/</c> prieeltjes<c type="kk">/</c> verandas<c type="kp">_</c> De huizen meest heel leelijk<c type="kk">/</c> sommigen echter oud en deftig. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> op dat moment kwam hoog over de weilanden<c type="kk">/</c> oneindig als de woestijn<c type="kk">/</c> ’t eene wolkgevaarte na ’t andere aangestuwd<c type="kk">/</c> en de wind stuitte ’t allereerst tegen de rij buitens met hun geboomte aan den overkant van de vaart<c type="kk">/</c> waar de zwarte kolenweg langsloopt. Die boomen<c type="kk">/</c> ze waren superbe<c type="kk">/</c> er was een drama in elk <hi rend="italics">figuur</hi> zou ik zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik bedoel in elken boom.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Dan<c type="kk">/</c> het geheel was bijna nog mooier dan die geteisterde boomen op zich zelf beschouwd<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat het moment zóó was dat zelfs die absurde koepeltjes een zonderling karakter kregen<c type="kk">/</c> natgeregend en verwaaid<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zag er in een beeld van hoe ook een mensch van absurde vormen en conventies<c type="kk">/</c> of een ander vol exentriciteit en caprices<c type="kk">/</c> mits maar een waarachtige smart hem aangrijpe – een calamiteit hem doe ontroeren – een dramatisch figuur van eigenaardig karakter kan worden<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik kwam er toe een oogenblik te denken aan de maatschappij van tegenwoordig<c type="kk">/</c> hoe bij het ten gronde gaan er van zij ook momenteel menigmaal<c type="kk">/</c> tegen het licht van een vernieuwing in gezien<c type="kk">/</c> als een groot<c type="kk">/</c> somber silhouet zich voordoet<c type="kp">_</c> Ja voor mij het drama van storm in de natuur<c type="kk">/</c> het drama van smart in het leven is wel het beste<c type="kp">_</c>– Een “paradou”<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> is mooi doch Ghetsemané is toch mooier.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Och een klein beetje lucht<c type="kk">/</c> een klein beetje geluk moet er zijn<c type="kk">/</c> doch vooral om den vorm te laten voelen<c type="kk">/</c> de lijnen van ’t silhouet te doen spreken<c type="kp">_</c> Maar laat het geheel maar somber wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik moet zeggen dat de vrouw zich goed houdt. Zij heeft er smart van en ik ook doch zij is niet moedeloos en zij weert zich goed.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik had nog een stuk goed gekocht onlangs om studielinnen van te maken zelf en ik heb het nu aan haar gegeven voor hemden voor de scharminkels. en goed van mij laat ik ook voor hen vermaken zoo dat zij nog een en ander meekrijgen<c type="kk">/</c> en daar is zij druk aan bezig<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Als ik zeg we scheiden als <hi rend="italics">vrienden</hi><c type="kk">/</c> is dat waar – maar gescheiden zijn we gedecideerd en sedert heb ik daar ook meer vrede bij gevonden dan ik dacht omdat wat haar mankeerde van dien aard is dat het voor mij zoowel als voor haar iets fataals was als wij aan elkaar gebonden waren<c type="kk">/</c> wegens men om zoo te zeggen voor elkaars gebreken verantwoordelijk is<c type="kp">_</c> Alleen blijft mijn zorg – hoe zal ’t met haar zijn over een jaar<c type="kp">_</c>– Bij mij in huis neem ik haar zeker <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> meer maar ik wilde toch haar niet uit het oog verliezen want ik houd te veel van haar en de kinderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Juist omdat het iets anders was en is dan een passie<c type="kk">/</c> kan dat ook<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik hoop dat het plan van Drenthe doorgaat.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Gij vraagt wat zou ik noodig hebben?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik behoef U niet te zeggen dat ik van plan ben veel te werken<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal dat moeten doen om mij te vernieuwen. En ginder heeft men <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> van schildergerij<c type="kk">/</c> dus wat betreft voorraad mee te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> zulke dingen mee te nemen als waarachtig nuttig zijn<c type="kk">/</c> bepaald hoe meer hoe beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Goed gereedschap is nooit weg en al is het duur<c type="kk">/</c> men haalt het er uit. En om er te komen moet men heel wat schilderen. De tijd die ik ginder zal doorbrengen hoop ik zeer weinig van te laten verloren gaan<c type="kk">/</c> en veel model te nemen ook<c type="kk">/</c> wat daar goedkoop genoeg zal wezen waarschijnlijk. Maar het leven is er goedkoop en ik zal meer met de frs 150 kunnen doen dan hier.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Maar dat alles kan<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ik schikken zoo als het uitkomt eigentlijk<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zou het wenschelijk vinden een groote uitgaaf te kunnen doen wegens veel mij mankeert wat anderen hebben en eigentlijk niet te missen is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Mijn plan is het in Drenthe een eind ver te brengen met het schilderen zoo dat ik in de termen val voor de teekenmaatschappij als ik terug kom.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Dat staat weer in verband tot een tweede plan<c type="kk">/</c> van naar Engeland gaan<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik geloof dat het gepermitteerd is te speculeeren mits men het maar niet in de lucht of op al te losse gronden doe<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo betreffende Engeland: Zeer zeker stel ik mij voor daar iets makkelijker te verkoopen dan hier – dat is zoo – dus ik denk wel eens aan Engeland. Doch hoe het punt waar toe ik gekomen ben staat tot de Engelsche liefhebbers weet ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> en omdat ik het niet weet wil ik eerst hier een klein positief begin hebben van verkoopen vóór ik ’t raadzaam acht demarches te doen ginder. <hi rend="italics">Als</hi> ik hier enkele dingen begin te verkoopen <hi rend="italics">dan</hi> aarzel ik geen oogenblik meer maar begin naar ginder te zenden of naar ginder te gaan. Doch zoolang ik hier absoluut niets verkoop zoo zou ik me in ’t tijdstip heel ligt vergissen als ik de wijsheid niet had te wachten tot ik hier zelfs een beginsel zie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik hoop dat gij dit idee dienaangaande billijk vindt<c type="kk">/</c> dat zoude mij een rust zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Want in Engeland is men zeer serieus als men eens begint<c type="kk">/</c> wie in Engeland in den smaak valt vind er <hi rend="italics">trouwe</hi> vrienden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zal b.v. Ed. Frere en Henriette Browne maar eens noemen<c type="kk">/</c> die nu evenmin vervelen als den eersten dag toen hun werk er gezien werd<c type="kp">_</c> Maar wil men er slagen<c type="kk">/</c> men moet het een beetje soigneeren en zeker zijn dat men productief kan zijn in dat wat men er heen zendt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Uw brief deed mij veel genoegen want ik zie dat gij in ’t plan van Drenthe iets ziet en dat is me genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> het zal zich dan van zelf later openbaren welke partij er van te trekken is<c type="kp">_</c> Maar voor mij staat het al vast direkt in verband met van de teekenmaatschappij lid zien te worden<c type="kk">/</c> en verder met Engeland – wegens ik zeker weet de motieven van ginder<c type="kk">/</c> als ik er eenig sentiment in slaag te leggen<c type="kk">/</c> sympathie zullen vinden in Engeland.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Enfin doorzetten maar met Drenthe<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij we veel of weinig voorlopig uitgeven kunnen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Als ik reisgeld heb ga ik er heen<c type="kk">/</c> al heb ik niet veel schilderbehoeften in voorraad<c type="kk">/</c> wegens de tijd van herfsteffecten reeds is begonnen en ik daar nog wat van hoop te snappen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-"/> Doch ik hoop het zoo zal zijn dat ik de vrouw nog iets geven kan voor den eersten tijd<c type="kp">_</c> Alleen<c type="kk">/</c> als ik weg <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> <hi rend="italics">ga ik weg</hi>.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik zeg tot <hi rend="italics">U</hi> dat ik de vrouw voorloopig van plan ben iets of wat te helpen<c type="kk">/</c> veel <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ik niet ook doch <hi rend="italics">niemand</hi> anders dan U spreek ik hierover<c type="kp">_</c> En wat ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> dat wat er ook met haar gebeure ik haar niet meer in huis kan of wil hebben<c type="kk">/</c> kunt gij van opaan<c type="kk">/</c> want het zit in haar niet om te doen wat ze als zoodanig doen moest<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb het Pa ook met een woord berigt dat ik van haar gescheiden was doch dat mijn brief aan Pa over met haar te blijven en te trouwen evenwel een daadzaak bleef<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en dat Pa daar eenigzins om heen gesproken had en op de eigentlijke kwestie geen antwoord gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> een tweede daadzaak<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Waarvan ik niet weet hoe in later jaren het zich zal voordoen en of dat niet beter ware geweest dan scheiden<c type="kk">/</c> nu zijn we bij alles te digt bij om het een en ander in zijn eigentlijk verband en gevolg te overkijken. Ik <hi rend="italics">hoop</hi> dat het alles op zijn pooten teregt komt maar de toekomst van haar en van mij zelf ook zie ik toch somber. Ik geloof ook wel dat er in haar nog iets wakker zal worden doch het zit hem juist daarin dat het reeds wakker <hi rend="italics">had moeten zijn</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en dat nu het haar moeielijk zal zijn haar betere gedachten te volgen als ze niemand heeft om er haar in te steunen. Nu wou ze niet luisteren<c type="kk">/</c> dan zal ze verlangen me te spreken en het zal niet meer kunnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo lang zij met mij is geweest had zij geen tegenstelling en nu zal ze in een andere omgeving dingen zich herinneren waar ze nu niet om gaf en niet op lette<c type="kp">_</c> Zij zal <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> door tegenstelling daar nog wel eens over denken. Nu is het voor mij soms door en door navrant dat wij beiden voelen het niet houdbare van zamen door de toekomst worstelen<c type="kk">/</c> en dat toch wij zóó gehecht zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Zij is vertrouwelijker dezer dagen dan gewoonlijk en de moeder had haar eenige streken opgestookt die zij niet heeft willen doen jegens mij. Dingen in het genre waar wij toen ge hier waart over spraken<c type="kk">/</c> van lawaai<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> maken of zoo<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ge ziet<c type="kk">/</c> er is iets in haar als een begin van iets degelijkers en mogt dat maar blijven<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wou dat zij trouwen kon en als ik U zeg dat ik een oogje op haar blijf houden is het omdat ik haar <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> aanraad<c type="kp">_</c> Als zij maar een man vind die half goed is<c type="kk">/</c> is ’t voldoende<c type="kk">/</c> dan zal zich datgene verder ontwikkelen wat hier er in beginsel in is gekomen<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk een meer huisselijken<c type="kk">/</c> eenvoudigen zin en als zij zich daaraan houdt zoo zal ik haar ook in ’t vervolg niet geheel en al aan haar lot hoeven over te laten want dan blijf ik haar vriend ten minste en opregt ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">schrijf me weer spoedig en gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik voeg nog een woordje hierbij – gij vraagt<c type="kk">/</c> wat heb ik noodig<c type="kp">_</c> ik dacht er nog over en onmogelijk is het mij te zeggen wat ik eigentlijk <hi rend="italics">noodig</hi> acht want dat zou lang niet weinig zijn en laat ons dus zien wat bereikbaar is en het daarmede doen. Waarschijnlijk zal het bereikbare blijven <hi rend="italics">onder</hi> het geen au fond noodig was maar in het leven is het al iets als men ten deele zijn plannen kan volvoeren. En ik voor mij zeg U dat ik het doen zal met wat ge er voor vinden kunt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Het leven is ginder goedkooper en van zelf zal ik kunnen bezuinigen bij hier vergeleken. en als er eens een jaar over heen gegaan is zal ik door die bezuiniging alleen reeds een eind verder kunnen gekomen zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Ik kan per <hi rend="italics">postpakket</hi> ook ginder zijnde verf &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> laten komen. dus <hi rend="italics">als ik kan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ja dat spreekt van zelf<c type="kk">/</c> neem ik voorraad mee maar als ik <hi rend="italics">niet kan</hi> stel ik daarom de reis niet uit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Dat het afgeloopen jaar toch solide zal blijken geweest te zijn heb ik hoop op<c type="kk">/</c> want mijn werk heb ik niet verwaarloosd en integendeel een aantal zwakke punten versterkt. Er zijn er nog meer te versterken natuurlijkerwijs maar die liggen dan ook aan de beurt nu.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Betreffende wat ik U schreef in een vorigen brief<c type="kk">/</c> dat de vrouw zekere beloften direkt had gebroken<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> dat was serieus genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. een demarche om als meid in een hoerenkast te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> wat de moeder gelegenheid toe had opgevischt en haar toe aanzette. De vrouw zelf<c type="kk">/</c> direkt heeft ze er sedert op nieuw spijt van gehad en ziet er vanaf doch evenwel zeer<c type="kk">/</c> zeer zwak is ’t van haar<c type="kk">/</c> en <hi rend="italics">juist op dat moment</hi> het te doen<c type="kk">/</c> maar zóó is zij – tot heden althans – de kracht om zoo iets tegen te spreken met een absoluut <hi rend="italics">neen</hi> heeft ze tot nog toe niet. Enfin mij dringt ze tot maatregelen die ik al dikwijls uitgesteld en uitgesteld heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Ik heb bij die gelegenheid echter iets gezien in haar van als of ’t een crisis – ik hoop een “tot hiertoe en niet verder” – ware geweest. En zoo is het dat zij zelf dit scheiden beschouwd als kunnende ten goede uitkomen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">En wegens zij met de moeder al te zeer in fataal rapport staat<c type="kk">/</c> moeten die twee of zamen den slechten of zamen den goeden weg op.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">En zal er zamenwonen met de moeder van komen en zamen bij beurten uit werken gaan en het op een eerlijke manier zien er af te brengen. Dat is hun plan en hebben zij eenige werkdagen reeds en heb ik advertenties geplaatst en zoeken zij dagelijks en krijgen er zelf pleizier in.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Ik zal dat ook blijven doen en zoolang ’t noodig is doorgaan met advertenties en enfin al die dingen waarmee ik van nut of meewerking kan wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">En als ik nu kan betaal ik voor hun bij mijn weggaan een aantal weken kamerhuur en een brood per dag of zoo<c type="kk">/</c> om hun nog meer tijd te laten om dat plan goed op touw te zetten en uit te breiden. Doch dat ik plan heb hun nog dat toe te stoppen is iets wat ik <hi rend="italics">hun</hi> nog niet heb <hi rend="italics">beloofd</hi> omdat ik zelf nog niet weet of ik het zal kunnen. En zal dat naar omstandigheden doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">En haar raad ik gedecideerd aan een mariage de raison met een weduwnaar of zoo<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik haar bij zeg zij voor zoo iemand <hi rend="italics">beter moet zijn dan voor mij</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">En dat zij zelf genoeg weet in welke opzigten ze bij mij te kort kwam<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-c"/> dat ze nu <hi rend="italics">wijs</hi> moet zijn en <hi rend="italics">leeren daaruit</hi> dat <hi rend="italics">ik het in ’t minst haar niet kwalijk neem omdat ik weet eene</hi> <hi rend="italics">verbetering of hervorming niet in eens lukt doch als ’t ware</hi> <hi rend="italics">trappen heeft</hi> en dus<c type="kk">/</c> mits zij nu maar blijve op dat punt waar ze nu is en van daar uit zich op werke doch geen zakken zich toelaat<c type="kk">/</c> zij zich ook haar fouten met mij niet hoeft aan te trekken of moedeloos worden<c type="kk">/</c> alleen het moet zien goed te maken door voor een ander beter te zijn.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">En dit een en ander ziet zij zelf nu voorloopig goed in en hoop ik levendig te houden. Het moedeloos worden en dan zich loslaten is echter hun beider zwak doch tevens<c type="kk">/</c> zij zijn geduldig ook in het weer van nieuws beginnen<c type="kk">/</c> de vrouw vooral wordt dat ook meer<c type="kk">/</c> en ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon haar fouten velen zijn en lastig genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> zoo weet ik au fond er iets goeds zit dat <hi rend="italics">alles</hi> verzacht en daarom ook wanhoop ik over haar toekomst niet. Voor zoo iemand <hi>moet miséricorde</hi> <hi rend="italics">in de natuur zelf liggen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> is iets wat ik wenschte ten volle te kunnen gelooven<c type="kk">/</c> en goddeloos van me zelf vind dat ik niet ten volle overtuigd ben daarvan<c type="kk">/</c> in zoover dat berusten in alles ik nu nog niet bij magte ben te doen evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> en ten minste nu nog niet <hi rend="italics">alles</hi> overgeven kan waar ik zeer op getobt heb om het teregt te brengen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">Schrijf me weer spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter just now when I came home from the dunes behind Loosduinen, soaking wet because I had spent 3 hours in the rain at a spot where everything was <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs></hi> or <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs></hi>. I came back with a study of crooked, windswept trees,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and a second of a farm after the rain.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Everything is already bronze, everything is what one can see in nature only at this time of year, or if one stands before one of those paintings like a Dupré, for instance, and so beautiful that one’s imagination always falls short of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You write about your walk to Ville-d’Avray that Sunday, at the same time on that same day I was also walking alone, and I want to tell you something about that walk, since then our thoughts probably crossed again in some degree.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I spoke to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> as I wrote to you — we felt that staying together in the future was ruled out, indeed that we’d make each other unhappy, but we felt on both sides how strongly we were attached to each other. And then I went out of doors, a long way away, to talk to nature for a while. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well, I came to Voorburg, and went from there to Leidschendam. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">You know the landscape there, superb trees full of majesty and serenity beside green, dreadful, toy-box summer-houses, and every absurdity the lumbering imagination of Hollanders with private incomes can come up with in the way of flower-beds, arbours, verandas. Most of the houses very ugly, but some old and elegant. Well, at that moment, high above the meadows as endless as the desert, came one driven mass of cloud after the other, and the wind first struck the row of country houses with their trees on the opposite side of the waterway, where the black cinder road runs. Those trees, they were superb, there was a drama in each <hi rend="italics">figure</hi> I’m tempted to say, but I mean in each tree.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Then, the whole was almost finer than those windblown trees seen on their own, because the moment was such that even those absurd summer houses took on a singular character, rain-soaked and dishevelled. In it I saw an image of how even a person of absurd forms and conventions, or another full of eccentricity and caprice, can become a dramatic figure of special character if he’s gripped by true sorrow, moved by a calamity. It made me think for a moment of society today, how as it founders it now often appears like a large, sombre silhouette viewed against the light of reform. Yes, for me the drama of a storm in nature, the drama of sorrow in life, is the best. A ‘paradou’<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> is beautiful, but Gethsemane is more beautiful still.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Oh, there must be a little bit of air, a little bit of happiness, but chiefly to let the form be felt, to make the lines of the silhouette speak. But let the whole be sombre. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I must say that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> is bearing up well. She feels sorrow and I do too, but she isn’t despondent and is making an effort. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I bought a piece of cloth recently to make some study linen for myself, and now I’ve given it to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> for vests for those scrawny children. And I’m having clothes of mine altered for them so that they’ll get one or two things, and she’s busy with that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">When I say we are separating as <hi rend="italics">friends</hi>, that is true — but we are definitely separated, and I’ve since been more at peace with that than I expected, because what was wrong with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> was of such a nature that it would have been fatal both for me and for her if we’d been bound to each other, given that one is responsible, so to speak, for each other’s failings. But I’m still left with the worry — how will she be in a year’s time? I’ll certainly <hi rend="italics">not</hi> take her into my house again, but I didn’t want to lose touch with her, because I love her and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs> too much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">That is also possible, precisely because it was and still is something different from a passion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I hope the Drenthe plan goes ahead.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">You ask what I might need.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I don’t need to tell you that I intend to do a lot of work, I must do that to revitalize myself. And over there they have <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> in the way of painting equipment, so as regards taking a supply, taking things that are really useful, definitely the more the better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Good tools are never a waste, and they pay for themselves even if they are expensive. And to get ahead one must do a great deal of painting. I hope to lose very little of the time that I’ll spend there, and to have a lot of models too, which will probably be cheap enough there. But life is cheap there, and I’ll be able to do more with the 150 francs than here.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">But in fact I can<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> arrange all that as it suits me. I would think it desirable to be able to make one big purchase, because I lack many things that others have and that are actually indispensable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">My plan is to get a long way with painting in Drenthe so that I’ll be eligible for the Drawing Society when I come back.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> That, in turn, is linked to a second plan, to go to England.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I believe that it’s permissible to speculate provided one doesn’t do it in the air or on foundations that are all too shaky. As far as England is concerned, I certainly expect to sell something more easily there than here — that’s true — so I think of England from time to time. But I don’t know how the point that I’ve reached stands in relation to the English art lovers, and because I don’t know that I would first like to have a small, positive beginning of sales here before I think it advisable to take steps over there. <hi rend="italics">If</hi> I begin to sell a few things here, <hi rend="italics">then</hi> I shan’t hesitate for a moment but start sending things over there or go there. Yet as long as I sell absolutely nothing here, I would very likely be mistaken as to the timing if I didn’t have the wisdom to wait until I see just a beginning here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I hope you find this idea reasonable, that would reassure me. For in England people are very serious once they begin; whoever finds favour in England finds <hi rend="italics">loyal</hi> friends there. I need only mention <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1023">E. Frère</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_912">Henriette Browne</rs>, for example, who are now just as well liked as on the first day their work was seen there. But if one wants to succeed over there, one must take a little care and be certain that one can be productive in what one sends over there. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Your letter pleased me greatly, for I see that you think that there’s something in the Drenthe plan, and that’s enough for me; later on it will become clear of itself what benefit there is to be gained. But for me it’s already linked directly to becoming a member of the Drawing Society and also to England — because I know for sure that the subjects from over there will be sympathetically received in England if I’m able to put some sentiment into them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">In short, press on with Drenthe, whether we can spend a great deal or a little for the time being.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I’ll go there when I have the money to travel, even though I have few painting materials left, because the time of autumnal effects has already begun, and I hope to capture some of them. Yet I hope I’ll be able to give the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> a little more for the early days. But if I <hi rend="italics">can</hi> leave <hi rend="italics">I shall</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I say to <hi rend="italics">you</hi> that for the time being I plan to help the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> a little, I <hi rend="italics">may </hi>not and indeed <hi rend="italics">cannot</hi> make it very much. I’m telling <hi rend="italics">no one</hi> else but you about this. And what I say to you — that whatever happens to her I cannot and shall not have her in my house again — you can rely on that, for it’s not in her to do what she should do. I also sent a few words to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> to say that I was separated from her, but that my letter to Pa about staying with her and getting married remained a fact all the same,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and that Pa had talked around that and given no answer to the real question, a second fact.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I don’t know how it will appear in years to come, or whether that wouldn’t have been better than separating; now we’re too close to everything to see things in their true context and the consequences. I <hi rend="italics">hope</hi> that it will all turn out for the best, but her future and my own look sombre to me. I do believe that something will still awaken in her, but that’s precisely the point — it <hi rend="italics">ought to have been</hi> awakened already, and now it will be difficult for her to follow her better thoughts when she has no one to support her in that. Now she wouldn’t listen, then she will yearn to speak to me and it won’t be possible. As long as she was with me, she had no contrasting example, and now in other surroundings she’ll remember things that she didn’t care about and paid no attention to at the time. <hi rend="italics">Now</hi>, because of the contrast, she’ll think about that sometimes. For me it’s sometimes thoroughly distressing that we both feel the impossibility of struggling through the future together, and yet that we’re so attached. She has been more confiding than normal of late, and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> had incited her to play some tricks which she didn’t want to inflict on me. Things of the kind we talked about when you were here, such as starting a row and the like.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">You see, there’s something in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> like the beginning of something more solid, and may that remain so. I wish she could marry, and when I tell you that I’ll keep an eye on her it’s because I advised her to do <hi rend="italics">that</hi>. If only she can find a man who is half good, that’s enough, then the beginnings of what has come into her here will develop further, that is, a more domestic, simple disposition, and if she sticks to that I won’t have to leave her entirely to her fate in the future either, for then at least I’ll remain her friend, and sincerely so.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Write to me again soon, and regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I’m adding a few words here. You ask what I need. I thought about that and it’s impossible for me to say what I really regard as <hi rend="italics">necessary</hi>, for that would be no small amount, so let’s see what’s within our reach and make do with that. What’s within our reach will probably remain <hi rend="italics">below</hi> what’s fundamentally needed, but in life it’s already something if one can carry out one’s plans in part. And I for one say to you that I’ll make do with what you can spare. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Life is cheaper over there, and I’ll be able to make savings automatically compared to here. And when a year has passed I’ll have made substantial progress through those savings alone. I can have paint &amp;c. sent by <hi rend="italics">parcel post</hi> when I’m over there. So I’ll take a supply <hi rend="italics">if I can</hi>, that goes without saying, but if <hi rend="italics">I can’t</hi> I shan’t postpone the journey because of that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I have hopes that the past year will turn out to have been solid, for I haven’t neglected my work and, on the contrary, I’ve strengthened a number of weak points. There are more that need strengthening, of course, but it’s their turn now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">  As for what I wrote to you in a previous letter, that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> had immediately broken certain promises,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> that was bad enough, namely an attempt to be a maid in a whorehouse, an opportunity the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> had fished out and urged on her. The woman herself immediately regretted it and has rejected it, but all the same it’s very, very weak of her, and especially to do it <hi rend="italics">at that particular time</hi>, but that’s what she’s like — up to now at least — so far she hasn’t had the strength to refuse such a thing with an absolute <hi rend="italics">no</hi>. Anyway, she forces me to take measures that I’ve often previously postponed and postponed. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">On this occasion, though, I saw something in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> as if it had been a crisis — I hope a ‘thus far and no further’. And so it is that she herself views this separation as possibly turning out for the best in the end. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">And because there’s an all too fatal rapport between <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs>, those two must go together down the wrong or the right road.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">And it will come down to living with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> and going out to work together by turns, and trying to get by in an honest way. That’s their plan, and they already have some workdays, and I’ve placed advertisements, and they look every day and are beginning to enjoy it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">I’ll keep on doing that and carry on with advertisements as long as necessary, and in short all the things whereby I can be of use or assistance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">And if I can I’ll pay several weeks’ rent for them when I go, as well as a loaf a day or some such to give them yet more time to set their plan up properly and add to it. But the fact that I intend to give them that is something I haven’t yet <hi rend="italics">promised them</hi>, because I don’t know myself if I’ll be able to do it. I’ll act according to circumstances. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">And I firmly recommend to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> a marriage of convenience with a widower or someone, to which I add that she’ll have to be <hi rend="italics">better</hi> for such a person <hi rend="italics">than she was for me</hi>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">And that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> herself knows well enough in what ways she fell short with me, that now she must be <hi rend="italics">wise</hi> and <hi rend="italics">learn from that</hi> that <hi rend="italics">I don’t blame her in the least, because I know that an improvement or reform doesn’t succeed all at once but has steps, so to speak,</hi> and so, provided she stays at the point where she is now and works her way up, starting from there, without allowing herself any relapse, she needn’t take her mistakes with me to heart or become despondent, just try to make amends by being better for someone else. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> herself well understands these things for the present, and I hope to keep them alive. Becoming despondent and then letting oneself go is, however, a weakness they share, yet at the same time they’re also patient when it comes to starting afresh, the woman in particular is showing that more, and I, although her faults are many and troublesome enough, yet I know that fundamentally there’s something good that extenuates <hi rend="italics">everything</hi>, and for that reason, too, I don’t despair of her future. That <hi>misericorde must</hi> <hi rend="italics">lie in nature itself</hi> for such a person is something I wish I could fully believe, and I find it wicked of myself that I’m not fully persuaded of it, in so far as I’m not yet able to resign myself to everything, however, and can’t, for the time being at least, give up <hi rend="italics">everything</hi> that I’ve struggled so hard to put right. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">Write to me again soon, won’t you?</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">At the end of <ref target="let380.xml">letter 380</ref> Vincent asked Theo to write ‘immediately’; the present letter is Vincent’s direct reaction to the letter Theo indeed wrote. Given that Vincent wrote two more letters before Monday, 10 September (<ref target="let382.xml">letters 382</ref> and <ref target="let383.xml">383</ref>), the frequency in this week was extremely high and we must assume that the two letters followed each other very quickly. This means that the present letter was written on or about Wednesday, 5 September 1883 at the latest.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The postscript to this letter (the second sheet, from <ref target="#l-179">l. 179</ref>) was earlier placed with the next letter <ref target="let382.xml">(382)</ref>. We believe that it belongs with the present letter because in this way Vincent does after all go into Theo’s question about the costs, which he touches on in the first part of the letter but does not answer properly (see <ref target="#l-75">ll. 75</ref> ff.). A second argument for moving this postscript is that it contains a description of Sien’s unreliable behaviour, which strengthens Van Gogh’s resolve to leave The Hague. This explains the decisiveness in the first paragraphs of the next letter; with the remark there that ‘I now know for certain’ that Sien’s motives are suspect (<ref target="let382.xml#l-6">letter 382, l. 6</ref>), he implicitly refers to the postscript that Theo had received with the present letter. </p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s plan to go to Drenthe <ref target="let379.xml">(379)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Conflict with Sien’s family <ref target="let338.xml">(338)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape with leaning trees</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3110">F 196 / JH 957</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Farm in Loosduinen near The Hague</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3111">F 16 / JH 391</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh puts forward a similar view of the similarities between trees and figures in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let175.xml">letter 175</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>For the reference to ‘Le Paradou’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_253">La faute de l’abbé Mouret</ref></hi> (1875), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-1">see letter 344, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>It is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘kon’ (could) instead of ‘kan’ (can).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh means that by painting he practises the use of colour, and that in this way at the same time he achieves the improvement in watercolour required in order to be admitted to the Hollandsche Teeken-maatschappij. For the latter, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let256.xml#n-8">see letter 256, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-">
                            
<p>‘snappen’: ‘grijpen’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s plan to seek work in England as an illustrator was mentioned earlier, cf. for example <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let358.xml">358</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let361.xml">361</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> about wanting to marry <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> is the one Theo had also read; it was sent with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let376.xml">letter 376</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was disappointed that in his reply to the earlier letter his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> had hardly touched on what was most essential; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let379.xml">see letter 379</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘ruzie’ (quarrel).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>For this broken promise, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let379.xml">see letter 379</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Read: ‘te kort schoot, in gebreke bleef’ (fell short, was deficient).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    