<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Thursday, 6 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let382"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b343 a V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>382</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>320</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>385</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-06">on or about Thursday, 6 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0343 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0343 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000439_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">In vorig schrijven kon ik omtrent mijn plannen nog niet in details treden<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik nu in sommige opzigten kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik begin met U te zeggen dat wat betreft de vrouw ik nu met zekerheid weet dat een &amp; ander wat ik reeds vermoedde – van dat zij den laatsten tijd onderhandeld heeft over haar toekomst<c type="kk">/</c> ook reeds vóór ik tot besluit van scheiden gekomen was – waar is. Juist omdat ik daar bijna zóó zeker van was <hi rend="italics">toen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> als <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> dat ik er meer precies van weet wat voor plannen het zijn<c type="kk">/</c> moest ik besluiten te scheiden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het besluit genomen zijnde wilde ik kort en krachtig nu met mijn reisplan voortgaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">De eerste te nemen maatregel was de huur opzeggen – dat is reeds gebeurd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De tweede maatregel is<c type="kk">/</c> hoe te doen met mijn goed dat mij in een tijd van nog niet precies weten waar ik voor lang blijven zal<c type="kk">/</c> ballast zou zijn en onkosten veroorzaken. Het blijft <hi rend="italics">hier in huis</hi> op den zolder<c type="kk">/</c> daar ik met mijn huisbaas<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> eene afspraak daaromtrent heb gemaakt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ge zult vragen<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik dan plannen te s’Hage terug te komen<c type="kp">_</c>– Neen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar over b.v. 1/2 jaar of 1 jaar 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>zal ik misschien weer in rapport met sommige schilders hier dienen te komen<c type="kk">/</c> als ik een eind verder ben<c type="kk">/</c> als ik een partij studies van nog eens echt buiten heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">En dan zal ik waarschijnlijk een tijd een voor atelier zeer geschikte kamer of liever bijgebouw nemen van dezen zelfden huisbaas in zijn eigen huis te VOORBURG<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">niet te s’Hage</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dat mij dan veel voordeeliger zal uitkomen dan hier in stad wonen<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik zoo ligt niet meer toe komen zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Zoo ben ik van overtolligen ballast af en weet meteen waar ik me aan kan houden als ik op een punt kom (vooreerst natuurlijk zeker niet maar stel over 1 jaar b.v.) wanneer een tijdelijk retour naar hier in de termen zou vallen<c type="kp">_</c>– Waarom – b.v. omdat tegen dien tijd ik misschien van de Teekenmaatschappij<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> zou kunnen lid worden<c type="kk">/</c> om maar iets te noemen. wat onder de dingen hoort waar ik dan misschien verlangen naar zou kunnen hebben en zou kunnen bereiken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Gij zult dat wel met mij eens zijn dat den Haag een zeer eigenaardige plaats is. Het is eigentlijk ’t centrum van de kunstwereld in Holland en tegelijk zijn de omstreken gevarieerd en zeer mooi<c type="kk">/</c> zoo dat men er altijd werken kan.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">En dus – ofschoon voorloopig zeker niet – over een tijd van b.v. 1 jaar zal alligt aanleiding zijn hier voor korter of langer te wezen. En door dezen maatregel omtrent het goed blijf ik in kennis met iemand die mij kent en zóó<c type="kk">/</c> als ik ’t vraag<c type="kk">/</c> in elk geval aan een woning kan helpen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Zoo dus ik ben vrij man en zonder ballast<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan weg wanneer ik wil.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En met de frs 150 van U kan ik nu meer doen dan toen er zooveel af moest<c type="kp">_</c> En door dat ik eens wat lucht krijg van zorgen die assommant waren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">De reiskosten vereenvoudigen zich niet weinig op die manier<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">De eenige “drawback”<c type="kk">/</c> “schaduwzij” of hoe ge ’t noemen wilt<c type="kk">/</c> is dat ik voor mij wel degelijk hoop op teregtkomen van de vrouw had in Drenthe<c type="kk">/</c> en nu een zwaar hoofd er in heb. Het is zeer zeker haar eigen doen dat mij tot handelen heeft doen beslissen maar als ik de middelen had kunnen vinden zoo had ik als uiterste poging voor haar haar toch meegenomen naar Drenthe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Enfin beslissen moest ik want elke week uitstel deed mij meer in de doornen raken hier<c type="kk">/</c> zonder vordering met haar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">In geval ik mijn goed zou meenemen kost 1/2 wagon n. Drenthe bij nadere berekening van Gend &amp; Loos<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> zeker nog iets meer dan f<c type="kp">_</c> 25<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. thuisbrengen en halen komt er nog bij<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon niet heel veel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dan zouden er eenige pakkisten noodig zijn die ik zou moeten koopen en dat kost ook al weer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Mijn goed te hebben was makkelijk doch het komt te duur uit en vooral als men ginder heen &amp; weer zou trekken.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik zoude vooreerst wel eens een kijkje willen nemen op Katwijk<c type="kk">/</c> om nog eenige zee studies te maken en omdat in elk geval dat te bereiken is<c type="kk">/</c> al zou ik met de reis n. Drenthe een tijd moeten wachten wegens het geld.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Och Theo mijn gevoel van dezer dagen zult ge wel begrijpen<c type="kk">/</c> een groote melankolie over de vrouw en de kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> maar het kon niet anders – tevens<c type="kk">/</c> al mijn gedachten zijn op het werk en heb ik veel animo wegens ik dingen kan doen nu die anders mij niet mogelijk waren geweest<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Beste broer – als gij precies voelen kondt wat er in mij omgaat en hoe om zoo te zeggen ik een stuk van mij zelf besteed heb aan de vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk alles vergeten en me geconcentreerd om haar er boven op te brengen – als gij precies voelen kondt een soort weemoed over ’t leven<c type="kk">/</c> die mij echter niet onverschillig er voor maakt<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel ik heb liever mijn smart over een &amp; ander dan vergeten of onverschillig worden – als gij precies voelen kondt in hoever ik mijn sereniteit put in <hi rend="italics">worship</hi> <hi rend="italics">of</hi> <hi rend="italics">sorrow</hi><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en niet in illusie – misschien voor U zelfs broer<c type="kk">/</c> zou mijn binnenste heel anders en meer los van het leven zijn dan gij U nu wel er in kunt denken. Ik zal over de vrouw zeker niet veel meer spreken<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal evenwel veel aan haar blijven denken. Met haar is ’t geweest een kwestie van alles of niets wat betreft helpen<c type="kk">/</c> van ’t begin af<c type="kp">_</c> Geld haar geven om vroeger op haar eigen te blijven kon ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> ik <hi rend="italics">moest</hi> haar bij me in nemen<c type="kk">/</c> wou ik <hi rend="italics">iets</hi> doen kunnen waar ze wat aan had<c type="kp">_</c> En mijns inziens was ’t een regten weg geweest haar te trouwen en mee te nemen naar Drenthe<c type="kp">_</c> Maar en zij zelf en omstandigheden geef ik toe het niet toelaten<c type="kp">_</c> zij is niet lief<c type="kk">/</c> zij is niet goed<c type="kk">/</c> doch ik zelf ben dat ook niet en zoo als we waren bestond er serieuse gehechtheid door alles heen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik heb behoefte aan werken en ik heb ook behoefte ge eens spoedig schrijft<c type="kp">_</c> adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I couldn’t yet go into detail about my plans in my last letter, but now I can in some respects.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ll begin my telling you that I now know for certain that one thing and another that I already suspected as regards the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> is true — that recently she was negotiating about her future even before I’d come to the decision to separate. I had to decide to separate, precisely because I was almost as certain of that <hi rend="italics">then</hi> as I am <hi rend="italics">now</hi> that I know more exactly what the plans were. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Having taken the decision, I wanted to go ahead with my travel plans without delay. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The first measure to be taken was to give notice to the landlord — that has now been done. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The second measure is what to do with my things, which would be an encumbrance and lead to costs at a time of not knowing exactly where I’ll stay for long. They’ll stay <hi rend="italics">here in this house</hi> in the attic, since I’ve agreed this with my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">landlord</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">You will ask, do I have plans to come back to The Hague then? No. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But in, say,  1/2  a year or 1 year 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I may have to get in touch with some painters here, when I’ve got much further, when I have a batch of studies of the real countryside. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And then for a while I’ll probably take a room or rather an annexe well suited for use as a studio from the same <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">landlord</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in his own house in VOORBURG, <hi rend="italics">not in The Hague</hi>, which will be much cheaper for me than living here in the city, which I shan’t readily do again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So I’m relieved of superfluous encumbrances, and know at once where to head for if I reach a point (certainly not for the time being, of course, but say in 1 year) when a temporary return here would be feasible. Why? — because, for instance, by that time I might be able to become a member of the Drawing Society,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> just to mention one thing. Which is one of the things I might desire and could achieve then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">You’ll agree with me that The Hague is a very remarkable place. It really is the centre of the art world in Holland, and at the same time the surroundings are varied and extremely beautiful, so that one can always work there.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And so — though certainly not for the time being — after a period of 1 year, say, there will probably be a reason for being here for a brief or a longer stay. And through this arrangement regarding my things I stay in touch with someone who knows me and so can at any rate find me a place to live, if I ask. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">So I’m a free man without encumbrances, I can leave when I like. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And I can now do more with the 150 francs from you than when so much had to come out of it. And because I have some relief from worries that were nerve-racking.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">The travel costs are made much simpler in this way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"> The only ‘drawback’, ‘disadvantage’ or whatever you want to call it is that, for my part, I really did have hope that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> would turn out all right in Drenthe, and now have grave doubts about that. It’s certainly her own behaviour that made me decide to act, but if I’d been able to find the means I’d have taken her to Drenthe nonetheless, in a final attempt for her. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Well, I had to decide, because every week of delay got me more entangled in thorns here, without any progress with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">If I took my things, a 1/2 wagon to Drenthe would certainly cost something more than 25 guilders, according to a revised calculation by Van Gend &amp; Loos,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> because there’s also the cost of delivering to and collecting from home, although this isn’t all that much. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Well, some packing cases would be needed, which I would have to buy, and that’s another expense. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">It would have been convenient to have my things, but it works out too expensive, and especially if one moved about over there.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I would first like to have a look at Katwijk, to do some sea studies, and because that at any rate is within reach, even if the journey to Drenthe has to wait a while on account of the money. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Oh, Theo, you’ll understand my feelings in recent days, a great melancholy about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, but it couldn’t be otherwise — at the same time all my thoughts are about work and I’m really eager, because now I can do things which would have been impossible for me otherwise. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Dear brother — if you could feel precisely what I’m feeling, and how I’ve devoted a piece of myself, so to speak, to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>, namely forgetting everything else and concentrating on getting her back on her feet — if you could feel precisely a kind of sadness about life, which doesn’t, however, make me indifferent to it, on the contrary, I would rather have my sorrow about one thing and another than forget or become indifferent — if you could feel precisely the extent to which I draw my serenity from <hi rend="italics">worship of sorrow</hi><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and not from illusion — perhaps even for you brother, my inner self would be very different and more detached from life than you can now imagine. I’ll certainly not say much more about the woman, but I’ll still continue to think about her often. From the beginning, with her, it was a question of all or nothing when it came to helping. I couldn’t give her money to live on her own before, I <hi rend="italics">had</hi> to take her in if I was to do <hi rend="italics">anything</hi> of use to her. And in my view the proper course would have been to marry her and take her to Drenthe. But, I admit, neither she herself nor circumstances allow it. She isn’t kind, she isn’t good, but neither am I, and serious attachment existed throughout everything as we were. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I need to work and I also need you to write soon. Adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This letter goes back to the subject of the travel plans mentioned in <ref target="let381.xml">letter 381</ref>; Van Gogh can now give more details <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-4)</ref>. Since the previous letter can be dated to on or about 5 September and the next one to 7 or 8 September, we date the present letter on or about Thursday, 6 September 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In earlier editions a second sheet was printed as a postscript. We regard it, however, as a postscript to <ref target="let381.xml">letter 381</ref>; see there under <hi rend="italics">Arrangement</hi>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Conflict with Sien’s family <ref target="let338.xml">(338)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s plan to go to Drenthe <ref target="let379.xml">(379)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">M.A. de Zwart</rs>, who lived in Kleine Laan in Voorburg.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For De Hollandsche Teeken-maatschappij, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let256.xml#n-8">see letter 256, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For Van Gend &amp; Loos, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let135.xml#n-19">see letter 135, n. 19</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let378.xml#n-7">letter 378, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh earlier quoted from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Carlyle</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_197">Sartor resartus</ref></hi>: ‘Knowest thou that “<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Worship of Sorrow</hi>”?’, where the phrase stands for the Christian religion. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let356.xml#n-8">See letter 356, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    