<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Friday, 7 or Saturday, 8 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let383"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b344 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>383</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>321</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>386</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-07">Friday, 7 or Saturday, 8 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0344" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0344" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000441_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Met pakken &amp;c. ben ik zoover dat direkt als ik reisgeld heb ik vertrekken zal. Het is ’t best dat in de gegevenen ik kortaf te werk ga<c type="kp">_</c> Want de tijd van verhuizen &amp;c. kan men niets goeds uitvoeren wat het werk betreft en zal ik niet weer op streek zijn tot ik ergens buiten zit. Zoo dus als gij tegen den 10<hi rend="super">den</hi> iets zendt hoop ik weg te kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> al is ’t dat ik niet in eens door kan zoo ga ik in een dorp digt bij desnoods een dag of wat logeeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik hoop dat het maar zal uitkomen volgens ’t geen gij mogelijk acht, trouwens ik zelf ook min of meer, dat het de vrouw tot een zwenking ten goede brengt. Doch ik vrees dat zal niet wezen en zij zal den ouden weg opgaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Als ik naar mijn intieme kennis van haar oordeel<c type="kk">/</c> is zij te zwak vooral in geest en wilskracht om op een regten weg door te gaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Toen ik tijdens Uw bezoek er over sprak was ik <hi rend="italics">besloten te beslissen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> maar er waren twee wegen m.i. en de beslissing <hi rend="italics">hoe</hi> hing meer van haar dan van mij af<c type="kp">_</c> Had zij vast gewild met mij doorzetten<c type="kk">/</c> zoo dat ’t iets anders dan een woord doch een daarlaten van die verkeerdheden welke den toestand onhoudbaar maakten geweest was<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof<c type="kk">/</c> hoe moeielijk en arm wij het zouden kunnen hebben gekregen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t ware een beter lot voor haar geweest dan zoo als zij ’t nu te wachten heeft. Doch ik zag in haar iets als een <hi rend="italics">sphinx</hi> die noch ja noch neen kan zeggen. En als ge mij vragen zoudt of ik weet wat zij doen gaat zoo weet ik dit alleen<c type="kk">/</c> “zeker niet zóó regt als ze ’t zou hebben kunnen doen”<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Deze laatste dagen zag ik weer duidelijk dat het naloopen van de advertenties maar voor den schijn werd gedaan en zij mijn vertrek waarschijnlijk afwachten om iets te beginnen waarover zij niet tot mij spreken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Reden te meer voor mij om direkt te vertrekken want 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>anders zoude er van komen dat ze opzettelijk de dingen hangende hielden. En hier heeft de moeder weer een handje in.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dit plan dat weer een verdraaiing is van wat zij een paar dagen geleden begonnen<c type="kk">/</c> zal zoo goed als zeker tot niets dan beroerdheid leiden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar ik zou gek moeten zijn om te helpen als zij niet open zijn tegenover me<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar. Ik ben dus van plan kortaf weg te gaan en een veertien dagen te laten voorbij gaan. Dan zal ik hen schrijven en zien hoe het gesteld is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik begin ook te gelooven dat ik weg <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> om hun tot ernst te brengen. Maar zulk een proef is gevaarlijk want ook in dien korten tijd reeds kunnen zij veel bederven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Waarom<c type="kk">/</c> waarom is de vrouw zoo onverstandig<c type="kp">_</c> Wat Musset heeft genoemd “Un enfant du siècle” – is zij geheel en al<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – en ik denk wel eens aan de ruine van Musset zelf als ik kom op haar toekomst.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">In Musset was iets hoogs<c type="kk">/</c> welnu in haar is er ook een je ne sais quoi<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon zij zeker geen artist is. <hi rend="italics">Was ze dat maar</hi><c type="kk">/</c> een beetje<c type="kp">_</c> Zij heeft haar kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> en worden die meer dan ze ’t nu zijn zelfs nog haar idee fixe<c type="kk">/</c> zoo is er iets solide in haar maar ook dat is nog niet wat ’t zijn moet<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon haar moederliefde toch<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon onvolkomen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t beste in haar karakter m.i. is.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het is voor mij een moeielijk iets dat ik veronderstel dat<c type="kk">/</c> als ik eenmaal weg ben<c type="kk">/</c> zij van een paar dingen spijt zal hebben en beter zal willen en mij noodig hebben. Ik wil in dat geval ook helpen<c type="kk">/</c> doch zal ik er <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> in krijgen dat gij me verteldet van de vrouw welke gij hebt ontmoet<c type="kk">/</c> tu m’as trouvé bien en bas<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">il</hi> <hi rend="italics">faut que je remonte</hi><c type="kp">_</c> In plaats van <hi rend="italics">il faut que je remonte</hi> zal 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>zij zeggen <hi rend="italics">l’abîme m’attire</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb eens gehoord dat er eene relatie geweest is tusschen Musset en George Sand. George was bedaard<c type="kk">/</c> positief<c type="kk">/</c> zeer ijverig<c type="kp">_</c> Musset was lâché<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> onverschillig en verwaarloosde zelfs zijn werk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het kwam tusschen die twee karakters tot een crisis en scheiding. Daarna een wanhopige poging van Musset en berouw maar niet dan nadat hij nog dieper in den modder gezakt was<c type="kk">/</c> en in tusschen had George Sand haar zaken in orde gebragt<c type="kk">/</c> zat geheel verdiept in een nieuw werk<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en zeide “het is te laat<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> het niet meer”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Alleen dit zijn zoo zeer kwesties van zielstrijd<c type="kk">/</c> en harten krimpen er meer bij zamen van pijn dan het wel schijnt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Theo als ik wegga zal ik niet gerust omtrent haar weggaan<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel ongerust omdat ik zoo vrees zij slechts wakker zal worden als het te laat is<c type="kk">/</c> slechts een vurige begeerte naar iets eenvoudigers en reiners zal krijgen als ’t moment om het te bereiken voorbij zal zijn gegaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als ik dat sphinxachtige in haar zie dan ken ik dat van ouds en in haar en in anderen<c type="kk">/</c> en het is een zeer kwaad teeken. Dan<c type="kk">/</c> het melankolieke kijken in den afgrond is ook fataal en het middel om dat te doen wijken: hard werken. En nu – Theo – ze legt de handen alweer te veel in den schoot – nu<c type="kk">/</c> melankolie<c type="kk">/</c> als ze te overwinnen is<c type="kk">/</c> moet overwonnen worden door sjouwen en wie dat zelf niet voelt<c type="kk">/</c> welnu die is er dan voor goed bij en gaat regelregt naar den kelder<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Haar zeggen heb ik gedaan<c type="kk">/</c> bij tijden het er een beetje in gekregen ook<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gij ziet<c type="kk">/</c> zij is wel aan ’t randje<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Het zal mijn hand niet zijn die er haar indondert doch eeuwig er bij blijven staan en haar terughouden <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ik ook niet<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo veel gezond verstand moet iemand hebben dat als hij gewaarschuwd<c type="kk">/</c> geholpen wordt<c type="kk">/</c> hij meewerkt.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik weet het<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn gevallen waar de melankolieke schijnt niet te willen<c type="kk">/</c> later stilletjes toch doet wat hij doen moet en geneest<c type="kp">_</c> Als zij nu maar zóó is dan is het best en komt ze nog teregt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">De melankolieke heeft aan niets meer – in de periode van herstelling – dan aan een vriend<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat is veel alsdan<c type="kk">/</c> al is die vriend arm<c type="kp">_</c> Welnu dat zal zij in mij blijven vinden – en al is ’t <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> zoo dat zij zeer hatelijk was en is bij tijden – natuurlijk <hi rend="italics">toch</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Een steun zal ze noodig hebben en dien steun zal ik blijven al ben ik weg<c type="kk">/</c> mits ik energie en goeden wil zie iets of wat<c type="kp">_</c> De menschen die <hi rend="italics">haar</hi> van <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> zochten afkeerig te maken (in haar familie) deden iets wat zoo erg zou zijn als een moord aan haar en haar kinderen indien ze het niet in hun verhardheid en domheid deden. Want zonder dat was ze veel verder geweest.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Tegen den tienden doe Uw best mij zooveel te sturen ik desnoods weg kan<c type="kk">/</c> wegens dit wijs zoude zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Evenwel breng niet U zelf in ongelegenheid want ik zal doen naar omstandigheden en U direkt schrijven hoe ik gedaan heb<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Is het te weinig voor Drenthe<c type="kk">/</c> ga ik een dag of wat naar Loosduinen en wacht daar af<c type="kp">_</c> Loosduinen heb ik nog prachtige dingen gevonden<c type="kk">/</c> oude boerderijen<c type="kk">/</c> en de effekten zijn superbe s’avonds daar. Ik zou dan mijn goed waarschijnlijk vooruitzenden of in depôt laten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Doch tevens is het juist een moment dat ik geschikt de huur kan afbreken en als Uw brief komt vertrek ik van hier.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Het is dan een wenk voor de vrouw dat zij doorzetten moet<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal nog advertenties er bij plaatsen doch deze twee laatste dagen was het weer slabakken en ik vrees zij in den grond het plan veranderd hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">adieu Theo, ik wou de dingen al geregeld waren want zulke dagen als deze zijn moeielijk en heeft men weinig aan. Heb het goed en voorspoed<c type="kk">/</c> geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Ik hoop gij niet ongesteld zijt geworden<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een tijd geleden ook diarrhee gehad maar is toch weer opgehouden. Misschien zijn eijeren nog het beste om de maag dan wat aan te sterken<c type="kk">/</c> als ten minste zwakheid de oorzaak is.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve got so far with packing &amp;c. that I’ll leave as soon as I have the travel money. It’s best in the circumstances that I set to work straightaway. For during the removals &amp;c. one can’t do anything good in the way of work, and I shan’t get back into my stride until I’m somewhere in the country. So I hope to be able to get away if you send something towards the 10th, if I can’t go straight through I’ll stay in a village close by for a day or two if need be. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I hope things will turn out as you think possible, indeed as I do too, more or less, that it will make the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> change direction for the better. Yet I fear that won’t happen and she’ll go down the old road. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">If I judge by my intimate knowledge of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, she’s too weak in spirit and willpower in particular to continue on a proper course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">When I talked about it during your visit I was <hi rend="italics">determined to decide</hi>, but in my view there were two roads, and the decision as to <hi rend="italics">how</hi> depended more on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> than on me. If she had definitely wanted to carry on with me, so that it was something more than words and a turning away from those faults that had made the situation impossible, I believe that it would have been a better lot for her than that awaiting her now, however difficult and poor things might have been for us. But I saw in her something like a <hi rend="italics">sphinx</hi> that cannot say either yes or no. And if you were to ask me if I knew what she’s going to do, all I know is this, ‘certainly not as straight as she could have done’. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">In recent days I again saw clearly how looking at the advertisements was done merely for the sake of appearances, and that they’re probably waiting for my departure before embarking on something they don’t discuss with me. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">All the more reason for me to leave immediately, for 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> otherwise they’d resort to delaying things deliberately. And the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> again has a hand in this.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">This plan, which is again a twisting of what they began a few days ago, will almost certainly lead to nothing but wretchedness. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But I would have to be mad to help when they’re not being open with me, wouldn’t I? So I intend simply to leave and to let fourteen days or so go by. Then I’ll write to them and see how things are. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m also beginning to think that I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> leave in order to make them be serious. But such a test is dangerous, for even in a short time they can spoil a great deal. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Why, why is the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> so unwise? She’s what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Musset</rs> has called ‘A child of the age’<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> through and through — and I sometimes think of the ruin of Musset himself when I consider her future.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">There was something elevated in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Musset</rs>; well, in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> there’s also a <hi rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi>, although she’s certainly not an artist. <hi rend="italics">If only she were</hi>, a little. She has her children, and there’ll be something solid in her if they become her <hi rend="italics">idée fixe</hi> even more than they are now, but that too isn’t what it should be, even though her mother love, although imperfect, is still the best thing in her character, in my view. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">It’s a difficult thing for me that I assume that, once I am gone, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs>’ll regret a few things and want to be better and will need me. I’m ready to help in that case, but I’ll get into her head <hi rend="italics">what</hi> you told me about the woman you met, you found me when I had sunk very low, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> <hi rend="italics">must climb up again</hi>. Instead of <hi rend="italics">I must climb up again</hi>, she 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> will say <hi rend="italics">the abyss draws me</hi>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I once heard that there was a relationship between <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Musset</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_848">George Sand</rs>. George was composed, positive, highly industrious. Musset was nonchalant,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> indifferent, and even neglected his work. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Things came to a head and a separation between these two characters. Later a desperate attempt by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Musset</rs> and remorse, but not before he had sunk still deeper into the mire, and in the meantime <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_848">George Sand</rs> had got her affairs in order and was completely absorbed in a new work,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and said ‘it’s too late, it’s <hi rend="italics">impossible</hi> <hi rend="italics">now</hi>’. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But these are so much questions of inner conflict, and hearts shrink more in pain because of them than appears.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Theo, when I leave I shan’t leave feeling easy about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> — on the contrary, uneasy — because I fear so much that she won’t wake up until it’s too late, not have a keen desire for something simpler and purer until the moment for attaining it has passed. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">When I see that sphinx-like quality in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, I recognize it of old both in her and in others, and it’s a very bad sign. Then staring melancholically into the abyss is fatal too, and the way to make that go away is hard work. And now — Theo — she’s again too passively resigned to things — well, melancholy, if it can be overcome, must be overcome by toil, and whoever doesn’t feel that is lost for ever and will go straight to the dogs. I’ve told her this, even got a little of it into her at times. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You see, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs>’s on the edge, isn’t she? </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">It shan’t be my hand that pushes her in, but nor <hi rend="italics">can</hi> I stand beside her forever, holding her back. A person must have enough common sense to cooperate when he is warned and helped.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I know, there are cases where the melancholic appears to be unwilling, but later quietly does what he must and recovers. If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs>’s like that, then that’s fine and she’ll be all right. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">The melancholic is helped by nothing more — in the period of recovery — than by a friend. That’s a great deal then, even if the friend is poor. Well, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs>’ll continue to find that in me — even if <hi rend="italics">now</hi> it’s true that she has been and is at times extremely nasty — of course <hi rend="italics">nonetheless</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">She</rs>’ll need a support, and I’ll still be that support even though I am gone, provided I see a little energy and good will. The people who tried to turn <hi rend="italics">her</hi> away from <hi rend="italics">me</hi> (in her family) did something that would be as bad as murdering her and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs> if it weren’t that they did it in their obduracy and stupidity. For without that she’d be much further along. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Do your best towards the tenth to send me enough for me to be able to leave if need be, because this would be wise. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">All the same, don’t put yourself in difficulties for I’ll act according to the circumstances and write to you straightaway to say what I’ve done. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">If it’s too little for Drenthe I’ll go to Loosduinen for a day or so and wait there. I’ve found splendid things in Loosduinen, old farmhouses, and the effects in the evening are superb there. In that case I would probably send my things ahead or put them in storage. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">But it’s also just the moment at which I can conveniently end the tenancy, and when your letter comes I’ll leave here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">That will be a sign for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> that she must persevere. I’ll place more advertisements, but these last two days it was idling about again, and I fear they’ve changed the plan fundamentally.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Adieu, Theo, I wish things were already sorted out, for days like these are difficult and little good to anyone. I wish you well and good fortune, believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I hope you haven’t fallen ill, I also had diarrhoea a while ago but it stopped. Eggs may be the best thing for strengthening the stomach, at least if weakness is the cause. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On the point of departing for Drenthe, Van Gogh writes: ‘if you send something towards the 10th ... I hope to be able to get away’ (<ref target="#l-7">ll. 7-8</ref> and <ref target="#l-131">l. 131</ref>). If Theo was to comply with this request, the letter had to have been sent at least two days before 10 September. It is clear from <ref target="let384.xml">letters 384</ref> and <ref target="let385.xml">385</ref> that Van Gogh received the money on the 10th, which means that the letter dates from no later than Friday, 7 or Saturday, 8 September 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s plan to go to Drenthe <ref target="let379.xml">(379)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Conflict with Sien’s family <ref target="let338.xml">(338)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_341">La confession d’un enfant du siècle</ref></hi> (1836), in which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Alfred de Musset</rs> portrayed the break between <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_848">George Sand</rs> and himself. The theme of the novel is the moral weakness of the generation of that time. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The much talked-about affair between <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_848">Sand</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_715">Musset</rs> ended in 1835. It was depicted in the work of both writers, especially in the roman à clef <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_353">Elle et lui</ref></hi> by Sand (1859), in which Musset (as Laurent de Fauvel) gives in to despair at the end. The rest of Musset’s life was marked by drinking, debauchery and little literary production. The relationship was also the subject of novels by other writers and led to a torrent of articles and prints. See Yves Lainey. ‘L’amour-passion. La liaison Musset-Sand’, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Musset ou la difficulté d’aimer</hi>. Paris 1978, chapter 5, pp. 69-115.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh uses the French word ‘lâché’ here in the sense of ‘loose, hasty’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_848">Sand</rs>’s biographer Renee Winegarten confirms: ‘Once at Nohant, George plunged into work on a new novel’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The double life of George Sand. Woman and writer. A critical biography</hi>. New York 1978, p. 155.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    