<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, on or about Friday, 21 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let388"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b349 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>388</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>326</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>391</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-21">on or about Friday, 21 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Hoogeveen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0349 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0349 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000447_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0349 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0349 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000448_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief heb ik zooeven ontvangen en dank er U regt hartelijk voor. En wil meteen U op nieuw een &amp; ander van mijn bevindingen schrijven. Vooreerst dat ik een brief van Rappard heb gehad uit West Terschelling en hij daar druk aan ’t werk is na eerst hier in Drenthe te Rolde<c type="kk">/</c> in de buurt van Assen<c type="kk">/</c> nog te hebben vertoefd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik hoop dezen winter ook zelf hem daar te bezoeken &amp; nog een paar studies te maken<c type="kk">/</c> de reis er heen voor zoo ver ik kan nagaan heen &amp; terug ongeveer drie gulden zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij ’t oversteken naar T. moeielijk zij. Maar dat is ’t wel waard om eens met een schilder te zijn en zal de eenzaamheid breken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Naar Uw volgenden brief<c type="kk">/</c> die hoop ik niet in de pen zal blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik zeer verlangend. Vergeet niet mij betreffende C.M<c type="kp">_</c> den afloop te melden<c type="kk">/</c> of gij hem nog hebt berigt ik hier was en of dien brief ook onbeantwoord is gebleven<c type="kp">_</c> Indien deze dingen zoo zijn zal ik<c type="kk">/</c> niet nu natuurlijk doch later<c type="kk">/</c> zeer zeker zelf C.M<c type="kp">_</c> gaan opzoeken en hem opheldering vragen van de reden waarom hij geen antwoord gaf. Schrijven zal ik niet doch onwrikbaar vast staat het bij mij dat ik <hi>niet</hi> vrede neem met zijn niet antwoorden<c type="kk">/</c> vooral <hi rend="italics">U</hi> niet antwoorden<c type="kk">/</c> en daar er dit bijkomt ook het <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> niet antwoorden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Iets te doen heb ik NOOIT BEWEERD dat hij <hi rend="italics">moest</hi>, noch doe ik zulks nu<c type="kp">_</c> Wat hij deed of eventueel doen zou<c type="kk">/</c> reken ik als een gunst waarvoor ik hem ook steeds als zoodanig voor heb bedankt en ook van mijn kant studies gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> zeker een 50 tal in ’t geheel<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> met het regt er bij die later nog in te ruilen<c type="kp">_</c> Doch dit een en ander zóó zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> behoef ik bepaald geen beleedigingen te verdragen<c type="kk">/</c> en het <hi rend="italics">is</hi> eene grove beleediging ik nu niet eens berigt heb dat hij het laatste pak studies heeft ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c>– Geen syllabe<c type="kp">_</c>– En als daar bij komt dat <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> brief onbeantwoord blijft<c type="kk">/</c> is het zòò dat het <hi rend="italics">een lafheid</hi> zou wezen het er bij te laten en <hi>moet</hi> en zal ik opheldering eischen. ’t welk zooals gezegd ik<c type="kk">/</c> al gaat er een tijd overheen<c type="kk">/</c> zeer beslist en door een persoonlijk bezoek zal doen. Indien alsdan hij mij niet te woord zou willen staan<c type="kk">/</c> was daar de zaak volstrekt niet mede uit want mijn wil is vast dat ik hierover satisfactie hebben <hi rend="italics">zal</hi>. Geeft hij me die<c type="kk">/</c> best<c type="kk">/</c> maar weigert hij me die te geven (ik heb geen enkele onbeleefde term jegens hem gebruikt<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb alleen op zeer koelen toon geschreven)<c type="kk">/</c> weigert hij<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> me dien te geven<c type="kk">/</c> <hi>mag</hi> <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> zeggen oog om oog<c type="kk">/</c> tand om tand<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en hem grof terug beleedigen<c type="kk">/</c> hetwelk in koelen bloede ik doen zoude.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Versta mij <supplied>w</supplied>el broer, begrijp me in dezen eens en voor altijd<c type="kk">/</c> wat er ook zij van het wenschelijke om finantieele hulp te krijgen – dat is toch verre van N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 1 te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> N<hi rend="super">o</hi> 1 is dat hij te ver gaat in het uit ’t oog verliezen der regten die ik als mensch heb<c type="kk">/</c> al was ik hem een vreemde (van verwantschap spreek ik nooit<c type="kk">/</c> baseer ik me nooit op)<c type="kk">/</c> om niet behandeld te worden als een mauvais sujet<c type="kk">/</c> om niet veroordeeld te worden of beschuldigd van dit of dat zonder zelf er in gehoord te worden. Ik heb <hi>regt</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">volle regt</hi> een antwoord te <hi>eischen</hi> en het in geval van zwijgen op te vatten als zeer grove beleediging.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik moet ronduit hierover spreken van wege ik tot nu toe heb gehoopt van zelf het zou teregt komen en ik een woord in antwoord zou ontvangen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Doch dat stil verdragen heeft eene grens en zoo als ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> over die grens zou het van mij lafheid<c type="kk">/</c> onmannelijk wezen er niet vierkant tegen te protesteeren<c type="kp">_</c> U verzoek ik dus vriendelijk mij eenvoudig Uw wedervaring betreffende ’t beantwoorden van Uw schrijven me te willen mededeelen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal dan voor mij zelf weten waaraan ik mij te houden heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal dan er geen woord meer over zeggen doch al ging er meer dan een jaar over heen<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik diep in mij<c type="kk">/</c> onverroest<c type="kk">/</c> klaar en helder als ik het op dit moment heb<c type="kk">/</c> dit zelfde gevoel van dat ik opheldering <hi rend="italics">moet hebben</hi> in mij terugvinden en niet rusten voor ik op de een of andere wijze mijn zaak met hem afgehandeld heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik geloof gij zult dit gevoelen in mij billijken en zoudt dit te meer indien gij precies wist wat in vroeger jaren tusschen hem en mij is voorgevallen. als wanneer ik zeer gewantrouwd heb betreffende het plan om te studeeren<c type="kk">/</c> of de belofte om dat door te voeren rondborstig was en doordacht – ik heb beschouwd toen dat <hi rend="italics">zij</hi> overijld het plan maakten en <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> overijld het goedvond<c type="kk">/</c> en het blijft opperbest m.i<c type="kp">_</c> het toen gestopt is<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik zelf heb bewerkt expres en zoo aangelegd dat de schande van het opgeven op mij kwam en niet op iemand anders<c type="kp">_</c> Gij begrijpt dat ik die wel andere talen geleerd heb<c type="kk">/</c> ook dat miserable beetje Latijn &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> wel magtig was te boven te komen<c type="kk">/</c> waartegen evenwel ik verklaard heb op te zien. Dit was een smoesje wegens ik tegenover protecteurs toen liever niet wilde zeggen dat ik de heele Universiteit (de Theologische althans) als een onuitsprekelijken knoeiboel beschouw<c type="kk">/</c> een kweekerij van Phariséers<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dat aan durven het mij niet ontbrak trachte ik te bewijzen door naar de Borinage te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> waar zeer zeker ik het moeielijker had dan als ik student zoude zijn geworden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik dacht dat C.M. b.v. beter mij doorgrond zou hebben<c type="kk">/</c> en reden te meer heb ik hem weinig fijngevoelig te vinden als ik bedenk hoe hij sedert mij met zekere verachting behandelde – <hi>Toen</hi> en <hi>nu</hi> heb ik een boel dingen voor me gehouden die ik had kunnen zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> waarvan als ik eens hem er over aangrijp hij<c type="kk">/</c> wat hij ook zegge<c type="kk">/</c> toch in zijn geweten een paar dingen zal moeten voelen; ik<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> noch vroeger noch nu eenige laagheid jegens hem heb bedreven<c type="kk">/</c> en dus deze beleediging van niet antwoorden heeft geen raison d’être<c type="kk">/</c> te meer daar het beter geweest ware indien van ’t begin af dat ik te s’Hage kwam al het verleden geheel vergeten &amp; vergeven was en eene goede verstandhouding vast besloten<c type="kk">/</c> waarover ik toen ook met ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> sprak<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik zeg <hi rend="italics">niet</hi>, broer, la paix à <hi rend="italics">tout prix</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en ik heb liever een onaangename explicatie dan een flaauw laten waaien zoodra dat flaauw wordt<c type="kk">/</c> en dat zou het nu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Weet nu echter dat ik U NIET er in noemen zal<c type="kk">/</c> al is het dat zijn beleediging jegens U<c type="kk">/</c> als hij dat niet verbetert (’t komt me voor hij jegens U ietwat van dezelfde politiek begint te gebruiken)<c type="kk">/</c> is datgene wat mij onwrikbaar maakt nog een appeltje met ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> te schillen en ik besloten ben hem veel dingen te zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik beloof U dat<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal alleen het doen voorkomen als of ik het had over mij alleen<c type="kk">/</c> als wist ik niets van U.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Voor dat mysterieuse<c type="kk">/</c> dat sphinxachtige zwijgen &amp;c. heb ik de allerdiepste verachting en verklaar U bij dezen er alles van te denken<c type="kk">/</c> behalve iets dat regtuit en trouw of waarachtig is.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het moge een beetje de algemeene politiek van tegenwoordig zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet dat wel<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik ben zoo als gij weet het niet eens met de algemeene politiek van tegenwoordig wegens ik haar als laag en alle kenmerken van decadence die op een pruikentijd uitloopt dragend beschouw.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Men zou kunnen schreijen over wat tegenwoordig bedorven wordt op allerlei gebied<c type="kk">/</c> waar vroegeren hun arbeid aan hebben gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> opregt<c type="kk">/</c> wordt nu lafhartig verwaarloosd en losgelaten<c type="kp">_</c>– Den tijd waarin wij leven is misschien iets uiterlijk fatsoenlijkers dan den vroegeren maar het nobele gaat er te veel uit dan dat men van de toekomst dezelfde groote dingen kan verwachten welke zijn geweest in ’t verleden. Enfin ieder moet het voor zich zelf weten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Nu over iets anders, maar het was noodig dit een &amp; ander te behandelen al heb ik er geen ’t minste pleizier in er over te schrijven, namelijk over mijn bevindingen hier. Hoogeveen zelf vind ik hoe meer ik in de omstreken rondloop<c type="kk">/</c> hoe langer hoe mooier en ik twijfel niet of dit zal zoo blijven. Als C.M<c type="kp">_</c> vervalt<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik vrees<c type="kk">/</c> zoo neemt dat niet weg dat op den duur het hier voordeeliger uitkomt dan te s’Hage. Maar wegens C.M<c type="kp">_</c> vervalt zal ik een zekeren tijd moeten kromliggen voor ik mijn plannen kan uitvoeren. En misschien verliezen we daar après tout volstrekt niets bij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Het is nu eenmaal zoo dat ik geld noodig heb en een voorraad verf en verschillende dingen<c type="kk">/</c> voor en aleer ik van den togt door den Zuid oosthoek van Drenthe bepaalde resultaten kan verwachten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Maar over b.v. een halfjaar zal ik dat bezuinigd hebben hoop ik en in den tusschentijd zal ik toch dingen kunnen doen hier<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo nu zal ik vooreerst niet voor goed naar verder weg gaan maar nog blijven werken in deze omstreken<c type="kp">_</c> Zal zien wat geld te besparen voor twee reizen<c type="kk">/</c> één door den zuidoosthoek<c type="kk">/</c> een door de heide tusschen hier en Assen. En aan laatstgenoemden togt noordwaarts hoop ik te verbinden ’t bezoek aan vriend Rappard en alsdan in zijn logement op Terschelling<c type="kk">/</c> ’t Scheepje genaamd<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> een tijd te vertoeven. De uitvoering van die twee togten zou te roekeloos zijn indien men zonder voorraad en zonder berekend te zijn op de omstandigheden ze ondernam. Maar met geduld zijn ze mogelijk want ik zie genoeg dat ik hier minder onkosten heb dan te s’Hage. En vóór ik dat begin wilde ik het geld van Rappard afdoen<c type="kk">/</c> ook al zij het dat daarna ik van hem misschien weer iets zal leenen na hem gezien te hebben en als ik zeker weet ik er iets bepaalds door maken kan.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik heb hier aanvankelijk eenigen tegenspoed met modellen gehad op de heide<c type="kk">/</c> waar er over gelagchen werd en ik voor den gek gehouden en begonnen figuurstudies niet af kon krijgen door onwil van de modellen die ik evenwel, althans voor hier, goed had betaald<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb echter daartegen mij verzet en op die zelfde plek op een enkel gezin mij geconcentreerd<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik nu eene oude vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> een meisje en een man kan krijgen en hoop heb die goed zullen blijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik heb een paar studies van de heide welke ik U zenden zal als zij goed droog zijn<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en ben ook aquarellen begonnen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> En ik ben ook weer pen<c type="shy">-</c>teekeningen begonnen<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> juist met het oog op het schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> omdat men met de pen in zulke details kan treden als geschilderde studies niet kunnen en men wel doet twee studies te maken<c type="kk">/</c> een geheel geteekend voor ’t in elkaar zitten der dingen én een geschilderd voor de kleur<c type="kp">_</c> Als het n.l. kan en de gelegenheid het toelaat is dit een weg om later de geschilderde studie op te voeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">De heide is rijk en er zijn moerassige weien die mij dikwijls aan Th<c type="kp">_</c> Rousseau herinneren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan U zeggen dat de buitenlucht en het leven hier mij veel opsterkt<c type="kp">_</c> Och had de arme vrouw het nog eens kunnen hebben – ik denk aan haar met zoo innigen weemoed – ondanks mijn gezond verstand mij ten duidelijkste zegt dat het nu onmogelijk kan in gegeven omstandigheden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ben ongerust over haar wegens ik niets van haar hoorde en daaruit opmaak zij dingen die ik haar aanraadde of niet heeft willen of niet heeft kunnen doen. Ik kan haar zelfs moeielijk schrijven wegens als zij in de Bagijnestraat blijft wonen ik primo weet mijn brief geopend wordt<c type="kk">/</c> waarschijnlijk door haar broer of haar moeder<c type="kk">/</c> en ten tweede zoolang zij daar woont ik er ook niet mee <hi rend="italics">wil</hi> te maken hebben<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">zelfs niet met haar</hi>.–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Enfin misschien hoor ik iets nog<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zal er sombere gedachten door hebben als ik niets naders verneem. Ik had gehoopt berigt te krijgen van een ander adres dan de Bagijnestr. en dat zij met haar moeder een zaakje om goed te wasschen en te strijken zouden begonnen zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">O Theo als zij geen familie had gehad zou ze zich zooveel beter gehouden hebben. Vrouwen zooals zij zijn wel degelijk slecht maar primo oneindig<c type="kk">/</c> zegge oneindig deerniswaardiger dan slecht<c type="kk">/</c> en ten tweede hebben ze een zekeren hartstogt<c type="kk">/</c> zekere warmte die iets zóó erg menschelijks heeft dat de braven er wel eens een lesje aan konden nemen en ik voor mij het woord van Jezus gevoel die zeide tot de oppervlakkig beschaafden<c type="kk">/</c> de fatsoenlijke lui van Zijn tijd<c type="kk">/</c> “de hoeren gaan <hi rend="italics">U</hi> VÓÓR”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Vrouwen zoo als zij<c type="kk">/</c> ze kunnen fataal slecht zijn (ik spreek hier niet eens van de Nana’s<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> volbloedig en wellustig<c type="kk">/</c> doch van de meer zenuwachtige<c type="kk">/</c> denkende temperamenten onder hen)<c type="kk">/</c> vrouwen zooals zij<c type="kk">/</c> ten volle regtvaardigen ze ’t woord van Proudhon<c type="kk">/</c> la femme est la désolation du juste<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – om wat wij “la raison” noemen geven ze niet en handelen regtlijnig en schuldig er tegen in, ik weet dat<c type="kk">/</c> maar zij hebben aan den anderen kant toch dat echt menschelijke dat maakt men niet zonder hen mag of kan en er van voelt er goeds in hen zit en iets almagtig goeds zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> al kan men het niet defineeren anders dan als een “je ne sais quoi qui fait qu’on les aime après<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> tout”<c type="kp">_</c>– Gavarni was serieus toen hij zei<c type="kk">/</c> avec chacune que j’ai quittée j’ai senti quelque chose se mourir en moi<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> En het mooiste woord en het <hi>beste</hi> dat ik ken betreffende de vrouwen kwestie is dat wat gij ook kent<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">o femme que </hi><hi><hi rend="italics">j’aurais</hi></hi><hi rend="italics"> aimée</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> en men zou daarmee de eeuwigheid in willen gaan<c type="kk">/</c> willende er niets verder meer dan dat van weten.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik weet dat er vrouwen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> absurd genoeg (zij toch doen er nog meer kwaad aan dan de mannen)<c type="kk">/</c> die geheel en al door eerzucht enz<c type="kp">_</c> worden bestuurd – Lady Macbeth is de type er van<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> – die vrouwen zijn fataal en ondanks hare charme moet men ze mijden of men wordt een schurk en staat in korten tijd voor ontzettend kwaad dat men bedreven heeft en nooit weer goed kan maken – doch zooiets was in haar met wie ik was niet<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ze ijdel was<c type="kk">/</c> even als we allen het zijn bij tijden. arm<c type="kk">/</c> arm<c type="kk">/</c> arm schepsel is het eenige wat ik voelde in ’t begin en ik nog voel in ’t eind<c type="kp">_</c> Slecht?– que soit<c type="kk">/</c> doch wie in onzen tijd is goed? Wie voelt zich zoo rein dat hij voor regter wil spelen<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat zij verre.– Delacroix zou<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> haar hebben begrepen en Gods <hi rend="italics">misericorde</hi><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> zal haar, denk ik soms, toch nog veel meer begrijpen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Zooals ik U schreef<c type="kk">/</c> het kleine mannetje hield erg veel van mij en toen ik al in den wagon zat<c type="kk">/</c> had ik hem <supplied>no</supplied>g op mijn schoot. en zoo zijn we van elkaar gegaan<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof van weerskanten met onuitsprekelijken weemoed maar meer ook niet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik verklaar U broer<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben niet goed op de manier van de domines<c type="kk">/</c> ik vind ook wel hoeren<c type="kk">/</c> om nu met ronde woorden te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> slecht<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik voel toch iets menschelijks in hen dat maakt ik niet de minste scrupule heb met hen te verkeeren<c type="kk">/</c> ik zie niets bijzonders kwaads aan hen<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb niet het allerminste berouw over kennis die ik met hen heb of gehad heb. Als onze maatschappij eene reine en geregelde was<c type="kk">/</c> o ja dan waren zij verleidsters nu – menigmaal zijn zij m<c type="kp">_</c>i<c type="kp">_</c> meer als soeurs de charité<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> te beschouwen dan als iets anders.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">En <hi rend="italics">nu</hi><c type="kk">/</c> even als in andere periodes van ondergang eener beschaving<c type="kk">/</c> zijn door de corruptie der maatschappij de verhoudingen van goed &amp; kwaad veel malen omgekeerd en komt men alweer raisonable teregt op het oude woord “eersten zullen de laatsten zijn en laatsten zullen de eersten zijn”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik ben zooals gij op Pere Lachaise geweest<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er graven gezien van mannen voor wie ik een onbeschrijfelijk respect heb<c type="kk">/</c> hetzelfde respect voelde ik bij ’t nederige grafzerkje van de maîtresse van Béranger dat ik expres opzocht (als ’k me wel herinner is het in een hoekje achter ’t zijne)<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en ik dacht daar nog aan de maitresse van Corot ook vooral.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Stille muzen waren zulke vrouwen en de emotie van die zachtmoedige meesters<c type="kk">/</c> het intieme<c type="kk">/</c> het penetrante van hun poezij<c type="kk">/</c> ik voel er steeds<c type="kk">/</c> altijd<c type="kk">/</c> overal den invloed van een vrouwelijk element in. Ik spreek een beetje serieus in dezen brief<c type="kk">/</c> niet wegens ik Pa’s gevoelens en zienswijs b.v. verkeerd vind in alles – verre van daar – gij zult b.v. in veel dingen wel doen met Pa’s raad te volgen – wij spraken over Pa<c type="kk">/</c> weet ge wel<c type="kk">/</c> bij Uw bezoek en op ’t moment van Uw heengaan – maar iets wat ik toen onbestemd voelde kan ik nu in duidelijker woorden zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi>als</hi> ge met Pa spreekt<c type="kk">/</c> denk dan tevens b.v. aan <hi rend="italics">Corot</hi><c type="kk">/</c> gij zult dan van zelf vermijden sommige uitersten waarin Pa veel te veel vervalt<c type="kk">/</c> en op die conditie van minder hoekigheid is Pa’s raad meestal goed<c type="kk">/</c> houd ik ’t er voor<c type="kk">/</c> en heb ik zelf menigmaal naar geluisterd. Maar ik wijs er eens op dat Pa en meer anderen <hi>niet weten</hi> dat er behalve hun regt leven – want Pa’s leven is regt – er andere regte levens zijn<c type="kk">/</c> meer in een zachter geest<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t karakter Corot<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Beranger zal ik maar zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij en ik ook voelen in elk geval dat veel meer. Omdat Pa en anderen DAT <hi>niet</hi> WE<supplied>TE</supplied>N<c type="kk">/</c> vergissen zij zich menigmaal en fataal in beoordeeling van zekere zaken.– Vergissingen in het genre van dat b.v. C.M<c type="kp">_</c> zeker zich er van houdt dat de Groux een slecht mensch was<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen<c type="kk">/</c> hoe zeker hij er zich van houde<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel hij mis heeft.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Ik zal U nu nog iets zeggen om U duidelijk te maken dat ik niet in ’t abstracte spreek doch over dingen die vastigheid en corps hebben. Wilt ge een voorbeeld van iemand die oorspronkelijk het gewone goede<c type="kk">/</c> Hollandsche karakter en gevoel had en sedert dat gevoel toch heeft gewijzigd<c type="kk">/</c> toch nog zich bezonnen en denk ik nog meer wijzigen zal. Dan noem ik als voorbeeld Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> die nu reeds veel zachter en humaner is dan ik hem eerst leerde kennen en m.i<c type="kp">_</c> veel verbeterd is<c type="kk">/</c> al was hij vroeger reeds goed. ofschoon<c type="kk">/</c> vrees ik<c type="kk">/</c> het niet door iedereen zoo beschouwd wordt en hij er wel eens strijd over reeds gehad heeft. Hij was vroeger ook wel degelijk goed maar toch hij is ontevreden geworden met <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> en is nu dieper en humaner dan toen<c type="kp">_</c>– Hij heeft het er niet makkelijker door – vroeger had hij veel minder strijd – dat weet ik zeker – want ik heb hem in der tijd nog genoemd spottenderwijs “<hi rend="italics">het gerust geweten</hi>” en hem daarover geplaagd<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik nu volstrekt niet meer doe omdat ik zie er een revolutie in hem is geweest. Hij is <hi rend="italics">een beetje</hi> minder elegant en hij is veel minder oppervlakkig als mensch<c type="kk">/</c> en een zekere geniale kiem heeft haar ontwikkeling begonnen en de klip van “verdorren” heeft hij omgezeild<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">In zake van menschen die het goede opregt zoeken vind ik waar wat Hugo zegt<c type="kk">/</c> “<hi rend="italics">il y a le rayon NOIR et</hi> <hi rend="italics">il y a le rayon BLANC</hi>”.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Pa mijns inziens heeft meer le rayon noir en Corot heeft meer le rayon blanc doch beiden hebben zij un rayon d’en haut.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Zoo noem ik niemand slecht van wie we bespraken<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">quand même</hi> NIET<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zeg dat le rayon noir een fatalen kant heeft en wegens ik sedert wel eens dacht aan wat gij mij zeidet op ’t perron van ’t station bij Uw heengaan<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik U nu tot explicatie nog van ’t geen waar ik toen zoo dadelijk geen woorden voor kon vinden<c type="kk">/</c> “ik weet dat Pa Pa is<c type="kk">/</c> maar er is behalve dat nog iets<c type="kk">/</c> n<c type="kp">_</c>l. wat we dan `le rayon blanc´ zullen noemen”<c type="kp">_</c> En daar vind ik meer positiefs<c type="kk">/</c> meer waarachtigen vrede in en heb ik veel meer mijn attentie op gevestigd. Betreffende Millet<c type="kk">/</c> hij is nog boven al de anderen uit de man die le rayon blanc had. Millet heeft een evangelie en ik vraag U of er niet een onderscheid is tusschen een teekening van hem en een mooie preek. De preek wordt er zwart bij<c type="kk">/</c> is ’t effet produit der vergelijking<c type="kk">/</c> al is ze (de preek nl.) mooi op zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> gesteld dat ze het is. Ik weet dat gij ook veel strijd hebt in deze dagen<c type="kk">/</c> al weet ik niet precies hoe of wat<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-24"/> En in elk geval is het uit sympathie dat ik U precies zeg hoe ik over een paar dingen denk<c type="kk">/</c> wegens ik ook veel strijd gehad heb en nog heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">En U wensch ik toe hoe langer hoe meer van le rayon <hi>blanc</hi> hoor! Dank voor ’t gezondene en een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve just received your letter and thank you right heartily for it. And want to write to you again straightaway to tell you a few things about my experiences. First of all, I’ve had a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> in West-Terschelling and he’s hard at work there, having first spent some time here in Drenthe, in Rolde near Assen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I hope to be able to visit him there myself this winter and to make a few more studies; the trip there, as far as I can make out, there and back, being three guilders, unless the crossing to T. should prove difficult. But it would be worth it to be with a painter again, and will break the isolation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m longing to get your next letter, which I hope won’t get stuck in the pen. Don’t forget to tell me the outcome regarding <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>, whether you’ve told him that I was here and whether your letter has also gone unanswered. If that’s the case I’ll certainly go and see C.M., not now of course but later, and ask him to explain why he didn’t reply. I shan’t write, but I’m unshakeably determined that I shall <hi>not</hi> put up with his not answering, particularly not answering <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, and since this is part of it, also his not answering <hi rend="italics">me</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’ve NEVER SAID that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">he</rs> <hi rend="italics">must</hi> do something, nor do I now. I count what he did or might do as a favour, and as such something for which I’ve always thanked him, and for my part have also given him studies, certainly 50 altogether,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> with the right to swap them later. And all this being so, I certainly don’t have to tolerate any insults, and it <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a gross insult that I haven’t even had word that he received the last packet of studies. Not a syllable. And should <hi rend="italics">your</hi> letter remain unanswered on top of this, it would be <hi rend="italics">cowardice</hi> to leave it at that, and I <hi>must</hi> and shall demand an explanation. Which, as said, I shall most certainly do, and in a personal visit, even though some time may elapse. If he isn’t willing to talk to me then, that would by no means finish the matter, because my mind is made up that I <hi rend="italics">shall</hi> have satisfaction about it. Should he give it me, well and good, but should he refuse to give it me (I haven’t used a single impolite term to him, I’ve only written in a very cool tone), should, I say, he refuse to give it me, <hi rend="italics">I </hi><hi>may</hi> say an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and insult him roundly back, which I would do in cold blood.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Make no mistake, brother, understand me in this once and for all, however desirable it might be to get financial help — that is far from being No. 1. No. 1 is that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">he</rs> goes too far in losing sight of the rights that I have as a human being, even were I a stranger to him (I never speak of our relationship, nor rely on it), not to be treated as a bad lot, not to be condemned or accused of this or that without being able to speak up for myself. I have the <hi>right</hi>, <hi rend="italics">every right</hi> to <hi>demand</hi> an answer and to consider silence a very gross insult.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I must speak frankly about this because I had hoped until now that it would come right of its own accord, and that I would receive word in reply.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But there’s a limit to this silent forbearance and, as I say, beyond that limit it would be cowardly and unmanly of me not to protest four-square against it. So I ask you kindly, simply to tell me what has happened as regards an answer to your letter; then I’ll know for myself what I must do, then I won’t say another word about it, but even if more than a year were to pass I’ll still find deep inside me, as untarnished, clear and bright as I have at this moment, this same feeling that I <hi rend="italics">must have</hi> an explanation, and not rest until I’ve settled matters with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">him</rs> one way or another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I think that you’ll appreciate my feelings, and would do so all the more if you knew precisely what occurred between <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">him</rs> and me in years past. When I was very dubious about the plan to study, whether the promise to bring that about was straightforward and well-considered — I thought then that <hi rend="italics">they</hi> made the plan too hastily and <hi rend="italics">I </hi>went along with it too hastily, and in my view it remains an excellent thing that it stopped when it did, which I deliberately brought about myself, contriving it such that the shame of giving up fell on me and not on anyone else. You know that I, who have learned other languages, could have managed to master that miserable little bit of Latin &amp;c., but I said I couldn’t cope. This was an excuse, because I didn’t want to tell my protectors that I regard the whole University (or at least the Theology Faculty) as an unspeakable mess, a breeding-ground for Pharisees.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I tried to prove that I didn’t lack courage by going to the Borinage, where life was most certainly much harder for me than it would have been had I become a student.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I thought that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>, for example, might have understood me better, and have all the more reason to believe him insensitive when I think how he has treated me with a degree of contempt ever since. <hi>Then</hi> and <hi>now</hi> I’ve kept to myself a good many things that I could have said, and if I ever tackle him about them he’ll have to feel a thing or two in his conscience, whatever he may say; how I, neither in the past nor now, have ever committed any base acts against him, so there’s no conceivable reason for this insult of his failure to reply, all the more so since it would have been better if, from the moment when I went to The Hague, all that was in the past had been forgiven and forgotten and we’d resolved to maintain cordial relations, which I discussed with His Hon. at the time. But I do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> say, brother, peace at <hi rend="italics">any price</hi>, and I would rather have an unpleasant explanation than weakly let things go when doing so would be weak, and it would be now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Be assured, though, that I shall NOT mention you, even though <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">his</rs> insult to you, if he doesn’t set it right (it occurs to me that he’s beginning to use something of the same policy towards you) is what’s making me resolved to have it out with His Hon., and I’ve decided to say a great many things to him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I promise you that, I’ll make it appear as if I was talking about myself alone, as if I knew nothing about you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I have the very deepest contempt for this mysterious, sphinx-like silence &amp;c., and I tell you here and now that I think all sorts of things about it, except for something that’s straightforward and honest or true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">It may have something to do with the general politics of the day, I know that, but as you know I don’t agree with the general politics of the day because I regard it as base and bearing all the traits of a decline that will end in a new periwig age.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">One could weep about what’s presently being spoiled in all sorts of areas, things to which our predecessors devoted their labours, honestly, are now being mean-spiritedly neglected and abandoned. The times we live in are perhaps outwardly a little more respectable than earlier days, but too much nobleness is being lost for us to be able to expect the same great things of the future that there have been in the past. Well, everyone has to make up his own mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now to change the subject — but it was necessary to deal with these matters, although I take not the slightest pleasure in writing about them — namely my experiences here. The more I walk around the area, the more I’m coming to like Hoogeveen itself, and I don’t doubt that this will remain so. If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> falls through, which I fear, this doesn’t alter the fact that in the long run it will work out cheaper here than in The Hague. But because of C.M. falling through I’ll have to scrimp and save for a while before I can carry out my plans. And perhaps we’ll lose absolutely nothing by it after all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The fact is that I do need money and a stock of paint and various things before I can expect any results from the trip through the south-east corner of Drenthe.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">But in six months or so I hope I’ll have saved enough, and in the meantime I’ll still be able to do things here. So for the present I won’t go further away for good, but will stay and work in this area. Will try to save some money for two trips, one through the south-east corner, one across the heath between here and Assen. And I hope to combine the latter trip to the north with a visit to friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> and spend some time in his lodgings on Terschelling, known as ’t Scheepje.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> It would be too reckless to go on these two trips if one were to undertake them without supplies and without being prepared for the circumstances. But with patience they’re possible, for I see well enough that I have fewer expenses here than in The Hague. And before I begin on that I’d like to pay <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> his money back, although it may be that later I’ll perhaps borrow something from him again after I’ve seen him, and if I know for sure that I can make something specific with it.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">At first I had some trouble here with models on the heath, where people laughed about it and I was ridiculed and couldn’t finish figure studies that I’d started because of the unwillingness of the models, although I had paid them well, at least for these parts. I stood firm, though, and concentrated on a single family in that same place, where I can now get an old woman, a girl and a man, and have hopes that they’ll remain willing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I have a few studies of the heath, which I’ll send you when they’re thoroughly dry,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and have also begun watercolours.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> And I’ve also started pen drawings again,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> specifically with a view to painting, because one can go into such details with the pen as painted studies cannot do, and one does well to make two studies, one entirely drawn for the way things are put together, and one painted for the colour. If this can be done, that is, and the occasion permits, this is a way of working up the painted study later. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">The heath is rich, and there are marshy meadows that often remind me of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1332">T. Rousseau</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Well, I can tell you that the open air and the life here are really doing me good. Oh if only the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> could have had it — I think of her with such profound sadness — although my common sense tells me quite clearly that it’s impossible now in the circumstances. I’m worried about her because I heard nothing from her, and from that assume that she has been either unwilling or unable to do things that I advised her to do. I can’t even write to her easily, because if she continues to live in Bagijnestraat I know first that my letter will be opened, probably by her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_469">brother</rs> or her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs>, and secondly as long as she lives there I don’t <hi rend="italics">want</hi> to have anything to do with it anyway, <hi rend="italics">not even with her</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Still, perhaps I’ll hear something yet, but my thoughts will be gloomy if I hear nothing further. I had hoped to get a message from an address other than Bagijnestraat, and that she and her mother had started a little business doing laundry and ironing.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Oh Theo, if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">she</rs> hadn’t had any family she’d have behaved herself so much better. Women like her really are bad, but first infinitely, I say infinitely, more pitiable than bad, and secondly they have a certain passion, certain warmth which has something so very human that the respectable could learn a lesson, and I for my part understand the words of Jesus, who said to the superficially civilized, the respectable people of His time, ‘the harlots go BEFORE<hi rend="italics"> you</hi>’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Women like her, they can be fatally bad (I’m not even speaking here of the Nanas,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> full-blooded and sensual, but of the more nervous, rational temperaments among them), women like her, they fully justify <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_722">Proudhon</rs>’s words, woman is the desolation of the righteous man<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> — they don’t care about what we call ‘reason’ and go against it directly and culpably, I know that, but on the other hand they still have that genuine humanity, which means that one may not and cannot do without them, and one feels that there’s good in them and even something almighty good, even though one can’t define it other than ‘I don’t know what makes one love them after all’. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> was serious when he said: I felt something die within me with every woman that I have left.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And the most beautiful saying and the <hi>best</hi> that I know on the question of women is the one that you know too, <hi rend="italics">oh woman whom </hi><hi><hi rend="italics">I could have</hi></hi><hi rend="italics"> loved</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> and one would willingly go into the infinite with that, wanting nothing more than that knowledge.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I know that there are women, absurdly enough (they indeed do even more harm to it than the men), who are wholly governed by ambition etc. — Lady Macbeth is this type<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> — these women are fatal, and one must avoid them despite their charm or one becomes a villain and very soon finds oneself faced with terrible evil that one has done and can never put right again — but there was nothing like this in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> with whom I was, although she was vain, just as we all are at times. Poor, poor, poor creature is all that I felt at the start and I still feel in the end. Bad? So be it, but who in our times is good? Who feels so pure that he wants to play judge? God forbid. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> would have understood her, I dare say, and God’s <hi rend="italics">misericorde</hi><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> will even, I sometimes think, understand her much more, surely.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">As I wrote to you, the little lad loved me very much, and when I was already sitting in the wagon I still had him on my lap. And so we parted, I believe with inexpressible melancholy on both sides, but nothing more.
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I tell you brother, I’m not good in the way of the ministers, I too, not to mince words, think whores are bad, but I nevertheless feel something human in them that means I don’t have the slightest scruple about consorting with them, I see nothing particularly evil in them, I haven’t the slightest remorse about the acquaintance I have or have had with them. If our society were a pure and ordered one, oh yes, then they were temptresses, now — many times it seems to me they should be regarded more as sisters of charity<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> than anything else.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And <hi rend="italics">now</hi>, as in other periods of the fall of a civilization, the relationships of good and evil are often reversed because of the corruption of society, and one reasonably comes back to the old saying: ‘the first shall be last and the last shall be first’.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Like you, I’ve been to Père Lachaise, I’ve seen the graves of men for whom I have indescribable respect; I felt the same respect by the humble little tombstone of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">Béranger</rs>’s mistress, which I visited expressly (if I remember rightly it’s in a little corner behind his),<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and I also thought there about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>’s mistress in particular.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Such women were silent muses, and I forever, always and everywhere feel the influence of a feminine element in the emotion of these gentle masters, the intimacy, the penetration of their poetry. I’m speaking a bit seriously in this letter, not because I think that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s feelings and views, for instance, are wrong in everything — far from it — you would, for example, do well to follow Pa’s advice in many things — we talked about Pa, you will recall, during your visit and at the moment you left — but something that I felt vaguely then I can now express more clearly, <hi>when</hi> you speak with Pa, think at the same time of <hi rend="italics">Corot</hi>, say, you’ll then automatically avoid some of the extremes into which Pa lapses much too much, and as I see it, on this condition that there’s less stiffness, Pa’s advice is usually good, and I have myself paid heed to it many times. But I point out that Pa and others <hi>do not know</hi> that besides their upright lives — for Pa’s life is upright — there are other upright lives, more in a milder spirit, in the character of Corot,<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Béranger, shall I say. You and I also feel that much more in any event. Because Pa and others DO <hi>not</hi> KNOW THAT, they are frequently and fatally mistaken when judging certain matters. Mistakes along the lines, for example, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> certainly believes that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> was a bad man, in which, however sure he is in his belief, he is nonetheless mistaken.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I’ll now tell you something else to make it clear to you that I’m not speaking in the abstract but about things that have solidity and substance. If you want an example of someone who originally had the ordinary, good Dutch character and feelings and yet has changed those feelings since, yet has reconsidered, and I think will change even more. Then as an example I give you <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, who is now already much gentler and more humane than when I first got to know him, and in my view is much improved, even though he was already good before. Although, I fear, not everyone sees it this way, and he has already had some conflict about it. In the past he really was good, but yet he became dissatisfied with <hi rend="italics">that</hi> and is now deeper and more humane than he was then. It doesn’t make things easier for him — he used to have far less conflict — I know that for certain — because at the time I jokingly called him ‘<hi rend="italics">the</hi> <hi rend="italics">clear</hi> <hi rend="italics">conscience</hi>’ and teased him about it, which I definitely no longer do, because I see that there has been a revolution in him. He’s <hi rend="italics">a little</hi> less elegant and he’s much less superficial as a person, and a certain germ of genius has begun its development, and he has steered clear of the pitfall of ‘withering’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">In respect of people who genuinely seek good, I think what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Hugo</rs> says is true, ‘<hi rend="italics">there is the BLACK ray and there is the WHITE ray</hi>’.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">In my view <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> has more the black ray and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> has more the white ray, but both of them have a ray from on high.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">So I don’t call anyone whom we’ve discussed bad, NO, <hi rend="italics">for all that</hi>, but I do say that the black ray has a fatal side, and because I’ve since thought about what you said to me on the station platform when you left, I tell you now in explanation of what I couldn’t readily find words for then, ‘I know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> is Pa, but there’s something else besides that, namely what we’ll call “the white ray”’. And I find more that’s positive, more true peace in that, and I’ve fixed my attention on it much more. As to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, he’s the man above all others who had the white ray. Millet has a gospel, and I ask you whether there’s a distinction between a drawing by him and a good sermon. It makes the sermon black, it’s the outcome of the comparison, even if it (the sermon, that is) is fine in itself, assuming that it is. I know that you too have a lot of strife at the moment, although I don’t know precisely the ins and outs of it.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> And in any event it’s out of sympathy that I tell you precisely what I think about a few things, because I’ve also had and still have a lot of strife.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">And I wish you more and more of the <hi>white</hi> ray, you hear! Thanks for what you sent, and a handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let389.xml">letter 389</ref> of 24 September 1883 Van Gogh says he is sending three paintings. In the present letter they are finished but not yet dry enough to be sent, so that this letter must have been written earlier. This means that the letter with his allowance for which Van Gogh thanks Theo here (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>) must have been the third in September. Because he also wanted to tell Theo ‘straightaway’ about his latest experiences <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, we have dated the letter on or about Friday, 21 September 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On the last sheet of the letter Van Gogh wrote the beginnings of a paint order, which he never finished. See RM13.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Drawings on commission with Uncle Cor <ref target="let378.xml">(378)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The following shipments sent by Van Gogh to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">uncle</rs> are known from the correspondence: 12 pen-and-ink drawings (sent in March 1882, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let210.xml">see letters 210</ref> ff.); 7 townscapes of The Hague (sent in May 1882; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let214.xml">see letters 214</ref> ff. and 235); 2 sketches of sand diggers in the dunes (sent in June 1883; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let350.xml">see letter 350</ref>); and ‘more than 20’ studies (sent in September 1883; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let380.xml">see letter 380</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Expression, referring to Exod. 21:24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘and when I think that I’ (‘I think’ conflated from l. 98).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The lodging-house <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">’t Scheepje</hi> was in De Lange Buren, also known as Lange Buurtstraat (now Commandeurstraat 31) in West-Terschelling. See Suzanne Boer, ‘Anthon van Rappard op Terschelling’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Schylge myn lântse</hi> 13 (1992), NS, pp. 86-88.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>We do not know exactly which painted ‘studies’ of the moor are referred to here. It is possible that <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cottages</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2446">F 17 / JH 395</rs>) was one of them, since Van Gogh sent Theo three paintings a few days later and this may have been among them (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let389.xml">letter 389</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>It is not possible to determine exactly which watercolours are meant here. Six watercolours from this period are known: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peat bog </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_528">F 1094 / JH 398</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape with a stack of peat and farmhouses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_529">F 1099 / JH 399</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Heath with a wheelbarrow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_530">F 1100 / JH 400</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape with a farmhouse</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_531">F 1101 / JH 401</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Farmhouse</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_532">F 1102 / JH 402</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Group of farmhouses</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_533">F 1103 / JH 403</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
  
<p>It is not possible to determine exactly which pen-and-ink drawings are meant here. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Farmhouse at night </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3039">F 1097 / JH 418</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape in Drenthe</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_535">F 1104 / JH 424</rs>) are both candidates.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Sien’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> was registered as living at Korte Bagijnestraat 33 in The Hague.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 21:31.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
  
<p>Nana, the eponymous protagonist of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs>’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_247">Nana</ref></hi> of 1880, is the type that Van Gogh describes as ‘full-blooded and sensual’ (words, incidentally, that he added later): this <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">femme fatale</hi> seduces men of the highest rank, gets them wholly in her power and ruins them.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_722">Pierre Joseph Proudhon</rs> wrote this in his eleventh study <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_356">De la justice dans la Révolution et dans l’église</ref></hi>, titled ‘Amour et mariage’ (Love and marriage). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Oeuvres complètes</hi>. Ed. C. Bouglé et H. Moysset. Paris 1935, p. 207. Van Gogh will have known the quote through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>, who cited it both in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_12">La femme</ref></hi> and in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi>; in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La femme</hi> with an attribution to Proudhon (Michelet 1863, p. 196; Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, p. 268).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Malgré’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>This saying is taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_224">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</ref></hi>. It occurs in a paragraph dealing with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>’s many amorous adventures: ‘However, he could not always limit himself to these delightful preludes, he was sometimes compelled to go further, and he once made the remark that attachments are sometimes a nuisance. But he was so much in the habit of being enveloped in them, of living within their caress and their pleasant agitation, they had become so necessary to the tenor of his life, that it seemed to him, when one of them was no longer there, “that something was dying within him.” Straightaway, he made haste to replace it’. (Toutefois, il ne pouvait pas se tenir toujours à ces jolis préludes, on le forçait souvent à aller plus loin, et il lui arrivait de faire la remarque que les affections sont parfois gênantes. Mais il avait tellement l’habitude d’en être enveloppé, de vivre dans leur caresse et leur aimable agitation, elles étaient devenues si nécessaires au sentiment de sa vie, qu’il lui semblait, quand l’une venait à lui manquer, “que quelque chose se mourait en lui.” Vite, il se dépêchait de la remplacer). See Goncourt 1873, pp. 221-222.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Taken from the last sentence of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi> (p. 418). In his ‘Notes et éclaircissements’ Michelet says that the quotation is by Etienne de Sénancour (p. 445).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh bases this on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s ‘Every woman, at every age, if she loves and if she is kind, gives a man the moment of the infinite. More than the infinite of the moment’ (Toute, à tout âge, si elle aime et si elle est bonne, donne à l’homme le moment de l’infini. Plus que l’infini du moment), likewise from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi>, and quoted previously in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let193.xml">letter 193</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>In <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_357">Macbeth</ref></hi> (c. 1606-1607) the unscrupulous Lady Macbeth persuades her husband to murder King Duncan of Scotland so that he will become king. At the end of the play she loses her reason and roams through the palace in a frenzy, in the belief that her hands are covered in blood.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>God’s mercy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Since <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">Béranger</rs> is mentioned after this, it is probably an allusion to the poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_126">Les deux soeurs de charité</ref>’ (The two sisters of charity) by Pierre Jean de Béranger, from which Van Gogh quoted in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let110.xml">letter 110</ref>. The theme of the poem, in which both a nun and a woman who has given physical love to many men gain admittance to the hereafter, is that there is more than one form of charity.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Saying, biblical; see Matt. 19:30; Mark 10:31 and Luke 13:30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>We know from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let093.xml">letter 93</ref> that in any event Van Gogh visited the famous Père Lachaise cemetery in Paris in the summer or autumn of 1875. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_530">Béranger</rs>’s mistress, whom he called Lisette in his verse, was Nicole Françoise Judith Frère. Their graves are indeed close together in the 28th division of the cemetery, under nos. 252 and 657. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dictionnaire de biographie française</hi>. Paris 1951, vol. 5, col. 1215.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>As a young man <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>, who never married, had various relationships about which little is known. The woman most often mentioned in this context is Anna Saint-Laurent. See Germain Bazin, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Corot</hi>. 2nd ed. Paris 1951, pp. 17-18. Cf. also Dumesnil 1875, p. 14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> was known as a kind, generous person; in the 1860s, for instance, he was among the friends who were instrumental in buying a house for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, who was almost blind. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml">letter 694</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>See for this reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let211.xml">letter 211</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_278">Quatre-vingt-treize</ref></hi>, part 3, book 2, chapter 7: ‘The friendship was between the two men, but the hatred was between the two principles; it was like a soul cut in two, and shared; Gauvain, in fact, had received half of Cimourdain’s soul, but the gentle half. It seemed that Gauvain had had the white side and that Cimourdain had kept for himself what one might call the black side.’ (L’amitié était entre les deux hommes, mais la haine était entre les deux principes; c’était comme une âme coupée en deux, et partagée; Gauvain, en effet, avait reçu une moitié de l’âme de Cimourdain, mais la moitié douce. Il semblait que Gauvain avait eu le rayon blanc, et que Cimourdain avait gardé pour lui ce qu’on pourrait appeler le rayon noir). See Hugo 1965, p. 228. Van Gogh repeats the expression in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let400.xml">letters 400</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let401.xml">401</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let403.xml">403</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let415.xml">415</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>See for this expression:<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let143.xml#n-5">letter 143, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Theo was having problems in – or because of – his relationship with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs>, but no details of these difficulties are known. His <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> were aware of this; from a few passages in the family correspondence it is clear that – in contrast to their attitude to the relationship between Vincent and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> – they supported Theo. In a letter of 2 August 1883 they sent their regards to Marie (FR 2244) and on 1 October 1883 Mrs van Gogh wrote to Theo: ‘just leave things to time if you encounter difficulties. We are looking forward to hearing from you when you write how things are with Marie. Be sensible, dear Theo, and may you be as happy as our hearts wish for you’ (FR b2245). The problems obviously continued for some time, since on 30 November she wrote: ‘So Maria’s Papa still doesn’t seem to be calm. With a view to what might happen it is cautious of you not to rush. How I should like to meet your acquaintances some time’, and: ‘Goodbye, dear Theo, give Marie our regards when you write to her’ (FR b2247).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    