<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, Friday, 28 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let391"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b352 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>391</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>329</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>394</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-09-28">Friday, 28 September 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Hoogeveen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0352 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0352 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000451_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0352 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000452_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000452_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0352 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000452_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000452_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Van morgen was het wederom beter weer &amp; ben ik uitgegaan om toch te schilderen<c type="kp">_</c> Alleen het was niet mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> 4 of 5 kleuren ontbraken me<c type="kk">/</c> en ik ben toch zoo beroerd weer terug gekomen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb spijt zonder voorraad mij zoo ver gewaagd te hebben – ik weet door ervaring toch vooruit hoe het worden kan als men zoo’n tocht onderneemt zonder te weten dat men ook antwoord zal krijgen &amp; er geluisterd zal worden naar billijke<c type="kk">/</c> gemotiveerde verzoeken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gij weet zelf eenigzins hoe het mij ging in de Borinage<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Welnu ik ben er al te zeer bezorgd over dat het mij hier weer precies eender zou gaan en ik moet eenige zekerheid hebben voor en aleer ik me verder waag en anders<c type="kk">/</c> welnu dan ga ik terug (och – ge weet<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg dit maar want ik wil juist blijven)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik heb er nu eenmaal geen pleizier in<c type="kk">/</c> ik zag er toen al geen heil in en nu nog veel minder<c type="kk">/</c> om tot een punt van uitputting te komen dat men zelfs het dak boven zijn hoofd missen moet en als een vagebond tot in ’t oneindige maar voortloopen en voortloopen zonder ergens ’t zij rust<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij voedsel<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij deksel<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> te vinden<c type="kk">/</c> bovendien zonder iets van werk met mogelijkheid te kunnen uitrigten<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Zie zelf op de kaart hoe ver het is van Mons tot <hi rend="italics">Courrières</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dien weg deed ik te voet van af Valenciennes heen<c type="kk">/</c> &amp; terug tot Mons met nog geen 2 francs in mijn zak – drie dagen &amp; drie nachten in ’t begin van Maart<c type="kk">/</c> in regen en wind zonder dak boven mijn hoofd.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het zijn die antecedenten broer, waartoe ik nu nog niet ben gekomen natuurlijk – doch komen zoude indien ik zonder zekerheid me ver waagde – indien ik niet raisonable orde stelde op mijn zaken – indien<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> ik me ver ’t land in waagde zonder ruggesteun.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Voor ik begin – het is geen wantrouwen<c type="kk">/</c> geen verdenking van U doch eenvoudig een maatregel van gezond verstand – voor ik begin – zeg ik – (en vrage het wegens zeer kort geleden gij mij schreeft als zijnde zelf bezorgd wegens ge vreesdet onraad en calamiteiten in ’t verschiet konden wezen) kunt gij mij verzekeren dat het gewone niet ontbreken zal?– 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>En tevens – al zij dat voldoende en meer niet noodig onder zekere voorwaarde – de voorwaarde waarop alleen het gewone voldoende is<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal ze u zeggen – goed geéquipeerd te beginnen<c type="kk">/</c> met voorraad van een &amp; ander te vertrekken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik die graag het initiatief om te handelen op me neem wegens er een bewijs van opregtheid<c type="kk">/</c> een daadzaak bewijzende dat men niet met woorden doch met daden te werk gaat<c type="kk">/</c> somwijlen noodig is – ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik ging tot hier in Drenthe zelf<c type="kk">/</c> deins terug niet voor den eersten doch wel voor de volgende stappen te doen zonder zeker te zijn van mijn ruggesteun. De <hi>ondervinding</hi> dwingt mij tot bepaalde onwankelbare afspraak – indien gij zelf ondervonden hadt wat ik op dien togt in de Borinage heb geleden<c type="kk">/</c> zoudt gij in mijn geval van nu precies ’t zelfde er door geleerd hebben als ik – het welk nu ik zóó duidelijk en klaar gevoel – al de omstandigheden en dingen waar ik mee te maken heb <hi rend="italics">herkennende</hi> als oude bekenden.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">De togten welke ik op het oog heb zijn onmogelijk en gekkenwerk indien ik ze ondername zonder voorraad<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zij zijn hoogst hagchelijk zonder een surplus van contant geld voor onvoorziene omstandigheden.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Kortom men moet ze niet ondernemen tenzij men door &amp; door gevoele dat overal en altijd men zal staan voor lui die iemand staan aan te gapen maar geen hand uit steken om mede te helpen. Men moet zich voorstellen in herbergen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> gewantrouwd te worden – als de eerste de beste arme marskramer (want als zoodanig wordt men beschouwd) – men moet het geld van logies dikwijls – gelijk ik hier zelfs doen moest – <hi rend="italics">vooruit</hi> geven om bij de gratie gods logies te krijgen.– En zoo dus ALLES IS PROZA<c type="kk">/</c> ALLES IS REKENEN wat betreft het plan voor een reis die toch poezij tot doel heeft.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Zoo scherp als dit heb ik het U nog niet gezegd en als ik het nu zóó zeg zoo is het<c type="kk">/</c> IK VERZEKER HET U<c type="kk">/</c> niet in ’t minst omdat ik U wantrouw maar omdat ik nog niet sinds het plan der reis U serieus als nu heb gesproken over de bezwaren en hunne rapporten tot hetgeen gij zoudt disponible hebben of er voor vinden kunnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik moet er nu wel over spreken omdat<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon in voorlaatst schrijven ik U melde dat hier alles mij medegevallen is – ’t welk ook wel degelijk alzoo blijft – ik toch in deze herberg bezwaren ontmoet in zake licht<c type="kk">/</c> ruimte<c type="kk">/</c> geschiktheid om met model te scharrelen – en daarom – al kan ik <hi rend="italics">desnoods</hi> toch wel me schikken en al zal ik dat <hi rend="italics">desnoods</hi> – er aan denk om ondanks ’t saizoen de reis voort te zetten dieper ’t land in<c type="kk">/</c> niet twijfelende of ik zal overal (waar ik heen zal gaan althans) minstens even goede gelegenheid tot werken vinden als hier en zelfs beter ruimte &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> hoop ik.–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het is nu een 14 dagen ik hier ben<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en ik spreek uit ervaring als ik U zeg dat in vele<c type="kk">/</c> ja alle opzigten mijn gereedschap en uitrusting en voorraad te ontoereikend mij blijkt.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Hoogeveen zelf is wel op de kaart<c type="kk">/</c> waar ’t met een roode stip is gemerkt<c type="kk">/</c> doch niet in de werkelijkheid eene stad (er is zelfs geen toren).<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Zoo ik kan niets krijgen van teekengerij zelfs<c type="kp">_</c>– Verder nog het land in zal ik nog meer gegêneerd zijn en moet op alles geprepareerd zijn of, ik herhaal het, het ware gekkenwerk. Nu zoude ik hiermede niet haasten indien niet het zoo vergevorderde saisoen tot den grootsten spoed mij drong. Reken dat de tijd verloopt &amp; vóór ik een woord van U heb er al weer misschien 14 dagen verloopen<c type="kp">_</c> Vóór den eigentlijken winter (<hi rend="italics">en de winter zal er maar al te snel zijn!!</hi> ik weet waarachtig niet hoe ik er kom) wou ik nog zien beter ingekwartierd – nog meer diep in de heide – ergens onder dak te komen. En ook mijn gemoedsstemming – die te somber is en waarvoor ik dringend gevoel behoefte aan grif kunnen doorwerken te hebben<c type="kk">/</c> als zijnde de allerbeste remedie &amp; afleiding – maakt dat ik op betere equipement moet aandringen<c type="kp">_</c> En dat bleef eigentlijk ook precies eender voor ’t geval dat ik hier op de plaats bleef.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik ben in besprek met 2 partijen oude verf die slechts uitwendig wat de tubes betreft is beschadigd<c type="kk">/</c> maar bovendien zouden er penseelen<c type="kk">/</c> schilderdoek<c type="kk">/</c> waterverf en whatman ook noodig wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Indien ik U zeide dit kan uitstel lijden<c type="kk">/</c> zoude ik flaauwhartig spreken want het is eenvoudig noodig het direkt gebeure. Kan dit niet<c type="kk">/</c> zoo kan het niet – maar dan kan ik ook niet voort<c type="kp">_</c> En ik zoude ook nu niet zoo melankoliek zijn geworden indien mijn slecht equipement mij niet te zeer de handen hadde gebonden. Indien in een &amp; ander opzigt ik geruststelling en ’t geen onmisbaar is vinden kan<c type="kk">/</c> zoo geloof ik hier wel op streek te zullen komen. Het land is zeer mooi – ik zag heden eene begrafenis<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> in een schuit die zeer curieus was – een zestal vrouwen in mantels gewikkeld in het vaartuig dat door de mannen werd getrokken door de vaart in de heide – den dominé – met steek &amp; korte broek – net een figuur van Meissonier – volgde aan den overkant<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – o er is van alles<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge moet me niet kwalijk nemen ik zoo schrijf – ik ben wat overhaast gegaan en ik voel nu pas al wat mij mankeert en dat ik wat ondoordacht heb gehandeld – maar hoe kon ik anders. En ik ben zoo ondragelijk melankoliek als het werk me geen afleiding geeft<c type="kk">/</c> dat zult gij wel begrijpen<c type="kk">/</c> en ik <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> werken en vlot werken – MIJ ZELF VERGETEN IN HET WERK<c type="kk">/</c> anders overdonderde het me. Nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik wantrouw U niet in het aller allerminst maar mijn ondervinding verbied mij een togt aan te vangen zonder te weten waarop ik rekenen kan en waarop niet. Spreek dus <hi rend="italics">absoluut</hi> <hi rend="italics">opregt</hi> want mijn besluit hangt er van af en ik zal mij in elk geval schikken naar omstandigheden. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Had ik vooruit geweten het met de vrouw toch op scheiden ware uitgekomen zoo ware ik hoogst waarschijnlijk 1/2 jaar geleden reeds gescheiden – maar ik heb toch<c type="kk">/</c> al doet het me zelfs nu nog schade<c type="kk">/</c> liever ik te lang dan te kort haar trouw gebleven zij<c type="kk">/</c> en voor ik U gesproken had persoonlijk wilde ik niet alleen volgens eigen opinie handelen<c type="kp">_</c> Vergeet niet als ge denkt aan verl. jaar<c type="kk">/</c> dat de reden der kosten minder waren de uitgaven voor ons persoonlijk dan de fatale prijzen van s’Hage. Had ik alles geweten – ik hadde 200 gulden bezuinigd op woning al had ik DEZE HEELE HERBERG MET TUIN ER BIJ – <hi rend="italics">hier</hi> genomen<c type="kk">/</c> en ziedaar uit èèn enkel artikel reeds meer dan mijn tekort. Zoo vooral de vrouw is onschuldig aan mijn tekort en ik zelf in zoover te s’Hage het al niet anders kon – doch had ik ’t geweten<c type="kk">/</c> ik ware verhuisd naar hier reeds veel vroeger<c type="kp">_</c> Dit verzuim – of liever deze onwetendheid – verwijt ik me zelf genoeg<c type="kp">_</c>– Toch verl. jaar is niet weg of niet nutteloos – het is een jaar van hard werk geweest en après tout met kalmte zie ik er op terug<c type="kp">_</c>– En wat er ook zij van momenteel niet zoo de handen vrij hebben als ik wensch – in geen geval heb ik die vrij – zelfs al komt er hulp – want een groot deel herfst zal alsdan reeds gepasseerd zijn – en vòòr den winter maar voor een deel afgedaan die studies die ik gehoopt had kunnen te krijgen – wat er ook zij van momenteele moeielijkheden<c type="kk">/</c> toch het zal hier opklaren met geduld<c type="kp">_</c>– Alleen – ik wou nog wel tusschen nu en Kerstmis een togt ondernemen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Laat ons woekeren met den tijd want tijdverlies kost het allerduurst.– Ik heb te s’Hage meer dan 70 geschilderde studies liggen<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – waren die maar van hier<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou er ook meer aan hebben gehad<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik moet U ronduit zeggen dat ik hier nu dezer dagen spijt heb gehad en zelfs nog heb<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik mijn schuld heb betaald van het geld terwijl ik wel schuldig was doch niemand van wie ik nu laatst betaald heb mij bepaald maande – wel vroeger</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">reeds –</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">en ik het nog had kunnen uitstellen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik weet het niet of men niet eerst voor zich zelf mag zorgen dat men de handen en zijn werkkracht vrij houdt want<c type="kk">/</c> ik herhaal het<c type="kk">/</c> ziedaar dat vóór den winter ik mijn noodige studies niet geschilderd zal kunnen krijgen en wie zal mij daar dank je voor zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik zelf zal het me verwijten en beroerd over zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik betaalde Leurs nu pas sedert Uw bezoek over de 30 gulden en nu ja<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou wel op crediet kunnen krijgen als ’t gewone verf was doch ik ben in besprek met oude verf die ik kan krijgen met 33 1/3 % af<c type="kk">/</c> doch à contant<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo is het met Furnee (dat is de vader van dien landmeter) ook<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb zijn verzekering dat hij mij vertrouwde maar ik zit er mee dat ik hem meestal contant betaalde als antecedent – en zie geen reden dat te veranderen daar ik anders schijn te veranderen van handelwijs en het misschien de vriendschap influenceert<c type="kk">/</c> en wat ik van dien wou nemen is ook een deel van die bewuste partij<c type="kk">/</c> ongeveer de helft<c type="kk">/</c> ook al weer een zaak à contant. Verder met penseelen<c type="kk">/</c> met nog een schilderkistje en studie etui<c type="kk">/</c> andere zaken nog – <hi rend="italics">als</hi> ik à contant neem krijg ik gunstiger condities en heb verder geen zorgen in ’t verschiet<c type="kk">/</c> en heb ik geen verdere zorgen dan kan ik aan ’t afdoen van Rappard beginnen.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">This morning the weather was better again and I went out to paint, regardless. Only it wasn’t possible, I was missing 4 or 5 colours, and so I came back again very wretched. I’m sorry I ventured so far without supplies — I know from prior experience how it can be if one undertakes an excursion like this without knowing that one will also get a response to reasonable, well-founded requests, and that they’ll be listened to.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You know yourself a little of how I fared in the Borinage.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Well I’m already all too anxious that exactly the same thing could happen to me here, and I must have some security before I venture any further and otherwise, well then I’ll go back (oh — you know, I’m only saying this because I really want to stay).<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I take no pleasure in it, I saw no good in it then and see even less now in reaching a point of destitution such that one doesn’t even have a roof over one’s head and must tramp on and tramp on like a vagabond into infinity without finding either rest or food or shelter anywhere, moreover without the possibility of doing any work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">See for yourself on the map how far it is from Mons to <hi rend="italics">Courrières</hi>, I covered that road there on foot from Valenciennes, and back to Mons with less than 2 francs in my pocket — three days and three nights at the beginning of March, in rain and wind, without a roof over my head.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">These are the precedents, brother, which I haven’t yet come to now, of course — but would come to if I were to venture far without security — if I weren’t to put my affairs in reasonable order — if, I say, I were to venture far into the countryside without backing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Before I start — it’s neither distrust nor suspicion of you but simply a common-sense measure — before I start — I say — (and ask because you wrote to me very recently that you yourself were worried because you feared that there could be trouble and calamities ahead) can you assure me that the usual won’t be lacking? 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And at the same time — although that’s enough and more wouldn’t be necessary on certain conditions — I’ll tell you the condition on which only the usual is sufficient — to start out well equipped, to set out with a supply of this and that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I, who like to take the initiative for acting myself, because a proof of sincerity, a deed proving that one deals in actions not words, is sometimes needed — I, although I came here this far in Drenthe myself, shrink from taking not the first step but the subsequent steps without being sure of my backing. <hi>Experience</hi> compels me to ask for a certain unshakeable understanding — if you yourself had experienced what I suffered on that expedition in the Borinage, then in my position now you would have learned exactly the same from this as I did — which I feel now so clearly and plainly — <hi rend="italics">recognizing </hi>all the circumstances and things I’m faced with as old acquaintances.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">The expeditions I have in mind are impossible and madness if I undertake them without supplies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">They are highly perilous without a surplus of cash for unforeseen circumstances. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In short, one mustn’t undertake them unless one feels through and through that one will always and everywhere be faced with people who stand gaping at someone but don’t lift a finger to help. One must picture oneself being mistrusted in inns &amp;c. — like any poor pedlar (for that’s how they view one) — one often has to pay the money for lodgings — as I had to do even here — <hi rend="italics">in advance</hi> in order to get a room by the grace of God. And so EVERYTHING IS PROSE, EVERYTHING IS CALCULATION in regard to the plan for a trip that after all has poetry as its goal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’ve never before told you as plainly as this, and if I tell you now it is, I ASSURE YOU, not in the least because I mistrust you, but because since I planned the trip I haven’t yet spoken to you as seriously as this about the drawbacks and their relationship to what you might have available or be able to find for it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I must speak of it now because, although in the letter before last I told you that everything here was better than I’d expected — which really does remain the case — I’m still encountering drawbacks in this inn as regards light, space, suitability for trying things out with models — and therefore — although I can <hi rend="italics">if necessary </hi>manage and I will do that <hi rend="italics">if necessary</hi> — I’m thinking of continuing my journey deeper into the countryside despite the season, not doubting that everywhere (or where I’ll go, at any rate) I’ll find at least as good an opportunity to work as here, and even better space &amp;c. I hope. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’ve now been here for about a fortnight<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and I speak from experience when I tell you that in many, indeed in all respects my tools and equipment and supplies prove to be inadequate.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Hoogeveen itself is indeed on the map as a town, where it’s marked with a red dot, but in reality it isn’t (there isn’t even a tower).<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> So I can’t even get any drawing materials. I’ll be even more embarrassed deeper in the countryside and must be prepared for everything or, I repeat, it would be madness. I wouldn’t be making haste with this were the season not so far advanced that it compels me to the greatest urgency. Bear in mind that time is passing, and another fortnight may perhaps have passed before I receive word from you again. Before the winter proper (<hi rend="italics">and winter will be here all too soon!!</hi> I really don’t know how I’ll manage) I’d like to be better housed — find quarters somewhere — even further into the heath. And my state of mind, too — which is too gloomy and for which I feel a pressing need to be able to go on working steadily, as being the very best remedy and distraction — means that I must insist on better equipment. And this would actually remain precisely the same should I stay here in this place.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m bargaining for 2 lots of old paint, which only has some outward damage to the tubes, but, over and above this, brushes, canvas, watercolours and Whatman would also be needed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">If I told you that this could be delayed, I would be speaking faint-heartedly, because it’s simply essential that it should happen immediately. If it can’t, then it can’t — but then I can’t go on either. And I wouldn’t have become so melancholy even now if my poor equipment hadn’t tied my hands too much. If, in these various respects, I can find reassurance and that which is indispensable, I believe I’ll be able to get on here. The countryside is very beautiful — today I saw a funeral<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> in a barge, which was very curious — six women wrapped in cloaks in the vessel that was being towed by the men along the canal in the heath — the minister — in tricorne and breeches — just like a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs> figure<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — followed on the other side — oh, there are all sorts of things. You mustn’t take exception to my writing in this way — I left rather too hastily, and it’s only now that I feel what I lack and that I acted rather rashly — but what else could I do? And I’m so unbearably melancholy when the work doesn’t provide me with a distraction, as you’ll understand, and I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> work and work steadily — FORGETTING MYSELF IN THE WORK, otherwise it would overwhelm me. Again, I don’t mistrust you in the very, very least, but my experience forbids me from embarking on an expedition without knowing what I can and what I can’t count on. So speak <hi rend="italics">absolutely frankly</hi>, because my decision depends upon it, and I’ll in any event bow to circumstances. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">If I’d known beforehand that it would come to a separation from the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> after all, I would most probably have separated  1/2 a year ago — but, although it still causes me harm even now, I would rather have been faithful to her for too long than for too short a time, and I didn’t want to act solely on my own opinion before I’d spoken to you personally. Don’t forget, when you think about last year, that the reason for the cost wasn’t so much our personal expenditure as the deadly prices in The Hague. Had I known everything — I could have saved 200 guilders on accommodation even if I had taken THIS WHOLE INN <hi rend="italics">here,</hi> WITH THE GARDEN THROWN IN — and there you have it, even more than my deficit on one single item. So the woman in particular is as innocent of my deficit as I am myself, in so far as it could be no different in The Hague — but if I had known I would have moved here much sooner. I do blame myself for this neglect — or rather this ignorance. And yet last year is not wasted or not fruitless — it has been a year of hard work and, after all, I look back on it with tranquillity. And as to my not having my hands as free as I’d wish at the moment — they’re not free anyway — even if help comes — for a large part of the autumn will already have passed by then — and only some of those studies that I hoped to have been able to do will have been done before the winter — whatever present difficulties there may be, things will nevertheless come right with patience. Only — I really would like to undertake a trip between now and Christmas.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> Let’s make the most of the time, because wasting time is the most expensive thing of all. I have more than 70 painted studies lying in The Hague<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — if only they were of here, they’d have been of more use to me. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I must tell you frankly that lately I was sorry, and still am, that I paid my debt out of the money while I was in debt, but none of the people I paid recently was actually dunning me — although they have done in the past — and I could have put it off even longer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I don’t know, may one not take care of oneself first so that one keeps one’s hands and one’s energies free because, I repeat, you see that I won’t be able to get the studies I need painted before the winter, and who will thank me for that?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I’ll blame myself and feel wretched about it. Since your visit I’ve paid <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_491">Leurs</rs> more than 30 guilders and now, well, if it was ordinary paint I could get it on credit, but I’m negotiating about old paint that I can get at 33 1/3 % off, but only for cash. It’s the same with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_370">Furnée</rs> (he’s the father of that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">surveyor</rs>), I have his assurance that he trusted me, but the thing is that I usually paid him cash in the past — and see no reason to change that, since otherwise I would seem to be changing the way I do business and it might affect the friendship, and what I would like to get from him is also part of the lot in question, about half, and again a cash deal. Then brushes, another painting box, and a portfolio for studies, and other things — <hi rend="italics">if </hi>I pay cash for them I get better terms and will have no further worries ahead, and if I have no further worries I can start paying <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> back.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says that he saw a funeral on the day he wrote <ref target="#l-130">(ll. 130-131)</ref>. This must have been on Friday, 28 September 1883 (<ref target="#n-6">see n. 6</ref>). The comment that the weather turned fine that day (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>) is moreover confirmed by the meteorological data for that Friday (<hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh orders paint in The Hague <ref target="let387.xml">(387)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was in the Borinage from some time around the beginning of December 1878 to around early October 1880 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let149.xml">see letters 149</ref>-<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let158.xml">158</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh added this remark in brackets later.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘onderdak’ (roof).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for this walk to Courrières: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let158.xml">letter 158</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>By then Van Gogh had been in Drenthe for 17 days.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In The Hague Van Gogh had seen a map on which Hoogeveen was shown as a town. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let378.xml">See letter 378</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This must have been the funeral of Alberdina Slot, on Friday, 28 September 1883. See Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 101-102, 124-125.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>A photograph of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_485">Wolter Alberts Kok</rs>, a serving minister at the time, shows him wearing the characteristic garb that Van Gogh describes. He was to wear this eighteenth-century regalia, the official dress of the strict orthodox school, for 43 years. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2117">Ill. 2117</rs>. See Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 101-102, 124-125, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Honderduit. Een eeuw gereformeerde kerk in Hoogeveen</hi>. Lambert ter Haar <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al.</hi> Hoogeveen 2000, pp. 171, 183 ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had stored his things in the attic of the house where he had been living in The Hague; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let382.xml">see letter 382</ref>. A great deal of it is unknown.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    