<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nieuw-Amsterdam, Friday, 12 or Saturday, 13 October 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let395"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b355 c V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>395</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>332</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>397</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-10-12">Friday, 12 or Saturday, 13 October 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nieuw-Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0355 c" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0355 c" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000457_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Bijgaande krabbeltjes stuur ik om U eenig begrip te geven van zooveel uiteenlopende dingen die het schijnbaar monotone land meebrengt. Ge ziet<c type="kk">/</c> ik grijp er maar in<c type="kk">/</c> het een en het ander pak ik bij den kop<c type="kk">/</c> het zal later van zelf zich ordenen en bezinken. Maar ik wil hier niet beginnen met een vooruit gemaakt plan<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil integendeel mijn plan bezinke uit mijn studies. Ik ken nu het eigentlijk karakter van het land nog niet – ik maak alles wat mij nu tegenkomt en dan later als ik ondervinding zal hebben<c type="kk">/</c> zoo wil ik trachten het te geven in ’t geen au fond het meest karakteristiek is.– Het een hangt zoo in het andere dat men alles moet aangrijpen<c type="kk">/</c> al heeft men nog zoo zeer een lust om te concentreeren<c type="kk">/</c> niets kan men missen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Zoo dus is er werk genoeg<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb nu een redelijk groote kamer waar een kagchel gezet is<c type="kk">/</c> waar toevalligerwijs een klein balcon aan is<c type="kp">_</c> Van waar ik reeds de heide met de keeten zien kan.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Verder zie ik op een heel curieuse ophaalbrug.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> beneden is herberg &amp; een boeren keuken met open turfvuur<c type="kk">/</c> heel gezellig s’avonds. Men kan ’t best denken bij zoo’n boerenhaard waar een wiegje bij staat.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Als ik melankoliek me voel of ergens niet uit kan<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/> ga ik maar eens naar beneden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik kan U vertellen dat ik indirekt iets weet van de vrouw. Ik kon après tout er geen touw aan vast maken waarom zij mij niet eens geschreven had<c type="kp">_</c> Welnu<c type="kk">/</c> ik schreef aan den timmerman naast ons<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> of de vrouw niet bij hem geweest was om het adres. Welnu<c type="kk">/</c> de schoelje schrijft me terug: O ja mijnheer, maar ik dacht dat U zeker niet zoudt willen dat zij Uw adres wist<c type="kk">/</c> dus heb ik maar net gedaan als of ik het niet wist<c type="kp">_</c> Verdommelingen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb toen direkt geschreven naar haar<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon dit niet zoo goed was als mijn afspraak die met hem en met haar uitdrukkelijk was gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik <hi rend="italics">wil</hi> <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> niet en <hi rend="italics">nooit</hi> mij verbergen of te verbergen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> en liever schrijf ik haar aan ’t adres van haar familie dan dat ik zelfs den schijn wil hebben van mij schuil houden. Zoo denk ik daarover<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En ik stuurde haar wat geld ook – of dat beroerde gevolgen kan hebben ben ik niet voor aansprakelijk<c type="kk">/</c> ik <hi>wil</hi> <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> valsch doen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik vond den brief van dien schobbejak te Hoogeveen nu bij mijn bezoek aldaar<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Vriend Rappard schreef me ook weer uit Terschelling en – nu heden – uit Utrecht – hij is weer terug!– Heeft studies meegebragt uit het oude lieden gesticht vooral<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik begrijp dit niet precies<c type="kk">/</c> mij zeide hij dat de dokter voor zijn gezondheid hem gedurende den winter zeelucht had aangeraden<c type="kk">/</c> dat bovendien hij zoo’n lust had in een winter buiten maar het schijnt anders te zijn geloopen. Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ge schreeft me van Liebermann – zijn koloriet bestaat uit leigraauwe toonen met overgangen tot bruin<c type="kk">/</c> tot geelgrijs hoofdzakelijk. Ik heb nooit iets van hem gezien maar nu ik de natuur hier zie begrijp ik perfekt hoe raisonable hij daartoe komt. Dikwijls herinneren me de dingen qua kleur aan Michel ook<c type="kp">_</c> Ge weet<c type="kk">/</c> die heeft ook een grijze lucht (leigraauw soms)<c type="kk">/</c> een bruinen grond met geelgrijzen<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is volkomen waar &amp; natuurgetrouw<c type="kp">_</c>– Er zijn effekten Jules Dupre – ja zeker zijn er die<c type="kk">/</c> maar in zoo’n herfst tijd<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is precies dat – zoo als ge schreeft betreffende Liebermann.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En <hi rend="italics">als</hi> ik dat vind wat ik zoek – en waarom zou ik ’t niet vinden – zoo zal ik het zeker dikwijls ook zoo doen in diezelfde gamma<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wel te verstaan<c type="kk">/</c> om ’t zoo te zien moet men niet kijken naar de locale kleur op zich zelf doch in verband met den toon v.d. lucht die locale kleur beschouwen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Die lucht is grijs – evenwel zóó lichtend dat ons wit <hi rend="italics">puur</hi> het niet eens zou geven misschien qua <hi rend="italics">licht</hi> en schittering<c type="kp">_</c>– Schildert men nu de lucht evenwel reeds grijs<c type="kk">/</c> blijvende alzoo ver onder de kracht der natuur<c type="kk">/</c> hoe veel te meer zal men om consequent te blijven de bruinen en geelgrijzen van den grond eenige toonen lager moeten stellen. Me dunkt dit is iets als men ’t ééns zóó analyseert<c type="kk">/</c> spreekt zóó van zelf dat men zich moeielijk begrijpen kan het niet altijd zoo gezien te hebben.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Doch het is de locale kleur van een groen veld of een rosbruine hei die op zich zelf beschouwd iemand ligt in de war brengt.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Schrijf mij weer eens spoedig want qua brief is uw laatste schrijven al merkwaardig beknopt – al te beknopt<c type="kk">/</c> doch was ook in de zaak geschreven blijkbaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Hoe is ’t met de Exposition triennale<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Er zal heel wat moois zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben wel nieuwsgierig iets er van te hooren wegens dit toch bepaald ook de karakteristieke dingen van ’t moment<c type="kk">/</c> niet van veel vroeger jaren zijn. Dus als ge een oogenblikje hebt<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf er eens iets van.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Naar een gerucht loopt schijnt Liebermann hier ergens in de buurt te wezen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Ik wou hem wel eens ontmoeten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben wel blij<c type="kk">/</c> juist wegens er nog al eens regen is en het slechte weer zoo te wachten<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-b"/> dat ik een geschikter werkplaats heb gevonden, om ’t huis niet met de handen in den schoot te behoeven te zitten. Ik wou ge het land eens kondt zien<c type="kk">/</c> s’avonds is het zoo onuitsprekelijk mooi<c type="kp">_</c> En mij dunkt de sneeuw zal ook aangrijpend zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik las een zeer mooi boekje v. Carlyle<c type="kk">/</c> Heroes &amp; heroworship<c type="kk">/</c> vol aardige dingen als bijvoorbeeld We have the <hi rend="italics">duty</hi> to be <hi rend="italics">brave</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> al wordt dit meestal als iets bijzonders beschouwd ten onregte. Het is in ’t leven ook zoo dat het goede zoo’n hoog licht is ’t als vanzelf spreekt we <hi rend="italics">daar</hi> toch niet bij kunnen. Stellen we onze gamma lager en trachten toch helder te blijven en niet in het doode te vervallen<c type="kk">/</c> is het meest raisonable en maakt het leven minder onmogelijk.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Er zijn hier verbazende types van afgescheiden dominés met varkensgezigten en steeken.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ook veel fameuse joden die buitengemeen afschuwelijk doen te midden van Milletachtige typen of op die naïve<c type="kk">/</c> trieste hei<c type="kp">_</c> Anders<c type="kk">/</c> ze zijn wel echt<c type="kp">_</c> ik reisde met een gezelschap joden die theologische discussies hielden met een paar boeren<c type="kp">_</c> Hoe zijn zulke absurditeiten mogelijk<c type="kk">/</c> zou men zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> in een land als hier<c type="kp">_</c> Waarom kunnen ze niet uit het raam kijken of pijpen rooken of zoo<c type="kk">/</c> en zich althans zoo raisonable gedragen als b.v. hun varkens die volstrekt niet hinderen al zijn het varkens<c type="kk">/</c> en in harmonie blijven met de entourage en er op hun plaats zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar eer de dominés<c type="kk">/</c> zóó als ik er hier zag<c type="kk">/</c> de hoogte van beschaving en rede van gewone varkens bereiken<c type="kk">/</c> moeten zij nog veel verbeteren en er zullen daartoe nog wel eeuwen noodig zijn voor zij op dat standpunt zijn. Nu is ’t eerste beste varken veel beter m.i.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik ga er weer eens op uit<c type="kk">/</c> als ge een oogenblikje hebt<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf dan eens en kijk vooral eens of Liebermann iets op de tentoonstelling heeft.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Gegroet – dus mijn adres blijft maar hier voorloopig<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – ’t beste U toegewenscht<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. a t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">I’m sending you the enclosed scratches to give you some idea of so many diverse things that the seemingly monotonous countryside has to offer. You see, I just take what’s there, I grab this and that by the neck; it will arrange itself and ripen of its own accord later. But I don’t want to begin here with a preconceived plan; on the contrary, I want my plan to ripen out of my studies. I don’t know the real character of the countryside as yet — now I’m doing everything I come across, and then later, when I have some experience, I want to try to convey it in what is fundamentally its most characteristic aspect. The one so much part of the other that one has to seize everything; however much one would like to concentrate, one may miss nothing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">There’s plenty of work, in other words. I now have a reasonably large room where a stove has been placed, where there happens to be a small balcony. From which I can even see the heath with the huts.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I also look out on a very curious drawbridge.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Well, downstairs is an inn and a peasant kitchen with an open peat fire, very cosy in the evenings. One can think best by one of those peasant hearths with a cradle beside it.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> If I feel melancholy or can’t work something out, I just go downstairs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I can tell you that I’ve heard something indirectly about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>. After all, I couldn’t for the life of me understand why she hadn’t even written to me. Well then, I wrote to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_472">carpenter</rs> next door to us<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> asking whether the woman hadn’t been to him for the address. Well then, the blackguard writes back to me: Oh yes sir, but I thought that you certainly wouldn’t want her to know your address, so I just made out that I didn’t know it. Bastards.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then I wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> directly, although this wasn’t as good as my agreement, which was expressly made with him and with her, but I <hi rend="italics">do </hi>not<hi rend="italics"> want now</hi> or <hi rend="italics">ever</hi> to conceal or to have to conceal myself, and I’d rather write to her at her family’s address than have even the semblance of hiding. That’s what I think about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And I sent <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> some money too — if this may have wretched consequences, I’m not responsible for them, I <hi>will</hi> <hi rend="italics">not</hi> play false. I found the letter from that scoundrel in Hoogeveen on my last trip there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> also wrote to me again from Terschelling and — now today — from Utrecht — he’s back again! Has brought studies with him, mostly of the old folks’ home.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I don’t quite understand this. He told me that the doctor had advised sea air for him during the winter for his health, that moreover he had such a desire to spend a winter in the country, but it seems to have turned out differently. Anyway. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">You wrote to me about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1181">Liebermann</rs>: his coloration consists of slate-grey tones with transitions chiefly to brown, to yellow-grey. I’ve never seen anything by him, but now that I see nature here I understand perfectly how reasonable it is that he arrives at it. As to colour, things often remind me of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1228">Michel</rs> too. You know, he also has a grey sky (slate-grey sometimes), a brown earth with yellow-greys. It’s completely true and faithful to nature. There are <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs> effects — yes, there are certainly those, but in autumn like this, it’s exactly that — as you wrote about Liebermann.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And <hi rend="italics">if</hi> I find that which I seek — and why shouldn’t I find it? — I’ll certainly often do it thus, in that same spectrum.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">That’s to say, in order to see it like this one mustn’t look at the local colour in itself, but consider that local colour in relation to the tone of the sky.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">That sky is grey — however <hi rend="italics">so</hi> luminous that even our <hi rend="italics">pure</hi> white might perhaps not capture it in terms of <hi rend="italics">light</hi> and brilliance. But if one starts by painting the sky grey, thus remaining far below the intensity of nature, then all the more, in order to remain consistent, will one have to set the browns and yellow-greys of the earth several tones lower. It seems to me that this is something which, once one analyzes it like this, is <hi rend="italics">so</hi> self-evident that one finds it hard to understand that one hasn’t always seen it thus.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">But it’s the local colour of a green field or a reddish-brown heath which, viewed in isolation, can easily confuse someone. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Write to me again soon because, as letters go, your last missive was remarkably brief — all too brief, but was also evidently written in the office.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">How’s the Triennial Exhibition going?<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> There’ll be a lot of beautiful things. I’m really interested to hear something about it, because these too are certainly the characteristic things of the moment, not of much earlier years. So if you have a moment, do write something about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">According to a current rumour, it appears that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1181">Liebermann</rs> is somewhere here in the neighbourhood.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I’d like to meet him sometime.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"> Well, I’m very pleased that I’ve found a more suitable studio, precisely because it’s rather rainy and the bad weather can be expected any time, so as not to have to sit idle at home. I wish you could just see the countryside; it’s so inexpressibly beautiful in the evening. And it seems to me the snow will be gripping too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I read a very good book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Carlyle</rs>, Heroes and hero-worship, full of nice things, like for instance, We have the <hi rend="italics">duty</hi> to be <hi rend="italics">brave</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> although this is usually wrongly regarded as something exceptional. It’s also true in life that the good is such a high light that it goes without saying that we can’t reach <hi rend="italics">that</hi>. If we set our spectrum lower and nonetheless try to remain bright and not lapse into lifelessness, this is the most reasonable thing to do, and makes life less impossible. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">There are amazing characters here — nonconformist ministers with pig faces and cocked hats.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Also many veritable Jews who look extraordinarily ugly amidst <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>esque types or on this unsophisticated, sad heath. On the other hand, they <hi rend="italics">are</hi> genuine. I travelled with a party of Jews who were having theological discussions with a couple of peasants. How are such absurdities possible, one would say, in countryside like this? Why can’t they look out of the window or smoke pipes or something, and at any rate behave as reasonably as their pigs, say, which aren’t a nuisance at all, even though they’re pigs, and remain in harmony with their surroundings and are in place there?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But before the ministers like the ones I saw here achieve the height of civilization and reason of common pigs, they have to improve a good deal more, and it will take centuries before they’re in that position. At the moment, any pig at all is much better, to my mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Well, I’m going out again, do write if you get a moment, and look particularly to see whether <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1181">Liebermann</rs> has anything in the exhibition.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Regards — so my address just remains here for the time being<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> — wishing you the best, with a handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh must have been in Hoogeveen on Friday, 12 October 1883 (<ref target="let394.xml">see letter 394</ref>). The present letter, written in Nieuw-Amsterdam <ref target="#l-38">(l. 38)</ref>, must date from soon after the trip back because Van Gogh describes his fellow passengers in the barge. If he travelled back on the Friday, he must have caught the barge that sailed at 13.00; if he spent that night in Hoogeveen, he could have left at 9.30 on Saturday morning. The fact that he writes that he is going out again <ref target="#l-130">(l. 130)</ref> does not necessarily mean that the letter cannot have been written on Friday evening, since Van Gogh was drawing evening effects that month (<ref target="let398.xml">see letter 398</ref>). He probably received Van Rappard’s letter from Utrecht (that was ‘today’, <ref target="#l-39">l. 39</ref>) just before he left Hoogeveen, as there are no indications that Van Rappard had Van Gogh’s address in Nieuw-Amsterdam. The sheet consequently dates from Friday, 12 or Saturday, 13 October 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 and in later editions this sheet was added to <ref target="let395.xml">letter 395</ref> after the signature, but that letter was written in Hoogeveen while the present letter was written in Nieuw-Amsterdam. We have therefore detached it. There is no salutation, so the letter is probably incomplete. Van Gogh writes that he is sending ‘scratches’ <ref target="#l-1">(l. 1)</ref>; we do not know which these were or whether there was any letter text on them.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s stay on Terschelling <ref target="let388.xml">(388)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In Nieuw-Amsterdam Van Gogh found a room in the lodging-house kept by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_195">Hendrik Scholte</rs>, in District E, no. 34 (later no. 47). He had evidently had an opportunity to move to a better room after he got back from Hoogeveen. On Scholte and his family: Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 161-169.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This is the bridge depicted in the watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Drawbridge in Nieuw-Amsterdam</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2449">F 1098 / JH 425</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The occupant of this cradle was the youngest child in the Scholte family, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_658">Alida Wilhelmina</rs>, who was born on 17 April 1883.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘ergens geen wijs uit kan worden, over iets in verwarring ben’ (can’t get a grip on something, am confused about something).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This carpenter was probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_472">Willem Kiesenberg</rs>; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let241.xml">letter 241</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs> made various works on the island, among them <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_329">Old women in the West-Terschelling home</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let416.xml">see letter 416</ref>, and cf. exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 84-85.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The Exposition Triennale (Triennial Exhibition) was a prestigious retrospective that the French government planned to stage once every three years as a counterweight to the Salon, which was controlled by artists. In 1883 (the only time the exhibition actually went ahead) the Triennale ran from 15 September to 31 October. See Mainardi 1993, pp. 91-120.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1181">Liebermann</rs> had worked in Drenthe between August and October 1882; there are no indications that he was also there in 1883. Cf. exhib. cat. The Hague 1980.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘in het vooruitzicht’ (in prospect).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This expression derives from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Thomas Carlyle</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">On heroes, hero-worship and the heroic in history</hi> (1841). ‘It is an everlasting duty, valid in our day as in that, the duty of being brave’ (Carlyle 1993, p. 28). Carlyle saw the history of the world as the biography of great men. In his book he explains what is needed for a well-ordered society. Van Gogh copied out a passage from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">On heroes</hi> as early as 1875. See Pabst 1988, p. 25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Cf. for the cocked hats worn by the ministers, the photograph printed with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let391.xml#n-7;">letter 391, n. 7;</ref> cf. for the comparison of people with animals: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let291.xml#n-7">letter 291, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1181">Liebermann</rs> showed his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La blanchisserie de Zweeloo (Hollande)</hi> (Bleaching field at Zweeloo (Holland)) at the 1883 Salon; Van Gogh mentions this painting in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let402.xml">letter 402</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>His accommodation address at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_195">Scholte</rs>’s.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    