<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nieuw-Amsterdam, Sunday, 11 November 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let405"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b361 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>405</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>338</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>403</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-11">Sunday, 11 November 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nieuw-Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0361" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0361" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000467_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">gij hebt mij in der tijd eens geschreven over een zeker verschil in onze respectieve physionomie<c type="kp">_</c>– Goed<c type="kp">_</c>– En was Uw conclusie ik meer denker zoude zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat zal ik U daarvan zeggen – Ik voel in mij wel degelijk een denken maar mijn denken is toch niet wat ik in mij speciaal georganiseerd gevoel. Ik gevoel mij iets anders dan een denker speciaal. Als ik aan U denk zie ik actie<c type="kk">/</c> zeer karakteristiek<c type="kk">/</c> que soit<c type="kk">/</c> doch ook zoo gedecideerd <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> op zich zelf staand en integendeel vergezeld gaande van zóóveel gevoel en wel degelijk <hi rend="italics">denken</hi> ook<c type="kk">/</c> dat slotsom bij mij is er tusschen U en mij meer overeenkomst is dan verschil<c type="kp">_</c>– ’K zeg niet er geen verschil is – doch U meer hebbende leeren kennen in laatste tijden blijkt mij ’t verschil geringer te zijn dan in vroeger jaren ik een wijle gedacht heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Indien ik naga ons temperament en type van physionomie vind ik rapporten en zeer geprononceerde overeenstemmingen tusschen b.v. de puriteinen en ons zelven. N.l. de lui ± uit Cromwells tijd die als klein troepje mannen &amp; vrouwen uitzeilden in the Mayflower naar Amerika<c type="kk">/</c> uit een oude wereld uit<c type="kk">/</c> en daar zich vestigden<c type="kk">/</c> vastberaden in ’t eenvoudige te blijven<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Tijden verschillen – zij hakten bosschen om – wij zouden in schilderen ’t zoeken<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik weet dat het initiatief<c type="kk">/</c> genomen door een klein troepje, pilgrimfathers genaamd in de historie, hoe klein op zichzelf<c type="kk">/</c> groote gevolgen had. En van ons zou ik primo meenen wij over groote gevolgen weinig zouden philosofeeren<c type="kk">/</c> niet anders zoeken dan een weg voor ons zelf om zelf zoo regt mogelijk door ’t leven te reizen<c type="kp">_</c>– Gevolgen premeditteeren is onze stemming <hi rend="italics">niet</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">noch de uwe</hi> <hi rend="italics">noch de mijne</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Indien ik over Pilgrimfathers spreek is het om reden van physionomie<c type="kk">/</c> om U er op te wijzen zekere rosharige lui met vierkante voorhoofden noch alleen denkers noch alleen mannen van actie zijn maar beide elementen gecombineerd plegen te hebben.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> In Boughtons schilderijen ken ik een figuurtje van een dier puriteinen waarvoor<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik ’t niet beter wist<c type="kk">/</c> ik meenen zou <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> geposeerd hadt. bepaaldelijk physionomie<c type="kk">/</c> precies<c type="kk">/</c> precies – een silhouetje op een rots tegen een fond van zee en mist – me zelf<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. die <hi rend="italics">variatie</hi> van zelfde physionomie<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik desnoods ook U wijzen doch mijn profiel is minder karakteristiek<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Pa verdiepte zich wel eens in de historie v. Jacob &amp; Esau<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> betreffende U en mij – niet heelemaal mis – doch gelukkigerwijs is er minder veete<c type="kk">/</c> om maar één verschil te noemen<c type="kk">/</c> en in den Bijbel zelf zijn voorbeelden genoeg van beter verhoudingen tusschen broers dan bestond tusschen de voornoemde eerwaardige patriarchen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Over het denker zijn heb ik zelf wel eens gedacht doch ik zag al meer en meer ik niet daarvoor was in de wieg gelegd en wegens nu ongelukkigerwijs het prejugé dat iemand die behoefte aan doordenken heeft <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> praktisch is en onder de droomers slechts hoort<c type="kk">/</c> wegens dit prejugé in de zamenleving zeer gerespecteerd wordt<c type="kk">/</c> stootte ik dikwijls mijn hoofd juist door het niet genoeg voor me zelf te houden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar sedert<c type="kk">/</c> juist de historie der puriteinen en de historie v<c type="kp">_</c> Cromwell zoo als b.v. Carlyle t’heeft opgevat<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> bragt mij er toe te zien hoe zeer denken en handelen elkaar niet uitsluiten en de scherpe afscheidingen die het heden ten dage gewoonte is te veronderstellen tusschen denken en handelen<c type="kk">/</c> als zou ’t een ’t ander uitsluiten<c type="kk">/</c> in der daad niet bestaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Betreffende twijfelen aan zich zelf of men artist is of niet – die heele kwestie is te zeer een abstractie<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zeg dat ik er niets op tegen heb er over te denken evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> mits ik maar tevens teekenen en schilderen mag. En – voor mijn leven is mijn plan zoo veel en zoo goede schilderijen &amp; teekeningen te maken als ik kan<c type="kp">_</c> dan<c type="kk">/</c> als mijn leven uit is hoop ik niet anders weg te gaan dan met liefde en weemoed terugziende en denkende<c type="kk">/</c> o schilderijen die ik gemaakt zou hebben!– Doch dit sluit het maken van het mogelijke s.v.p. niet uit<c type="kp">_</c>– Hebt gij hier op tegen ’t zij voor mij ’t zij voor U<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wenschte het schilderen zóó idee fixe bij u werd dat de vraag<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik artist of ben ik geen artist<c type="kk">/</c> ietwat onder de abstracties werd gerangschikt en meer praktische vragen betreffende het in elkaar zitten van een figuur of landschap<c type="kk">/</c> amusanter zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> op den voorgrond kwamen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Theo ik verklaar U dat ik liever denk over hoe armen<c type="kk">/</c> beenen<c type="kk">/</c> kop aan den romp zitten dan over of ik zelf niet of meer of minder artist ben. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Ik denk van U dat gij liever aan een lucht met graauwe wolken en hun schitterende randen boven een modderig terrein denkt dan U in de kwestie van U zelf verdiept<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet het echter wel<c type="kk">/</c> soms is het gemoed daarvan vol<c type="kk">/</c> het kan niet anders. Zie broer<c type="kk">/</c> maar al is ons gemoed wel eens vervuld met de kwestie <hi rend="italics">is er een God</hi> of <hi rend="italics">is Hij er</hi> <hi rend="italics">niet</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zoo is zulks voor ons geen reden expres een goddelooze daad te verrigten<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar. Evenzoo moet in het artistieke de vraag<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik artist of niet? niet ons er toe brengen om <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> te teekenen of <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> te schilderen. Veel dingen zijn niet te defineeren en al te veel tijd er op verliezen verkeerd m.i. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> als ’t werk niet vlot of men stuit op een onwetendheid<c type="kk">/</c> raakt men in den modder van zulke gedachten en onoplosbare kwesties<c type="kp">_</c>– En daardoor zich getroubleerd gevoelende is ’t het best oorzaak der distractie te overwinnen door een nieuwen blik op het praktische van ’t werk te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij <hi rend="italics">en</hi> in U <hi rend="italics">en</hi> in mij iets ziende van het puriteinsch karakter dat denken en doen zoozeer vereenigt en zoo ver er van daan is alleen denker of alleen machine te willen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> dat behoefte heeft <hi rend="italics">en</hi> aan principes van eenvoud <hi rend="italics">en</hi> aan gemotiveerd werk tegelijk<c type="kk">/</c> admitteer <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> een scheiding of uit elkaar loopen<c type="kk">/</c> veel minder een tegenovergesteld zijn van U en van mij<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Erreur de point de vue ware het mijns inziens indien gij Parijsche zaken doorzettet<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Dus conclusie<c type="kk">/</c> twee broers schilder<c type="kp">_</c>– Of het in Uw natuur ligt? gij zoudt wel eens bezig kunnen zijn hard en onvruchtbaar te strijden tegen de natuur in juist door het te betwijfelen of ge kunt en daardoor uw vrijwording zelf belemmeren. Ik weet daar helaas het mijne van<c type="kp">_</c>– Après tout – zelfs ondanks ons eigen tegen ons zelf zijn begin ik wel meer en meer in te zien<c type="kk">/</c> l’homme s’agite, Dieu le mène<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Boven ons goed doen en ons verkeerd doen is een oneindige magtige kracht<c type="kp">_</c> Zoo Uw omstandigheden – wees er wijs in – misschien zelfs zóó wijs dat ge schilder wordt kort en goed<c type="kp">_</c> Het zou mij zóó geruststellen au fond indien ik U ’t penseel zag grijpen dat ik de calamiteit en schipbreuk van ’t moment van minder belang zou rekenen dan de vastheid voor de toekomst in onberouwelijke rigting te zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Maar ik wou wel gij meteen ruste vondt voor Uw hart in zake vrouwenkwestie. Als dat kon<c type="kk">/</c> ge waart <hi rend="italics">nog</hi> sterker<c type="kk">/</c> daar être aimé zekere vlerken geeft<c type="kk">/</c> zekeren verbazenden moed en energie<c type="kp">_</c> Men is dan meer een <hi rend="italics">heel</hi> mensch dan anders<c type="kp">_</c>– En hoe eer men dat is hoe beter<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">In elk geval<c type="kk">/</c> ik reken het onder de mogelijkheden gij zelf tot bewustzijn komt van dat Uw weg ’t schilderen is<c type="kk">/</c> en dan beste broer<c type="kk">/</c> puritein sans le savoir<c type="kk">/</c> zou het wel eens zijn kunnen ge Uw langste dagen te Parijs gehad hadt<c type="kk">/</c> een oude wereld voor U zich sloot op weinig genereuse manier – een nieuwe wereld evenwel zich voor U ontsloot – onherbergzaam en ruw zich voordoende, met dat al een zekere hoop en hoogen moed in t’hart<c type="kk">/</c> voelt men ’t quelque chose là-Haut<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> boven ’t barre strand en dus de hand slaat men aan den ploeg<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – asking no questions<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> denk er over meer of minder<c type="kk">/</c> lang of kort<c type="kp">_</c> Doch het zou U niet helpen of ge zeidet<c type="kk">/</c> Vincent zwijg er over<c type="kk">/</c> want daarop zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> Theo ’t zal in U <hi rend="italics">zelf</hi> misschien niet zwijgen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">      <hi rend="italics">On le contient plus malaisément</hi></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">      <hi rend="italics">Que la source des grands fleuves</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Theo<c type="kk">/</c> van de arme vrouw<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> hoorde ik sedert een paar keer<c type="kk">/</c> zij schijnt door te werken<c type="kk">/</c> te wasschen voor de lui<c type="kk">/</c> als noodhulp te dienen<c type="kk">/</c> enfin haar best te doen. Schrijft haast onontcijferbaar en onzamenhangend. Schijnt spijt te hebben van sommige dingen van vroeger. Kinderen gezond en wel<c type="kp">_</c> Het medelijden en gehechtheid is bij mij zeker niet dood ten opzigte van haar en ik hoop wel dat wij een band van gehechtheid houden<c type="kk">/</c> al zie ik niet in dat zamenleven opnieuw wenschelijk of mogelijk zoude zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Medelijden is geen liefde misschien doch dit neemt niet weg het diep kan zitten<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Nu broer<c type="kk">/</c> om van iets anders te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> het sneeuwt hier van daag in den vorm van kolossale hagelsteenen. Ik zeg sneeuwt wegens ’t effekt<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zwijg over het mooie van hier omdat ik TE VEEL U er van te zeggen zou hebben. Betreffende werk<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben haast te vol wegens ’t idee dat gij het zoudt beginnen<c type="kk">/</c> dat mij verbazend vervult<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wou ’t zich decideerde juist om vaste plannen te kunnen maken van zamenwerken. Drenthe is zóó mooi<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zeer pakt het me algeheel in en voldoet mij absoluut dat ik<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik niet voor altijd hier kon zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik liever ’t maar niet gezien had. Het is onbeschrijfelijk schoon. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">You once wrote to me about a certain difference in our respective physiognomies. Very well. And your conclusion was that I would be more of a thinker. What shall I say about that? I am indeed aware of a mode of thinking within me, but nevertheless I don’t feel that my thinking is really organized within me. I feel that I’m a little different from being a real thinker. When I think about you I see action, very characteristic, so be it, but also so decidedly <hi rend="italics">not</hi> in isolation, and on the contrary accompanied by so much feeling and indeed <hi rend="italics">thinking</hi> too, that my conclusion is that there’s more similarity than difference between you and me. I don’t say there’s no difference — but having got to know you better of late it seems to me that the difference is less than I thought for a while in years past.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">When I look at our temperament and type of physiognomy, I find rapports and very pronounced similarities between, for example, the Puritans and ourselves. I.e. the folk from around <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_339">Cromwell</rs>’s time, a small band of men and women who sailed out to America in the Mayflower, away from an old world, and settled there, determined to live in simplicity.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Times change — they cut down forests — we’d turn to painting. I know that the initiative taken by a small band, known to history as the Pilgrim Fathers, however small in itself, had great consequences. And for ourselves I’d think in the first place that we shouldn’t really philosophize about great consequences, should seek nothing but a path for ourselves so that we can travel through life as straight as possible. Premeditating consequences is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> our way, <hi rend="italics">neither yours nor mine</hi>. When I speak of the Pilgrim Fathers it’s for reasons of physiognomy, to point out to you that certain red-headed folk with square foreheads aren’t thinkers alone nor men of action alone, but usually have both elements combined.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I recognize a figure of one of those Puritans in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>’s paintings, and if I didn’t know better I would believe that <hi rend="italics">you</hi> had posed for it. The physiognomy above all, exact, exact — a little silhouette on a rock against a background of sea and mist — if need be I can also show you myself, i.e. that <hi rend="italics">variation</hi> of the same physiognomy, but my profile is less characteristic.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> sometimes mulled over the story of Jacob and Esau<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> with regard to you and me — not entirely mistakenly — although happily there’s less enmity, to mention just one difference, and in the Bible itself there are examples aplenty of better relations between brothers than existed between the aforementioned venerable patriarchs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I sometimes thought myself about being a thinker, but I saw more and more that I wasn’t cut out for it, and because now, unfortunately, the prejudice that someone who has a need to think things through is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> practical and only belongs among the dreamers, because this prejudice is very respected in society, I usually got into trouble precisely by not keeping things to myself enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But since then, the very history of the Puritans and the history of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_339">Cromwell</rs>, as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Carlyle</rs> conceived it,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> for instance, made me see how much thinking and acting don’t rule one another out, and the sharp distinctions between thinking and acting that it’s customary to assume nowadays, as if one rules out the other, don’t actually exist.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">As to doubting oneself, whether one is an artist or not — that entire question is too much of an abstraction. I say that I have nothing against thinking about it, though, provided I may also draw and paint. And — my plan for my life is to make paintings and drawings, as many and as well as I can — then, when my life is over, I hope to depart in no other way than looking back with love and wistfulness and thinking, oh paintings that I would have made! But this doesn’t, if you please, rule out making what is possible. Do you have anything against this, either for me or for you? I wish that painting became such a fixed idea with you that the question, am I an artist or am I not an artist, was somewhat consigned to the realm of abstractions, and that more practical questions concerning putting a figure or a landscape together would come to the fore, being more enjoyable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Theo, I declare to you that I would rather think about how arms, legs, head attach to a torso than whether or not I myself am more of an artist or less. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I think that you would rather think about a sky with grey clouds and their shining edges over a muddy piece of land than ponder on the question of yourself.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"> Well, I do know it though, sometimes the mind is full of it, it can’t be helped. Look here, brother, even if our mind is sometimes occupied by the question <hi rend="italics">is there a God</hi> or <hi rend="italics">does He not exist</hi>, this is no reason for us deliberately to commit a godless act, is it? Likewise the question, artistically, am I an artist or not? shouldn’t lead us <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to draw or <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to paint. Many things can’t be defined, and in my view wasting too much time on them is wrong. Now, if the work doesn’t go well or one runs up against a lack of knowledge, one becomes bogged down in such thoughts and insoluble questions. And feeling troubled by this, the best thing to do is to overcome the cause of the distraction by getting a fresh view of the practical side of the work. Now for my part, seeing both in you <hi rend="italics">and </hi>in me something of that puritanical character that unites thinking and doing so much and is so far from wanting to be only a thinker or only a machine, that has a need both for principles of simplicity <hi rend="italics">and</hi> for motivated work at the same time, I do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> admit a separation or divergence, much less that you and I should be opposites.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In my view it would be an error of judgement if you were to continue in business in Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">So the conclusion, two brothers, painters. Whether it’s in your nature? You could occupy yourself struggling hard and fruitlessly against nature precisely by doubting whether you can, and thus hamper your own liberation. Sadly, I know that all too well in my own case. After all — even despite our being against ourselves, I’m starting to realize more and more, man proposes, God disposes.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">There’s an infinitely powerful force over our doing right and our doing wrong. Likewise your circumstances — be sensible — perhaps even so sensible that you become a painter for good and all. It would basically reassure me so much if I saw you pick up the brush that I’d reckon the disaster and shipwreck of the moment as being of less importance than the future certainty of heading in a direction you won’t regret.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But I do wish you would find immediate tranquillity for your heart in the matter of women. If that were possible, you would be <hi rend="italics">even</hi> stronger, since being loved gives one certain wings, certain surprising courage and energy. Then one is more a <hi rend="italics">whole</hi> person than otherwise. And the sooner one is that the better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">In any case, I reckon it among the possibilities that you yourself will come to realize that your path is painting, and then, my dear brother, Puritan without knowing it, it could well be that your time in Paris is coming to an end, an old world closing itself off from you in a less than generous manner — however a new world opening up to you — appearing inhospitable and rough, together with all that, a certain hope and high courage in the heart, one feels the something on High<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> above the barren shore, and so one turns one’s hand to the plough<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> — asking no questions.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Well, think about it, more or less, for a long or short while. But it wouldn’t help if you were to say, Vincent, be quiet about it, for I’d reply, Theo, perhaps it won’t be quiet in <hi rend="italics">yourself</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"><hi rend="italics">It is more difficult to contain</hi></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">Than the source of great rivers.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Theo, I’ve heard from the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> a few times since. She seems to be carrying on working, doing washing for people, serving as a temporary help, in short doing her best. Writes almost indecipherably and incoherently. Seems to regret some things from the past. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">Children</rs> healthy and well. My pity and affection for her are certainly not dead, and I do hope that we’ll retain a bond of affection, although I don’t believe that living together again would be desirable or possible. Pity may not be love, but that doesn’t alter the fact that it can go deep.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Well brother, to change the subject, it’s snowing here today in the form of colossal hailstones. I say it’s snowing because of the effect. I’m keeping silent about the beauty of it here, because I would have TOO MUCH to tell you about it. As to work, I’m almost overbrimming because of the idea that you might start on it, which has a surprising hold on me. I wish it could be decided, precisely so that we could make definite plans for working together. Drenthe is so beautiful, it absorbs and fulfils me so utterly that, if I couldn’t stay here forever I would rather not have seen it at all. It’s inexpressibly beautiful. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes: ‘it’s snowing here today in the form of colossal hailstones. I say it’s snowing because of the effect’ <ref target="#l-163">(l. 163)</ref>. There were no hailstorms in October but it hailed twice in November: during the morning of Sunday, 11 November, and at about nine in the evening on Monday, 19 November. Since Van Gogh refers to the ‘effect’ of the hailstones and says ‘today’, it is most likely that this was hail that fell during the day. This letter is therefore dated Sunday, 11 November 1883. See also Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 179-180.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The Pilgrim Fathers were English Puritans; in 1620 they emigrated to North America in the Mayflower and settled in Massachusetts.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh based his observations about relating a person’s temperament to his physiognomy on what he had read of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_489">Lavater</rs>’s ideas and writings in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1713">Alexandre Ysabeau</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_206">Lavater et Gall. Physiognomonie et phrénologie rendues intelligibles pour tout le monde</ref></hi>, Paris 1862 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let160.xml#n-8">see letter 160, n. 8</ref>). In it we read: ‘Noticeably square foreheads usually denote a firm, confident character, combined with a high degree of caution. In the physiognomic study of the forehead, any straight form indicates strength, rigidity, and at the same time, intelligence’ (Les fronts sensiblement carrés annoncent en général un caractère ferme et sûr, allié à beaucoup de prudence. Dans l’étude physiognomique du front, toute forme droite indique la force, la roideur, et en même temps l’intelligence); quoted in exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1988, p. 172, n. 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh added the passage about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs>’s painting <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-38">(ll. 38-43)</ref> later. The figure he describes is probably the man with the helmet and sharp profile, sitting on a rock, in Boughton’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landing of the Pilgrim Fathers</hi>, 1869 (Sheffield, Graves Art Gallery). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_615">Ill. 615</rs>. Leistra, however, suggested that Van Gogh was referring to the young man in the painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">New English Pilgrims waiting for relief ship</hi>. See Leistra 1987, pp. 28-30.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  Gen. 25:24-34. Esau, the firstborn son of Isaac and Rebecca, was tricked out of his birthright by his younger twin Jacob.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Carlyle</rs> restored <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_339">Cromwell</rs>, who had become idealized over time, to his rightful position as a historical figure whose words and deeds should be considered critically. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_239">Oliver Cromwell’s letters and speeches</ref></hi> bear witness to his character – Carlyle calls him ‘a man of truths’, ‘an earnest man’ and ‘a noble figure’, and writes: ‘We discover features of an Intelligence, and Soul of a Man, greater than any speech’. See Carlyle 1846, vol. 1, pp. 19, 100, 102; and cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let211.xml#n-14">letter 211, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>After ‘yourself’ Van Gogh wrote ‘It is so almighty tedious’ (‘Het is zoo magtig vervelend’), but he crossed it out.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Cf. for this formulation <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let035.xml#n-2">letter 35, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Cf. Rom. 11:29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>See for this phrase: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let288.xml#n-15">letter 288, n. 15.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Cf. Luke 9:62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
 Cf. 1 Cor. 10:25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
  
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_235">Du prêtre, de la femme, de la famille</ref></hi>. 3th ed. Paris 1845, p. 14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien Hoornik</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    