<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nieuw-Amsterdam, Monday, 26 November 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let407"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b367 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>407</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>342</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>409</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-26">Monday, 26 November 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nieuw-Amsterdam</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0367 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0367 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000476_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0367 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0367 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000477_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Mag ik er U eens opmerkzaam op maken dat de post van Maandag 26 Nov. zooeven passeert zonder Uw brief te hebben gebragt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Dat wegens ’t nog naar Hoogeveen moet &amp; terug<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> wij nu op een punt gekomen zijn dat het bijna gelijkstaat of ik een keer ’t gewone niet had gehad<c type="kk">/</c> want gesteld eerst volgende post brengt den brief<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang ik ’t geld niet voor 28 Nov. s’avonds laat of 29 Nov. s’morgens.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gevolgelijk is dit eigentlijk een tekort want Uw volgenden brief<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. die ik anders tegen 1 Dec. zou hebben meenen te verwachten kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> zal dan wel niet komen. Wegens nu sedert ik hier op Nieuw Amst. ben telkens de brieven later &amp; later kwamen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Indien ik een woordje tot waarschuwing had ontvangen overeenkomstig onze afspraak<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zou het in mij niet die stemming opwekken die ik onwillekeurig wel gaandeweg ietwat krijgen moet. Namelijk dat er ietwat dubbelzinnigheid begint in te sluipen in onze verhouding die begon opregtelijk te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> wederzijdsch elkaar begrijpen en respecteeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dat het boven vermelde mij een teleurstelling is en zeer voelbaar mij hindert<c type="kk">/</c> ook afgescheiden van gedachten die ik niet precies helpen kan bij me opkomen<c type="kk">/</c> is toch niet wat mij heden ’t meest op t’harte drukt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Veeleer is het een onbestemde onrust betreffende U<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks – misschien juist <hi rend="italics">wegens</hi> – ik pas gisteren van t’huis verneem zij een goeden brief van U hadden gehad<c type="kp">_</c>– Hieruit zou ik dus opmaken dat die bewuste crisis onderdrukt<c type="kk">/</c> afgewend<c type="kk">/</c> gestopt is<c type="kk">/</c> enfin hoe ge ’t noemen wilt. En dus 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>dit eene bevestiging zou zijn van Uw woordje aan mij<c type="kk">/</c> “ik geloof wel dat voorloopig de dingen zóó blijven zullen”<c type="kp">_</c> Waarvan ik echter reeds liet doorstralen het mij maar half beviel<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> of liever veeleer te meer verontrustte in plaats van geruststelde betreffende uw toekomst<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik hoop nu maar dat gij mij verstaan zult en niet <hi rend="italics">mis</hi> verstaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Op dit moment verdenk ik U niet van onoprecht<c type="shy">-</c>heid – houd s.v.p. dat vast als mijn uitgangspunt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Omdat ik in U geloof dus als eerlijk man zoo reken ik U betrekkelijk veilig tot nog toe quand même – zelfs in geval van catastrophe<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar nu komt het punt waar ik vrees gij een gevaar loopt – kwetsbaar zijt<c type="kp">_</c>– Gesteld al wat dreigde is afgewend<c type="kk">/</c> gesteld alles is gecalmeerd, zoo wilde ik U herinneren aan ’t gezegde: don’t fear the storm but dread the <hi rend="italics">calm</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">treacherous</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">enchanted</hi> ground<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Gesteld zachtjes aan en onmerkbaar wordt gij door een stillen stroom meegevoerd in een ander vaarwater dan <hi rend="italics">regt</hi> door zee<c type="kp">_</c> Gesteld dat wat ik zal noemen – vergeef me de expressie – vergift van de Parijsche atmosfeer – het jesuitisme van dien dampkring – dringt zoetjes aan in uw porien – onmerkbaar voor u zelf – maar toch is uitwerking gij over eenige jaren het zelf begint te bespeuren – ik ben van den koers af – ik ben <hi rend="italics">te</hi> onopregt<c type="kk">/</c> te weinig me zelf uitgedraaid<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> en ik heb <hi rend="italics">te</hi> <hi rend="italics">veel</hi> toegegeven aan het den voorspoed maar volgen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Broer – indien gij onlangs schreeft “ik geloof ik op finantieel gebied een nieuwe opvatting op ’t spoor ben”<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – dacht ik er van kortweg: dat’s kwaad genoeg<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat zou ik niet gedacht hebben indien ge b.v. hadt kunnen schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben iets op ’t spoor op ’t gebied van drukkerij b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> of – ik heb eenige flinke nieuwe artisten ontdekt met wie ik wel wat zal kunnen doen – enfin al wat ge wilt op ’t gebied van werk of kunst hadde ik opperbest gevonden maar – finantieel gebied – neem me niet kwalijk – dat is mij te veel in de lucht.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Nu kerel – neemt gij ’t mij kwalijk ik niet volkomen gerust ben U aangaande? en tweedens<c type="kk">/</c> gelooft ge dat ik hier ook niet de dingen U aangaande verwar met mijn eigen zaken als zijnde in zekeren zin van de Uwen afhankelijk<c type="kp">_</c>– al zijn mijn zaken van de Uwen afhankelijk<c type="kk">/</c> toch het is niet daarover dat ik ongerust ben nu – mijn ongerustheid is regelregt over U – over U als mensch – als man – als regtschapen<c type="kk">/</c> eerlijk man<c type="kp">_</c>– En mijne vraag<c type="kk">/</c> zult gij geen schade lijden en achteruitgaan – als mensch – indien ik er toe kom die vraag te stellen<c type="kk">/</c> het is omdat Parijs Parijs is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ik zeg niet dat ik van mij zelf weet ik altijd die geestkracht zou hebben<c type="kk">/</c> dus ik spreek niet van mij zelf maar van een persoon uit ver verleden. Die<c type="kk">/</c> zegt men<c type="kk">/</c> toen hij voelde dat hij op een betooverden grond in een betooverde atmosfeer was waar hij voelde hij ontzenuwd werd<c type="kk">/</c> kort en bondig op een balk of vlot van het bewuste eiland in volle zee zich waagde<c type="kk">/</c> denkende: de zee is zóó gevaarlijk niet als <hi rend="italics">dit</hi> en <hi rend="italics">dat</hi>. En mijns inziens was die man magtig wijs<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">Dit</hi> en <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> moet ge mij permitteeren ik het niet defineere maar alleen er van zegge<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn dingen waarvan men weten moet dat ze iemand zachtjes aan betooveren en in korten tijd veranderen kunnen tot het precies tegenovergestelde van waar men heen ging zoolang men opregt was<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Mijn woorden mogen somber zijn – goed<c type="kp">_</c>– Voor mij zelf heb ik wel oogenblikken dat alles mij zeer duister is in eigen vooruitzigten – toch<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ik U reeds schreef<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof niet dat mijn lot afhankelijk is van wat er tegen schijne. Zij tegen mij van allerlei<c type="kk">/</c> er <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> iets zijn magtiger dan ’t geen ik zie dreigen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik noemde ’t woord fataliteit<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – bij gebrek aan een beter woord – wie nog niet vallen moet zal ook nog niet vallen<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo betreffende mij zelf geef ik het over en doe als of er niets gaande was<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Betreffende U<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als ik zeide<c type="kk">/</c> zoolang ik geloof in Uw opregtheid<c type="kk">/</c> en nu geloof ik het tegendeel nog niet<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik ook dat ondanks geluk of ongeluk gij veilig zijt<c type="kk">/</c> al ware het <hi rend="italics">alleen</hi> in die bewuste werkelijkheid die zweeft boven den schijn der dingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar ik moest glimlagchen over wat zij t’huis schreven over een “goeden” brief – met een enkel algemeen woord waar ik overigens niets van weet – en dat het scheen de zaken weer een gunstiger keer hadden genomen. Ik dacht: goed – indien gijlieden zegt dat gij gerust zijt<c type="kk">/</c> wees gijlieden dan gerust<c type="kp">_</c>– Meer dacht ik er echter niet van als dat<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Indien de enkele zin in bewusten brief over U eindigde met: “doch in ’t volgende jaar verwacht men<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> er belangrijke gebeurtenissen zullen plaats hebben en wij hopen maar dat hij (n<c type="kp">_</c>l. dus gij) daar geen schade door lijden zult”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-b"/> zoo kwam ’t mij voor die gebeurtenissen in kwestie aan U als man zooveel niet af of toe zullen doen<c type="kk">/</c> doch de kwestie zal veeleer zijn een what shall he do with it<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> – met zijn karakter<c type="kk">/</c> aanleg – <hi rend="italics">ziel</hi> in een woord – kwestie in mijn oog tot heden onbeslist<c type="kp">_</c>– Afhangende van eigen nadenken en eigen willen zeer zeker voor een hoogst belangrijk deel<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar weet dit eene broer – dat welke keuze gij doen moogt of welke beslissing nemen of niet nemen – dat ’t zij gij in mijn oog beter worden mogt of slechter – en tevens of al dan niet er ten opzigte van geld of zaken direkte rapporten meer of minder zullen blijven tusschen ons<c type="kk">/</c> dit door <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> zal worden opgevat als een elkaar den rug toe draaien<c type="kp">_</c>– Verschil van zienswijs<c type="kk">/</c> verschil van levensopvatting<c type="kk">/</c> verschil van beginselen zelfs (gesteld die later ons blijken mogten – nu zijn ze zoozeer nog <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> gebleken) zijn voor <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> nog <hi rend="italics">geen</hi> redenen om weg te cijferen wat daadzaak is<c type="kk">/</c> dat wij broers zijn n<c type="kp">_</c>l. en in veel punten overeenkomsten hebben<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik druk hier eens op<c type="kk">/</c> juist tot wederzijdsche geruststelling hoop ik<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gij hebt Uw vrijheid<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb mijn vrijheid om te handelen zooals het ons het meest raisonable toeschijnt<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar<c type="kp">_</c> En blijft men dit steeds op den voorgrond stellen<c type="kk">/</c> dat men ’t elkaar niet kwalijk neemt of vijandig is of hatelijk wordt of elkaars leven bemoeielijkt wegens eventueel verschil van inzigt<c type="kk">/</c> zoo blijven de dingen ondanks er eens een tijd van meerdere koelheid moge ontstaan ten minste goddank buiten dweeperij of intrigue. Wat helaas niet altijd met iedereen ’t geval is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Zoo ook betreffende ’t geld waarover ik begon te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik PRIMO bedoel is<c type="kk">/</c> laat er nooit twist komen tusschen ons daaromtrent en weet dat ik natuurlijkerwijs niet in ’t minst het u kwalijk neem als gij het niet hebt<c type="kk">/</c> ook niet al ben ik soms fameus in moeielijkheden er over<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">En betreffende het kapitaal er reeds ingestoken door U en door mij<c type="kk">/</c> want ik steek er toch mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> enfin mijzelf met huid &amp; haar in – betreffende dat een &amp; ander – ik heb steeds nog wel degelijk hoop op teregtkomen daarvan in de toekomst – ofschoon<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon – misschien niet alleen ik maar gij ook van Uw kant in een paar dingen ons vergist hebben – die evenwel in elk geval nog niet fataal of onherstelbaar zijn – en waarop ik nu niet eens komen wil<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Zie gij in dit schrijven als in voorgaande brieven niet een wantrouwen<c type="kk">/</c> niet een verdenking<c type="kk">/</c> niet een beleediging<c type="kk">/</c> zie er in een waarschuwing betreffende sommige Parijsche dingen die ik U in bedenking geef<c type="kk">/</c> niet als of ik onfeilbaar ware<c type="kk">/</c> niet als of ik eischen zou van U het met mij eens te zijn – maar wegens ik zekere symptomen zoo meen te bespeuren die mij van raadselachtigen en onheil<c type="shy">-</c>spellenden aard voorkomen te wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">En ja – <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> het er nu uit – ik vraag niet eens om een antwoord – zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> ik verzoek U het niet eens als een vraag te beschouwen maar als een woord<c type="kk">/</c> om U volkomen duidelijk te maken ik een <hi rend="italics">ongerustheid</hi> heb nog <hi rend="italics">in</hi> <hi rend="italics">de</hi> algemeene <hi rend="italics">ongerustheid</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin de kern van veel is – de vrouw van U<c type="kk">/</c> is zij goed? is zij opregt?</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Is zij <hi rend="italics">eenvoudig</hi><c type="kk">/</c> staat zij op den gewonen grond<c type="kk">/</c> ofwel loopt er een onkruidje van een wat gevaarlijke zucht naar wat ik nu maar grootheid zal noemen onder haar tarwe<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Ik dacht aan lady Macbeth<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Macbeth was eerlijk man maar – – – – maar – werd betooverd en stond toen hij en zij wakker werden voor meer en erger kwaad dan hun bedoeling geweest was<c type="kp">_</c>– En Macbeth viel – maar met een <hi rend="italics">grooten</hi> val.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Als het kan stel me gerust – betreffende calamiteiten<c type="kk">/</c> dat is niet waar ik zoo bijzonder bang voor ben – over ’t geheel moet men niet vreezen dan alleen voor slechter worden<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij weet nu ’t allervoornaamste ook waar ik soms zorg over heb als ik aan U denk<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ziedaar<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben nu ruw omdat ik ronduit wou zeggen ik zoo heel dankbaar zoude zijn indien ik op dat punt gerustgesteld was<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Naar bijzonderheden herhaal ik ik in ’t allerminst niet vraag. Maar er zijn nu eenmaal mannen die vallen op die manier. En er zijn mannen die in tijds keeren<c type="kp">_</c>– Is eene vrouw eenvoudig goed zoo is ’t een zegen – maar er is gevaar waar de vrouw schitteren zou willen voor de wereld<c type="kk">/</c> dat zij een man laaghartig make<c type="kp">_</c>– Deze ziekte te noemen is iets anders dan te zeggen dit Uw geval is<c type="kk">/</c> niet waar<c type="kk">/</c> en integendeel ik vraag<c type="kk">/</c> zeg één woord en ik zal volkomen gerust zijn en niet verder vragen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">De vrouw met wie ik was<c type="kk">/</c> wie is ze – eene hoer<c type="kk">/</c> al geschonden van de pokken<c type="kk">/</c> al verwelkt en verouderd<c type="kk">/</c> al moeder van 2 kinderen – o – zij is geen <hi rend="italics">goede</hi> vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> que soit – maar hier heeft het ongeluk die hoogte bereikt dat zij geen lady Macbeth meer zou hebben <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> wezen<c type="kk">/</c> en betreffende verleiding dus<c type="kk">/</c> indien in vroeger jaren zij misschien <hi rend="italics">leelijk</hi> slecht is geweest<c type="kk">/</c> juist het ongeluk heeft de kracht tot kwaad doen zóó gekortwiekt (gesteld die had bestaan en ik ben daar niet eens zeker van) dat verleiding zoo moeielijk ooit in de termen zou hebben kunnen vallen nu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">En ik zeg dus niet tegen U wat ik zeg als wilde ik rapporten maken<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat er zooveel verschil is zou er geene kans zijn van het bovengenoemde lady Macbeth achtige in mijn betrekking met de vrouw van mij<c type="kk">/</c> doch gij staat tegenover eene persoonlijkheid die een magt van charmeeren heeft en die charme kan fataal zijn indien aangewend in rigting wereldsche ambitie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Betreffende mij<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat de vrouw met wie ik was iemand is door en door ongelukkig en zoo zwaar belast met een slechten naam<c type="kk">/</c> 2 kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> armoede &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik<c type="kk">/</c> al vond 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>ik haar niet goed<c type="kk">/</c> niet alle banden breken willen en ter wille van niemand zou ik het laten haar te zien<c type="kk">/</c> te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> wat geld te zenden als ik ’t eventueel had<c type="kp">_</c> Laat de menschen daar iets van denken of zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> best<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb al lang ’t hun niet eens meer kwalijk genomen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Maar ziehier<c type="kk">/</c> bij U <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> er zijn een invloed van charme dat misschien zeer gewigtige hartesnaren<c type="kk">/</c> die van gevoel voor regt en onregt<c type="kk">/</c> verdoofd. Ik zeg niet dat dit zoo is<c type="kk">/</c> herhaal ik nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik vraag zelfs niet: is het zóó<c type="kk">/</c> herhaal ik nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik noem het als een wenk dien ik wenk<c type="kk">/</c> maar dien gegeven hebbende wegens er een soort van mogelijkheid zou kunnen zijn ik ’t er ook bij laat en niet volg met mijn gedachten verder. En ook meen deze zorg van mij geexcuseerd zal worden door U en mij niet kwalijk genomen in geval van geen raison d’être hebben er van<c type="kk">/</c> welk geval ik hoop wij hier mee te maken hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Hebt ge mijn studies ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Sedert maakte ik eene groote geschilderde en een groote geteekende studie van een ophaalbrug en nog een tweede geschilderde er van zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> met ander effekt.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Die zoodra wij sneeuw krijgen ik hoop te gebruiken om met meer juistheid het sneeuweffekt eens aan te pakken<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dezelfde nu gevonden lijnen &amp; in elkaar zitten houden. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop spoedig van U te hooren – welken invloed deze of die gebeurtenis die nog niet eens precies aan den horizon is hebben zal op U<c type="kk">/</c> denk ik bijzonder weinig over doch wel denk ik zoo als ge ziet over U zelf als mensch<c type="kk">/</c> over ’t what shall he do with it – met Uw werkkracht en persoonlijke energie ook. Met een handdruk<c type="kk">/</c> geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Gisteren berigt dat Furnee door zijn laatste examen is en nu weer zijn handen vrij heeft om door te gaan met zijn begonnen schilderen.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">ofschoon het niet mijn eerste preoccupatie moge zijn<c type="kk">/</c> toch ’t is me verre van onverschillig hoe het in elkaar zit van die kwestie van <hi rend="italics">bijna</hi> <hi rend="italics">10</hi> <hi rend="italics">dagen</hi> verschil in ontvangst van het geld.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">May I draw your attention to the fact that the post of Monday, 26 Nov. has just been without having brought your letter.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> That because it still has to go to Hoogeveen and back,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> we’ve now reached a point where it’s almost the same as if I hadn’t had the usual once, for supposing the next post brings the letter, I won’t receive the money before late evening on 28 Nov. or the morning of 29 Nov.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Consequently this is actually a deficit, because your next letter, namely the one that I’d otherwise have thought I could expect around 1 Dec., will probably not come. Because since I’ve been here in Nieuw-Amsterdam the letters have come later and later each time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">If I’d received a word of warning in accordance with our agreement, it wouldn’t have engendered in me this feeling that, little by little, I cannot help getting slightly. Namely that some ambiguity is beginning to creep into our relationship, which began by being sincere, by mutually understanding and respecting each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well, that the above-mentioned is a disappointment to me and very palpably distresses me, even aside from thoughts that I can’t exactly help welling up in me, still isn’t the most pressing thing on my mind today.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It is, rather, a vague disquiet about you, although — perhaps precisely <hi rend="italics">because</hi> — I heard from home only yesterday that they’d had a good letter from you. From this, then, I would infer that that particular crisis has been suppressed, averted, stopped; well, whatever you want to call it. And that 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> this, then, would be a confirmation of your words to me, ‘I think that things will stay as they are for the time being’. As to which, however, I already hinted that it only half pleased me,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> or rather that it worried me much more than reassured me about your future. I just hope that you will understand and not <hi rend="italics">mis</hi>understand me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">At this moment I don’t suspect you of insincerity — please hold on to that as my starting-point.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Because I thus believe in you as an honest man, I reckon you to be relatively safe up till now despite everything, even in the event of a catastrophe.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But now comes the point where I fear you run a risk — are vulnerable. Suppose everything that threatened is averted, suppose everything has calmed down, I’d like to remind you of the saying: don’t fear the storm but dread the <hi rend="italics">calm, treacherous, enchanted</hi> ground.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Suppose you are slowly and imperceptibly carried along by a silent current into other waters rather than forging <hi rend="italics">straight</hi> ahead. Suppose that what I’ll call — forgive the expression — poison in the Paris atmosphere — the Jesuitism of its miasma — seeps insidiously into your pores — imperceptible to you — but nevertheless you’ll begin to notice its effect yourself in a few years — I’ve strayed from the course — I’m <hi rend="italics">too</hi> insincere, have become too little myself, and I’ve yielded <hi rend="italics">too much</hi> to just seeking prosperity. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Brother — when you recently wrote ‘I believe I’m on to a new idea in the financial sphere’<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> — I just thought: that’s bad enough. I wouldn’t have thought that if, say, you’d been able to write, I’m on to something in the sphere of printing, for instance, or — I’ve discovered some bold new artists with whom I’ll be able to do something — in short, I’d have found anything you like in the field of work or art capital, but — financial sphere — I’m sorry — it’s too much up in the air for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Well, old chap, do you take it amiss that I’m not completely at ease about you? And secondly, do you believe that I’m not confusing the things that concern you with my own affairs, as being in a sense dependent on yours? Although my affairs are dependent on yours, that isn’t what’s worrying me now — my worry is purely about you — about you as a human being — as a man — as an upright, honest man. As to my question, will you not suffer harm and go downhill — as a human being? If I bring myself to ask this question it’s because Paris is Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I don’t say that I know that I would always have that strength of mind, so I don’t speak of myself but of a person from the distant past. He, so they say, when he felt that he was on enchanted ground in an enchanted atmosphere, where he felt he was being enervated, resolutely ventured from the island in question, on a beam or raft, into the open sea, thinking: the sea isn’t as dangerous as <hi rend="italics">this</hi> and <hi rend="italics">that</hi>. And in my view that man was very wise.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">You must permit me not to define <hi rend="italics">this</hi> and <hi rend="italics">that</hi>, but simply say of it, there are things that one must be aware can enchant someone insidiously and can in a short time turn one precisely the opposite way from where one was going as long as one was honest.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">My words may be gloomy — very well. As to myself, I have moments when all my own prospects seem very dark to me — yet, as I already wrote to you, I don’t believe that my fate is dependent on what may appear to be against it. Even if all manner of things are against me, there <hi rend="italics">can</hi> be something more powerful than what I see threatening. I used the word fatality<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — for want of a better word — he who doesn’t have to fall yet, won’t fall. So as for myself, I submit to it and act as if nothing was the matter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">As for you, as I said, as long as I believe in your sincerity, and I don’t yet believe the opposite, I also believe that, despite good fortune or ill fortune, you are safe, albeit <hi rend="italics">only</hi> in that particular reality that hovers above the appearance of things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But I had to smile about what they wrote from home with a single, general word about a ‘good’ letter — and I know nothing more about it than this, and that it seemed that things had taken a more favourable turn. I thought: good — if you people say that you’re at ease, then let you people be at ease. I didn’t think any more of it than that, though. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">If the single sentence about you in the letter in question ended with: ‘but in the coming year they<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> expect that important events will take place and we just hope that he (you, in other words) won’t suffer any harm from them,’ it occurred to me that the events in question won’t add to or detract from you much as a man, but the question will rather be: what shall he do with it?<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> — with his character, aptitude — <hi rend="italics">soul</hi> in a word — question in my view undecided thus far — very certainly dependent to a highly significant degree on one’s own reflections and own will. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But know this one thing, brother — that whatever choice you may make or whatever decision you take or don’t take — that whether you’d become better or worse in my view — and also whether or not more or less direct rapport with regard to money or business will remain between us, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> will <hi rend="italics">not</hi> conceive of this as our turning our backs on each other. Difference of perspective, difference of outlook on life, difference even of principles (supposing they might become apparent to us later — now they have <hi rend="italics">not</hi> yet become so apparent) are still <hi rend="italics">no</hi> reason for <hi rend="italics">me</hi> to ignore what is a fact, namely that we’re brothers and have many points in common. I stress this here above all for our mutual reassurance, I hope.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You have your freedom, I have my freedom, to act as appears the most reasonable to us, haven’t we? And provided one always keeps this in the forefront — that one doesn’t blame the other or is hostile or becomes malicious, or makes the other’s life difficult on account of some difference of opinion — although there may be a time of greater coolness, at least things will, thank God, remain free of fantasy or intrigue. Which sadly isn’t always the case with everyone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"> It’s the same as regards the money, which I started by writing about, what I mean FIRST AND FOREMOST is: let there never be any dispute about it between us, and know that of course I don’t hold it against you in the slightest if you don’t have it, not even though I’m sometimes hugely in difficulties because of it. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And as regards the capital already invested in it by you and by me, for after all I’m investing my work, in fact every fibre of my being — as regards all this — I still have a real hope of its working out in the future — although, although — perhaps not only I, but you too for your part have been mistaken about a few things — which, however, aren’t yet fatal or irreparable in any event — and which I don’t even want to touch on now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Don’t regard this letter or previous letters as mistrustful, as suspicious, as insulting, regard them as a warning about some Parisian things that I ask you to consider, not as if I were infallible, not as if I’d demand that you agree with me — but because I believe I detect certain symptoms that seem to me to be of a puzzling and ominous nature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">And yes — now it <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be said — I don’t even ask for an answer — in fact, I ask you not even to consider it as a question but as a statement, in order to make it absolutely clear to you that I have another <hi rend="italics">concern within the </hi>general<hi rend="italics"> concern</hi>. In short, the crux of a great deal is — this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">woman</rs> of yours, is she good? Is she sincere? Is she <hi rend="italics">simple</hi>, does she stand on the ordinary ground, or is there a little weed of a rather dangerous desire for what I’ll call greatness running through her wheat?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I was thinking of Lady Macbeth.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Macbeth was an honest man, but — — — — but — was enchanted, and when he and she woke up, was faced with more and worse evil than had been their intention. And Macbeth fell — but with a <hi rend="italics">great</hi> fall.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Reassure me if you can — as for disasters, that’s not what I’m so terribly afraid of — on the whole one shouldn’t fear anything other than becoming worse. Now you know the chief thing I sometimes worry about when I think of you. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">There you are, I’m being harsh now because I wanted to say straight out that I would be so very thankful if I was reassured on that point.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I repeat, I don’t in the least ask for particulars. But the fact remains that there are men who fall in that way. And there are men who turn back in time. If a woman is simply good, well it’s a blessing — but there’s a danger, when the woman wants to shine in the eyes of the world, that she might make a man base. Mentioning this sickness isn’t the same as saying that this is your case, is it? — and on the contrary I ask, say one word and I’ll be completely reassured and not ask any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> I was with, who is she? — a whore, already marked by the pox, already withered and aged, already mother of 2 children — oh — she isn’t a <hi rend="italics">good</hi> woman, all right — but here, misfortune has reached such a height that she <hi rend="italics">could </hi>not have been a Lady Macbeth any more, and so as to temptation, if in former years she has perhaps been <hi rend="italics">deeply </hi>wicked, her very misfortune has so curtailed the power to do harm (assuming it had existed, and I’m not at all sure of that) that there could hardly have been any question of temptation now. And so I don’t say what I say to you because I wanted to strike a rapport; precisely because there’s so much difference, there would be no chance of the above-mentioned Lady Macbeth effect in my relations with my woman, but you’re faced with a personality that has the power of charm, and that charm could be fatal if it were directed towards worldly ambition.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">As for me, precisely because the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> I was with is someone who is unhappy through and through and so heavily burdened with a bad name, 2 children, poverty &amp;c., that, even if 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/> I thought she wasn’t good, I wouldn’t want to break all the ties, and I wouldn’t let anyone stop me from seeing her, speaking to her, writing to her, sending her some money if I should have any. Let people think something of it or talk about it, fine, I’ve long since ceased even to take it amiss.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">But look here; in your case charm <hi rend="italics">could</hi> perhaps have the effect of numbing very important heartstrings, those governing the sense of right and wrong. I don’t say that this is so, I repeat once more, I don’t even ask: is it so? I repeat once more, I mention it just as a hint that I hint, but having given it because there could be a sort of possibility, I’ll leave it at that and not pursue it any further in my thoughts. And also believe you’ll excuse this concern of mine and not take it amiss should it have no <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi>, which is what I hope we’re dealing with here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Have you received my studies?<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> I’ve since made a large painted study and a large drawing of a drawbridge, and even a second painted one of it, with a different effect.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> I hope to use them as soon as we get snow to tackle the snow effect more accurately, that is keeping the same lines and way it fits together as I’ve found now. Well, I hope to hear from you soon — I think very little about what effect one event or another that isn’t yet exactly on the horizon will have on you, but I do, as you see, think about you as a human being, about the ‘what shall he do with it’ — with your capacity for work and personal energy too. With a handshake, believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Heard yesterday that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">Furnée</rs> passed his final exam and now has his hands free again to get on with painting again.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Although it may not be my first preoccupation, I’m nonetheless far from indifferent as to what’s happening in this question of <hi rend="italics">almost 10 days’</hi> difference in receipt of the money.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes that the post of ‘Monday, 26 Nov. has just been’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, thus establishing the date of the letter as Monday, 26 November 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back on his time with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See for cashing the allowance Theo sent: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let402.xml#n-14">letter 402, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>As appears from a letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> to Theo, the previous allowance on 10 November had been larger than usual, evidently because Theo foresaw that around the 20th he would not be in a position to send the customary amount (FR b2247). Vincent had apparently failed to understand this. See further <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let408.xml#n-8">letter 408, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let406.xml">letter 406</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The source of this quote has not been found. ‘Enchanted Ground’ is a key concept in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_558">Bunyan</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_103">A pilgrim’s progress</ref></hi> and is a metaphor for sham, deceit, the wrong way. ‘Don’t fear the storm’ is the title of a gospel song. Cf. also the phrases ‘terre enchantée’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let507.xml">letter 507</ref>) and ‘terrain enchanté’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let822.xml">letter 822</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘geworden’ (become).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In view of what follows, this means a new idea for financial investment or speculation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This is a reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_655">Homer</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_144">Odyssey</ref></hi>. Odysseus’s ship is wrecked and he is washed ashore, clinging to a spar, on the island of Ogygia, where he is held captive and seduced by the nymph Calypso. Although she gives him everything he might be supposed to desire, the hero spends most of his time bemoaning his fate and proclaiming his homesickness for his native land. On the orders of the gods he is given the chance to build a raft of tree trunks and take to the sea. Poseidon sends fierce storms to test him, but his courage does not fail and, after twenty days, he reaches the land of the Phaeacians. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, book 5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh writes about ‘fatality’ in this context in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let397.xml">letters 397</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let401.xml">401</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Theo’s employers in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘zal’ (will). The error was caused by the ‘gij’ (you) in the brackets.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This may be an allusion to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_365">What will he do with it?</ref></hi> (1859) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_702">Edward Bulwer-Lytton</rs>; cf. also <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_366">Othello</ref></hi>, act 3, scene 3: ‘What he will do with it / Heaven knows, not I’. See Shakespeare 1882, p. 91.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 13:25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh queries <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_508">Marie</rs>’s motives, and fears that she could have the same malign influence on Theo as Lady Macbeth had on her husband. For Lady Macbeth in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_357">Macbeth</ref></hi> (c. 1606-1607), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let388.xml#n-14">see letter 388, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Macbeth was bewitched and allowed his wife to persuade him to murder the king so that he could become king himself. In the end, he is murdered too. (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_357">Macbeth</ref></hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means the six studies that he said he had sent in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let406.xml">letter 406</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The two painted studies are not known; the ‘large drawing’ is the watercolour <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Drawbridge in Nieuw-Amsterdam</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2449">F 1098 / JH 425</rs>), which measures 38.5 x 81 cm. Details of the location in: Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 242-245.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>While he was in The Hague, Van Gogh had given lessons to the surveyor <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">Antoine Philippe Furnée</rs>, the son of a paint supplier, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let362.xml">see letter 362</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    