<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 7 December 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let410"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b370 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>410</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>345</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>412</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-07">on or about Friday, 7 December 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0370" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0370" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000482_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ik lag den halven nacht wakker Theo<c type="kk">/</c> nadat ik U gisteren avond geschreven had<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik ben zielsbedroefd over het verschijnsel dat<c type="kk">/</c> toen nu na twee jaar afwezigheid ik terug kom<c type="kk">/</c> de ontvangst t’huis wel ten allerzeerste vriendelijk en lief was doch in den grond niets<c type="kk">/</c> niets<c type="kk">/</c> niets is veranderd van die wat ik moet noemen verblindheid en onverstand tot in ’t desperate toe wat aangaat het inzien der positie<c type="kp">_</c> Dat namelijk wij waren op den allerbesten weg tot op het moment dat Pa – niet in drift alleen maar ook “omdat hij het moede was”<c type="kk">/</c> mij het huis verbood<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Er had toen moeten begrepen worden dat zulks iets zóó importants was voor mijn slagen of niet slagen<c type="kk">/</c> dat tiendubbel moeielijk het mij werd gemaakt daardoor – haast onhoudbaar<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Indien ik alstoen niet gevoeld had ook datzelfde dat ik nu ook weer voel<c type="kk">/</c> dat ondanks alle goede intenties<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks alle vriendelijkheid in het ontvangen<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks al wat ge wilt er een zekere ijzerhardheid en ijskoude<c type="kk">/</c> iets dat schrijnt als droog zand<c type="kk">/</c> glas of blik is in Pa – ondanks al zijn uiterlijke zachtheid – indien ik alstoen<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> dat niet reeds had gevoeld als nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik zoude toen ook het zoo hoog niet hebben opgenomen. Ik ben ook nu weer in een slingering en tweestrijd haast ondragelijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Gij begrijpt wel dat ik niet zou schrijven zooals ik schrijf – zelf uit eigen beweging de reis herwaarts ondernomen hebbende<c type="kk">/</c> mijn eigen trots gebogen hebbende het eerst – als er niet werkelijk iets was waar ik op stuit.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als ik nu gezien had dat er eenig EMPRESSEMENT was om te doen zoo als de Rappards hebben doorgevoerd met de beste resultaten<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en zoo als wij hier begonnen ook met goede resultaten<c type="kk">/</c> als ik nu gezien had dat Pa ook had ingezien dat hij mij het huis <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> had moeten sluiten<c type="kk">/</c> ik ware gerust geweest op de toekomst<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Niets<c type="kk">/</c> niets van dat alles. Toen was er<c type="kk">/</c> nu is er bij Pa geen zweem<c type="kk">/</c> geen schijn of schaduw van twijfeling of hij toen goed gedaan heeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Pa kent het berouw niet zoo als gij en ik en ieder die menschelijk is<c type="kp">_</c> Pa gelooft in zijn eigen geregtigheid terwijl gij<c type="kk">/</c> ik en andere menschelijke menschen doordrongen zijn van het gevoel dat wij <hi rend="italics">bestaan</hi> uit vergissingen en efforts de perdu<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik beklaag menschen als Pa<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">ik kan niet boos op hun worden in mijn hart</hi> omdat ik vind dat zij ongelukkiger zijn dan ik zelf<c type="kp">_</c> Waarom vind ik hen ongelukkiger – omdat zelfs het goede dat in hen is verkeerd door hen toegepast wordt en werkt als kwaad – omdat het <hi rend="italics">licht</hi> dat in hun is zwart is – donkerheid<c type="kk">/</c> duisternis<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> rondom hen verspreid. Hun hartelijke ontvangst desoleert mij – hun <hi rend="italics">zich</hi> <hi rend="italics">schikken</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zonder de vergissing in te zien<c type="kk">/</c> is voor mij zoo mogelijk erger dan de vergissing zelf<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">In plaats van grif te begrijpen en gevolgelijk en mijn en indirekt hun eigen welzijn met een zekere vurigheid te bevorderen<c type="kk">/</c> gevoel ik in alles een draling en aarzeling die mijn eigen lust en energie verlamt als een looden dampkring<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Mijn mannelijk verstand zegt mij dat ik het moet beschouwen als onherroepelijke fatale daadzaak dat Pa en ik tot in ’t diepste diep onverzoenlijk zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Mijn compassie en met Pa en met mij zelf zegt mij “onverzoenlijk? <hi rend="italics">nooit</hi>” – tot in ’t oneindige bestaat er mogelijkheid<c type="kk">/</c> moet men geloof hebben in de mogelijkheid eener definitieve verzoening. Maar dat laatste<c type="kk">/</c> ach waarom is het helaas waarschijnlijk “eene illusie”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Zult gij dit vinden een te zwaar tillen der dingen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ons leven is eene ontzettende werkelijkheid en wij zelf loopen tot in ’t oneindige, wat is – is – en onze opvatting<c type="kk">/</c> zwaarder of minder zwaar<c type="kk">/</c> doet niets af of toe aan het wezen der dingen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Zoo denk ik er over bijvoorbeeld s’nachts als ik wakker ben<c type="kk">/</c> of zoo denk ik er over in den storm op de heide s’avonds in de trieste schemering<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Over dag in ’t dagelijks leven zie ik er soms even ongevoelig uit als een wild varken misschien en kan ik mij best begrijpen dat de menschen <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> grof vinden.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Toen ik jonger was dacht ik zelf ook veel meer als nu dat het hem zat in toevalligheden of kleine dingen of misverstanden die geen gronden hadden. Maar ouder wordende kom ik meer en meer daarvan terug en zie dieper gronden. Het leven is ook “een raar ding”<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> broer.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Gij ziet wel hoe geschokt mijn brieven zijn<c type="kk">/</c> nu eens denk ik <hi rend="italics">het kan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dan weer <hi rend="italics">het kan niet</hi>. Een ding blijkt er mij uit<c type="kk">/</c> dat het niet <hi rend="italics">grif</hi> gaat<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als ik zeide<c type="kk">/</c> dat er geen “empressement” is. Ik heb besloten eens naar Rappard te gaan en hem te zeggen dat ik zelf ook het goed zou vinden als ik t’huis kon zijn<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat tegenover al de voordeelen die het hebben zou staat een je ne sais quoi met Pa dat ik helaas begin voor ongeneesselijk te houden en dat mij lusteloos en magteloos maakt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Gisteren avond wordt beslist dat ik een tijd hier zijn zal<c type="kk">/</c> den volgenden morgen<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks alles<c type="kk">/</c> heet het weer – laat ons er nog eens over verzinnen.– Ja wel<c type="kk">/</c> nachtjes er op slapen en bezinnen!!! <hi rend="italics">als</hi> <hi rend="italics">men</hi> <hi rend="italics">er</hi> <hi rend="italics">2</hi> JAAR <hi rend="italics">over</hi> <hi>had kunnen</hi> denken<c type="kk">/</c> <hi>had moeten</hi> denken van zelf<c type="kk">/</c> als iets natuurlijks<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Twee jaar voor mij elken dag een dag van zorg<c type="kk">/</c> voor hen – het gewone leven – als of er niets gebeurd was of niets gebeuren zou<c type="kk">/</c> op hun heeft de last niet gedrukt<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij zegt<c type="kk">/</c> zij uiten het niet maar voelen het<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi>dat geloof ik niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb het wel eens zelf gedacht maar het is <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">in</hi> <hi rend="italics">den</hi> <hi rend="italics">haak</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Wat men <hi>voelt</hi><c type="kk">/</c> DAAR <hi rend="italics">handelt</hi> men naar<c type="kp">_</c>– Onze <hi>handelingen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ons vlug willen of ons aarzelen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">daar zijn wij aan te kennen</hi> – niet aan wat wij zeggen met de lippen<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – vriendelijk of onvriendelijk<c type="kp">_</c> Goede intenties<c type="kk">/</c> meeningen<c type="kk">/</c> eigentlijk is dat <hi rend="italics">minder</hi> dan <hi rend="italics">niets</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gij moogt van mij denken wat gij goedvindt Theo maar ik zeg U dat het geen verbeelding van mij is<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Pa wil niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik zie nu wat ik zag <hi rend="italics">toen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik sprak toen vierkant TEGEN Pa<c type="kk">/</c> ik spreek nu <hi rend="italics">in elk geval</hi><c type="kk">/</c> hoe het ook loope<c type="kk">/</c> wederom TEGEN PA<c type="kk">/</c> als <hi rend="italics">willende</hi> NIET<c type="kk">/</c> als makende het ONMOGELIJK. Het is verdomd beroerd broer<c type="kk">/</c> de Rappards handelden intelligent<c type="kk">/</c> maar hier!!!!!! En al wat gij er aan deed en doet<c type="kk">/</c> het wordt 3/4 vruchteloos door <hi rend="italics">hen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Het is lam<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> broer. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Om een vriendelijke of onvriendelijke ontvangst geef ik minder<c type="kk">/</c> het smart mij zij geen spijt hebben van ’t geen zij toen deden. Zij denken <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> ZIJ <hi rend="italics">toen</hi> NIETS GEDAAN HEBBEN en dat is mij te bar<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I lay awake half the night, Theo, after I’d written to you yesterday evening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’m heartbroken about the fact that when I come back now, after an absence of two years, the reception at home was as friendly and kind as could be, yet at bottom nothing, nothing, nothing has changed in what I have to call blindness and stupidity to the point of desperation when it comes to understanding the situation. Which was that we were going along in the very best of ways until the moment when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> banned me from the house — not just in a passion but also ‘because he was tired of it’.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It should have been understood then that this was something <hi rend="italics">so</hi> important to my succeeding or not succeeding that it was made ten times more difficult for me because of it — almost intolerable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">If I hadn’t felt the same then as I feel again now, that despite all the good intentions, despite all the friendliness of the reception, despite whatever you will, there’s a certain steely hardness and icy coldness, something in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> that grates like dry sand, glass or tin — despite all his outward mildness — if I hadn’t already, I say, felt it then as I do now, I wouldn’t have taken it so badly then. Now I’m once again in almost unbearable indecision and inner conflict.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You understand that I wouldn’t write as I write — having undertaken the journey here of my own volition, having been the first to swallow my pride — if there wasn’t really something I’m running up against. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If I had now seen that there was any WILLINGNESS to do as the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_135 bio.xml#_183">Rappards</rs> did with the best results<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and as we began here, also with good results, if I had now seen that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> had also realized that he should <hi rend="italics">not</hi> have barred the house to me, I would have been reassured about the future.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Nothing, nothing of all that. There wasn’t then, nor is there now any trace, any hint of a shadow of a doubt in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> as to whether he did the right thing then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> doesn’t know remorse as you and I and everyone who is human does. Pa believes in his own righteousness while you, I and other human beings are permeated with the feeling that we <hi rend="italics">consist</hi> of mistakes and forlorn attempts.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I pity people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, <hi rend="italics">I can’t find it in my heart to be angry with them</hi> because I believe that they’re unhappier than I am myself. Why do I think they’re unhappier? Because they use even the good in them wrongly so that it works as evil — because the <hi rend="italics">light</hi> that’s in them is black — spreads darkness, gloom<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> around them. Their friendly reception desolates me — to me, the way they <hi rend="italics">make the best of it</hi>, without recognizing the mistake, is even worse, if possible, than the mistake itself. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Instead of readily understanding and consequently promoting both my and indirectly their own well-being with a degree of fervour, I sense a procrastination and hesitancy in everything, which paralyzes my own passion and energy like a leaden atmosphere.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">My intellect as a man tells me that I have to regard it as an unalterable fact of fate that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and I are irreconcilable down to the deepest depths. My compassion both for Pa and for myself tells me ‘irreconcilable? <hi rend="italics">never</hi>’ — until eternity there’s a chance, one has to believe in the chance of an ultimate reconciliation. But the latter, oh why is it sadly probably ‘an illusion’?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Will you think that I’m making too much of things? Our life is an awful reality and we ourselves go on into eternity, what is — is — and our view, weighty or less weighty, takes nothing from and adds nothing to the essence of things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">That’s how I think about it when I’m lying awake at night, for instance, or that’s how I think about it in the storm in the sad twilight in the evening on the heath.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Perhaps I sometimes appear as insensitive as a wild pig during the day in everyday life, and I can readily understand that people find <hi rend="italics">me</hi> coarse.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> When I was younger I used to think much more than now that the problem lay in coincidences or little things or misunderstandings that were groundless. But as I get older I draw back from that more and more, and I see deeper grounds. Life’s ‘an odd thing’,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> brother. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">You can see how up and down my letters are, first I think <hi rend="italics">it’s possible</hi>, then again <hi rend="italics">it’s impossible</hi>. One thing is clear to me, that it doesn’t happen <hi rend="italics">readily</hi>, as I said, that there’s no ‘willingness’. I’ve decided to go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> and tell him that I would like it too if I could be at home, but that against all the advantages that this would have there’s a <hi rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi> with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> that I’m afraid I’m beginning to think is incurable, and that makes me apathetic and powerless.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Yesterday evening it’s decided that I’ll be here for a while, the next morning, despite everything, we’re back to — let’s think about it again. Go ahead, sleep on it, think about it!!! <hi rend="italics">As if they</hi> <hi>hadn’t had</hi> 2 YEARS to think about it, <hi>ought</hi> to have thought about it as a matter of course, as the natural thing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Two years, every day a day of worry for me, for them — normal life — as if nothing had happened or nothing would happen. The burden didn’t weigh on them. You say, they don’t express it but they feel it. <hi>i don’t believe that.</hi> I’ve sometimes thought it myself, but it’s <hi rend="italics">not right</hi>. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">People <hi rend="italics">act</hi> AS they <hi>feel</hi>. Our <hi>actions</hi>, our swift readiness or our hesitation, <hi rend="italics">that’s how we can be recognized</hi> — not by what we say with our lips<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — friendly or unfriendly. Good intentions, opinions, in fact that’s <hi rend="italics">less</hi> than <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You may think of me what you will, Theo, but I tell you it’s not my imagination, I tell you, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs></hi> <hi rend="italics">is not willing</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I see now what I saw <hi rend="italics">then</hi>, I spoke out four-square AGAINST <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> then, I speak now <hi rend="italics">in any event</hi>, whatever may come of it, AGAINST PA again, as being UN<hi rend="italics">willing</hi>, as making it IMPOSSIBLE. It’s damned sad, brother, the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_135 bio.xml#_183">Rappards</rs> acted intelligently, but here!!!!!! And everything you did and do about it,  3/4  of it is rendered fruitless by <hi rend="italics">them</hi>. It’s wretched, brother. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I don’t care so much about a friendly or unfriendly reception, what grieves me is that they aren’t sorry for what they did then. They think <hi rend="italics">that </hi>THEY DIDN’T DO ANYTHING <hi rend="italics">then</hi>, and for me that’s going too far.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written the day after <ref target="let409.xml">letter 409</ref>. Since that has been dated on or about Thursday, 6 December, we are placing the present letter on or about Friday, 7 December 1883. It precedes <ref target="let411.xml">letter 411</ref>, which is a direct continuation of it.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Although in his first three letters from Nuenen Van Gogh writes nothing about the work he has done, he had in fact got down to drawing straightaway. On the evening of Saturday, 8 December 1883 Mr van Gogh wrote to Theo: ‘Don’t you think the pen-and-ink drawings of the old tower that Vincent sent you are good? He does them so easily’ (FR b2248). This batch is not mentioned anywhere in the surviving correspondence, but it must have consisted of two winter landscapes showing the churchyard at the foot of the old tower; they were sent, rolled up, on 7 December, as can be seen from the postmark on the back of one of the drawings, <hi rend="italics">Churchyard in winter</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_985">F 1237 / JH 433</rs>).  (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). See cat. Amsterdam 1997, pp. 30-35, cat. nos. 69-70.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>After a disagreement with his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>, Van Gogh left his parents’ home at Christmas 1881: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let194.xml">see letter 194</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>We do not know what financial and practical arrangements <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_135 bio.xml#_183">Van Rappard’s family</rs> had made among themselves; from the subsequent letters it would appear that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> was given the opportunity to devote himself to his art.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Biblical.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to the walk with which he began his journey from Drenthe to Nuenen; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let409.xml">see letter 409</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>After ‘find me coarse’ Van Gogh originally wrote: ‘People are like brushes – the ones that look the best do not work the best’ (‘Het is met de menschen als met de penseelen – die er het fijnst uit zien werken niet het fijnst’). He had previously written: ‘Very fine pens, like very elegant people, are sometimes amazingly impractical, and in my view often lack the suppleness or elasticity that most ordinary pens have to some degree’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let325.xml">letter 325</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This could be a reference to a remark previously made by Theo, since Vincent once wrote: ‘I remind you of your own words that “marrying”’ (i.e. civil marriage) ‘is such a odd thing’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let336.xml">letter 336</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Cf. Matt. 15:8 and Mark 7:6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘beroerd’ (wretched).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    