<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Saturday, 8 December 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let411"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b371 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>411</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>345a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>413</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-08">on or about Saturday, 8 December 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0371" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0371" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000483_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Het is nog vroeg, ik wilde nog een woordje bij mijn schrijven van gisteren voegen om te trachten U eenige dingen duidelijker te maken<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch ik verzoek U wat ik U zeg in dezen brief te beschouwen als zoude ik het zwijgen<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> indien ik niet meende op Uw discretie en intelligentie te kunnen rekenen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb met Pa en Moe geen woord gesproken over de <hi rend="italics">eigentlijke kwestie</hi> van twee jaar geleden<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb echter wel gesproken over eene <hi rend="italics">bijzaak</hi> van toen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Pa en Moe van hun kant noemen <hi rend="italics">haar</hi> naam<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> niet zelfs<c type="kp">_</c>– Goed – <hi rend="italics">zij</hi> hoeven <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> <hi rend="italics">daarover</hi> niet te spreken noch <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> <hi rend="italics">hen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Indirect raakte ik het evenwel aan<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeide tot Pa dat het eene groote fout was in mijn oog dat op een zeker moment (twee jaar geleden) ik gedwongen was het huis te verlaten. Ik zeide dat hiervan aanmerkelijke finantieele schade niet alleen het gevolg was geweest doch ook dat ik<c type="kk">/</c> tot een uiterste gedreven<c type="kk">/</c> veel meer in extremes<c type="kk">/</c> veel meer tot parti pris genoodzaakt ben geweest dan ik uit vrijen wil alleen toe zou zijn overgegaan. Ik wees op het voorbeeld der familie Rappard in tegenstelling met de familie van Gogh. Ik wees er op hoe Rappard ook wel eens verschilt met zijn vader in dit of dat doch dat steeds zij niet alleen voor de wereld doch ook voor hun zelf steeds uitersten vermijden en Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon hij ook geen cent verdient met zijn werk (dat niet te min zeer degelijk<c type="kk">/</c> zeer mooi zelfs is) toch steeds voor de wereld met waardigheid<c type="kk">/</c> ook in zoover installage en atelier &amp;c. aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> voor den dag kan komen<c type="kp">_</c> En hoe door de familie wordt gezorgd ook nergens bij verfleveranciers schuld is &amp;c. Ik zeide tot Pa hoe nobel<c type="kk">/</c> hoe flink en hoe regt gezien ik het vond van U Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dat gij steeds mij geholpen hebt voor zoover het U maar eenigzins mogelijk was. Ik wees er op hoe<c type="kk">/</c> indien toen Pa minder ijzerachtig en eigenzinnig en enfin onintelligent geweest was<c type="kk">/</c> Uw hulp efficace zou zijn geweest terwijl nu Uw hulp niet efficace was en wij slechts ten halve slaagden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Tot zoover raakte ik dus het verleden wel degelijk aan. Tevens wees ik erop dat op dit moment ik al weer moeielijk extrêmes vermijden kan<c type="kk">/</c> daar de verhouding waarin ik mij voel tot de familie in het algemeen zóó slecht is dat het mij duidelijk wordt den band tusschen U en mij niet houdbaar is als alles maar steeds blaauw blaauw wordt gelaten.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dat ik wanneer ik nadenk er over of het regt of onregt is geld van U te accepteeren<c type="kk">/</c> in consideratie moet nemen den schijn dien het heeft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik zeg U ronduit dat ik den geest in onze familie<c type="kk">/</c> bepaaldelijk dien van Pa en ook b.v. dien van C.M.<c type="kk">/</c> meer en meer verkeerd vind.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik sta nu tegenover U op deze wijs: aan den eenen kant geloof ik er nog eene mogelijkheid is Uw karakter als het mijne terugkomt van veel dingen die ons geleerd zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ja ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik acht het mogelijk in Uw gemoed eene t’zij geleidelijke ’t zij plotselinge ommekeer komt zóó dat gij U gedrongen zult voelen tot eene andere levensopvatting en dat welligt gij ook nog schilder wordt als eindresultaat daarvan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">aan den anderen kant staat hier scherp tegenover bij voorbeeld Uw gezegde van dezen zomer “ik word meer &amp; meer als Pa”.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Indien dit laatste – n.l. dat gij meer en meer een “van Gogh”<c type="kk">/</c> een karakter als Pa of C.M. werd en door steeds in de zaken te verkeeren een levensopvatting kreegt geheel verschillend van de mijne – een handelaarsgeest<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. een min of meer politiek persoon werd – wel<c type="kk">/</c> ronduit gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou dan liever niet intiem met U zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou dan beter vinden in plaats van banden te versterken<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> wij elkaar lieten schieten als begrijpende we niet bij elkaar hoorden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb op dit moment Pa onder de oogen – wat Pa is<c type="kk">/</c> zie ik<c type="kk">/</c> hoor ik<c type="kk">/</c> voel ik – en vind ik niet goed – gedecideerd niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Zijt gij <hi rend="italics">zoo</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wordt gij meer en meer zoo – dan is het wijs te scheiden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Nu kom ik terug op wat ik zeide tot Pa<c type="kk">/</c> dat het eene fout was wij twee jaar geleden zoo getwist hadden dat het huis voor mij sedert gesloten was – (wiens schuld doet er niet eens toe zoo zeer<c type="kk">/</c> de twist zelf had het in Pa’s eigen principes<c type="kk">/</c> als hij er aan consequent gebleven was<c type="kk">/</c> moeten liggen te vermijden – quand même te vermijden)<c type="kp">_</c> Wat zegt Pa daarop<c type="kp">_</c>– Ja maar<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan toch niets terugnemen van wat ik toen deed<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb steeds alles gedaan voor uw bestwil en ik heb steeds mijn oprechte meening gevolgd<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik hernam daarop dat “de meening” van een mensch wel eens lijnregt staan kan tegenover het <hi rend="italics">geweten</hi><c type="kk">/</c> lijnregt<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> tegenover elkaar kan staan <hi rend="italics">wat men MEENT te moeten doen</hi> en wat men <hi>moest</hi> doen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zeide tot Pa dat in den Bijbel zelf termen kunnen gevonden worden om onze “<hi rend="italics">meeningen</hi>” te toetsen of zij ook billijk en regtvaardig zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En Pa dit maar al te veel gewoon was achterwege te laten en doldriftig doorgaat – mijns inziens zeer onregtvaardig<c type="kk">/</c> zeer willekeurig<c type="kk">/</c> zeer laakbaar – op zijn “<hi rend="italics">meening</hi>” – niet – op zijn geweten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik stond dus voor een ijzeren barriere van onverzoenlijkheid in der daad<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon Pa dat zocht te maskeeren<c type="kk">/</c> zocht mij er om heen te leiden en mijn er op doorgaan af te wenden<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch ik liet in dezen mij niet van streek brengen en zeide – Pa ik heb hier te doen met Uw eigengeregtigheid die fataal was en is voor U en voor mij<c type="kp">_</c>– Toen zegt Pa “dacht gij dat ik voor je knielen zou”<c type="kp">_</c> ik zeide ik het Pa hoogst kwalijk nam<c type="kk">/</c> het zeer grof vond<c type="kk">/</c> dat Pa slechts <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> er in zag en dat ik er verder geen woorden over zou vuil maken<c type="kp">_</c> Pa hoeft niet tot mij te zeggen dat <hi rend="italics">hij</hi> fout deed tegenover <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> maar Pa moest in die twee jaren geleerd hebben wat ik leerde<c type="kk">/</c> dat het een groote fout was op zich zelf en dat die direkt geredresseerd had moeten worden zonder te vragen naar wiens schuld het was<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zoo broer<c type="kk">/</c> mijns inziens vervalt Pa eeuwig in <hi rend="italics">klein</hi>geestigheid in plaats van grooter<c type="kk">/</c> ruimer<c type="kk">/</c> breeder<c type="kk">/</c> humaner te zijn. Het was dominésijdelheid die toen de dingen tot een uiterste dreef<c type="kk">/</c> het is ook nu nog die zelfde dominésijdelheid die nog in het tegenwoordige &amp; toekomst meer onheil stichten zal<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik vraag van U geen bemiddeling<c type="kk">/</c> ik vraag van U iets meer persoonlijks<c type="kk">/</c> ik vraag U ronduit<c type="kk">/</c> hoe staan we tegenover elkaar<c type="kk">/</c> zijt gij ook een “van Gogh”<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik beschouwde U altijd als “<hi rend="italics">Theo</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c> In karakter wijk ik nog al af van de verschillende leden der familie en ik ben eigentlijk <hi rend="italics">geen</hi> “van Gogh”<c type="kp">_</c> Maar als gij een personaliteit werd – een rol speeldet in de wereld als Pa of C<c type="kp">_</c>M<c type="kp">_</c> of oom V. zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou daar niet aan tornen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou U in Uw waarde laten<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou zwijgen er over<c type="kk">/</c> doch onze wegen zouden te zeer uiteen loopen dan dat ik den band in ’t finantieele zóó als die nu is<c type="kk">/</c> zoude raadzaam blijven achten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik hoop gij mij begrijpen zult. Indien niet<c type="kk">/</c> zoo moet de tijd er over heen gaan<c type="kk">/</c> wie weet of in de eerstvolgende 3 jaren gij sommige kwesties niet min of meer als ik zult beginnen te zien<c type="kp">_</c>– Waarom – omdat gij door de kunst en omgang met artisten ook geinfluenceerd wordt en enfin<c type="kk">/</c> er misschien vierkanter en breeder door worden zult in plaats van smaller en naauwer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Nu kerel – als gij kunt<c type="kk">/</c> zorg ik hier weg kan – weest gegroet en geloof mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">It’s still early; I wanted to add a word or two to my letter of yesterday in order to try to make a few things clearer to you. But I ask you to regard what I tell you in this letter as something I would keep silent about if I didn’t think I could rely on your discretion and intelligence.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I haven’t said a word to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> about the <hi rend="italics">real question </hi>of two years ago. I have, though, spoken about a <hi rend="italics">side issue</hi> at that time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">For their part, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526 bio.xml#_524">Pa and Ma</rs> don’t even mention <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">her</rs></hi> name.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Very well — <hi rend="italics">they</hi> don’t have to speak to <hi rend="italics">me about it</hi>, nor <hi rend="italics">I </hi>to<hi rend="italics"> them</hi>. I did touch on it indirectly, though; I told Pa that in my view it was a great mistake that at a certain point (two years ago) I was forced to leave the house. I said that not only had considerable financial harm been the consequence, but also that, driven to the limit, I had been forced to go to extremes much more, to much greater intransigence than I would have displayed of my own free will alone. I pointed to the example of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_135 bio.xml#_183">Rappard family</rs> in contrast to the Van Gogh family. I pointed out how <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> also has differences with his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_183">father</rs> about this or that, but that they always avoid extremes not only for the world but also for themselves and, although he doesn’t earn a penny from his work (which is nonetheless very sound, very fine even), Rappard can still always face the world with dignity, also in so far as equipment and studio &amp;c. are concerned. And how the family makes sure there are no debts anywhere with colourmen &amp;c. I told Pa how noble, how stalwart and how clear-sighted I thought it was of you, Theo, that you’ve always helped me in so far as it was at all possible for you. I pointed out how, if Pa hadn’t been so steely and obstinate and in short unintelligent then, your help would have been effective, whereas now your help wasn’t effective and we’ve only half succeeded.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">So to that extent I certainly did touch on the past. At the same time I pointed out that at this moment it’s again difficult for me to avoid extremes, since the relationship to the family in general in which I feel I stand is <hi rend="italics">so</hi> bad that it’s becoming clear to me that the bond between you and me cannot endure if everything is always just left as it is. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">That when I think about whether it’s right or wrong to accept money from you, I have to take appearances into consideration.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"> I tell you frankly that I find the spirit in our family, particularly <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s and also, for instance, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>’s, more and more wrong.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">My position vis-à-vis you now is this: on the one hand I believe that there’s still a possibility that your character, like mine, will go back on many of the things we were taught; yes, I say, I think it possible that you’ll have a change of heart, be it gradual, be it sudden, so that you’ll find yourself compelled to adopt another outlook on life, and that perhaps the upshot will be that you’ll yet become a painter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">On the other hand, this is in stark contrast, for example, to what you said this summer: ‘I’m becoming more and more like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In the event of this last — that is, that you became more and more a ‘Van Gogh’, became a character like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> and by always being involved in business acquired an outlook on life entirely different from mine — a trader’s spirit, that is became a more or less political person — well, to be quite frank, then I’d rather not be intimate with you, then I’d find it better that, rather than strengthening bonds,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> we should let each other go, understanding we didn’t belong together.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">At present I’m observing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> — I see, I hear, I feel what Pa is — and I don’t like it — decidedly not. If you are <hi rend="italics">thus</hi>, if you’re becoming more and more thus — then it’s wise to part. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Now I return to what I said to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, that it was a mistake that we quarrelled so seriously two years ago that the house has been barred to me since then — (whose fault it was doesn’t even matter that much; it would have been in accordance with Pa’s own principles — if he had maintained them consistently — that the quarrel itself should have been avoided — avoided come what may). What does Pa say to this? Yes, but I can’t take back anything I did then, I’ve always done everything for your own good, and I’ve always acted on my sincere opinion. To which I replied that a person’s ‘opinion’ may sometimes be diametrically opposed to his <hi rend="italics">conscience</hi>, I mean <hi rend="italics">what one THINKS one should </hi>do and what one <hi>ought</hi> to do may be diametrically opposed to one another. I told Pa that terms may be found in the Bible itself to judge whether our ‘<hi rend="italics">opinions</hi>’ are fair and just.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was all too much in the habit of failing to do this and going on hot-headedly — in my view very unjustly, very arbitrarily, very reprehensibly — according to his ‘<hi rend="italics">opinion</hi>’ — not — according to his conscience.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Enough, so I was faced with an iron barrier of irreconcilability indeed, although <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> tried to mask it, tried to lead me around it and to divert me from pursuing it. But I didn’t allow myself to be put off by this, and said — Pa, this is about your self-righteousness, which was and is fatal for you and for me. Then Pa said, ‘did you think I would go down on my knees to you?’ I said I took it very ill of Pa, thought it extremely crude, that Pa saw only <hi rend="italics">that</hi> in it, and that I wouldn’t waste my breath on it any longer. Pa doesn’t have to tell me that <hi rend="italics">he </hi>acted badly towards <hi rend="italics">me</hi>, but Pa should have learnt what I learnt in those two years — that it was a great mistake in itself, and that it should have been redressed immediately without asking whose fault it was. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">So brother, in my view <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> eternally descends into <hi rend="italics">petty</hi>-mindedness instead of being more open, more liberal, broader, more humane. It was minister’s vanity that drove things to extremes then, and it’s still the same minister’s vanity that will still cause more mischief in the present and the future.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t ask you to intercede, I ask you for something more personal, I ask you frankly: how do we stand towards each other; are you a ‘Van Gogh’ too?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I always regarded you as ‘<hi rend="italics">Theo</hi>’. In character I’m quite different from the various members of the family, and I’m actually <hi rend="italics">not</hi> a ‘Van Gogh’. But if you were to become a personality — played a part in the world like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle V.</rs> even, very well, I wouldn’t interfere with that, I would accept you as you were, I would keep silent about it, but our paths would diverge too greatly for me to be able to continue regarding the financial tie advisable, as it stands now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I hope you’ll understand me. If not, we’ll have to give it time. Who knows if, in the next 3 years, you won’t start to view some questions more or less as I do. Why? Because you’ll also be influenced by art and by mixing with artists, and in short may perhaps become squarer and broader in consequence instead of narrower and more constricted.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Well old chap — if you can, see to it that I can get away from here — regards and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">As is clear from <ref target="#l-2">l. 2</ref>, the letter was written the day after <ref target="let410.xml">letter 410</ref>. Because that letter has been dated on or about Friday, 7 December, we are dating the present letter on or about Saturday, 8 December 1883. It precedes <ref target="let413.xml">letter 413</ref>, in which the question of the discord in the parental home is gone into in more detail and Vincent can respond directly in that connection to a letter from Theo he had just received.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘voor me houden, verzwijgen’ (keep to myself, withhold).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This refers to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_776">Kee Vos</rs>, for whom Van Gogh had developed an intense love in the summer of 1881 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let179.xml">see letters 179</ref> ff.). The following December his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> asked him to leave the house. The cause was Vincent’s refusal to go to church, but he himself believed that the opposition of his parents and family to a union with Kee was the real reason. At the end of December 1881 he wrote to Theo: ‘But oh, there’s actually much more to it, including the whole story of what happened this summer between me and K.V.’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let194.xml">letter 194</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>A prayer written and often recited in the family circle by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let113.xml">see letter 113</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    