<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Sunday, 16 December 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let414"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b373 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>414</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>347</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>416</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-16">on or about Sunday, 16 December 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0373" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0373" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000486_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Mauve heeft mij in der tijd eens gezegd “gij zult uw eigen vinden als gij doorwerkt in de kunst<c type="kk">/</c> als gij dieper doordringt dan gij tot nog toe hebt gedaan”<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat zeide hij 2 jaar geleden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik denk veel over dat woord van hem dezer dagen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb mijn eigen gevonden – <hi rend="italics">ik ben dien hond</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu kan mijn gedachte wat hoog opgevoerd zijn – de werkelijkheid minder geprononceerd in haar opposities – minder absoluut dramatisch – toch au fond de ruwe karakterschets is geloof ik waar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De ruige herdershond dien ik trachtte U aan het verstand te brengen in mijn schrijven van gisteren<c type="kk">/</c> het is mijn karakter en het leven van het beest is mijn leven<c type="kk">/</c> als n.l. men de details weglaat en het essentieele slechts aangeeft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Dit moge U overdreven voorkomen – maar ik neem het niet terug<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Zonder personaliteiten<c type="kk">/</c> alleen als karakterstudie – onpartijdig als sprak ik in plaats van over U en mij en Pa over vreemden<c type="kk">/</c> ter wille van analyse wijs ik U nog eens op verleden zomer. Ik zie twee broers loopen te s’Hage (beschouw ze als <hi rend="italics">vreemden</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">anderen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> denk niet aan U zelf of aan mij of Pa)<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">De een zegt “ik word meer &amp; meer als Pa – ik moet een zekeren stand ophouden – een zekere weelde (zeer matig en bij U en bij Pa) – ik moet in den handel blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof niet dat ik schilder zal worden”<c type="kp">_</c> De ander zegt – “ik word minder &amp; minder als Pa – ik word een hond<c type="kk">/</c> ik voel dat de toekomst mij leelijker en ruwer zal maken waarschijnlijk en ik zie “een zekere <hi rend="italics">armoede</hi>” als mijn lot – maar – maar – <hi>ik zal schilder zijn</hi> en <hi rend="italics">mensch</hi> of <hi rend="italics">hond</hi><c type="kk">/</c> enfin wezen met <hi rend="italics">gevoel</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c></p>
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dus de een<c type="kk">/</c> een zekeren stand of weelde en handelaar<c type="kp">_</c></p> 
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">,, ,, ander<c type="kk">/</c> ,, ,, armoede en uitgesloten ,, schilder<c type="kp">_</c> </p>
<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">En diezelfde twee broers zie ik in vroeger jaren – toen gij pas in de schilderij wereld kwaamt<c type="kk">/</c> pas begont te lezen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c>&amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> – bij den Rijswijkschen molen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">of bijvoorbeeld op een tocht s’winters naar Chaam over de besneeuwde heide s’morgens vroeg!<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <hi rend="italics">zóó</hi> <hi>het zelfde voelend</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi>zoo het zelfde denkend en geloovend</hi> – dat ik me zelf afvraag – zijn dat dezelfden??? Vraag – hoe zal het nu verder afloopen – gaan ze voor eeuwig uit elkaar of komen ze voor goed op een zelfden weg<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik zeg U <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> <hi rend="italics">kies</hi> <hi rend="italics">het</hi> <hi rend="italics">bewuste</hi> <hi rend="italics">hondenpad</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik blijf <hi rend="italics">hond</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik word <hi rend="italics">arm</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik word <hi rend="italics">schilder</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ik wil <hi rend="italics">mensch</hi> blijven<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">in</hi> de natuur <hi rend="italics">in</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">In mijn oog<c type="kk">/</c> wie uit de natuur uit gaat<c type="kk">/</c> wie altijd zijn hoofd vol moet hebben met het ophouden van dit of het ophouden van dat<c type="kk">/</c> ook als zulks hem uit de natuur uit brengt<c type="kk">/</c> zóó dat hij zelf niet laten kan dit te zeggen – och – op die wijs komt men m.i. zoo ligt op een punt dat men geen wit van zwart meer kan onderscheiden – en – en men wordt precies het tegenovergestelde van dat waar men voor doorgaat of zelf denkt te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Bij voorbeeld – Op dit moment nog is er in U een mannelijke vrees voor mediocreteit in den slechten zin van het woord<c type="kp">_</c>– Waarom gaat gij desniettegenstaande het beste in Uw ziel dooden<c type="kk">/</c> uitblusschen<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Dan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ja <hi rend="italics">dan</hi> zou die vrees wel eens kunnen bewaarheid worden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Hoe wordt men mediocre? door van daag dit en morgen dat te schikken en te plooijen<c type="kk">/</c> zóó als de wereld het wil en maar niet tegen te spreken tegen de wereld en maar de publieke opinie te volgen! Versta mij wel<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg juist dat au fond gij beter zijt dan dat – ik zie het in U als ge b.v. de partij voor Pa opneemt<c type="kk">/</c> als gij denkt dat ik het Pa lastig heb gemaakt<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij past Uw oppositie verkeerd toe mijns inziens<c type="kk">/</c> met uw welnemen<c type="kk">/</c> in deze zaak<c type="kk">/</c> doch ik apprecieer juist dat en zeg<c type="kk">/</c> wees er nu wijs bij<c type="kk">/</c> pas die drift ergens anders op toe en vecht met die kracht tegen eenige andere invloeden dan wel precies de mijne – en – en dan zult ge waarschijnlijk minder van streek raken.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik spreek niet tegen Pa wanneer ik Pa op zichzelf beschouw<c type="kk">/</c> doch ik spreek tegen Pa als ik Pa vergelijk bij den grooten Vader Millet b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Diens leer<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is zóó groot dat Pa’s zienswijs er bitter klein bij wordt<c type="kp">_</c>– Dit komt U nu vreesselijk voor van mij – ik kan er niets aan doen – het is mijn overtuiging diep in mij en ik kom daar voor uit wegens <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> verwart <hi rend="italics">Pa</hi>’s karakter met dat van Corot b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Hoe ik Pa beschouw? als een persoon van soortgelijk karakter als de <hi rend="italics">vader</hi> <hi rend="italics">van</hi> <hi rend="italics">Corot</hi> – maar van Corot zelf heeft Pa niets<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Corot hield toch van zijn vader <hi>maar volgde hem niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ik houd ook van Pa<c type="kk">/</c> zoolang mijn weg niet al te zeer bemoeielijkt wordt door verschil van inzigten. Ik houd <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> van Pa op een moment waar zekeren kleingeestigen trots eene algeheele en definitieve<c type="kk">/</c> zoo wenschelijke verzoening verhindert royaal en afdoende tot stand te komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Maatregelen door mij beoogd en wegens welke ik ook herwaarts kwam<c type="kk">/</c> hadden geenszins het oogmerk Pa of U op kosten te jagen doch in tegendeel van het geld van U een beter partij te trekken zóó dat wij minder verliezen<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. minder tijd<c type="kk">/</c> minder geld en minder energie<c type="kp">_</c>– Ben ik te laken in dezen wanneer ik wijs op de Rappards die<c type="kk">/</c> al zijn ze rijker dan Pa of gij of ik<c type="kk">/</c> het verstandiger aanleggen en beter resultaten verkrijgen door eendragt<c type="kk">/</c> al is die niet altijd heel makkelijk voor hen waarschijnlijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ben ik te laken wanneer ik wilde stellen een tot hiertoe en niet verder aan een tweedragt in de familie. In welk opzigt heb ik ongelijk wanneer ik het wil <hi rend="italics">door</hi> <hi rend="italics">en</hi> <hi rend="italics">door</hi> en afdoend en <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">content</hi> ben met een <hi rend="italics">schijn</hi> of te <hi rend="italics">slappe</hi> verzoening<c type="kp">_</c>– Verzoening met slag om den arm<c type="kk">/</c> condities enz<c type="kp">_</c> bah!– daar belief ik niet van gediend te zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="italics">Grif</hi> – of <hi rend="italics">niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c> met empressement<c type="kk">/</c> anders geeft het glad niets en is erger te voorzien.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Gij zegt gij vind het <hi rend="italics">laf</hi> van mij ik opsta tegen Pa – in woorden is dit <hi rend="italics">opstaan</hi> primo – hier is geen geweldenarij<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Van een anderen kant kan het bezien worden<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat ik te triester en teleurgestelder ben en te ernstiger spreek en te beslister juist omdat Pa’s grijze haren mij er op wijzen dat de tijd dien wij hebben voor verzoening voorwaar misschien niet lang meer is<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik hecht weinig aan verzoeningen<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> op sterfbedden<c type="kk">/</c> liever zie ik ze <hi rend="italics">bij het leven</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Toegeven dat Pa wel goed het bedoelt wil ik wel<c type="kk">/</c> doch zoo oneindig liever was het mij als het bij bedoelen niet bleef maar komen mogt<c type="kk">/</c> al zij het zeer laat<c type="kk">/</c> ten minste <hi rend="italics">ooit</hi> tot een elkaar verstaan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Indien ik moet vreezen “dit zal niet geschieden!”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> indien gij wist hoe triest ik dat vind<c type="kk">/</c> indien gij wist hoe ik daarover treur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Gij zegt – Pa heeft wel andere dingen aan zijn hoofd – zoo – goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik zelf voel hoe <hi rend="italics">onbelangrijk</hi> me die dingen in kwestie voorkomen die Pa’s hoofd verhinderen door te denken jaar in jaar uit. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dat is het eigentlijk juist<c type="kp">_</c>– Pa voelt niet dat er iets te verzoenen of op te maken is<c type="kk">/</c> pa denkt aan andere dingen – goed – laat hem bij zijn andere dingen<c type="kk">/</c> begin ik nu te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– Blijf <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> ook bij <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> “andere dingen”. Pa zegt “we zijn altijd immers goed geweest” &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> ik zeg – Zóó – zijt gij tevreden?– ik niet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Iets beters dan den tijd van de Rijswijksche molen – namelijk datzelfde eens en voor altijd – twee arme broers artist – opgaande in eenzelfde gevoel voor eenzelfde natuur en kunst – zal het daar ooit op uitdraaijen?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">De zekere stand<c type="kk">/</c> de zekere weelde<c type="kk">/</c> zal die het winnen?– o<c type="kk">/</c> laat die het winnen – maar dat het zij slechts voor een tijd die uitkomt op uw teleurstelling dien aangaande<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> is hetgeen ik voorzie geschieden zal voor gij 30 jaar zijt<c type="kp">_</c>– En indien niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Wel indien niet<c type="kk">/</c> dan – dan – dan – <hi>Tant</hi> PIS<c type="kp">_</c> Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> said to me at the time, ‘you’ll find yourself if you keep on working at art, if you go into it more deeply than you have done so far’. He said that 2 years ago.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I think a lot about those words of his these days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I have found myself — <hi rend="italics">I am that dog</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now my idea may be somewhat overstated — the reality less pronounced in its contrasts — less absolutely dramatic — yet I believe the rough character sketch is fundamentally true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The shaggy sheepdog I tried to get you to understand in my letter yesterday  it’s my character, and the animal’s life is my life, if, that is, one leaves out the details and simply gives the essentials.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">This may seem exaggerated to you — but I don’t take it back.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For the sake of analysis, no personalities involved, just as a character study, I refer you once more to last summer impartially as if I spoke about strangers rather than about you and me and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>. I see two brothers walking in The Hague (view them as <hi rend="italics">strangers, other people</hi>, don’t think of yourself or of me or Pa).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">One of them says, ‘I’m becoming more and more like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> — I have a certain position to keep up — a certain affluence (very modest in both your case and Pa’s)  I must stay in the trade, I don’t believe that I’ll become a painter’. The other says — ‘I’m becoming less and less like Pa — I’m becoming a dog, I feel that the future will probably make me uglier and rougher, and I see “a certain <hi rend="italics">poverty</hi>” as my lot — but — but — <hi>i will be a painter</hi> and, <hi rend="italics">man</hi> or <hi rend="italics">dog</hi>, in short a being with <hi rend="italics">feeling</hi>’.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So, the one, a certain position or affluence and a businessman.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">,, ,, other, ,, ,, poverty and exclusion ,, ,, painter. </p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And I see those same two brothers in earlier years — when you were just coming into the world of painting, just beginning to read &amp;c. &amp;c. — by the mill in Rijswijk.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Or, for example, on an outing to Chaam in the winter, across the snow-covered heath, early in the morning!<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <hi>feeling</hi> <hi rend="italics">so</hi> <hi>much the same</hi>, <hi>thinking and believing so much the same</hi> — that I ask myself — are they the same people??? Question — what will happen now? — will they part company forever, or will they find the same path once and for all? 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I tell you, <hi rend="italics">I choose the said dog’s path</hi>, I’ll remain a <hi rend="italics">dog</hi>, I’ll be <hi rend="italics">poor</hi>, I’ll be a <hi rend="italics">painter</hi>, I want to remain <hi rend="italics">human</hi>, <hi rend="italics">in</hi> nature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">To my mind, anyone who turns away from nature, whose head always has to be full of keeping this up or keeping that up, even if things like that take him away from nature, to such an extent that he can’t help saying it — oh — in this way one so easily arrives, in my view, at a point where one can no longer distinguish white from black — and — and one becomes precisely the opposite of what one is taken to be or thinks oneself to be. For instance — at this moment you still have a manly fear of mediocrity in the bad sense of the word. Why are you nonetheless going to kill, extinguish the best in your soul? <hi rend="italics">Then</hi>, yes <hi rend="italics">then</hi>, that fear could well come true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">How does one become mediocre? By going along with this today and conforming to that tomorrow, as the world wants, and by not speaking out against the world and by only following public opinion! Understand me clearly, what I’m saying is that at bottom you’re better than that — I see it in you when, for example, you take <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s part when you think I’ve made it difficult for Pa. Permit me to say that in my view you’re directing your opposition wrongly in this case, but I do appreciate exactly that, and I say, at the same time be sensible, direct that anger at something else and fight with that strength against some influences other than mine, of all things — and — and then you’ll probably get less upset. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I don’t differ with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> when I consider Pa in himself, but I do differ with Pa when I compare Pa with the great <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, say.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">His doctrine<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is <hi rend="italics">so</hi> great that <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s</hi> way of looking at things seems extremely petty beside it. You will think this terrible of me — I can do nothing about it — it’s my conviction, deep inside me, and I stick up for it because <hi rend="italics">you</hi> confuse <hi rend="italics">Pa’s</hi> character with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>’s, for instance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">How do I see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>? As a person of similar character to <hi rend="italics">Corot’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_48">father</rs></hi>, but Pa has nothing of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> himself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> did love his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_48">father</rs>, <hi>but he didn’t follow him</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I love <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, too, so long as my path isn’t made too difficult by a difference of opinion. I do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> love Pa at a moment when a certain petty-minded pride stands in the way of the generous and conclusive achievement of a complete, definitive and so desirable reconciliation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Measures I envisaged and which also brought me here were in no way intended to cause <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> or you expense, but on the contrary to make better use of your money so that we lose less, that is, less time, less money and less energy. Am I to be condemned in this respect when I point to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_135 bio.xml#_183">the Rappards</rs> who, although they’re wealthier than Pa or you or I, go about things more sensibly and get better results through unity, even though it’s probably not always very easy for them either?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Am I to be condemned when I wanted to say ‘thus far and no further’ to a division in the family? In what respect am I wrong when I want it to be <hi rend="italics">through and through </hi>and conclusive and am <hi rend="italics">not content</hi> with a <hi rend="italics">sham</hi> or too <hi rend="italics">feeble</hi> a reconciliation? Reconciliation with reservations, conditions etc., bah! — I refuse to accept it. <hi rend="italics">Readily</hi> or <hi rend="italics">not at all</hi>; willingly, or else it’s utterly pointless and worse can be foreseen. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">You say that you think it <hi rend="italics">cowardly</hi> of me to rebel against <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> — in the first place this <hi rend="italics">rebellion</hi> is in words — there’s no violence here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">It can be seen from another side, that is, that I’m all the sadder and more disappointed and speak all the more earnestly and resolutely precisely because <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s grey hair tells me that the time that we have for reconciliation is verily perhaps not very long. I don’t think much of deathbed reconciliations,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I’d rather see them <hi rend="italics">during life</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I’m prepared to admit that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> means well, but I would so infinitely prefer it if it weren’t to stop at intentions but might at least <hi rend="italics">sometime</hi>, albeit very late, lead to a mutual understanding.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">If I have to fear that ‘this will never happen’,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> if you only knew how sad I find that, if you only knew how I grieve about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">You say — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> does have other things on his mind — really — well then, I myself feel how <hi rend="italics">unimportant </hi>those things, which prevent Pa’s mind from thinking things through year in and year out, appear to me. Well, that’s precisely it. Pa doesn’t believe that there’s anything to reconcile or make up, Pa thinks about other things — very well — I’m beginning to say now: leave him to his other things. And <hi rend="italics">you</hi> stick to <hi rend="italics">your</hi> ‘other things’ too. Pa says ‘we’ve always been good after all’ &amp;c. I say — really? — are you satisfied?  I’m not.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28"> Something better than the time of the Rijswijk mill — namely the same once and for all — two poor brothers, artists — bound up in the same feeling for the same nature and art — will it ever come to that?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">The certain position, the certain affluence, will they win out? Oh, let them win out  but that it will be only for a time that ends with your disappointment in this respect,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> is what I foresee will happen before you’re 30. And if not — Well, if not, then — then — then — <hi>Too</hi> BAD. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh refers in his letter to that of ‘yesterday’ <ref target="#l-11">(l. 11)</ref>. He must be referring here to <ref target="let413.xml">letter 413</ref>, in which he had compared himself to a dog – he repeats this metaphor now. Since that letter was written on or about Saturday, 15 December, we have dated the present letter on or about Sunday, 16 December 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 this letter is made up of three parts; one of them, however, we regard as part of <ref target="let403.xml">letter 403</ref>. One reason for this is that the paper on which the section we have moved is written does not occur anywhere else in the Nuenen letters, whereas it was used several times in Drenthe. (Interestingly, Jo van Gogh-Bonger in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 did not include any continuation with the main letter at all.) See further <hi rend="italics">Arrangement</hi> in the notes to <ref target="let403.xml">letter 403</ref>.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">We have also taken the previous third part to be a continuation of <ref target="let413.xml">letter 413</ref> and not of the present letter. See further <hi rend="italics">Arrangement</hi> in the notes to <ref target="let413.xml">letter 413</ref>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh recalled this spot, which is an important memory in the relationship between the brothers, on a number of occasions. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let011.xml">See letter 11</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This winter trip to Chaam in Brabant must have been the one that Van Gogh refers to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let100.xml">letter 100</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh knew <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s views through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238">La vie et l’oeuvre</ref></hi> (1881), which he had read in The Hague.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The wealthy <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_48">Jacques Louis Corot</rs> owned a fashion house in Paris. He and Corot’s mother, Marie Françoise Corot-Oberson, encouraged their <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">son</rs> – against his inclination – to become a cloth merchant. After he had begged his parents to be allowed to become a painter for several years, they finally agreed in 1822. See exhib. cat. Paris 1996, pp. 15-16. Van Gogh may have acquired his knowledge from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1809">Dumesnil</rs> 1875.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh crossed out ‘theatrical’ (‘theatrale’) before ‘reconciliations’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Kings 2:10 and Isa. 7:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>After ‘in this respect’ Van Gogh crossed out: ‘Perhaps <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">[</hi>indeed<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">[?]</hi> you will also turn into a dog and go out into nature’ (‘U maakt <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">[</hi>ja<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">[?]</hi> misschien ook tot een hond doch weer in de natuur in’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    