<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Wednesday, 26 December 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let417"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b379 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>417</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>350</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>419</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-26">on or about Wednesday, 26 December 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0379 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0379 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000493_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0379 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000494_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000494_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0379b V/1962" xml:id="surf-extra-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000494_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000494_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Gisteren avond kwam ik terug te Nunen en nu moet mij maar dadelijk van het hart af wat ik U dien te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Mijn gereedschap<c type="kk">/</c> studies &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> heb ik ginder ingepakt en naar hier gestuurd<c type="kk">/</c> en Pa en Moe het kamertje leeg gemaakt hebbende ben ik reeds voorloopig in die nieuwe werkplaats geinstalleerd waar ik hoop het mij zal mogen lukken wat te vorderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Weet nu verder dat ik de vrouw heb gesproken en dat nog meer definitief zelfs het ons besluit is zij blijve op zich zelf en ik op mij zelf in alle geval<c type="kk">/</c> zoo dat voor de wereld er niet billijkerwijs kan worden aanmerking gemaakt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu wij eenmaal gescheiden zijn blijven wij ook gescheiden<c type="kk">/</c> alleen van achteren beschouwd betreuren wij het niet liever een middenweg te hebben gekozen<c type="kk">/</c> en zelfs nu nog blijft wederzijdsch eene gehechtheid die te diepe wortels of gronden heeft dan dat zij vergankelijk zij.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik moet nu U een paar dingen zeggen waarop ik na dezen niet zal terug komen – die gij kunt opvatten zoo als gij wilt – waarover het U vrij staat na te denken of van U af te schuiven – dat is mijn zaak niet – weet gij dat voor U zelf<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Weet dan dat ik met een diep leedwezen terugzie op Uw bezoek van dezen zomer<c type="kk">/</c> op onze gesprekken van alstoen en op hetgeen er uit voortvloeide<c type="kp">_</c> De tijd is er nu over heen gegaan maar ik mag niet ontkennen van achteren beschouwd het mij niet regt voorkomt van ons<c type="kp">_</c> En ik beschouw Uw woorden en U zelf nu eenigzins anders en ik kan niet precies met hetzelfde gevoel meer aan U denken als vroeger<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik zie nu namelijk duidelijker hoe gij en anderen schenen te wenschen ik zou scheiden van haar<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Aan de goede bedoelingen twijfel ik niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Het was aan mij om er in te beslissen en dus<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik verkeerd deed<c type="kk">/</c> m.i. ik mag het U niet in de <hi rend="italics">eerste</hi> plaats verwijten (in de <hi rend="italics">eerste</hi> plaats verwijt ik me zelf) doch U in de <hi>tweede</hi> plaats<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">De hefboomen die op mij werkten zoo dat ik van mijn stuk raakte en waar gij althans wel eenigzins mede te maken hebt – waren 1 het aanroeren van een oneindig teere kwestie uit het verleden die mij troubleerde<c type="kk">/</c> tweedens uw zeggen dat “mijn pligt” mij misschien brengen zou op scheiden<c type="kp">_</c> Nu – als het geheel op zich zelf stond wat gij zeidet – zou ik er niet eens op terug komen – maar het klopt te veel met de gevoelens van andere personen van wie ik ook verschil dan dat Uw opinies door mij kunnen beschouwd worden als staande geheel op zich zelf<c type="kp">_</c> Ik trad in Uw zienswijs – ofschoon waarschijnlijk met bedoelingen nog heel anders dan gij U wel voorstelt, en zullende dienaangaande de tijd U nog een &amp; ander ophelderen dat nu niet aan de orde is om er over te spreken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Gij weest mij op een geval waar het “goed had gewerkt” dat zeker man zekere vrouw had verlaten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dat <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> waar zijn op zich zelf – zeer waar – doch was het <hi rend="italics">hier</hi> toepasselijk betreffende haar en mij<c type="kp">_</c> zie<c type="kk">/</c> dat is een tweede.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En ik ben zoo vrij geweest mijn oog er eens over te laten gaan “<hi rend="italics">of het goed gewerkt had</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c> En – vriend – dat is nu maar al te twijfelachtig<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Weet dat de vrouw zich goed heeft gehouden<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">werkende</hi> (n<c type="kp">_</c>l. als waschvrouw)<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> om te voorzien in haar onderhoud en dat van hare kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> gevolgelijk haar pligt heeft betracht en dat in groote ligchamelijke zwakte<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Gij weet dat ik haar bij mij in huis heb genomen omdat bij haar bevalling er dingen gebeurd zijn die maakten de dokters te Leiden er op wezen zij ergens rustig moest zijn wilde zij en haar kind er boven op komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Er was anemie en reeds een beginsel van tering misschien<c type="kp">_</c> Nu<c type="kk">/</c> zoolang ik met haar was is zij niet erger geworden doch in veel opzigten sterker<c type="kk">/</c> zoodat verscheidene leelijke verschijnselen weg bleven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar nu is dat alles weer verergerd en ik vrees zeer voor haar behoud<c type="kk">/</c> en ook het arme kindje<c type="kk">/</c> waar voor ik zorgde als was ’t mijn eigen<c type="kk">/</c> is niet meer wat het was<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Broer<c type="kk">/</c> ik vond haar in groote ellende en ik ben zeer bedroefd er over<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik weet wel dat het meer mijn eigen schuld is natuurlijk<c type="kk">/</c> doch gij hadt ook anders kunnen spreken. Ik begrijp nu te laat beter sommige buijen van humeur in haar<c type="kk">/</c> en sommige dingen die ik dacht moedwillig zij verkeerd deed<c type="kk">/</c> als verschijnselen ook van zenuwen en hebbende zij ze meer als ’t ware onwillekeurig gedaan<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo als zij mij reeds bij meer dan een gelegenheid later zeide “<hi rend="italics">Soms weet ik niet wat ik doe</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">En er is zoowel voor mij als voor U een verontschuldiging in het begrijpelijke van dat men bij zulk eene vrouw soms niet weet waaraan zich te houden<c type="kk">/</c> en bovendien de finantieele bezwaren – doch wij hadden meer een middenweg moeten kiezen en indien wij dien nu nog konden vinden – ofschoon die nu moeielijk te vinden zal zijn – het ware nog humaan en minder wreed<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik heb haar geen hoop willen geven evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> en ik heb haar aangemoedigd en trachten te troosten en te sterken <hi rend="italics">op den weg waarop zij nu is</hi><c type="kk">/</c> alleen staande<c type="kk">/</c> werkende voor zich en haar kinderen. Toch mijn hart word sterk tot haar getrokken met hetzelfde innige medelijden van vroeger<c type="kk">/</c> medelijden hetwelk ook steeds leefde in mij in deze laatste maanden<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs bij eene scheiding<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> onze vriendschap<c type="kk">/</c> broer<c type="kk">/</c> is er zeer door geschokt en indien gij zoudt zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> wij hebben ons zeker niet vergist<c type="kk">/</c> en indien gij mij zoudt blijken te zijn in dezelfde stemming nog van toen – ik zoude U niet meer kunnen achten precies als vroeger.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Respecteerende ik U vroeger juist ook omdat op een moment waar anderen mij niet meer wilden kennen wegens ik met haar was<c type="kk">/</c> gij mij hielpt om haar in ’t leven te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik zeg niet er geen wijziging of verandering noodig was maar – wij zijn (of liever ik ben) geloof ik wat ver gegaan. Door dat ik nu hier een atelier heb is misschien meer dan één finantieel bezwaar minder fataal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik eindig met te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> denk er over na als gij wilt – maar indien uw stemming na wat ik U zeg precies blijft als dezen zomer<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik voor U niet meer ’t zelfde respect hebben als vroeger<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Overigens ik ben tevens besloten U over een eventueele verandering van Uw omstandigheden of carriere geen woord meer te spreken<c type="kp">_</c> Want ik zie als ’t ware twee naturen in U die in U zelf strijden tegen elkaar – verschijnsel dat ik in mij zelf ook zie<c type="kk">/</c> doch zijnde voor U<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> misschien bij mij<c type="kk">/</c> door dat ik 4 jaar ouder ben<c type="kk">/</c> een paar kwesties beslist<c type="kk">/</c> welke bij U meer in gisting zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Denk eens na over wat ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik het best vinden<c type="kk">/</c> doch gij kunt het ook van U afschuiven<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik voor mij wou er ronduit over spreken tot U en kan mijn gevoelens U niet verheelen. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Betreffende mijn gevoelen hoe ver men gaan <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> in een geval waar het geldt een arm<c type="kk">/</c> verlaten<c type="kk">/</c> ziek schepsel zich aan te trekken<c type="kk">/</c> dat zeide ik U reeds bij eene vroegere gelegenheid en herzeg het</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">            <hi rend="italics">tot in het ONeindige</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">En daar staat tegenover ook onze wreedheid oneindig wezen kan.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I came back to Nuenen yesterday evening, and now I must get what I have to tell you off my chest straightaway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I packed up my tools, studies, &amp;c. there and sent them here and, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> having cleared out the little room, I’m already installed for the time being in this new workplace, where I hope I may be able to make some progress.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Know also that I spoke to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and that it’s our decision, even more definitely, that she will stay by herself and I by myself in any event, so that the world can’t reasonably find fault.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now that we’ve parted we’ll remain parted, only looking back we regret that we didn’t choose a middle way instead, and even now there remains a mutual attachment that has roots or grounds that go too deep to be transitory.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Now I have to tell you a few things that I won’t return to again after this — which you may take as you will — which you’re at liberty to reflect about or to dismiss — that’s not my business — you must decide that for yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Know, then, that I look back with deep regret on your visit this summer, on our conversations then, and on what arose out of them. Time has now passed over it, but I can’t deny, looking back, that it seems to me that we weren’t right. And now I regard your words and you yourself rather differently, and I can no longer think of you with exactly the same feeling as before. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For I now see more clearly how you and others appeared to wish that I should part from her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I don’t doubt the good intentions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It was up to me to decide and so, if I did wrong, I may not, in my view, blame you in the <hi rend="italics">first</hi> place (in the <hi rend="italics">first</hi> place I blame myself), but you in the <hi>second</hi> place.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The levers that worked on me so that I was unsettled, and with which you were at least to some extent concerned — were, first, touching on an infinitely tender question from the past that troubled me, secondly your saying that ‘my duty’ would perhaps lead me to part. Well — if what you said had been entirely isolated — I wouldn’t even mention it — but it’s too much like the feelings of other people with whom I also differ for me to be able to regard your opinions as being entirely isolated. I accepted your point of view — although probably with intentions very different from what you imagine, and concerning which time will clear up one thing and another for you that now isn’t the time to discuss.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You drew my attention to a case where it ‘had worked well’ that a certain man had left a certain woman.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">That <hi rend="italics">may</hi> be true in itself — very true — but was it applicable <hi rend="italics">here</hi> concerning her and me? You see, that’s something else.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And I’ve taken the liberty of looking back over it to see ‘<hi rend="italics">whether it had worked well</hi>’. And — my friend — that’s only too doubtful now. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Know that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> has managed well, <hi rend="italics">working</hi> (namely as a washerwoman)<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> to keep herself and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, consequently has done her duty, and that in great physical weakness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">You know that I took <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> into the house with me because things happened during her confinement that made the doctors in Leiden say that she had to be somewhere quiet if she and her child were to pull through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">There was anaemia and perhaps already the first signs of consumption, too. Well, as long as I was with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> she didn’t get any worse, but stronger in many respects, so that various nasty symptoms didn’t recur.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But now all that is worse again, and I fear very much for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> well-being; and the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">baby</rs>, which I cared for as if it were my own, is no longer what it was either.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Brother, I found <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> in great wretchedness and I’m very sad about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I know that it’s more my own fault, of course, but you could have spoken differently too. Now, too late, I understand better that some of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> fits of temper, and some things that I thought she did wrong deliberately, were also symptoms of nerves, and that she did them more unwittingly, as it were. As she said to me on more than one occasion later, ‘<hi rend="italics">Sometimes I don’t know what I’m doing</hi>’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Both you and I have an excuse, in that it’s understandable that one sometimes doesn’t know how to deal with a woman like that, and then there were the financial difficulties — but still we should have chosen more of a middle way, and if we could still find it even now — although it will be difficult to find now — it would still be humane and less cruel. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I didn’t want to get <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> hopes up though, and I encouraged her and tried to comfort her and strengthen her <hi rend="italics">on the path she is on now</hi>, alone, working for herself and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>. Yet my heart is strongly drawn to her with the same profound pity as in the past, pity that has always lived on in me during these last months, even with a separation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Well, our friendship, brother, has taken a heavy blow from this, and if you should say, we were certainly not mistaken, and if you should reveal yourself to me to be of exactly the same mind now as you were then — I would no longer be able to esteem you precisely as I did in the past.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I respected you then precisely because, at a time when other people didn’t want to know me because I was with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, you helped me to keep her alive.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I don’t say that no change or alteration was necessary, but — I think we (or rather I) went too far. Now that I have a studio here, perhaps more than one financial difficulty is less fatal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I end by saying, think about it if you will — but if, after what I’ve told you, your sentiments remain precisely the same as this summer, I can no longer have the same respect for you as I did before.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Incidentally, I’ve also resolved not to say another word to you about a possible change in your circumstances or career. For I see as it were two natures in you, struggling with each other within you — a phenomenon that I also see in myself, but there are still, perhaps, a few questions fermenting in you that in your eyes have already been resolved for me because I’m 4 years older. Think about what I’ve said, that would be very good, although you can also dismiss it. But for my part I wanted to talk to you frankly about it, and can’t conceal my feelings from you. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">As to my view about how far one <hi rend="italics">may</hi> go in a case where one concerns oneself with a poor, forsaken, sick creature, I’ve already told you on a previous occasion, and repeat,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32"><hi rend="italics">to INfinity</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">And on the other hand, our cruelty can be infinite too.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter dates from after Van Gogh’s trip to The Hague. On 20 December Mr van Gogh told Theo that Vincent had left for Utrecht that morning and that he would then go on to The Hague ‘to return within a few days so he has said’ (FR b2250). Assuming that Van Gogh stayed for about four days and in view of the fact that in the present letter he speaks of having spent a night back in Brabant <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, we have dated the letter on or about Wednesday, 26 December 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s trip to The Hague <ref target="let416.xml">(416)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is given the mangle room to use as his studio <ref target="let413.xml">(413)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Both the emphasis on ‘working’ and the addition in brackets are to indicate that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> had succeeded in keeping out of prostitution.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘In uw ogen’ (in your eyes).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
<p>A reference to what Van Gogh had written in April 1883 ‘“How far may one go in becoming involved with an unfortunate woman?” Answer — “ad infinitum”’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let336.xml">letter 336</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    