<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 28 December 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let418"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b380 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b215 a-b V/1962 (sheets 2, 3)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>418</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>350a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>420</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-12-28">on or about Friday, 28 December 1883</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0380" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0380" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000495_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0215 a" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000250_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000250_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0215 a" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000250_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000250_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0215 b" xml:id="surf-pb-3r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000251_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3r-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000251_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0215 b" xml:id="surf-pb-3v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000251_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3v-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000251_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Weet het goed dat ik het meen wat ik tot U zeg met betrekking tot de vrouw<c type="kp">_</c>– Weet het goed dat al wat Uw bezoek van dezen zomer voor teleurstelling meebragt voor mij – meer dan gij weet – voor zoo ver ’t me persoonlijk raakte is dat niet iets wat ik zwaar zal tillen – maar het andere – dat n.l. ik nu haar terugvond zóó dat het hart mij er week van wordt – dat – het zal blijven – een onoverkomelijk iets tusschen U en mij – <hi rend="italics">tenzij ze nog gered wordt</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Gij waart toen ligtzinnig met Uw woorden – gij dacht niet na bij wat gij zeidet en spraakt blijkbaar zonder voldoende gronden – en hoe ik daar over denk<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg het U zonder omwegen – dat ge met Pa<c type="kk">/</c> die ook dikwijls zóó doet<c type="kk">/</c> gemeen hebt ge <hi rend="italics">wreed</hi> zijt met Uw wereldwijsheid<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wreed<c type="kk">/</c> herzeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> want wat is wreeder dan eene zóó ongelukkige<c type="kk">/</c> verwelkte vrouw en haar kindje een steun te ontnemen<c type="kp">_</c> Denk niet dat gij ’t u zelf wijs zult kunnen maken het niets was of maar verbeelding van mij<c type="kk">/</c> denk niet dat het U zal helpen te redeneeren dat het slechts eene verlepte hoer en hoerenkinderen hier geldt<c type="kp">_</c>– Reden te meer tot innige compassie<c type="kk">/</c> in <hi rend="italics">mijn</hi> oog<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat ik trouwens getoond heb ook.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik heb <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> opgemerkt GIJ in al dien tijd <hi rend="italics">geen woord</hi> ooit schreeft betreffende haar en <hi rend="italics">niet antwoordet</hi> toen ik U zeide ik van haar gehoord had.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En meer andere dingen merk ik <hi>nu</hi> op en <hi rend="italics">omdat</hi> <hi rend="italics">ik ze nu opmerk</hi> spreek ik tot U niet meer op denzelfden toon van vroeger<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik weet wel dat betrekkelijk gij het met eene goede bedoeling deedt – ik weet wel hoe gij tracht vrede te houden met iedereen (wat ik geloof niet te doen is) – ik weet wel dat gij zelfs in dit geval U waarschijnlijk niet eens bewust zijt iets gedaan te hebben wat niet regt was – doch – broer – het <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> niet zamengaan met de wereld goede vriendjes te blijven en ons geweten te volgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Uw <hi rend="italics">geweten</hi> geeft ge niet het zijne<c type="kp">_</c> Ik weet ook dat niet iedereen in mijn geval en omstandigheden ’t ondernemen zou U tegen te spreken doch al zou niet iedereen dat doen<c type="kk">/</c> ik ten minste wil het U zeggen dat ik in dezen iets tegen U heb en in het algemeen U waarschuw tegen Uwe politiek. Die <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> TE politiek vind<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Want ik voorzie gij later (misschien veel later) spijt zult hebben van veel wat gij nu voor regt houdt<c type="kp">_</c>– Waarom ik dat denk hoef ik U nu geen reden van te geven voorloopig<c type="kk">/</c> want gij zoudt me niet gelooven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dien tijd dat ik van haar gescheiden ben geweest heeft weer bedorven grootendeels wat gewonnen was voor haar behoud<c type="kk">/</c> en dat maakt het nu al moeielijker en moeielijker. Is er nu nog iets aan te doen – maar op welke manier?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Het is hier voorwaar geen kwestie van geld <hi rend="italics">alleen</hi> want de arme vrouw mist mij zelf ook zoo als ik was voor haar en voor haar kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat ik hield van hen en nog evenveel<c type="kk">/</c> zoo niet meer hart voor hen heb nu<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat gij schrijft betreffende “dat ik haar en mij zelf een slechten dienst zou bewijzen” in een zekeren brief<c type="kk">/</c> wees zoo goed dat terug te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> gedachtig zijnde aan den dienst door U dezen zomer bewezen aan haar en haar kinderen en mij<c type="kk">/</c> werkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> zwijg dat maar liefst!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Gij <hi rend="italics">presumeert</hi> bovendien in den brief in kwestie<c type="kk">/</c> waarin die éénige uitdrukking voorkomt betreffende haar die ge sedert dezen zomer geschreven hebt – ge <hi rend="italics">presumeert</hi> dat ik “die persoon” zoo als ge haar noemt mee naar Drenthe zou willen nemen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik zou dat niet kunnen <hi rend="italics">zelfs indien ik het wilde</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wegens ik er het geld niet voor heb<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Wat het geld betreft – broer – ge begrijpt ik er geen pleizier meer in heb niet waar<c type="kk">/</c> dat begrijpt ge wel goed niet waar<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">ik had er pleizier in wegens het niet alleen tot mijn maar ook tot het behoud van die arme schepsels diende<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het is een triesten brief aan ’t eind van dit jaar – voor mij triest om te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> voor U triest om te ontvangen (ofschoon ’t U vrijstaat het van U af te schuiven<c type="kk">/</c> weet gij <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> voor U zelf) maar erger is het voor de arme vrouw. Gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">b. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik heb berigt van haar op nieuw<c type="kk">/</c> daar ik haar naar een dokter stuurde en een &amp; ander daaromtrent vernam.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Verder – broer – mijn antwoord op de tijding dat een calamiteit die U dreigde was afgewend<c type="kk">/</c> weet gij dat koel was<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb dienaangaande geen ander antwoord dan: “<hi rend="italics">tant</hi> PIS pour vous – mon ami.” Misschien zult ge later begrijpen waarom<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zeg niet dat het geen calamiteit zou zijn geweest maar............................... Er zijn van die momenten in ’t leven waarop ’t beter is de slag valle<c type="kk">/</c> al zij die hard<c type="kk">/</c> dan dat men in de termen valle door de wereld <hi rend="italics">gespaard</hi> te worden m.i.– Mij aangaande<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben vast aan het ongeluk en mislukking<c type="kk">/</c> het is verdomd hard soms maar enfin<c type="kk">/</c> nogthans de zoogenaamd gelukkigen en eeuwig slagenden benijd ik niet daar ik te veel er achter heen zie<c type="kp">_</c> Neem de <hi rend="italics">Prisonnier</hi> van Gerome – de man die geboeid ligt is voorzeker er leelijk aan toe maar het is beter te zijn m.i. hem zelf dan dien anderen kerel die het heertje is en hem treitert.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik zeg dit<c type="kk">/</c> U wijzende op de extrêmes van toestanden<c type="kp">_</c> geenszins verwar ik b.v. mijn eigen lot met hooger opgevoerde misère zoo als van den prisonnier<c type="kp">_</c> Evenwel een je ne sais quoi van waar ik op wijs ziet men ook in onze maatschappij<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">En ik voor mij <hi rend="italics">feliciteer</hi> U <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> met dat het te voorzien is gij het houden kunt met zekere authoriteiten<c type="kp">_</c> Het kwam mij voor het niet overbodig was mij eens te verklaren tegenover U<c type="kp">_</c>– Gij kunt het opvatten net precies zoo als ge wilt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik vergeet ook niet dat in het begin gij deernis hebt gehad met de vrouw in kwestie. Maar juist omdat ikzelf ook niet blind was noch ben voor haar fouten doch <hi rend="italics">ondanks dat</hi> haar behoud zocht en zoek<c type="kk">/</c> zoo had dit gevoelen van mij door U geloof ik meer kunnen gerespecteerd worden en beter begrepen – alsdan zoudt gij ook vaster mijn partij hebben kunnen opnemen tegenover wie er minder van wisten dan gij en het ware voor mij zoo hoog niet geloopen dat ik het wel <hi rend="italics">moest</hi> opgeven<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Ik waarschuw nu U nog omdat het <hi rend="italics">misschien</hi> nog niet te laat is<c type="kk">/</c> wordt het erger zoo is het de tijd van waarschuwen niet meer<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Hebt ge noodig ik nog duidelijker U alles verklare<c type="kk">/</c> ziehier<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge zegt het zelf dat gij wenscht ik de vrouw verlate<c type="kk">/</c> ja absoluut verlate<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Goed, maar dat wil of kan ik niet doen<c type="kk">/</c> verstaat ge, vriend, en het ware valsch indien ik zulks deed – ik denk aan een oud Bijbelwoord<c type="kk">/</c> “<hi>verberg uw aangezigt niet voor uwen naaste</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Vierkantweg zeg ik U <hi rend="italics">nu</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi>neen</hi> Theo (wilt gij nu presumeeren ik dit of dat wil doen<c type="kk">/</c> denk gij er van precies wat ge wilt<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal doen zoo als ik doen zal D.v.)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik weet nu zeer wel dit een teer punt is dat zamenhangt met het finantieele. Niet in den zin waarop gij in Uw brief doelt alleen<c type="kk">/</c> maar in de eerste plaats nog in een anderen. Indien ik geld van U accepteer en doe iets waar gij U lijnregt tegen verklaart<c type="kk">/</c> zou dit scheef zijn<c type="kp">_</c> ik heb altijd met U gesproken openhartig over alles en juist mij getoond zoo als ik was<c type="kk">/</c> getracht naar opregtheid maar ik heb niet gehandeld zonder er U in te kennen. Goed<c type="kk">/</c> waar dit zou ophouden en wij nu in ons privé leven elkaar niet meer zouden kennen<c type="kk">/</c> zou onze positie iets scheefs krijgen. En daar bedank ik voor.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik heb me uitgesproken over Pa<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb me uitgesproken over U wat dezen zomer aangaat<c type="kp">_</c> waarom? om U over te halen tot <hi rend="italics">mijn</hi> zienswijs?– Neen<c type="kk">/</c> maar omdat ik het valsch van mij zou vinden ik zulke dingen in mij op sloot. Een verrader ben ik nu eenmaal niet en indien ik tegen iemand iets heb zoo zeg ik het en voor de gevolgen vrees ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> al kunnen die serieus genoeg zijn.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik ben nu eenmaal zoo – Ik zelf helder de positie op en zeg<c type="kk">/</c> stop eens<c type="kk">/</c> want dit en dat denk ik heel anders over dan gij en ik kan niet meer met de oude hartelijkheid met U omgaan (’k zeg niet dat ik <hi rend="italics">in ’t geheel niet</hi> meer wil omgaan met Pa of U – ik ben zoo’n drijver niet)<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Maar ik voel het als er iets gebroken is<c type="kp">_</c>– En ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> wat gebroken is is gebroken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Als ik dat doe zoo vind ik ten minste mijn sereniteit terug<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou mijn sereniteit verliezen als ik niet oprecht genoeg was.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ik durf de toekomst onder de oogen zien mits – ik maar niet treed in dingen welke ik zou voelen valsch te zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">En wilt ge nog een reden te meer<c type="kk">/</c> ziehier dan: Ter wille van de vrouw er boven op te houden zou ik zelfs mijn eigen trots op dit of dat principe willen opofferen wat betreft het aannemen van geld, en deed dit meer dan eens om harentwil en voor de kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> maar als de vrouw er <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> is dan ben ik nog trotscher als anders<c type="kp">_</c>– (Dat zei ik u reeds te s’Hage ten antwoord op iets betreffende goede vrienden zijn met H.G.T.<c type="kk">/</c> toen gij zeidet “ja dat dacht ik wel”<c type="kp">_</c>) En nu is de toestand in mijn oog zóó dat in de gegevenen ik<c type="kk">/</c> als ik geen steun heb van b.v. U<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> doen kan voor de vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> gevolgelijk ik denk bij mij zelf dat het <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> in <hi rend="italics">mijn</hi> eigen magt is haar te helpen – ten minste niet dadelijk. Gij hebt dus magt over mij – gij vooral in combinatie met veel anderen<c type="kk">/</c> die geen van allen het eens zijn kunt met mij. <hi rend="italics">En toch zult gij mij</hi> <hi rend="italics">niet krijgen tot een afstand doen van haar</hi> – met al Uw finantieele magt<c type="kp">_</c> En omdat ik op dat punt van de vrouw dus niet zal toegeven en dat duidelijk wil zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> verstaanbaar voor de hardst hoorende ooren zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> zoo verklaar ik vooruit dat ik besloten heb met haar te deelen het geen mijn eigendom is en ik van U geen geld wensch te accepteeren dan hetgeen ik zonder arrière pensée als eigendom kan beschouwen.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Vincent</p>
    <pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/>
    

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Weet kortom dat ik geloof ik alles doen <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> waar ik een ander niet door benadeel en die vrijheid<c type="kk">/</c> waarop niet alleen ik doch m.i. elk mensch ’t volle<c type="kk">/</c> van zelf sprekende regt heeft – die vrijheid<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik den pligt op te houden als zijnde dat <hi rend="italics">den eenigen stand</hi> welke men op te houden heeft. Ik vraag wel degelijk<c type="kk">/</c> benadeel ik iemand met dit of dat voor en aleer ik tot een daad overga<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar tenzij men mij degelijk bewijze ik iemand benadeel met iets dat ik doe<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik ’t niet behoeven te laten.</p>
<pb f="3v" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-3v-8" facs="#zone-pb-3v-8"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Zoo ik die niet dwing<c type="kk">/</c> wil ook niet gedwongen zijn – ik die anderer vrijheid respecteer<c type="kk">/</c> sta ook op de mijne<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">En betreffende de vrouw en de kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> zij is aan mij gehecht en dat <hi rend="italics">zelfs na de scheiding</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en ik aan haar<c type="kp">_</c> En nu zou ik in eenig opzigt mij stilzwijgend of niet stilzwijgend verbinden tot haar te verlaten<c type="kp">_</c> Neen<c type="kk">/</c> daar zal ik mij nu eens geenszins toe verbinden. Ik vraag U niet verantwoordelijk te zijn voor welke kosten dan ook<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> ge kunt ’t geld verminderen<c type="kk">/</c> geheel doen ophouden<c type="kk">/</c> maar van wat ik heb zal zij haar deel hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">Het ware lafheid van mij broer<c type="kk">/</c> in dezen dubbelzinnig te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Indien ’t er op uit moest loopen ik zelf niets had<c type="kk">/</c> goed – dat ware dan ook ’t ergst en er zouden misschien nog anderen zijn dan gij die mij het leven eenigzins mogelijk zouden maken. En indien niet – nu dan niet.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">You must know that I mean what I say to you regarding the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>. You must know that all the disappointment that your visit this summer caused me — more than you know — in so far as it touched me personally, it isn’t something that I’ll attach much importance to — but the other thing — namely that I found her again in such a state that my heart melted in me — that — it will remain — something insurmountable between you and me — <hi rend="italics">unless she is yet saved</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You were careless with your words then — you didn’t consider what you were saying and evidently spoke without sufficient grounds — and I’ll tell you straight out what I think about that — that in common with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, who often acts thus, you are <hi rend="italics">cruel</hi> in your worldly wisdom.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Cruel, I repeat, because what is crueller than to deprive such an unfortunate, withered <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and her little <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">child</rs> of support? Don’t think that you can fool yourself that it was nothing, or just my imagination; don’t think that it will help you to argue that this is just about one faded whore and her bastards. All the more reason for profound compassion, in <hi rend="italics">my</hi> view. Which I indeed displayed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I have <hi rend="italics">now</hi> realized that in all that time YOU never wrote<hi rend="italics"> a single word</hi> about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, and <hi rend="italics">didn’t reply</hi> when I told you I’d heard from her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And I <hi>now</hi> realize several other things, and <hi rend="italics">because I realize them now</hi> I no longer speak to you in the same tone as before. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I do know that you did it with good intentions under the circumstances — I do know how you try to keep the peace with everyone (which I believe can’t be done) — I do know that even in this case you’re probably not actually aware of having done something that wasn’t right — yet — brother — remaining good friends with the world and following our conscience <hi rend="italics">cannot</hi> go together. You don’t give your <hi rend="italics">conscience</hi> its due. I also know that not everyone in my case and circumstances would undertake to contradict you, but although not everyone would do that, I at least want to tell you that I do hold something against you in this matter, and that in general I warn you against your policy. Which <hi rend="italics">I</hi> find TOO politic.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">For I foresee that later (perhaps much later) you’ll regret much of what you now take to be right. For the time being I don’t have to give you any reason why I think that, because you wouldn’t believe me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The time that I was parted from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> has largely spoiled again what had been gained for her well-being, and this is making it more and more difficult now. Is there anything still to be done? — but in what way?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">This is truly not a question of money <hi rend="italics">alone</hi>, for the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> also misses me as I was for her and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, namely that I loved them, and still feel as much if not more for them now. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Be so good as to take back what you write in a certain letter ‘that I would do <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> and myself a disservice’; mindful of the service you did her and her children and me this summer, you’d best keep quiet about that!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You <hi rend="italics">presume</hi> moreover, in the letter in question, which contains the <hi rend="italics">only</hi> reference to her that you’ve written since this summer — you <hi rend="italics">presume</hi> that I would want to take ‘that person’, as you call <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs>, to Drenthe with me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I couldn’t do that <hi rend="italics">even if I wanted to</hi>, because I don’t have the money for it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">As to the money — brother — you understand that I don’t take any pleasure in it any more, don’t you? You do understand that, don’t you?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I did take pleasure in it because it meant not only my survival, but also that of those poor creatures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">It’s a sad letter at the end of this year — sad for me to write, sad for you to receive (although you’re at liberty to dismiss it, decide <hi rend="italics">that</hi> for yourself), but it’s worse for the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’ve had news from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">her</rs> again, since I sent her to a doctor and have heard various details about it.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Further — brother — you know that my response was cool to the tidings that a calamity that threatened you has been averted, I have no other response in that regard than ‘<hi rend="italics">too</hi> BAD for you — my friend’. Perhaps you’ll understand why one day. I don’t say that it wouldn’t have been a calamity, but ............................... It seems to me that there are those moments in life when it’s better that the blow should fall, albeit it hard, than that one should be liable to be <hi rend="italics">spared</hi> by the world. As to me, I’m bound to misfortune and failure, it’s damned hard sometimes, but there it is. I still don’t envy the so-called fortunate and eternally successful ones, since I see too much behind it. Take the <hi rend="italics">Prisonnier</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs> — the man lying shackled is in a bad way to be sure, but in my view it’s better to be him than that other fellow who’s lording it over him and tormenting him.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I say this to point out to you the extremes of circumstances. In no way do I, for example, confuse my own fate with more aggravated misery like that of the prisoner. Nevertheless, in our society one also sees a <hi rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi> of what I refer to.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">And for myself I do <hi rend="italics">not congratulate</hi> you that it may be expected that you’ll be able to keep in with certain authorities. It occurred to me that it wouldn’t be superfluous to declare myself to you. You can take it just exactly as you like.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I don’t forget, either, that at the beginning you had compassion for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> in question. But precisely because I myself was not and am not blind to her faults, but sought and seek her preservation <hi rend="italics">despite them</hi>, I believe that you could have respected and better understood this feeling of mine — then you would also have been able to take my part more resolutely against anyone who knew less about it than you, and it wouldn’t have got to such a high pitch that I <hi rend="italics">had to</hi> give it up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I’m warning you now, because <hi rend="italics">perhaps</hi> it’s still not too late; if it gets any worse the time for warnings will be past.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">If you need me to explain everything to you even more plainly, here you are. You say yourself that you wish I would leave the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs>, yes, leave her completely.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Very well, but I won’t or can’t do it, do you understand, my friend, and it would be treachery if I were to do such a thing — I’m thinking of old words from the Bible, ‘<hi>hide not thy face from thy neighbour</hi>’<hi rend="italics">.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <hi rend="italics">Now</hi> I tell you outright, <hi>no</hi> Theo (if you choose to presume that I want to do this or that, think exactly what you like, I shall do what I shall do, D.V.).<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">I know very well that this is a sore point that relates to the financial aspect. Not only in the sense you refer to in your letter, but in the first place in another. If I accept money from you and do something you declare yourself to be directly opposed to, that would be wrong. I’ve always talked openly to you about everything, and revealed myself just as I was, tried to be honest, but I haven’t acted without consulting you. Very well, should this stop and should we not know each other in our private lives any more, there would be something false about our position. And that I decline.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I’ve spoken my mind about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, I’ve spoken my mind about you as far as this summer is concerned. Why? To convert you to <hi rend="italics">my</hi> way of thinking? No, just because I would consider it treacherous of me if I were to keep such things to myself. I am simply not a traitor, and if I have something against someone, then I say so and I don’t fear the consequences, although they can be serious enough. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">That’s simply the way I am — I clarify the position myself and say: hold on, because I think very differently from you about this and that, and I can’t associate with you with the old cordiality any more (I’m not saying that I don’t want to associate with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> or you <hi rend="italics">at all</hi> any more — I’m not such a zealot).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">But I feel it when something has been broken. And I say, what’s broken is broken.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">If I do this, at least I’ll regain my serenity, I would lose my serenity if I wasn’t frank enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I dare to face the future provided — I don’t enter into things that I’d feel were dishonest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">And if you want yet another reason, well here you are then. For the sake of putting the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> back on her feet, I would even sacrifice my own pride over this principle or that as far as taking money is concerned, and did this more than once for her sake and for the children, but if the woman were <hi rend="italics">not</hi> there then I would be even prouder than ever. (I already told you that in The Hague in response to something about being good friends with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G.T.</rs>, when you said then, ‘yes, I thought as much’.) And now, in my view, the situation is such that I can do <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> for the woman in the circumstances if I have no support, from you for instance, and that consequently I think myself that it is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> in <hi rend="italics">my</hi> power to help her — at least not right away. So you have power over me — you, above all, in conjunction with many others, none of whom are able to agree with me. <hi rend="italics">And yet you will not get me to renounce her</hi> — with all your financial power. And because I won’t give in on the issue of the woman and want to say that clearly, make it audible to even the deafest of ears, I declare in advance that I’ve decided to share with her that which is my property, and I don’t wish to accept any money from you except what I can regard as my property without second thoughts.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Vincent</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36"><pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Know, in short, that I believe I’m <hi rend="italics">allowed</hi> to do anything that doesn’t harm anyone else, and that freedom, to which not just I but, in my view, every human being has the full, self-evident right — that freedom, I say, I have a duty to uphold as being <hi rend="italics">the only position</hi> that I have to uphold. I really do ask: will I harm someone with this or that before I act? But unless people really prove to me that I would harm someone with something that I do, I don’t have to refrain from doing it. 
        <pb f="3v" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-3v-8" facs="#zone-pb-3v-8"/> So, I who don’t coerce also don’t want to be coerced — I who respect others’ freedoms also insist on my own.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">And as for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">woman</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466 bio.xml#_467">children</rs>, she’s attached to me, and that <hi rend="italics">even after the parting</hi>, and I to her. And now I should in some way undertake, tacitly or not tacitly, to abandon her? No, I won’t undertake any such thing. I’m not asking you to be responsible for any costs whatsoever; on the contrary, I tell you, you can reduce the money, stop it altogether, but she’ll have her share of what I have.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">True cowardice on my part, brother, would be to be ambiguous about this. If it had to come to it that I myself had nothing, very well — that would be the worst, and there would still perhaps be others besides you who would make my life possible, to some extent. And if not — well, then not.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter must have been written after <ref target="let417.xml">letter 417</ref>, which dates from about Wednesday, 26 December, because it elaborates on and explains the point of view expressed in the previous letter: the remark about being ‘cruel’ at the beginning of this letter ties in with the end of the previous one. This also increases the likelihood that it was written soon afterwards. The letter in any event dates from before the end of the year (<ref target="let419.xml">letter 419</ref>). Vincent moreover repeats his views about Theo’s attitude to Sien, and says he means what he wrote about this before (<ref target="let417.xml">letter 417</ref>). Since he also remarks ‘It’s a sad letter at the end of this year’ <ref target="#l-82">(l. 82)</ref> and he has meanwhile received another letter from Sien <ref target="#l-89">(ll. 89-91)</ref>, we have dated the letter on or about. Friday, 28 December 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The order of the last two pages of the first sheet has been reversed in respect of that in <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990. We retain Van Gogh’s usual order of writing on folded sheets; this is borne out by the content of the letter and the duct of the hand.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The last part of the letter (<ref target="#l-132">ll. 132</ref> ff.) was previously printed as a separate, incomplete letter (<ref target="let421.xml">421</ref> [193a]). We regard it as a continuation of the present letter because of the absence of a salutation. It means that there are two signatures in the letter, but this is far from exceptional in Van Gogh’s correspondence.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to The Hague in August <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
 <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>There are two versions of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Jean Léon Gérôme</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">prisoner</hi>: one dating from 1861 (Nantes, Musée des Beaux-Arts) and one from 1863 (private collection). See Ackerman 1986, pp. 210-211, cat. nos. 134-135. Goupil had included a photograph in the series <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Oeuvre de J.-L. Gérôme</hi>, Goupil s.a. (no. 567), while the engraving <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The prisoner</hi> appeared in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Illustrated London News</hi> 56 (14 December 1872), between pp. 558-559. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_132">Ill. 132</rs>. It is not possible to say for certain which version Van Gogh knew.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>An allusion to Ps. 69:18 (in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 69:17), where the word is ‘servant’ (‘knecht’) not ‘neighbour’ (‘naaste’). Van Gogh probably changed the wording here deliberately, to make it more specifically relevant to their situation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Deo volente (God willing).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    