<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Sunday, 3 February 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let428"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b386 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>428</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>355</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>429</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-02-03">on or about Sunday, 3 February 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0386" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0386" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000504_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ik was blijde met Uw brief van heden en het ingeslotene en dank U zeer voor beiden. Het komt mij voor dat tot heden het herstel van Moe over ’t algemeen genomen zeer voorspoedig gaat. En er hoe langer hoe minder <hi rend="italics">direkt</hi> gevaar is en het meer en meer wordt gereduceerd tot eene kwestie van tijd vooral<c type="kp">_</c> Toch – geheel de zelfde zal Moe zeker niet zijn als de breuk digtgegroeid zal wezen. ’t Effekt op haar en van den weeromstuit op Pa welligt ook<c type="kk">/</c> zal m.i<c type="kp">_</c> zijn ’t hun in eens een heel eind verder in den ouden dag heeft geplaatst.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">In de gegevenen was ik blijde t’huis te zijn. en het gebeurde ongeluk natuurlijkerwijs eenige kwesties (waarin ik nog al verschil van inzigt met Pa en Moe) geheel op den achtergrond geschoven hebbende – gaat het alles nog al wel tusschen ons en kan er wel van komen ik in ’t vervolg meer en langer te Nunen zal blijven dan aanvankelijk ik wel veronderstelde ’t geval te kunnen wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het ligt toch eenigzins in den aard der zaak dat juist ook in later tijd<c type="kk">/</c> als Moe meer zal verdragen<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> moeten worden &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> ik een handje zal kunnen helpen. Nu de consternatie der eerste dagen wat voorbij is kan ik betrekkelijk heel geregeld mijn werk doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik <hi rend="italics">schilder</hi> dagelijks aan studies van de wevers hier,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> die geloof ik beter zijn van techniek dan de geschilderde studies uit Drenthe die ik U stuurde.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Die gevallen van de weefgetouwen met die betrekkelijk gecompliceerde machinerie in ’t midden waarvan het figuurtje zit<c type="kk">/</c> zal dunkt mij voor penteekeningen zich ook prêteeren en zal ik er eenigen van maken in gevolge den wenk dien gij in uw schrijven mij geeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7"><hi rend="italics">Vóór</hi> het ongeluk gebeurde was mijn afspraak met Pa dat ik kosteloos een tijd hier zou inwonen ten einde daardoor ruimte te krijgen om eenige rekeningen in ’t begin van ’t jaar af te doen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En ’t geld dat gij zondt met Nieuwejaar en in half Januarij ongeveer was daarvoor klaar. Doordat ik toen het ongeluk gebeurde dit aan Pa gaf<c type="kk">/</c> zijn het deze keer die verfrekeningen die aan de beurt liggen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Te meer daar Pa net een buitenkansje heeft van f<c type="kp">_</c> 100 van Oom Stricker<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik heel aardig van oom S<c type="kp">_</c> vind<c type="kp">_</c> In het finantieele heb ik dus door mijn hierzijn <hi>niet</hi> geprofiteerd<c type="kp">_</c> En het is mijn plan krachtig door te zetten met het werk<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">Over een jaar zoowat</hi> dan zullen 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>de moeielijkheden in ’t finantieele<c type="kk">/</c> die het ongeluk van Moe niet in gebreke zal blijven na zich te slepen<c type="kk">/</c> voor Pa meer voelbaar zijn dan nu denk ik<c type="kp">_</c> Laat ons in den tusschentijd trachten iets met mijn werk ook te doen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Après tout zijn <hi rend="italics">Pa en Moe persoonlijk</hi> voor hun leven <hi rend="italics">gedekt</hi><c type="kk">/</c> Pa’s pensioen gelijkstaande met zijn tegenwoordig inkomen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar broer<c type="kk">/</c> <hi>de arme zusters</hi> – zonder kapitaal<c type="kk">/</c> in een tijd dat de animo om meisjes zonder geld te trouwen niet groot is in de maatschappij – voor hun kon ’t leven wel eens graauw en triest blijven<c type="kk">/</c> en hun normale ontwikkeling gedwarsboomd. Doch wij willen den tijd niet vooruit loopen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Hoe het altijd stil liggen op Moe’s gestel werken zal<c type="kk">/</c> is moeielijk vooruit te bepalen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Alle voorzorgen die wij nemen kunnen om doorliggen te voorkomen<c type="kk">/</c> zijn natuurlijk van belang. We hebben een soort draagbaar gemaakt om Moe te kunnen verbedden als het wenschelijk is<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – doch hoe minder dit voorloopig geschiedt hoe beter. Rustig liggen is nommer 1<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Moe’s humeur is gelukkig<c type="kk">/</c> haar moeielijke positie in aanmerking genomen, zeer gelijkmatig en tevreden. En zij amuseert zich met kleinigheden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb het kerkje met de heg en de boomen geschilderd onlangs voor haar.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> zoo’n soort geval<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Dat ik de natuur hier heerlijk vind zal U zeker zeer begrijpelijk voorkomen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Als ge ooit komt zal ik U eens in de hutten der wevers brengen<c type="kp">_</c>– De figuren der wevers en de vrouwen die garen winden zullen U zeker treffen<c type="kp">_</c> De laatste studie die ik maakte is het figuur van een man die in ’t weefgetouw zit op zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> de buste en de handen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik ben ook aan ’t schilderen van een weefgetouw – van oud groenachtig bruin geworden eikenhout – waarin ’t jaartal <hi rend="italics">1730</hi> staat gesneden. Bij dat getouw<c type="kk">/</c> aan een raampje waardoor men een groen veldje ziet<c type="kk">/</c> staat een kinderstoel en het kleine kind zit daarin uren lang te kijken naar het heen en weer schieten van den weversspoel<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb dat geval aangepakt net zoo als ’t in de natuur was<c type="kk">/</c> het getouw met het wevertje<c type="kk">/</c> ’t raampje en die kinderstoel in het armzalige vertrekje met leemen vloer.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als ge wilt<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf me iets meer uitvoerigs over expositie Manet<c type="kk">/</c> zeg eens welke schilderijen er van hem te zien zijn<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Manet’s werk heb ik steeds zeer oorspronkelijk gevonden<c type="kp">_</c>– Kent gij het stuk van Zola over Manet?<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ik betreur het van hem slechts zeer enkele schilderijen te hebben gezien.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Ik zou vooral zijn naakte vrouwenfiguren graag eens zien. Ik vind het niet overdreven dat sommigen<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. Zola<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">dweepen</hi> met hem ofschoon ik voor mij volstrekt niet vind hij onder de allereersten dezer eeuw kan worden gerekend<c type="kp">_</c> Doch ’t is een talent dat <hi rend="italics">zijn raison d’être</hi> <hi rend="italics">zeer zeker heeft</hi> en dat is al veel. Het stuk dat Zola over hem schreef staat in het deeltje “mes haines”<c type="kp">_</c> de <hi rend="italics">conclusies</hi> die Zola maakt als ware Manet een man die als ’t ware een nieuwe toekomst opent voor moderne opvatting in de kunst<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik voor mij niet deelen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> voor mij is niet Manet doch <hi rend="italics">Millet</hi> die essentieel moderne schilder die den horizon opende voor velen. Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Van allen gegroet – <hi rend="italics">schrijf aan Moe maar eens een keer meer</hi><c type="kk">/</c> de brieven zijn zoo’n afleiding<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I was glad to get your letter today and the enclosure, and thank you very much for both. It seems to me that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s recovery is proceeding very well so far, generally speaking. And that the longer it goes on, the less <hi rend="italics">immediate</hi> danger there is, and the more it’s reduced to a question of time above all. Yet — Ma will certainly not be entirely the same once the fracture has healed. The effect on her, and perhaps as a result on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> too, will in my view be to push them instantly a whole lot further into old age.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I was glad to be at home in the circumstances, and the fact of the accident naturally having pushed some questions (on which I have a considerable difference of opinion with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>) entirely into the background — it’s all going pretty well between us, and it may mean that I’ll stay more and longer in Nuenen than I originally imagined could be the case.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">To some extent it’s in the nature of things, after all, that it’s precisely at a later stage, when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> will have to be moved more &amp;c., that I’ll be able to lend a hand. Now that the consternation of the first few days has subsided a little, I can do my work quite regularly, in the circumstances.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Every day I <hi rend="italics">paint</hi> studies of the weavers here,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which I think are better in technique than the painted studies from Drenthe that I sent you.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I think those things of the looms with that quite complicated machinery, in the middle of which sits the little figure, will also lend themselves to pen drawings, and I’ll make some as a result of the tip you give me in your letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><hi rend="italics">Before</hi> the accident happened, my arrangement with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was that I would live here free of charge for a while, so as to get breathing space to settle some bills at the beginning of the year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And the money that you sent at New Year and about the middle of January was ready for that. Because I gave that to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> when the accident happened, this time it’s those paint bills that are waiting their turn.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The more so since <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> has just had a windfall of 100 guilders from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>, which I think very kind of Uncle S. So I have <hi>not</hi> profited financially from being here. And my plan is to press ahead vigorously with the work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">In a year or so</hi> the 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> financial difficulties that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s accident can’t fail to bring in its train will be more noticeable to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> than now, I think. So in the meantime, let’s also try to do something with my work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">After all, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> personally</hi> are <hi rend="italics">secure</hi> for their lives, Pa’s pension being equivalent to his current income. But brother, <hi>the poor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401 bio.xml#_407">sisters</rs></hi> — without capital, at a time when there’s no great inclination in society to marry girls without money — for them life could well remain drab and sad, and their normal development thwarted. We don’t want to anticipate things, though.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">How lying still all the time will affect <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s constitution is difficult to tell in advance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">All the precautions we can take to prevent bedsores are important, of course. We’ve made a sort of stretcher in order to be able to change <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s bedclothes when needed — although the less this happens the better for the time being.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Lying quietly is number 1.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Fortunately <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s mood is very equable and content, considering her difficult situation. And she amuses herself with trifles. I recently painted the little church with the hedge and the trees for her,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> something like this,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">You will certainly find the fact that I love the countryside here very understandable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">If you ever come I’ll take you into the weavers’ cottages sometime. The figures of the weavers and the women who wind the yarn will certainly strike you. The last study that I made is the figure of a man sitting in the loom on his own, the bust and the hands.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’m also painting a loom — of old oak gone greenish brown — with the date <hi rend="italics">1730</hi> carved into it. Next to that loom, by a little window through which one can see a small green field, there’s a high chair, and the little child sits in it, watching the weaver’s shuttle fly back and forth for hours. I’ve tackled that affair just as it is in reality, the loom with the little weaver, the small window and that high chair in the wretched little room with the clay floor.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">If you would, write to me in rather greater detail about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> exhibition, tell me which of his paintings are to be seen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I’ve always found Manet’s work very original. Do you know <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s piece on Manet?<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I regret that I’ve only seen very few paintings by him.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I would particularly like to see his female nudes. I don’t find it excessive that some people, Zola, for instance, <hi rend="italics">idolize</hi> him, although for myself I really don’t think that he can be counted among the very best of this century. Still, it’s a talent that <hi rend="italics">very certainly has its raison d’être</hi>, and that’s a great deal in itself. The piece that Zola wrote about him is in the volume ‘Mes haines’. For myself I can’t share the <hi rend="italics">conclusions</hi> that Zola draws, as if Manet were a man who’s opening up a new future for modern ideas in art,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> as it were; to me <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs></hi>, not Manet, is that essential modern painter who opened the horizon to many. Regards, with a handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Regards from all — <hi rend="italics">do write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> a bit more often</hi>, the letters are such a diversion.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh received the regular allowance, which must have been the first for February, ‘today’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). As a rule the letter would consequently be dated on or about 2 February. The detail that Uncle Stricker had ‘just’ sent 100 guilders <ref target="#l-54">(ll. 54-55)</ref> moreover dates from after 1 February, for Mr van Gogh does not mention it in his letter of that date to Theo (FR b2251); he does, however, refer to it in his letter of 10 February (FR b2252). We have therefore dated the letter a day later than we would otherwise have done, that is to say on or about Sunday, 3 February 1884.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 <hi rend="italics">Weaver</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_544">F 1120 / JH 443</rs>) is listed as an enclosed sketch. The drawing was not included with the letter in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, however; this was done for the first time, by way of illustration, in the <hi rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1952-1954. Hulsker also states ‘Sketch probably sent with’ (Hulsker 1996, p. 106). The decision to combine the letter and the drawing was undoubtedly based on Van Gogh’s reference to drawing weavers, but we see nothing to substantiate the idea that the drawing was actually sent with this letter. Both the type of paper and the ink used in the letter and the sketch are different.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mrs van Gogh’s broken leg <ref target="let423.xml">(423)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘van de ene plaats naar de andere gedragen’ (carried from one place to another).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> told Theo with satisfaction: ‘Vincent also remains tireless and he moreover spends the day painting and drawing with exemplary ambition’, and nine days later ‘Vincent remains exemplary in nursing and is also working with the greatest ambition on drawing and painting. I do so hope that his work might find some approbation. For he works so much it is exemplary’ (FR b2251, 1 February 1884; FR b2252, 10 February 1884).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had sent Theo two batches containing a total of nine paintings from Drenthe; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let389.xml">see letters 389</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let406.xml">406</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had told Furnée’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_371">son</rs> that he would pay by the twentieth of January: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let421.xml">see letter 421</ref> and cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let422.xml">letter 422</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>A modified bed was created for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs>; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> explained it as follows: ‘the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_495">Doctor</rs> got us to make a sort of stretcher, by laying straps under her, at short distances apart, at both ends of which was a large loop, through which strong hands were thrust. In this way, while the Doctor was there, we were able to lift her without difficulty and lay other bedclothes on the couch. That brought her great relief and it can be repeated again later in the same way if necessary’ (FR b2251, 1 February 1884).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Congregation leaving the Reformed Church in Nuenen </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2486">F 25 / JH 521</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> had this work in her possession until she died. In contrast to the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Reformed Church in Nuenen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_129">F - / JH 447</rs>) – which shows a labourer and in this respect corresponds with the pen-and-ink drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Reformed Church in Nuenen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_743">F 1117 / JH 446</rs>) – there are churchgoers in the painting, but we know that Van Gogh added this group in the autumn of 1885. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 58-65, cat. no. 6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Most probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2451">F 26 / JH 450</rs>), of which there is also a finished pen-and-ink drawing (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_547">F 1122 / JH 454</rs>). As a rule, when Van Gogh used the term ‘study’ he meant a painting.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>There is a watercolour, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver, with a baby in a highchair </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_936">F 1119 / JH 449</rs>), and a drawing, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver, with a baby in a highchair</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_545">F 1118 / JH 452</rs>), of this composition; there is no known painting of it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The memorial exhibition marking <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs>’s death in 1883 was staged in the Ecole Nationale des Beaux-Arts in Paris in January 1884. There were 179 works at this exhibition. It was followed on 4 and 5 February by a sale of Manet’s works (Lugt<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1938-1987, no. 43575). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exposition des oeuvres de Edouard Manet</hi>. Exhib. cat. Paris 1884.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>In the compilation edition of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_311">Mes haines</ref></hi>, which Van Gogh knew and refers to a little later, there were two pieces about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let358.xml#n-19">see letter 358, n. 19</ref>). The most important and most comprehensive was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_340">Ed. Manet, étude biographique et critique</ref></hi>; the other, shorter piece was an essay in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_594">Mon Salon</ref></hi>. Van Gogh is referring to the former (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-10">see n. 10</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The ‘very few paintings’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> that Van Gogh could have seen included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_539">Repose: portrait of Berthe Morisot</rs></hi>, 1870<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>(Providence, Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_540">Le bon bock</rs></hi>, 1873<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>(Philadelphia Museum of Art). They had hung at the Salon of 1873, which Van Gogh had visited (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let009.xml">see letter 9</ref>). It is possible that he also saw Manet’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_541">Argentueil</rs></hi>, 1874<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>(Tournai, Musée des Beaux-Arts) at the Salon of 1875. The London branch of Durand-Ruel exhibited two paintings by Manet during Van Gogh’s time in London (1873-1874), possibly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_542">The balcony</rs></hi>, 1868-1869<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>(Paris, Musée d’Orsay) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_543">Young man in the costume of a Majo</rs></hi>, 1863 (New York, The Metropolitan Museum of Art). He may have seen them there. See exhib. cat. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Manet</hi>. Françoise Cachin <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al</hi>. Paris (Grand Palais) and New York (The Metropolitan Museum of Art)<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1983. New York 1983, pp. 513-514, 537.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>In <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_340">Ed. Manet, étude biographique et critique</ref></hi>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> proclaimed <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> as a painter of the future: ‘I consider it an honour to have been the first to hail the arrival of a new master.’ (Je tiens à honneur d’avoir été le premier à saluer la venue d’un nouveau maître.) The ‘conclusions’ referred to by Van Gogh are taken from chapter 2: ‘There will probably be in it too original, too human a manifestation for the truth not to be ultimately victorious... The future belongs to him; I do not even dare to imprison him in the present.’ (Il y aura là une manifestation trop originale, trop humaine, pour que la vérité ne soit pas enfin victorieuse... L’avenir est à lui; je n’ose même l’enfermer dans le présent.) See Zola 1966-1970, vol. 12, pp. 821, 840.</p>

<p rend="indent">In the article ‘M. Manet’ in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_594">Mon Salon</ref></hi> Zola wrote: ‘I am so sure that Mr Manet will be one of tomorrow’s masters, that I would believe I was doing a good piece of business, if I was rich, by buying all his canvases’ (Je suis tellement certain que M. Manet sera un des maîtres de demain, que je croirais conclure une bonne affaire, si j’avais de la fortune, en achetant toutes ses toiles) (p. 802).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    