<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. Nuenen, on or about Thursday, 13 March 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let437"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8376 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>437</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R44</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>438</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-03-13">on or about Thursday, 13 March 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8376 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8376 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001635_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8376 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001636_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001636_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8376 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001636_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001636_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief over de teekeningen deed me genoegen<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat de weefstoel betreft<c type="kk">/</c> werkelijk is dat een studie van ’t werktuig van ’t begin tot ’t eind op de plaats zelf gemaakt en was moeielijk – wegens men er zóó digt op moest zitten dat het nemen van opmetingen zeer lastig was<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Figuur teekende ik er toch in<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – maar ik wil er niets anders mee zeggen als: “wanneer dat zwarte gevaarte van goor geworden eikenhout met al zijn latten zoowat zóó afsteekt tegen den grijzigheid waar het in staat<c type="kk">/</c> dan zit <hi rend="italics">dáár</hi><c type="kk">/</c> in dat midden, een zwarten aap of kabouterman<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> of spook en kleppert van vroeg tot laat met die latten”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> En gaf die plek aan door een soort gedaante van een wever te zetten door eenige krabben &amp; kladden op de plek waar ik hem zag<c type="kp">_</c>– Gevolgelijk aan proportie van armen of beenen dacht ik toen meest absoluut niet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Toen mijn machine-teekening klaar was gemaakt tamelijk zorgvuldig<c type="kk">/</c> vond ik het zoo onuitstaanbaar dat ik hem niet hoorde klepperen<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik het spook er nog in liet verrijzen<c type="kp">_</c>– Goed – en – laat het nu een machineteekening zijn – houd hem eens naast een <hi rend="italics">model</hi> van een weeftouw en – – – – – de mijne zal <hi rend="italics">toch meer</hi> SPOKEN <hi rend="italics">hoor</hi><c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Overigens</hi> is het niet dan een machineteekening – overigens, op een je ne sais quoi na<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>En – mijn studie leggende naast een teek. v. een werktuigkundige – die een model v. een weefst. zou hebben geteekend – zou de mijne meer uitdrukken dat het ding van door zweeterige handen goor geworden eikenhout is en zou bij wijlen als ge er op keekt (<hi rend="italics">al teekende</hi> ik hem er <hi rend="italics">absoluut niet</hi> in<c type="kk">/</c> of al teeken ik hem er in uit de proportie)<c type="kk">/</c> zoudt ge bij wijlen onwillekeurig denken aan den <hi rend="italics">werkman</hi><c type="kk">/</c> terwijl absoluut niets van die gedachten bij U zou oprijzen kijkende op ’t model van een weefst. door een werktuigkundige<c type="kp">_</c> Er moet soms een soort zucht of klacht uit die latten rommel<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> komen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik zie heel graag teekeningen van machines van U – waarom – omdat als ge ’t vliegwiel <hi rend="italics">alleen</hi> teekent<c type="kk">/</c> IK voor mij ook onwillekeurig denken moet aan den jongen die het draait en zijn presentie ik weet niet hoe voel<c type="kp">_</c> En zij die <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> machineteekeningen beschouwen als <hi rend="italics">modellen v. werktuigen</hi> begrijpen <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> van Uw kunst.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Doch – voor zich zelf – als men zoo’n werktuig teekent – ben ik ’t met U eens men het zoo werktuigkundigachtig mogelijk moet doen<c type="kk">/</c> wil men als studie er iets aan hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Intusschen<c type="kk">/</c> volkomen begrijp ik Uw idee dat wou het een <hi rend="italics">teekening</hi> geweest zijn – die ik <hi rend="italics">hoop</hi> nog eens te maken als ik mijn model magtig kan worden – alsdan het zwarte spookje op den achtergrond het centrum<c type="kk">/</c> het uitgangspunt<c type="kk">/</c> het <hi rend="italics">hart</hi> zou moeten wezen en ’t meest gevoeld<c type="kk">/</c> geacheveerd – de rest 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>ondergeschikt gehouden daaraan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> het doet me pleizier dat ge iets voeldet voor mijn wintertuintje<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Die tuin maakte mij zoo aan ’t droomen en ik heb sedert van ’t zelfde motief er nog een gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> ook met een zwart spookje<c type="kk">/</c> ’t welk er ook weer niet in staat als navolgenswaardig voorbeeld van de structuur v. h. menschelijk ligchaam doch als <hi rend="italics">tache</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ik stuur U die ook en nog een paar anderen<c type="kk">/</c> </p>
 
<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">nl. sepia schets<c type="kk">/</c> in het broek<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> –<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> penteekening<c type="kk">/</c> Knotberken<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – Populierenlaan<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – Achter de Heggen<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – de IJsvogel<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en Wintertuin<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik stuur U die op een rolletje<c type="kk">/</c> wees zoo goed en zet ze in de portefeuille bij de anderen<c type="kk">/</c> ook vooral bij het terugzenden<c type="kk">/</c> dat ze zoo mogelijk vlak blijven. Ik voeg er een stuk grijs papier bij – als ge ze daarop houdt dan zullen ze beter uitkomen.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Betreffende deze teekeningen en de kunstbesch. De kunstbeschouwing kan me niet schelen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar wat me wel schelen kan is dit – ik werk iederen dag natuurlijk – en er is geen week of ik heb eenige studies als deze b.v. Ik reken het altijd onder de mogelijkheden den een of anderen dag een liefhebber te vinden die trek heeft ze van mij te nemen – niet een of twee<c type="kk">/</c> maar 50 b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik weet van meer dan een schilder die zoo doende wel zijn studies (die hij als hij ’t had <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> doen waarschijnlijk zelf had bewaard) zijn studies wel afgeven moest<c type="kk">/</c> doch van den anderen kant eenig geld kreeg om door den tijd te komen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">En als ik U vraag ze eens te laten zien aan lui die gij mogelijk tegenkomt is het omdat, nog eens, <hi rend="italics">het gansch niet onmogelijk</hi> is ge me te eeniger tijd een zoodanig liefhebber zult bezorgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Indien dit niet gebeurt<c type="kk">/</c> ook goed – maar voor mij<c type="kk">/</c> wegens mijn leven eer moeielijker als makkelijker wordt<c type="kk">/</c> is het een pligt gelegenheden te zoeken<c type="kk">/</c> kansen op te sporen om mijn werk te plaatsen<c type="kp">_</c>– En daarom vraag ik U<c type="kk">/</c> laat ze kijken als het eens in de termen valt<c type="kp">_</c>– Wordt er niet op gelet<c type="kk">/</c> best – ik ben natuurlijk daar ook op geprepareerd. Een kunstbesch. te geven van mijn werk alleen zou ik voorloopig zelf zeer zeker <hi>niet</hi> begeeren<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat betreft de lui die zich met teekeningen occupeeren – bij het gewone publiek der liefhebbers heeft men altijd <hi rend="italics">een</hi> KANS <hi rend="italics">gevoel</hi> te vinden – een beetje vertrouwen en geloof nog – slechts bij de oppervlakkig ingewijden als handelaars (<hi rend="italics">zonder uitzondering</hi>) vindt men <hi rend="italics">zeker geen</hi> gevoel<c type="kk">/</c> geloof of vertrouwen<c type="kk">/</c> maar slechts altijd de zelfde oude vijlen van oppervlakkige beoordeelingen – algemeenheden – <hi rend="italics">conventioneele</hi> critiek.– Oude vijlen op welke m.i. het tijd verliezen zou zijn – en <hi rend="italics">tanden</hi> verliezen – zich ’t gebit stomp te bijten<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dus – laat gij ze eens kijken als ooit ge in de gelegenheid zijt<c type="kk">/</c> maak er s.v.p. echter geen <hi rend="italics">werk</hi> van – forceer niet – doch<c type="kk">/</c> nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij moet het doen. Als ik niet <hi rend="italics">moest</hi> zou ik studies althans zeer zeker veel liever voor me zelf houden. en zou ze <hi>niet willen</hi> verkoopen<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar – – –</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu – gegroet – ik ben weer aan ’t schilderen dezer dagen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">b. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">ik denk er wel eens over om niets anders meer te doen dan penteekeningen en – schilderen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Het moet U niet verwonderen sommige figuren van mij zoo heel anders zijn dan die welke ik op zekere oogenblikken naar ’t model maak<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik werk heel zelden uit het hoofd – ik oefen me daar <hi rend="italics">haast niet</hi> in<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Doch begin zòò gewoon te worden aan het zitten direkt voor de natuur<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik veel meer dan heel in ’t begin dan mijn persoonlijk gevoel vrij houd – minder duizel – meer <hi>me zelf</hi> <hi rend="italics">ben soms</hi> <hi>juist als ik voor de natuur zit</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Tref ik het met een model dat het bedaard en rustig is en ken ik het reeds<c type="kk">/</c> teeken ik dat model herhaaldelijk<c type="kk">/</c> loopt er eindelijk onder de studies een door die iets anders is dan een gewone studie<c type="kk">/</c> typiger<c type="kk">/</c> meer gevoeld n.l.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Toch is die onder de zelfde omstandigheden gemaakt als meer houterige<c type="kk">/</c> minder gevoelde studies die voorafgingen. Dit is een manier van werken als een andere – even begrijpelijk m.i<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Zoo deze wintertuintjes – ge zegt het zelf<c type="kk">/</c> ze zijn <hi rend="italics">gevoeld</hi> – goed<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat’s geen toevalligheid<c type="kk">/</c> herhaaldelijk teekende ik ze vòòr dezen en ’t gevoel was er <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> in<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Daarna – na die ijzerachtigen – kwamen dezen–; zoo ook het onhandige en onbeholpene<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">hoe het komt dat ik daar iets</hi> <hi rend="italics">mee uitdruk</hi> is: – omdat het ding in mijn geest zich reeds gevormd heeft wanneer ik begin<c type="kp">_</c> De eersten zijn voor anderen <hi rend="italics">absoluut</hi> ongenietbaar<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zeg dit opdat ge weten zoudt dat <hi rend="italics">als</hi> er iets in is<c type="kk">/</c> dit niet <hi rend="italics">toevallig</hi> is doch wel degelijk beredeneerd en gewild<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Zeer verheugde het mij dat gij opgemerkt hebt dat in den laatsten tijd ik er nog al op werk &amp; aan hecht om de verhouding der waarden der massas tegen elkaar uit te drukken en hoe in den duizelingwekkenden warreboel van ieder hoekje uit de natuur de dingen van elkaar af komen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vroeger was ’t licht en bruin in mijn studies meestal meer willekeurig<c type="kk">/</c> ten minste niet logisch doorgevoerd, en waren ze daarom kouder en platter<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25"><hi rend="italics">Als</hi> ik eenmaal een motief <hi rend="italics">voel</hi> – <hi rend="italics">ken</hi> – dan maak ik het <hi rend="italics">meestal</hi> in 3 of meer <hi rend="italics">variaties</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij ’t een figuur ’t zij ’t een landschap gelde<c type="kk">/</c> maar – altijd weer neem ik voor ieder de natuur er bij<c type="kp">_</c>– En ik doe zelfs <hi rend="italics">mijn best</hi> DAN <hi>geen</hi> <hi rend="italics">details te geven – want</hi> <hi rend="italics">dan gaat de droomerij er uit</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Als Tersteeg en mijn broer &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> dan zeggen: wat is dat nu<c type="kk">/</c> gras of kool?– zeg ik: <hi rend="italics">blij</hi> GIJ dat niet kunt onderscheiden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">En toch zijn ze nog precies genoeg naar de natuur dat de eerzame inboorlingen van dit gewest b.v. details herkennen waar ik ter naauwernood op gelet heb<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. zeggen: ja dat is de <hi rend="italics">heg</hi> van jufvrouw Renesse<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> en daar staan de boonestaken van de Louw<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I was pleased with your letter about the drawings. As far as the loom is concerned, that really is a study of the machine made from start to finish in the place itself and was difficult — because one had to sit <hi rend="italics">so</hi> close that it was very tricky to take measurements. I drew the figure in after all<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — but I don’t want to say anything with it except: ‘when that black monster of begrimed oak with all its slats somehow shows up like this against the greyness in which it stands, then <hi rend="italics">there</hi>, in the centre of it, sits a black ape or goblin or apparition, and clatters with those slats from early till late’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And indicated the spot by setting down a sort of a shape of a weaver with a few scratches and blotches at the place where I saw him. Consequently, I didn’t give the slightest thought to the proportions of arms or legs at the time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">When my machine drawing had been finished fairly carefully, I found it so unbearable that I couldn’t hear it clatter that I let the apparition appear in it after all. Very well — and — say it’s only a machine drawing — just put it next to a <hi rend="italics">design</hi> for a loom and — — — — — I tell you, mine will <hi rend="italics">really</hi> <hi rend="italics">be more</hi> HAUNTING. <hi rend="italics">Otherwise</hi> it’s nothing but a machine drawing — otherwise, apart from a <hi rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi>. <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And — putting my study next to a drawing by a mechanical engineer — who had drawn a design for a loom — mine would more clearly express that the thing’s made of oak begrimed by sweaty hands, and would every now and then, when you looked at it (<hi rend="italics">even if</hi> I <hi rend="italics">absolutely did not</hi> draw him in, or even if I drew him out of proportion), every now and then you couldn’t help thinking of the <hi rend="italics">workman</hi>, whereas absolutely no ideas of this kind would occur to you looking at the design for a loom by a mechanical engineer. A sort of sigh or lament must sometimes come out of all that clutter of the slats.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I like to see your drawings of machines very much — why? — because when you draw <hi rend="italics">only</hi> the flywheel, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> for one also can’t help thinking about the boy who turns it and feel his presence, I don’t know how. And those who regard your machine drawings as <hi rend="italics">designs for machines</hi> understand <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> about your art.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Yet — for oneself — if one draws a machine like this — I agree with you that one should make it as mechanical as possible if one wants the study to be of any use.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Meanwhile, I completely understand your idea that, were it to be a <hi rend="italics">drawing</hi> — which I still <hi rend="italics">hope</hi> to make if I can get hold of my model — then the black apparition in the background must become the centre, the starting-point, the <hi rend="italics">heart</hi>, and the most felt, worked up — the rest 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> kept subordinate to it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Well, it pleases me that you like my little winter garden.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> This garden set me so to dreaming, and I’ve since made another of the same subject, also with a little black apparition, which yet again isn’t in it as an example of the structure of the human body worthy of imitating, but as a <hi rend="italics">blotch</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I’m sending you that one too, and a few others,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">namely sepia sketch, in the marsh<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> —</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">pen drawing, Pollard birches<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — Avenue of poplars<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — Behind the hedgerows<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — The kingfisher<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and Winter garden.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m sending them to you on a little roll; be so good as to put them in the portfolio with the others, particularly when you send them back, so that they stay flat if possible. I’m enclosing a piece of grey paper with them — they’ll show up better if you put them on that.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">As to these drawings and art presentations. I don’t care about art presentations. But what I do care about is this — I work every day, of course — and not a week goes by without me having several studies like this one, say. I always count it among the possibilities that some day or another I’ll find an art lover who would like to take them off me — not one or two, but 50, say.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I know of more than one painter who had to let his studies (which he would probably have kept himself if he <hi rend="italics">could</hi>), his studies go like this, but on the other hand received some money to get by on for a while. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And if I ask you to show them to people you may meet it’s because, once again, <hi rend="italics">it isn’t entirely impossible</hi> sometime that you might be able to provide me with such an art lover. If this doesn’t happen, well and good — but for me, on account of my life getting more difficult rather than easier, it’s a duty to seek opportunities, track down chances to place my work. And that’s why I ask you, show them, when it seems appropriate. If they take no notice, very well — I’m prepared for that, too, of course. For the time being I would very definitely <hi>not</hi> want to give a talk about my work alone. As far as the people who occupy themselves with drawings are concerned — one always has <hi rend="italics">a</hi> CHANCE of finding <hi rend="italics">feeling</hi> among the ordinary art-loving public — a bit of trust and faith still — only among the superficially initiated like dealers (<hi rend="italics">without exception</hi>) one finds <hi rend="italics">absolutely no</hi> feeling, faith or trust, but always the same old files of superficial judgements — generalities — <hi rend="italics">conventional</hi> criticism. Old files on which in my view it would be a waste of time — and <hi rend="italics">teeth</hi> — to blunt one’s teeth.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">So — will you just show them if ever you get the opportunity, but please don’t go to any <hi rend="italics">trouble</hi> — don’t force it — but, once again, for my part I have to do it. If I didn’t <hi rend="italics">have to</hi>, I’d most certainly much rather keep studies, at least, for myself, and I would <hi>not want</hi> to sell them. But — — —</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Well. Now — regards — I’m painting again these days.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I sometimes think about not doing anything else except pen drawings and — painting</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You shouldn’t be surprised that some of my figures are so very different from those that I do from a model at certain times.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I very seldom work from the imagination — I <hi rend="italics">almost never</hi> practise that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">But am starting to become <hi rend="italics">so</hi> accustomed to sitting directly in front of reality that I’m keeping my personal sensibility free then, far more so than right at the very beginning — getting less dizzy — <hi rend="italics">am sometimes</hi> more <hi>myself precisely when I’m sitting in front of reality</hi>. If I hit it off with a model so that it’s calm and quiet and I’m already familiar with it, if I draw that model repeatedly, then among the studies one will eventually come through that’s something different from an ordinary study, more true to type, that’s to say: more felt.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Yet, that one’s made under the same conditions as more wooden, less felt studies that preceded it. This is a way of working like any other — just as understandable, to my mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">For instance, these little winter gardens — you say it yourself, they’re <hi rend="italics">felt</hi> — very well, but that’s not a fluke, I drew them repeatedly before these and the feeling <hi rend="italics">wasn’t</hi> in them.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> After that — after those iron-like ones — came these; so too the clumsy and awkward ones. <hi rend="italics">How it comes about that I express something with them</hi> is: because the thing has already formed itself in my mind when I begin. The first ones are <hi rend="italics">utterly</hi> unpalatable to other people. I say this so that you should know that <hi rend="italics">if</hi> there’s something in it, this isn’t a <hi rend="italics">fluke</hi> but in fact properly reasoned and sought. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">It really delighted me that you’ve noticed that recently I’ve been working on and attaching importance to expressing the relationship of the values of the masses against one another quite a bit, and the way things stand out from one another in the dizzying confusion of every nook and cranny in life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Previously the light and shade in my studies was usually more haphazard, at any rate not carried through logically, so they were colder and flatter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26"><hi rend="italics">Once</hi> I <hi rend="italics">feel</hi> — <hi rend="italics">know</hi> — a subject, then I <hi rend="italics">usually</hi> make it in 3 or more <hi rend="italics">variations</hi>, whether it’s a figure or a landscape, but — every time I always involve reality for each one. And I even do <hi rend="italics">my best</hi> <hi>not</hi> <hi rend="italics">to give</hi> <hi>any</hi> <hi rend="italics">details</hi> THEN — <hi rend="italics">because then the reverie goes out of it</hi>. If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> and my brother &amp;c. then say: so what’s that, grass or cabbages? — I say: <hi rend="italics">glad</hi> YOU can’t make it out.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">And yet they’re still true enough to nature so that, for instance, the honest natives of these parts recognize details that I’ve scarcely noticed — say, for instance: yes, that’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_635">Miss Renesse</rs>’s<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> <hi rend="italics">hedge</hi>, and there are <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_493">De Louw</rs>’s beanpoles.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">See for the dating of this letter: <ref target="let435.xml">letter 435</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The second sheet of this letter was previously published as part of <ref target="let354.xml">letter 354</ref>. However, the references to ‘these little winter gardens’ <ref target="#l-149">(l. 149)</ref> and to ‘the honest natives of these parts’, ‘Miss Renesse’ and ‘De Louw’ <ref target="#l-185">(ll. 185-186)</ref> tell us that this is part of a Nuenen letter. The mention of ‘these little winter gardens’ must relate to drawings that Van Rappard had received and commented on. Since the winter gardens are discussed in the present letter, we have added this sheet to it. Going by the reproduction, both sheets were moreover written on the same squared paper, whereas <ref target="let354.xml">letter 354</ref> was not. Cf. exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 162 (n. 3).</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>We cannot say for certain which drawing this is. A little later Van Gogh writes that he depicted the figure of the weaver with a few ‘scratches and blotches’; the only surviving small pen-and-ink drawing of a weaver from this period which might possibly fit the bill is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_548">F 1124 / JH 456</rs>); it measures just 9.5 x 13 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘spooksel’ (apparition).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Zemel linked this passage with the ideas of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_590">George Eliot</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_563">Thomas Carlyle</rs>; see Zemel 1997, pp. 62-64.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘die wanorde, warboel van latten’ (this disorder, confusion of slats).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The small sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Parsonage garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_131">F 1133 / JH 485</rs>); since <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> was familiar with it, we assume that it must have been sent with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let433.xml">letter 433</ref>. The sketch is after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Parsonage garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_549">F 185 / JH 484</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Winter garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2458">F 1128 / JH 466</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            
 
<p>Means: ‘drasland, waterland’ (marshland).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This drawing is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pollard birches </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2460">F 1240 / JH 469</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Avenue of poplars</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2456">F 1239 / JH 464</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">‘Behind the hedgerows’ </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2454">F 1129 / JH 461</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The kingfisher</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2459">F 1135 / JH 468</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Parsonage garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2457">F 1130 / JH 465</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Cf. for this recommendation for a grey mount: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let216.xml#n-4">letter 216, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh used the same metaphor in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let432.xml">letter 432</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
 
<p>It is not certain which drawings Van Gogh is referring to here. He gave both <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Parsonage garden in the snow with one figure</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_550">F 1127 / JH 426</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Parsonage garden in the snow with three figures</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_551">F 1131 / JH 427</rs>) a French title (‘Mélancolie’ and ‘Jardin d’hiver’). ‘This suggests that he sent the sheets to Theo in Paris in the hope that they were marketable, or at any rate that they would build up his reputation’. Cat. Amsterdam 1997, p. 38.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            
 
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_635">Johanna Hendrika Amilda van Renesse</rs>, an unmarried woman of independent means, lived in De Berg no. 505 (district F, now Beekstraat) in Nuenen (FR b2255 and b2254; and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>De Louw was a very common name in Nuenen at that time and several of these De Louws were labourers or farmers. We consider it most likely that Van Gogh was referring here to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_493">Johannes de Louw</rs>: he lived in the same district F as the Van Goghs, at De Berg no. 499 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>).</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh evidently had contact with him: on the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Lamp in front of a window</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_552">F 1158v / JH -</rs> ) there is a note of an appointment: ‘Monday in a week’s time Louw’. See cat. Amsterdam 1997, pp. 157-158 (n. 3).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    