<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 18 March 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let439"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8375 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>439</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R43</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>440</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-03-18">on or about Tuesday, 18 March 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8375 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8375 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001633_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8375 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8375 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001634_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard –</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw brief – waar ik blijde mee was<c type="kp">_</c>– Het deed me pleizier dat ge in mijn teekeningen iets vondt<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Algemeenheden over techniek treed ik niet in maar wel voorzie ik dat<c type="kk">/</c> juist dan wanneer ik in wat ik zal noemen <hi rend="italics">zeggingskracht</hi> sterker word dan ik op dit moment ben<c type="kk">/</c> de lui niet <hi rend="italics">minder</hi> maar wel <hi rend="italics">meer nog</hi> dan nu zullen zeggen dat ik <hi rend="italics">geen</hi> techniek heb<c type="kp">_</c>– Gevolgelijk – wel ben ik ’t volkomen met U eens dat ’t geen ik zeg in mijn werk van nu ik nog <hi rend="italics">krachtiger</hi> moet zeggen – en ik sjouw er op in dat opzicht me te sterken – maar – dat <hi rend="italics">dan</hi> het algemeen publiek beter begreep – neen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dat neemt niet weg – mijns inziens – toch de redenatie van den braven man die van Uw werk vroeg “schildert-i-om geld”<c type="kk">/</c> eene redenatie is van neukepietje<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> – waar dit intelligent creatuur onder de axiomas rangschikt dat oorspronkelijkheid geld verdienen met zijn werk zou verhinderen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Dit als <hi>axioma</hi> te willen laten doorgaan<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">omdat</hi> als <hi rend="italics">stelling</hi> ’t gedecideerd <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> te bewijzen is<c type="kk">/</c> is zoo als gezegd – ’t gewone maniertje dier neukepietjes – en <hi rend="italics">luie</hi> jesuitjes<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Denkt gij dat ik om techniek niet geef of er niet naar zoek? jawel – maar slechts in zoover dat – ’t geen ik te zeggen heb ik zeggen wil – en waar ik dat nog niet of niet voldoende kan<c type="kk">/</c> ik er op werk me te verbeteren<c type="kp">_</c> maar of mijn taal in den haak is met die der redenaars heb ik maling aan – (ge weet gij maaktet de vergelijking – indien iemand iets nuttig’s, waar’s – noodigs te zeggen had en het zeide in termen die moeielijk te begrijpen waren<c type="kk">/</c> zou dan ’t zij spreker ’t zij hoorders er veel aan hebben<c type="kp">_</c>)</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik wil dit punt eens vast houden – juist omdat ik dikwijls een tamelijk curieus verschijnsel in de geschiedenis heb terug gevonden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Versta me wel: dat men spreken moet in de moeder<c type="shy">-</c>taal van het gehoor als dat gehoor maar één taal kent – dat spreekt van zelf en absurd zou ’t zijn dat niet van zelf aan te nemen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar nu het tweede deel der kwestie<c type="kk">/</c> gegeven een man die iets te zeggen heeft en spreekt in de taal die<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> zijn gehoor ook van nature benul van heeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dan – zal ’t verschijnsel zich telkens openbaren de <hi rend="italics">waarheidspreker</hi> weinig <hi rend="italics">oratorische chic</hi> heeft – en <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> in den smaak valt van het <hi rend="italics">meerendeel</hi> van zijn gehoor – ja uitgemaakt wordt voor een man “zwaar ter tale”<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en als zoodanig <hi rend="italics">veracht</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Van geluk mag hij spreken indien er één is<c type="kk">/</c> of heel enkelen op zijn hoogst<c type="kk">/</c> die gesticht zijn door hem wegens het deze hoorders te doen was niet om de oratorische tirades doch juist effektief om – het ware<c type="kk">/</c> nuttige<c type="kk">/</c> noodige der woorden<c type="kk">/</c> hetwelk hun verlichtte<c type="kk">/</c> verruimde<c type="kk">/</c> vrijer of intelligenter maakte<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">En nu de schilders – is het doel en non plus ultra der kunst die eigenaardige <hi rend="italics">vlekken</hi> kleur – die grilligheid der teekening<c type="kk">/</c> die wat men noemt distinctie der techniek<c type="kp">_</c>– Voorzeker niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Neemt men een Corot<c type="kk">/</c> een Daubigny<c type="kk">/</c> een Dupré<c type="kk">/</c> een Millet of een Israels – lui die voorzeker de groote voorgangers zijn – zoo is hun werk <hi>buiten de verf</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> het onderscheidt zich van de lui van chic<c type="kk">/</c> even als een oratorische tirade (b.v. van een Numa Roumestan)<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> iets heel anders is als een gebed of – een goed vers<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">Werken</hi> op techniek dus – <hi>moet</hi> <hi rend="italics">men</hi> in zooverre men beter<c type="kk">/</c> juister<c type="kk">/</c> inniger moet zeggen wat men voelt doch – met hoe minder omhaal van woorden hoe beter. Doch de rest – hoeft men zich niet mee te occupeeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Waarom ik dit zeg is omdat ik meen opgemerkt te hebben dat gij soms in Uw eigen werk dingen niet goed vind die wel goed zijn m.i<c type="kp">_</c> In mijn oog is <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> techniek beter dan b.v. die van Haverman – omdat Uw penseelstreek reeds dikwijls iets eigenaardigs<c type="kk">/</c> kennelijks<c type="kk">/</c> gemotiveerds en gewilds heeft wat bij Haverman eeuwig conventie is<c type="kk">/</c> altijd aan ’t <hi rend="italics">atelier</hi> herinnert<c type="kk">/</c> niet aan de natuur<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Voor de schetsen van U b.v. die ik zag<c type="kk">/</c> het wevertje<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en de Terschellingsche wijven<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> voel ik iets – het is een greep in ’t hart der dingen<c type="kp">_</c>– Voor Haverman voel ik al heel weinig anders dan malaise en verveling<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik vrees dat gij – en ik <hi rend="italics">feliciteer</hi> U er mee – ook in ’t vervolg nog dezelfde aanmerkingen OOK over techniek zult hooren<c type="kk">/</c> behalve over sujet en..... alles<c type="kk">/</c> enfin ook dan wanneer die penseelstreek van U die reeds zoo veel karakter heeft<c type="kk">/</c> dat nog meer krijgt.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">Er zijn echter</hi> liefhebbers die après tout juist voor het geen met emotie is geschilderd hart hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Al zijn we niet meer in den tijd van <hi rend="italics">Thoré</hi> en van Theophile Gautier – helaas<c type="kp">_</c>– Denk er eens over na of men wel wijs doet<c type="kk">/</c> in den tegenwoordigen tijd bepaaldelijk<c type="kk">/</c> veel over techniek zich uit te laten – ge zult zeggen ik doe dat bij dezen zelf – ik heb er ook eigentlijk spijt van<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Maar ik voor mij neem me voor – ook dan als ik mijn penseel veel meer meester zal zijn dan nu – tot de lui systematisch te zeggen <hi rend="italics">dat ik niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">schilderen kan</hi>. Verstaat ge – <hi rend="italics">ook juist dan</hi> als ik wel degelijk een eigen manier van doen zal hebben<c type="kk">/</c> compleeter en nog beknopter dan nu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Mooi vond ik wat Herkomer zeide toen hij een eigen art-school opende – voor een aantal lui <hi rend="italics">die reeds schilderen</hi> <hi rend="italics">kenden</hi> – hij verzocht zijn leerlingen vriendelijk of ze als je blieft <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> wilden schilderen zoo als hij – maar volgens hun eigen ik – ’t is me te doen, zegt hij, om oorspronkelijkheden vrij te doen worden – niet om discipelen te winnen voor <hi rend="italics">de</hi> <hi rend="italics">leer</hi> van Herkomer<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21"><hi rend="italics">Entre lions on ne se singe pas</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb nog al geschilderd deze laatste dagen<c type="kk">/</c> een meisje dat spoelen zit te winden voor de wevers<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en ’t figuur van den wever apart<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Ik ben er wel verlangend naar dat gij mijn geschilderde studies eens zien zult – niet omdat ik er zelf over tevreden ben maar omdat ik geloof dat gij er door overtuigd zult worden dat ik wel degelijk mijn hand oefen en<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik geef betrekkelijk weinig om techniek<c type="kk">/</c> dit niet doe om dat ik me zelf moeite spaar of moeielijkheden zoek te ontwijken<c type="kp">_</c>– Want dat is mijn systeem niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Verder verlang ik er naar gij dezen hoek van Brabant – m.i. veel mooier dan den kant van Breda – nog eens zult leeren kennen<c type="kp">_</c> Het is dezer dagen hier verrukkelijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Er is hier een dorp <hi rend="italics">Zon en Breugel</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> dat verbazend op Courrières lijkt<c type="kk">/</c> waar de Bretons wonen – toch de figuren zijn ginder nog wel zoo mooi. Als men den <hi rend="italics">vorm</hi> meer gaat liefkrijgen krijgt men wel eens het land aan – “de Hollandsche kleederdragten” zooals op de photographie albums staat die men de vreemdelingen verkoopt<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik stuur U bij dezen een klein boekje betreffende Corot – dat ge als ge ’t niet kent – denk ik met pleizier lezen zult – er staan met juistheid eenige levensbijzonderheden in<c type="kp">_</c>– Die tentoonstelling waarvan dit de catalogus is zag ik in der tijd nog.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Merkwaardig vind ik er in dat die man zoo lang bezonken en gerijpt heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Let er eens op wat hij deed op dezen en die leeftijd<c type="kp">_</c>– Van zijn eerste <hi>eigentlijke</hi> werk heb ik dingen gezien – resultaat van jaren studie reeds – eerlijk als goud<c type="kk">/</c> door en door solide – maar wat zullen de lui het veracht hebben! Voor mij zijn de <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> van Corot een les geweest toen ik ze zag en in dien tijd reeds gefrappeerd werd door het verschil met studies van veel andere landschapschilders<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Het boerenkerkhofje van <hi rend="italics">U</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> als ik er niet <hi rend="italics">meer techniek</hi> in zag als in de studies van Corot – zou ik er bij vergelijken<c type="kp">_</c> Van sentiment is het identiek – een streven om het intieme en het essentieele alleen te geven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Wat ik in dezen brief zeg komt hierop neer – Laat ons trachten zóó achter de geheimen der techniek te zijn dat de lui er in loopen en zweeren bij hoog en laag we geen techniek hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Laat het werk zoo savant zijn dat het naif <hi rend="italics">lijkt</hi> en niet naar onze knapheid stinkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Dat <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> dit punt ’t welk ik zou begeeren nog <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> bereikt heb geloof ik<c type="kk">/</c> want ik geloof niet eens dat <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> die verder zijt dan ik ’t reeds hebt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Ik geloof dat in dit schrijven ge iets anders zien zult dan woordenfitterij<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Ik geloof dat hoe meer men omgaat met de natuur zelf – hoe dieper men er in doordringt – hoe minder aantrekkelijkheid men vinden gaat in al die trucs d’atelier<c type="kk">/</c> en toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil die in hun waarde laten en <hi rend="italics">zien</hi> schilderen<c type="kp">_</c> veel op ateliers komen is iets waar ik zelf wel naar verlang<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Niet in de boeken heb ik het gevonden</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">En van “geleerden” – och, weinig geleerd</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">staat in de Genestet zoo als ge wel weet<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>Men zou als variatie hierop kunnen zeggen<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">niet in ’t atelier heb ik het gevonden</p> 
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">En van de schilders } och<c type="kk">/</c> weinig geleerd<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.39" n="39">             de kenners }</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.40" n="40">Misschien schokt het U ik om het even schilders of kenners zou inlasschen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.41" n="41">Maar over iets anders – het is weergaasch moeielijk om niets te voelen<c type="kk">/</c> geen invloed te ondervinden van wat zulke neukepietjes als “schildert-i om geld” – zeggen. Dat gezanik hoort men dag in dag uit en later wordt men kwaad op zich zelf dat men er zich iets van heeft aangetrokken. zoo gaat het mij – en ik denk dat het U ook wel eens zoo gaat<c type="kp">_</c>– Men heeft er wel maling aan doch het maakt zenuwachtig – net als wanneer men valsch hoort zingen of <hi rend="italics">door een op U verbitterd draaiorgel</hi> <hi rend="italics">vervolgd wordt</hi>. Vindt gij dat niet waar van het draaiorgel en dan dat hetzelve ’t speciaal op U zou hebben begrepen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.42" n="42">Want waar men ook komt<c type="kk">/</c> overal is ’t hetzelfde deuntje<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.43" n="43">o ik voor mij – ik ga doen wat ik U zeg – als de lui tegen mij zeggen dit en dat – ga ik zelf vóór zij uitgesproken zijn de zinnen aanvullen – op de wijs dat wanneer ik van iemand weet hij de gewoonte heeft mij een vinger te geven in plaats van een hand (ik lapte het gisteren een eerwaardig collega van mijn vader) ik van mijn kant ook één vinger klaar houd en zonder mijn gezigt te vertrekken voorzigtig den zijnen daarmee ontmoet bij het een hand geven – op een manier dat de man er niets van <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> zeggen maar gevoelt ik hem terugverneuk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.44" n="44">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb pas iemand zeer kwaadaardig gemaakt met iets dergelijks – verliest men daar iets aan – neen want waarachtig<c type="kk">/</c> die lui hinderen en dat ik U schrijf betreffende sommige expressies van U is om U te vragen<c type="kk">/</c> weet gij zeker dat zij die de techniek zoo ophemelen de bonne foi zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Juist omdat <hi rend="italics">ik weet dat uw streven is om atelier</hi> <hi rend="italics">chic te vermijden</hi> vraag ik het eens<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you for your letter — which made me happy. I was pleased that you saw something in my drawings.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I won’t go into generalities about technique, but I do foresee that, precisely when I become stronger in what I’ll call <hi rend="italics">power of expression</hi> than I am at this moment, people will say, not <hi rend="italics">less</hi> but in fact <hi rend="italics">even more</hi> than now, that I have <hi rend="italics">no</hi> technique. Consequently — I’m in complete agreement with you that I must say even <hi rend="italics">more forcibly</hi> what I’m saying in my present work — and I’m toiling away to strengthen myself in this respect — but — that the general public will understand it better <hi rend="italics">then</hi> — no.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">All the same, in my view that doesn’t alter the fact that the reasoning of the good man who asked about your work, ‘does he paint for money?’, is the reasoning of a moaner — since this intelligent creature counts it among the axioms that originality prevents one from earning money with one’s work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Passing this off as an <hi>axiom</hi>, <hi rend="italics">because</hi> it can decidedly <hi rend="italics">not</hi> be proved as a <hi rend="italics">proposition</hi> is, as I said — the usual trick of moaners — and <hi rend="italics">lazy</hi> little Jesuits. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Do you think that I don’t care about technique or am not searching for it? I do — but only to the extent that — I want to say what I have to say — and where I can’t do it yet, or not well enough, I work on it to improve myself. But I don’t give a damn whether my language squares with that of these orators — (you know you made the comparison — if someone had something useful, true — necessary to say, and said it in terms that were difficult to understand, what good would it be to either speaker or audience?).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I want to stay with this point for a moment — precisely because I’ve often come across a rather curious historical phenomenon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Let it be clearly understood: that one must speak in the audience’s mother tongue if that audience only speaks one language — that goes without saying, and it would be absurd not to take it as read.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But now the second part of the question. Given a man who has something to say and speaks in the language that his audience is also naturally familiar with.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Then — the phenomenon that the <hi rend="italics">speaker of truth</hi> has little <hi rend="italics">oratorical chic</hi> will manifest itself time and time again — and does <hi rend="italics">not</hi> appeal to the <hi rend="italics">majority</hi> of his audience — indeed is branded a man ‘slow of speech’<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and <hi rend="italics">despised</hi> as such.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">He may consider himself lucky if there is one, or a very few at most, who are edified by him, because these listeners weren’t concerned with oratorical tirades but precisely, effectively with — the truth, usefulness, necessity of the words, which enlightened, broadened them, made them freer or more intelligent. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And now the painters — is the purpose and <hi rend="italics">non plus ultra</hi> of art those singular <hi rend="italics">spots</hi> of colour — that waywardness in the drawing, that which is called distinction of technique? Certainly not. If one takes a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>, a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>, a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Dupré</rs>, a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> or an <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> — fellows who are certainly the great forerunners — their work is <hi>beyond the paint</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> it stands apart from the chic fellows, just as an oratorical tirade (by, say, a Numa Roumestan)<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> is something very different from a prayer or — a good poem.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><hi rend="italics">One</hi> <hi>must</hi> therefore <hi rend="italics">work</hi> on technique in so far as one must say what one feels better, more accurately, more profoundly, but — with the less verbiage the better. But the rest — one needn’t occupy oneself with it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Why I say this is because I believe I’ve observed that you sometimes think things in your own work aren’t good, which to my mind are good. In my view, <hi rend="italics">your</hi> technique is better than, say, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1072">Haverman</rs>’s — because already your brushstroke often has something singular, distinctive, reasoned and deliberate about it, which in Haverman is endless convention, always redolent of the <hi rend="italics">studio</hi>, not of nature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"> Those sketches of yours that I saw, for instance, the little weaver<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and the old women of Terschelling,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> appeal to me — they get to the heart of things. I get little but malaise and boredom from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1072">Haverman</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’m afraid that in the future, too — and I <hi rend="italics">congratulate</hi> you on it — you will ALSO hear the same comments about technique, as well as about subject and..... everything, in fact, even when that brushstroke of yours, which already has so much character, gets even more. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">There are however </hi>art lovers who do, after all, appreciate precisely those things that have been painted with emotion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Although we’re no longer in the days of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">Thoré</rs></hi> and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_607">Théophile Gautier</rs> — alas. Just think about whether it’s wise, particularly nowadays, to talk a lot about technique — you’ll say I’m doing that here myself — actually I do regret it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">But for my part, I intend to tell people consistently <hi rend="italics">that I can’t paint</hi>, even when I’ve mastered my brush much better than now. You understand? — <hi rend="italics">especially then</hi>, when I really will have an individual manner, more finished and even more concise than now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I liked what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Herkomer</rs> said when he opened his own art school — for a number of people <hi rend="italics">who could already paint</hi> — he kindly asked his students if they would be so good as to <hi rend="italics">not</hi> want to paint like him — but according to their own nature — I am concerned, he says, with setting originality free — not with winning disciples for Herkomer’s <hi rend="italics">doctrine</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"><hi rend="italics">Lions do not ape one another.</hi><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Well, I’ve painted quite a lot these last few days, a seated girl winding shuttles for the weavers,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and the figure of the weaver separately.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I’m longing for you to see my painted studies sometime — not because I’m satisfied with them myself, but because I believe that you’ll be convinced by them that I really am exercising my hand and, when I say I care relatively little for technique, it’s not because I’m saving myself trouble or trying to avoid difficulties. Because that’s not my system.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I’m also longing for you to get to know this corner of Brabant sometime — much more beautiful than the Breda side in my view. It’s delightful here at the moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25"> There’s a village here — <hi rend="italics">Son en Breugel</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> which is amazingly like Courrières, where the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899 bio.xml#_900">Breton</rs>s live — yet the figures over there are at least as beautiful. As one starts to appreciate the <hi rend="italics">form</hi> more, one sometimes takes a dislike to — ‘the Dutch traditional costumes’, as they’re called on the photograph albums that they sell to foreigners.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I’m sending you herewith a little booklet about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> — which I think you’ll enjoy reading if you don’t know it — there are several accurate biographical details in it. I saw the exhibition at the time, for which this is the catalogue.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">What’s remarkable in it is that that man ripened and matured for so long. Just look at what he did at different times in his life. I’ve seen examples of his first <hi>actual</hi> work — itself the result of years of study — honest as the day is long, thoroughly sound — but how people must have despised it! <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>’s <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> were a lesson to me when I saw them, and was already struck at the time by the difference from studies by many other landscape painters.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">If I didn’t see <hi rend="italics">more technique</hi> in <hi rend="italics">your</hi> little peasant cemetery<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> than in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>’s studies — I’d liken it to them. In sentiment it’s identical — an endeavour to express only the intimate and the essential.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">What I’m saying in this letter amounts to this — let’s try to get the hang of the secrets of technique so well that people are taken in and swear by all that’s holy that we have no technique. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Let the work be so skilful that it <hi rend="italics">seems</hi> naive and doesn’t stink of our cleverness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">I don’t believe that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> have reached this desirable point<hi rend="italics"> yet</hi>, for I don’t even believe that <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, who are further on than I am, are already there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I believe you’ll see more in this letter than nitpicking about words.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I believe that the more one has to do with nature itself — the deeper one penetrates into it — the less attraction one sees in all these studio tricks, and yet, I do want to take them as they are and <hi rend="italics">see</hi> them painting. I would really like to spend a lot of time in studios.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Not in the books have I found it</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">And from the ‘learned’ — oh, little learned</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">is in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">De Génestet</rs>, as you know.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> One might say as a variant on this,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Not in the studio have I found it</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">And from the painters } oh, little learned</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">the connoisseurs }</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">Perhaps my inserting painters or connoisseurs as equals shocks you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">But changing the subject — it’s devilishly difficult to feel nothing, not to be affected by what such moaners as ‘does he paint for money’ say. One hears that rot day in and day out, and later one gets angry with oneself for having taken any notice of it. That’s how it is with me — and I think that it must occasionally be the same with you. One doesn’t give a damn about it, but all the same it gets on one’s nerves — like when one hears someone singing off-key or <hi rend="italics">is pursued by a barrel-organ with a grudge against you</hi>. Don’t you think that’s true about the barrel-organ, and also that it seems to pick on you specifically?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">For wherever one goes, it’s the same old tune everywhere. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Oh, as to me — I’m going to do what I tell you — when people say this and that to me — I’m going to finish their sentences before they do — in the same way as, when I know someone is in the habit of offering me a finger instead of a hand (I pulled it off yesterday with a venerable colleague of my father’s), I for my part also have one finger ready and, keeping a straight face, carefully touch his with it when shaking hands — in a way that the man <hi rend="italics">can’t</hi> say anything about it but realizes I’m bloody well getting my own back on him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Well, I’ve recently made somebody very angry with something of the sort — does one lose anything by it? No, for in truth these people are a hindrance, and the fact that I write to you about some expressions you use is to ask you: are you sure that those who are praising technique to the skies are in good faith? I just ask it precisely because <hi rend="italics">I know that your aim is to avoid studio chic</hi>.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh did indeed send the drawings that he promised to send in <ref target="let437.xml">letter 437</ref>, and he thanks Van Rappard here for the appreciative response that he has meanwhile received <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref>. See further <ref target="let435.xml">letter 435</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                    	            
                                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter has no conclusion or signature, so in all likelihood it is incomplete.</p>
                    	                
                    	            
                                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">De brieven </hi>1990 a sheet was included as part of this letter that we have placed, on grounds of content, with <ref target="let332.xml">letter 332</ref>. It contains a false reference to an earlier part of the letter, and the duct of the handwriting and type of paper differ from that of the present letter. See also <ref target="let332.xml">letter 332</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Arrangement</hi>.</p>
                    	                
                    	        
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had promised to send drawings in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let437.xml">letter 437</ref>, which dates from around the middle of March 1884.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Probably means: ‘zeikerd, zaniker’ (bore, moaner) (in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-196">l. 196</ref> the word ‘gezanik’ (moaning) is used synonymously); cf. also the compound ‘zeurpiet’ (nag).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Waar’ (which, that).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Cf. Exod. 4:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>A common expression among artists at the time. Carel Vosmaer, for instance, wrote in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_401">Amazone</ref></hi>. The Hague 1880: ‘There was no doubt, this example is the very finest. Everything that people had admired in the other one was here to an even higher degree. Something of the same can be observed in marble statues as in paintings when the colours in them do not appear as pigments, but the substance of them vanishes and the impression is that of life or reality, in other words when the physical media do not stand between the work of art and the viewer, but the mind of the creating artist speaks <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">directly </hi>to that of the viewer. Then painters say that a painting is ‘beyond the paint’. Something of the kind also occurs with sculptures’ (p. 162).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Alphonse Daudet</rs>’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_402">Numa Roumestan – Moeurs parisiennes</ref></hi> (1881) is about the political figure Numa Roumestan, who attained the ministry thanks in part to his skill in rhetoric. Oratorical tirades are not rendered literally, but they are described (in chapter 20): ‘On the balcony, the orator was working himself up, uttering long outpourings of which all that could be heard were the first words of each sentence, accentuated in the southern manner: “My soul… My blood… Morality… Religion… Country…”, given emphasis by the cheers of that audience, made in his image’. (Sur le balcon, l’orateur s’exaltait, arrivait aux grandes effusions dont on n’entendait que les départs accentués à la méridionale, “Mon âme... Mon sang... Morale... Religion... Patrie...” soulignés par les hurrahs de cet auditoire fait à son image). See Daudet 1986-1994, vol. 3, p. 214.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is probably referring to a painting. Cf. with regard to the subject <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s (undated) drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver</hi> (private collection). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 83, cat. no. 99.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>See for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_329">Old women in the West-Terschelling home</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let416.xml#n-4">letter 416, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs> set up his Art School in Bushey in 1883. A week later <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> reported on the 34 students who would be given intensive training, and what Herkomer had in mind with the school: ‘All of these are able to draw or paint fairly well from the life, and for the next nine months their powers will be tested in a somewhat severe and continuous manner’. On Herkomer’s attitude towards their individual development, the piece continued: ‘The style of work, Mr Herkomer said, he wanted his students to form for themselves, and he implored them not to strive to imitate him; they might be eccentric at first if they liked – rather that than to be timid, and amateurish, and niggling, but they must produce artistic work’. [Anonymous], ‘Opening of the Herkomer Art School’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic </hi>28 (1 December 1883), p. 539.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh probably derived this saying, which means that great minds do not imitate, from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">William Shakespeare</hi>. See Hugo 1864, p. 383, and exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 32.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This painting of a girl winding thread is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh made several paintings of individual weavers during this period; it is not possible to say which one he means here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The villages of Son and Breugel, about 5 km to the north-west of Nuenen.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>There were all sorts of books about national costumes on the market; for example C.P.E. Robidé van der Aa, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Nederlandsche kleederdragten. Een geschenk voor knapen en meisjes</hi> (Amsterdam 1839) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Kleederdragten en typen der bewoners van Nederland</hi> (Amsterdam [1865]).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_558">Exposition de l’oeuvre de Corot</ref></hi> (Exhib. cat. Paris 1875-2). Van Gogh went to see the exhibition in May 1875 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let034.xml">see letter 34</ref>). The last remark may well be an echo of what <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1694">Burty</rs> wrote: ‘his work was carried out as though imbued with every noble thought that it evoked’ (son oeuvre s’accomplissait comme imprégnée de toutes les nobles pensées qu’il évoquait). See exhib. cat. Paris 1875-2, p. 19.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Cf. for a cemetery by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-8">letter 344, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>An allusion to the first verse of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_615">P.A. de Génestet</rs>’s poem ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_568">Waar en hoe</ref>’ (Where and how):</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">No, I found it not in the schools of my youth</p>

<p rend="indent">From the learned, alas, precious little I learned</p>

<p rend="indent">And what men of wisdom proclaim as the truth</p>

<p rend="indent">Will one day by wiser men be overturned</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p rend="indent">(Niet in de scholen, neen, heb ik gevonden,</p>

<p rend="indent">En van geleerden, och, weinig geleerd;</p>

<p rend="indent">Wat ons de wijzen als waarheid verkonden,</p>

<p rend="indent">Straks komt een wijzer, die ’t wegredeneert.)</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p>See De Génestet 1869, vol. 1, p. 271. The publisher Tiele also quoted the first two lines in his ‘Levensschets van P.A. de Génestet’, which precedes <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_569">De dichtwerken</ref></hi> (vol. 1, p. 47). It is possible that they had meanwhile attained the status of a maxim. Van Gogh himself put inverted commas around the word ‘learned’ to produce the desired effect. This enabled him to add extra force to the variation he devised, and to criticise his fellow painters, the dealers, collectors and connoisseurs by comparing them to pseudo-scholars.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    