<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 28 March 1884. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let443"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b399 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b414 d V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>443</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>365</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>446</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-03-28">on or about Friday, 28 March 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0399" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000527_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000527_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0399" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000527_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000527_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000527_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0414 d" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000551_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000551_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0414 d" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000551_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000551_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">de teekeningen voor deze maand zijn nog bij Rappard<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> anders had ik ze U reeds gestuurd<c type="kp">_</c>– En daar er een plan is Rappard heel binnen kort eens hier komt logeeren heb ik hem nu verzocht ze maar zelf mede te brengen dan.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het doet me pleizier dat gij op die manier eens over Cor hebt geschreven<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> als ik uit Uw brief aan Pa en Moe vernam. Gelukkig dat Braat weer beter wordt – ge zult toch wel gezien hebben dat betreffende wat gij meendet me te moeten schrijven over hem<c type="kk">/</c> ge radicaal abuis in hebt gehad – niet waar<c type="kp">_</c>– ik hoop gij dit hebt ingezien<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wat ik U heb geschreven over Rappard kom ik nog even op terug<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik vind het niet noodig met hem veel over U te spreken als gij en ik niet beter met elkaar zijn dan ’t momenteel gesteld is. Denk gij er nu echter zelf nog eens over na of het al dan niet van U onaardig zou zijn jegens hem als gij geen notitie eens er van nemen zoudt als hij nu binnen kort weer eens hier zal zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik geloof dat gij er geen spijt van zoudt hebben den wenk dien ik U hieromtrent geef eens aan te nemen<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat ik zou willen is eenvoudig gij de kennis met hem eens vernieuwt.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Vooral omdat hij verder is dan ik<c type="kk">/</c> is er te meer reden voor. Ik zeg dit eenvoudig om te voorkomen ge een negligence begaat<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik weet niet wat voor impressie ’t op Rappard zou maken als ik hem mededeelde wat we in den laatsten tijd met elkaar hebben gehad<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar ik weet wel dat het werk dat hij van mij heeft gezien van deze laatste maanden hem beviel<c type="kp">_</c> Liever had ik<c type="kk">/</c> ik hem kon zeggen alles wel was tusschen U en mij<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Maar ik zal hier ook niet over zaniken<c type="kp">_</c> Wilt gij de kunst verdeelen met scherpe<c type="kk">/</c> regt steile lijnen in dingen die men aan het licht mag brengen en dingen die men met groote standvastigheid moet stil laten liggen – dat is uw zaak<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En op dit moment is de heele kwestie mij zoo regt hatelijk dat ik er ook niet op wil doorgaan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat Rappard betreft<c type="kk">/</c> het is curieus wat absurde dingen hij soms over zijn werk hoort – wat door hem heel leuk<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> wordt opgenomen<c type="kp">_</c>– Men moet daarop geprepareerd zijn en een zeker zelfvertrouwen hebben om zich niet te laten overdonderen of van streek maken<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Vrienden die de beroerdigheid die men over het werk heeft vergoeden door hartelijkheid<c type="kk">/</c> zijn voor een schilder veel waard<c type="kp">_</c>– Waar gij voor R<c type="kp">_</c>’s werk persoonlijk sympathie zoudt voelen<c type="kk">/</c> zoudt gij zeker hem ook niet onverschillig zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Doch hij – en ik ook – maken ons hoe langer hoe minder illusies van sympathie te ondervinden en zetten ons meer en meer tot doorzetten zonder naar wie dan ook om te kijken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het is met Moe nu zoo dat zij eigentlijk niets meer mankeert dan dat zij het loopen weer geheel van voren af aan moet leeren – en langzamerhand door oefenen het been minder stijf moet worden<c type="kp">_</c>– En het had veel erger kunnen afloopen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">b. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Iets wat ik U vragen wou is<c type="kk">/</c> Waarom gaat Cor niet naar Goupil<c type="kk">/</c> zooals gij en ik toen we zijn jaren hadden er begonnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik hoor iets van een plan om hem nog voor 2 jaar op de Burgerschool te laten – ik hoor ’t lumineus idée opperen<c type="kk">/</c> in alle serieux door Pa<c type="kk">/</c> hem “<hi rend="italics">consul</hi>” te laten worden<c type="kp">_</c>– Ofschoon niemand hier in huis noch iemand dergenen met wie over deze zaak voorloopige corres<c type="shy">-</c>pondentien zijn gehouden<c type="kk">/</c> eigentlijk weet wat een consul eigentlijk uitvoert.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De zaak kan mij niet in ’t minst schelen – ik geloof dat dit consulaat iets dergelijks is als dat een oude dame hier op het dorp de <hi rend="italics">maréchaussées</hi> zulke mooie mannen vindt om te zien<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/>Maar erg verwondert het mij dat ik eenvoudig nooit over Goupil heb hooren praten betreffende Cor<c type="kp">_</c>– Waarom niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Vooral als gij er in blijft<c type="kk">/</c> dunkt mij<c type="kk">/</c> ligt het voor de hand Cor er ook in moest gaan – later hebt ge gezelschap en hulp aan elkaar – en hij is er in elk geval beter aan toe, leert meer, ziet meer, dan als “consul” of op een “notariskantoor” &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> of “de posterijen”<c type="kk">/</c> allemaal overigens niet weinig fatsoenlijk en één pot nat. Cor zelf<c type="kk">/</c> voor zoover ik weet<c type="kk">/</c> heeft geen bepaald idee dat hij of in dit of in dat vak begeert te gaan – wegens hij van digt bij nog waarschijnlijk weinig anders heeft gezien dan boeken<c type="kk">/</c> den straatweg &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Hij is nu dunkt me een aardige jongen doch wel wordt het tijd hij in de praktijk komt dunkt me<c type="kk">/</c> anders schieten ze door<c type="kk">/</c> die luidjes<c type="kk">/</c> vooral als ze op een wat al te leeg kantoortje komen – schieten door in pedanterie en nulliteit<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">The drawings for this month are still with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> otherwise I would have already sent them to you. And since there’s a plan for Rappard to come and stay here very soon, I’ve asked him to bring them with him then.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’m pleased that you wrote about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> in that way,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> as I learned from your letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>. Fortunate that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_305">Braat</rs> is getting better again — you’ll no doubt have seen — won’t you? — that you’d been fundamentally mistaken in what you felt you had to write to me about him. I hope you’ve realized this.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I return briefly to what I wrote to you about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I don’t find it necessary to talk to him much about you as long as you and I aren’t on better terms than we are at present. However, just think again for a moment whether or not you’d be being unkind to him if you were to take no notice of him if he’s going to be here again soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I don’t think you’d regret taking the hint I give you about this. What I’d like is simply for you to renew your acquaintance with him. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">There’s all the more reason for it, particularly because he’s further on than I am. I say this simply to prevent you from being negligent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I don’t know what impression it would make on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> if I told him how things had been between us recently.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But I know very well that he liked the work of mine that he’s seen these last few months. I would rather that I could tell him all was well between you and me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">But I won’t harp on about this either. If you want to divide art with sharp, dead straight lines into things that one may bring into the open and things that one must persistently leave alone — that’s your business.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And at this moment the whole question is so downright odious to me that I don’t want to pursue it any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">As far as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> is concerned, it’s curious what absurd things he sometimes hears about his work — which he takes very coolly. One has to be prepared for this and have a certain self-confidence in order not to allow oneself to be overwhelmed or upset. 
    <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Friends who make up for the unpleasantness about the work with warm-heartedness are of great value to a painter. Were you to feel personal sympathy for R.’s work, he’d certainly not be indifferent to you either. Yet he — and I too — increasingly cherish fewer and fewer illusions about encountering sympathy, and set ourselves more and more to carrying on without bothering about anyone at all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s condition is now such that there’s actually nothing more wrong with her than that she has to learn to walk again right from the beginning — and her leg should gradually get less stiff by exercising. And it could have turned out much worse.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Something I wanted to ask you is why isn’t <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> going to Goupil, just as you and I started there when we were his age? I heard something about a plan to leave him at a Secondary School for another 2 years — I heard <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> suggest, in all seriousness, the bright idea of his becoming a ‘<hi rend="italics">consul</hi>’. Although no one here at home, nor anyone with whom there has so far been any correspondence on this matter, actually knows what a consul actually does.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I couldn’t care less about the business — I believe that this consulate is something like the way an old lady in the village here thinks that the military police are such handsome men to behold. 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/> But it does surprise me greatly that I’ve simply never heard any talk about Goupil in regard to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>. Why not? Particularly if you stay there, it seems to me, it’s obvious that Cor should go there too — later on you’d be company and support for each other — and in any event he’d be better off there, learn more, see more, than as a ‘consul’ or in a ‘notary’s office’ &amp;c., or ‘the post office’, all highly respectable anyway, and much of a muchness. Cor himself, as far as I know, has no particular idea about wanting to enter this profession or that — because he’s probably seen little else at close quarters but books, the main road &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">He’s a nice boy now, it seems to me, but it’s time that he did something practical, it seems to me, otherwise they go to seed, these young fellows, particularly if they end up in a rather too empty little office — go to seed in pedantry and nonentity.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The drawings for Theo ‘for this month’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>), which had already been discussed for some time, are the March drawings. See for the reasons for dating this letter on or about 28 March: notes to <ref target="let442.xml">letter 442</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">At the end of the letter we have added a separate sheet that had previously been put with <ref target="let463.xml">letter 463</ref> of 30 September 1884 (<ref target="#l-65">ll. 65</ref> ff.). The passage in question deals with Cor’s choice of profession, something that was a dead issue by the end of September. We have added the sheet here because the only letter in which this subject occurs is the present one <ref target="#l-4">(l. 4)</ref>, although it is remarkable that Van Gogh should have added a separate sheet while there was still a blank page on the first sheet of the letter.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Invitation to Van Rappard to come to Nuenen <ref target="let441.xml">(441)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mrs van Gogh’s broken leg <ref target="let423.xml">(423)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See for the twelve drawings by Van Gogh that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had at this time: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let441.xml">letter 441</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This request is in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let441.xml">letter 441</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Evidently the family was corresponding about brother <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>’s impending choice of profession. He was about to take his high school examinations, which he passed in July. On 19 July 1884 it was decided to apprentice him to Egbert Haverkamp Begemann’s engineering works in Helmond, at a cost of 810 guilders a year. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> informed Theo of this sum because he was going to provide financial assistance (FR b2255).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo had reproached Vincent for having written critically about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_305">Frans Braat</rs> – undeservedly according to Vincent. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let438.xml">See letters 438</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let440.xml">440</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the passage about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let440.xml">letter 440</ref>, ll. 199 ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘kalm’ (calm).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    