<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 6 June 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let449"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b404 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>449</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>370</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>452</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-06-06">on or about Friday, 6 June 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0404" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0404" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000532_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Nog dikwijls denk ik aan Uw prettig bezoek<c type="kk">/</c> dat hoop ik zich weldra voor wat langer tijd eens herhalen zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Sedert ge er geweest zijt heb ik nog al druk gewerkt aan eene spinster<c type="kk">/</c> waarvan ik U eens hierbij een krabbeltje stuur<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het is nog al groot en in een donkeren toon geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> het figuur is in ’t blaauw<c type="kk">/</c> met een doek die zoowat muiskleurig is<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik hoop er nog een soortgelijk te maken van een oud mannetje aan het spoelwiel bij een raampje<c type="kk">/</c> waar ge U misschien een kleine studie van herinnert.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Regt gaarne zou ik hebben ge me spoedig die maat van Uw lijsten opgeeft<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik er aan kunnen beginnen.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Misschien maak ik als ’t met de maat uitkomt een kleintje van die spinster.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik schrijf hier eens over een passage uit les artistes de mon temps van Ch<c type="kp">_</c> Blanc:<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Trois mois environ avant la mort d’Eug. Delacroix, nous le rencontrâmes dans les galeries du Palais Royal, sur les dix heures du soir, Paul Chenavard et moi. C’était au sortir d’un grand dîner où l’on avait agité des questions d’art, et la conversation s’était prolongée entre nous deux sur le même 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>sujet, avec cette vivacité, cette chaleur que l’on met surtout aux discussions inutiles. Nous en étions à la couleur, et je disais “Pour moi, les grands coloristes sont ceux qui ne font pas le ton local.”– et j’allais developper mon thème, lorsque nous aperçumes Eugène Delacroix dans la galerie de la Rotonde<c type="kp">_</c> Il vint à nous en s’écriant: je suis sûr qu’ils parlent peinture! En effet – lui dis-je, j’étais sur le point de soutenir une proposition qui n’est pas, je crois, un paradoxe, et dont vous êtes en tout cas meilleur juge que personne: je disais que les grands coloristes ne font pas le ton local, et avec vous je n’ai pas besoin sans doute d’aller plus loin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Eugène Delacroix fit deux pas en arrière, selon son habitude en clignant les yeux: “Cela est parfaitement vrai – dit-il; voilà un ton<c type="kk">/</c> par exemple (il montrait du doigt le ton gris et sale du pavé); eh bien, si l’on disait à Paul Veronèse: peignez-<c type="shy">-</c>moi une belle femme blonde, dont la chair soit de ce ton-là – il la peindrait, et la femme <hi rend="italics">serait une</hi> <hi rend="italics">blonde dans</hi> SON <hi rend="italics">tableau</hi>.”</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Van “snotkleurtjes” gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> men moet niet de kleuren van een schilderij mijns inziens op zich zelf beschouwen – een snotkleurtje als het bij voorbeeld tegen krachten van bruinrood<c type="kk">/</c> van donker blaauw<c type="kk">/</c> of van olijfgroen aan staat – kan een heel teer en frisch groentje van een weiland of korenveldje uitdrukken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En toch geloof ik dat de Bock<c type="kk">/</c> die zekere kleuren “snotkleuren” gedoopt heeft<c type="kk">/</c> dit bovenstaande zeker niet zoude tegenspreken eigentlijk – want ik heb hem zelf eens hooren zeggen dat op sommige schilderijen van Corot in avondluchten b.v. toonen zitten die <hi rend="italics">op ’t schilderij</hi> heel <hi rend="italics">lichtend</hi> zijn en <hi rend="italics">op zich zelf</hi> beschouwd eigentlijk een <hi rend="italics">tamelijk donkeren</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> grijsachtigen toon zijn</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">T’huis zullen zij U ook spoedig schrijven en bedanken U voor Uw brief.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Doch om nog even op die kwestie terug te komen dat men met een vuil kleurtje als het grijs van de straatkeien een avondlucht of een blonde vrouw zou kunnen schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> als men dat nagaat is die kwestie nog een <hi rend="italics">dubbele</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Want vooreerst heeft men<c type="kk">/</c> een <hi rend="italics">donkere</hi> kleur kan <hi rend="italics">licht</hi> lijken (of liever <hi rend="italics">doen</hi>)<c type="kp">_</c> dit is eigentlijk nog meer een kwestie van <hi rend="italics">toon</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Maar dan wat de eigentlijke <hi rend="italics">kleur</hi> aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> een roodgrijs<c type="kk">/</c> betrekkelijk weinig rood<c type="kk">/</c> zal naarmate van de kleuren die er naast staan meer of minder rood schijnen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">En zoo met het blaauw en zoo met het geel eveneens<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Men hoeft maar een heel klein beetje geel in een kleur te doen om ’t <hi rend="italics">erg</hi> geel te laten doen<c type="kk">/</c> als men die kleur in of naast een violetten of lilas toon zet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik herinner me hoe iemand trachtte een rood dak waar ’t licht op viel uit te drukken door middel van vermiljoen en chromaat enz. Dat ging niet<c type="kp">_</c> Jaap Maris deed het in menige aquarel door een heel klein beetje te glaceeren met roode oker over een kleurtje dat roodachtig was<c type="kp">_</c> En het drukte perfect ’t zonlicht op de roode daken uit<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als ik er tijd voor heb zal ik uit dat stuk over Delacroix nog iets overschrijven over de wetten die altijd doorgaan bij de kleuren<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ik heb wel eens gedacht dat menschen als zij over kleur spreken eigentlijk toon bedoelen<c type="kp">_</c> En misschien zijn er tegenwoordig meer <hi rend="italics">toonisten</hi> dan <hi rend="italics">coloristen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Dit is niet hetzelfde ofschoon ’t heel best kan zamengaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik ben wel met U eens dat tegenwoordig men dikwijls al heel moeielijk bevrediging kan vinden voor de behoefte om eens te spreken met menschen die raad <hi rend="italics">weten</hi> te geven en van wie men <hi rend="italics">leert</hi> en <hi rend="italics">licht</hi> krijgt – juist zonder dat zij den leermeester uithangen en tevens zonder dat zij maar enkel groote<c type="kk">/</c> holle woorden die au fond of doodslaanders of algemeenheden zijn<c type="kk">/</c> opdischen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Enfin – de <hi rend="italics">natuur</hi> is echter iets waar men veel toch van te weten kan komen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Gegroet – denk s.v.p. om de <hi rend="italics">Sponning</hi>maat<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> van Uw lijsten. geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">b. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I still often think about your pleasant visit, which I hope will presently be repeated for a rather longer time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Since you were here I’ve been working quite hard on a woman spinning, a little scratch of which I send you herewith.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">It’s quite large and painted in a dark tone, the figure is in blue, with a shawl that’s sort of mouse-coloured.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I hope to make another one like it of a little old man at the bobbin winder near a little window; you might remember a small study of it.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I would be very glad if you’d let me know the size of your frames soon, then I could make a start.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> If the size works out, I might make a small one of that woman spinning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ll just copy out a passage from Les artistes de mon temps by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">C. Blanc</rs>:<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">About three months before the death of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">E. Delacroix</rs>, we met him in the Palais Royal galleries, at about ten o’clock in the evening, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_943">Paul Chenavard</rs> and I. It was as we were leaving a lavish dinner party at which questions of art had been debated, and the conversation had continued between the two of us on the same 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/> subject, with the liveliness, the heat, that one devotes to futile discussions especially. We were talking about colour, and I said: ‘To my mind, the great colourists are those who don’t do local tones’ — and I was about to enlarge on my theme when we noticed Eugène Delacroix in the Rotunda gallery. He came over to us, exclaiming: I’m sure they’re talking painting! Indeed — I said to him — I was on the point of putting forward a proposition which is not, I believe, a paradox, and on which you’re in any case a better judge than anyone: I was saying that the great colourists don’t do local tones, and with you I have doubtless no need to go further.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs> took two steps backward, winking as was his wont: ‘That’s perfectly true — he said; look, there’s a tone, for example (he pointed to the dirty grey tone of the cobblestone); well, if one were to say to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1418">Paolo Veronese</rs>: paint me a nice blonde woman whose flesh should be of that tone — he’d paint her, and the woman <hi rend="italics">would be a blonde in HIS painting</hi>.’ </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Speaking of ‘snot colours’, to my mind one shouldn’t consider the colours in a painting in isolation — if, for instance, a snot colour is placed against strong tones of brownish red, of dark blue or of olive green — it can express the very tender and fresh green of a meadow or a little wheatfield.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And yet I believe that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_868">De Bock</rs>, who christened certain colours ‘snot colours’, certainly wouldn’t contradict the above, actually — for I myself once heard him say that in some paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> there are tones in evening skies, for instance, which are very <hi rend="italics">luminous in the painting</hi> and are actually, regarded <hi rend="italics">in themselves</hi>, a <hi rend="italics">fairly dark, greyish tone</hi>. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Those at home will also write to you soon, and thank your for your letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">But to return for a moment to this question of being able to paint an evening sky or a blonde woman with a dirty colour like the grey of cobblestones; if one thinks about it, this question is actually a <hi rend="italics">double</hi> one.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">For firstly one has a <hi rend="italics">dark</hi> colour that can seem <hi rend="italics">light</hi> (or rather <hi rend="italics">appear to be</hi>). This is actually more a question of <hi rend="italics">tone</hi>.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But then as far as the actual <hi rend="italics">colour</hi> is concerned, a reddish grey, relatively little red, will appear more or less red depending on the colours that are next to it.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">And the same with blue, and the same with yellow likewise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">One only has to add a very little bit of yellow to a colour to make it appear <hi rend="italics">very</hi> yellow, if one puts that colour into or next to a violet or lilac tone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"> I remember how someone tried to suggest a red roof on which the light was falling by means of vermilion and chromate etc. It didn’t work. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jaap Maris</rs> did it in many a watercolour by glazing a very little bit with red ochre over a colour that was reddish. And it suggested the sunlight on the red roofs perfectly. 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"> If I have time I’ll copy something else out of that piece about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, about the laws that always apply to colours.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I’ve sometimes thought that when people talk about colour they actually mean tone. And perhaps there are more <hi rend="italics">tonists</hi> than <hi rend="italics">colourists</hi> these days. This isn’t the same, although it can very easily go together.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I do agree with you that these days one often finds it very hard to satisfy the need to talk to people who <hi rend="italics">know</hi> how to give advice and from whom one <hi rend="italics">learns</hi> and gets <hi rend="italics">light</hi> — but without their playing the schoolmaster and at the same time without their just dishing up large, empty words that at bottom are either full of conversation killers or generalities.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Anyway — <hi rend="italics">nature</hi> is something that one can still learn a lot about, though.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Regards — please don’t forget the <hi rend="italics">rabbet</hi> size of your frames.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter dates from shortly after Theo’s visit to Nuenen at Whitsun, which fell on 1 June. Since Theo left, Vincent has ‘been working quite hard on a woman spinning’ <ref target="#l-5">(ll. 5-6)</ref> and after getting back to Paris Theo has sent a letter that has meanwhile been received in Nuenen <ref target="#l-60">(ll. 60-61)</ref>. It is not possible to give a precise date; we place the letter on or about Friday, 6 June 1884.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Contrary to <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 we do not regard <hi rend="italics">Woman winding yarn</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_556">F 1137 / JH493</rs>) as a sketch enclosed with this letter; see further note 1.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to Nuenen at Whitsun <ref target="let448.xml">(448)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The painting, which was ‘quite large’, is mentioned again in the next letter; it must have measured 100 x 75 cm. Over the next few months Van Gogh repeatedly returns to this woman spinning. Since at the end of September he sent Theo a photograph of a painting of a woman spinning – together with one of a sower – we may assume that this is the same painting in every case; it is known from a ‘carte de visite’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let463.xml#n-1">see letter 463, n. 1.</ref> Subsequently mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let450.xml">letters 450</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let451.xml">451</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let454.xml">454</ref> and – possibly – <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let466.xml">466</ref>.</p>
    
<p rend="indent">It was previously supposed that the small pen-and-ink drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman winding yarn</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_556">F 1137 / JH 493</rs>) was the enclosed ‘little scratch’, but this is a woman winding yarn, not spinning it. Cf. cat. Amsterdam 1997, p. 78 (n. 3).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This could possibly be <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man winding yarn </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2468">F 1138 / JH 486</rs>), which measures 22.5 x 23 cm. We do not know whether Van Gogh ever did make a painted version of it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>During Theo’s visit the brothers must have agreed that Vincent would make work the size of Theo’s frames, so that he could perhaps show them to other people. Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let451.xml">letter 451</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The quote is the opening of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Charles Blanc</rs>’s essay on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_403">Les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi> (Blanc 1876, pp. 23-24). Van Gogh had borrowed the book from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let459.xml">see letter 459</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh likewise derived these views on the use of colour from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, by way of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Blanc</rs>’s essay.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In his essay on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_403">Les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Blanc</rs> writes about ‘the principles of colour’ and ‘the laws of colour’ (Blanc 1876, pp. 62-67). He too repeatedly talks about ‘tone’. In April 1885 Vincent sent Theo the passage in question: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let494.xml">see letter 494</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This is the inside measurement at the back of the frame into which the work has to fit.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    