<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Wednesday, 2 July 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let451"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b406 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>451</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>372</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>454</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-07-02">on or about Wednesday, 2 July 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0406" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0406" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000535_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Hartelijk dank voor Uw brief en ingesl. frs 200<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dank voor de opgaaf van de grootte der lijst waarin ik denk een spinstertje te maken naar de groote studie.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het deed me genoegen eens goede berigten van Breitner te hooren.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> De laatste indrukken die ik van hem had waren zoo als gij weet nog al ongunstig ingevolge van 3 groote lappen die ik bij hem zag en waar ik letterlijk niets in zag dat men ’t zij in de werkelijkheid ’t zij in een denkbeeldige wereld kon t’huis brengen.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Maar een paar aquarellen die hij toen onder handen had – paarden in de duinen – waren toen ook<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon zeer schetsachtig<c type="kk">/</c> toch beter.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> En daar zag ik dingen in die maken ik best begrijpen kan het sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> waar ge van spreekt goed zal zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wat betreft de teekenmaatschappij:<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ik heb het primo glad vergeten wegens ik aan die bewuste figuren schilderde; tweedens<c type="kk">/</c> nu ik door Uw brief er weer eens op kom te denken heb ik er bitter weinig animo voor<c type="kk">/</c> aangezien zoo als ik U toen van den zomer reeds zeide ik er niets anders van verwachten zou dan een weigering van ’t gevraagde lidmaatschap<c type="kk">/</c> welke weigering men dan evenwel als een soort noodzakelijk kwaad kan beschouwen waar een volgend jaar redres op komt en als zoodanig de demarche desnoods raison d’être bekomt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar aangezien het me glad door ’t hoofd is gegaan heb ik bovendien geen een aquarel onder handen en zou gehaast nieuwe moeten opzetten als ’t niet reeds te laat is voor dit jaar<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En als ik U zeg ik nu juist weer verdiept ben in twee nieuwe groote studies van weversinterieurs<c type="kk">/</c> begrijpt ge ik er niet voor gestemd ben<c type="kp">_</c> Vooral daar het met nog al onaangenaamheden kon gepaard gaan indien ik me weer aanmelde bij de Haagsche heeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Wat betreft die twee wevers – het eene is een stuk van ’t getouw met het figuur en een raampje.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">’t andere een interieur met 3 raampjes die uitzien op het geelachtig groen<c type="kk">/</c> dat contrasteert met het blaauw van ’t goed dat op ’t getouw wordt geweven en den kiel van den wever die weer van een ander blaauw is<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Maar ’t geen hier me dezer dagen in de natuur ’t meest heeft getroffen heb ik door gebrek aan goed model er voor nog niet begonnen<c type="kp">_</c>– De halfrijpe korenvelden hebben tegenwoordig een donker goudblonden toon<c type="kk">/</c> ros of goudbrons<c type="kp">_</c> Dit wordt tot een maximum van effekt gebragt door oppositie van den gebroken cobalttoon van de lucht<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Verbeeld U op een dusdanig fond vrouwenfiguren<c type="kk">/</c> zeer ruw<c type="kk">/</c> zeer energiek<c type="kk">/</c> door de zon gebronsd van gezigt en armen en voeten<c type="kk">/</c> met bestoven indigo grove kleeding en zwarte muts in den vorm eener baret op de kort geschoren haren – 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>terwijl zij op een stoffig pad van ros violet met wat groen onkruid tusschen t’koren doorgaan naar hun werk<c type="kk">/</c> met onkruid<c type="shy">-</c>krabbers op den schouder<c type="kk">/</c> of een roggebrood onder den arm<c type="kk">/</c> een kruik of koperen koffijketel<c type="kp">_</c>– Herhaaldelijk<c type="kk">/</c> in allerlei variaties zag ik dezer dagen telkens datzelfde motief<c type="kp">_</c> En ik verzeker U dat het terdeeg echt was<c type="kk">/</c> zeer rijk en toch zeer sober<c type="kk">/</c> zeer uitgezocht<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> artistiek<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">En het preoccupeert mij zeer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Mijn verfrekening staat echter zoo dat ik een beetje zuinig moet zijn met het op touw zetten van nieuwe dingen in een grooter formaat<c type="kk">/</c> en te meer daar het mij nog al veel aan model zal kosten indien ik nog maar eens geschikte modellen<c type="kk">/</c> juist van het type dat ik in ’t hoofd heb (ruwe<c type="kk">/</c> platte gezigten met laag voorhoofd en dikke lippen<c type="kk">/</c> niet dat scherpe maar vol en Milletachtig) en juist met die kleeding<c type="kk">/</c> kan krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Want het luistert hier naauw en men heeft geen vrijheid af te wijken van de kleuren van ’t costuum<c type="kk">/</c> daar ’t effekt ligt in de analogie van den gebroken indigotoon met den gebroken cobalttoon<c type="kk">/</c> opgevoerd door de geheime elementen oranje in ’t rosbrons van het koren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het zou iets zijn dat goed <hi rend="italics">Zomer</hi> uitdrukt – zomer is m.i. niet makkelijk uit te drukken<c type="kp">_</c> Meestal<c type="kk">/</c> althans dikwijls<c type="kk">/</c> is een zomereffekt of onmogelijk of leelijk – dit is mijn gevoelen althans – daar staan echter tegenover de schemeringen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Maar ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> het is niet makkelijk een zomer zoneffekt te vinden dat even rijk en even eenvoudig en even prettig om te zien is als de karakteristieke effekten der andere jaargetijden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De lente is teer groen (jong koren) en rose (appelbloessem)<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">De herfst is het contrast der geele blaren tegen violette toonen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">De winter is de sneeuw met de zwarte silhouetjes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Doch als nu de zomer is de oppositie van blaauwen tegen een element van oranje in ’t goudbrons van ’t koren<c type="kk">/</c> zou men zoodoende juist in ieder van de contrasten der complementaire kleuren (rood en groen<c type="kk">/</c> blaauw en oranje<c type="kk">/</c> geel en violet<c type="kk">/</c> wit en zwart) een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> kunnen schilderen dat de stemming der jaargetijden goed uitdrukte.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben zeer verlangend eens te vernemen hoe het staat met Uw reis n. Londen<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> enz<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Het blijft nog maar weinig vooruitgaan met het loopen van Moe. Wil is naar Noordwijk en dat is een goed ding.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Lies is hier geweest doch ik vond haar werk niet vooruitgegaan – zij heeft nog niet geleerd uit haar oogen te kijken en te maken wat zij werkelijk zag of voelde<c type="kp">_</c> Het blijft bij het afgezaagde van ik weet niet welke half sentimenteele half godsdienstige beschouwing<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Doch dat kan door den tijd nog veranderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Gegroet en nogmaals dank voor Uw schrijven en het ingeslotene.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Geloof me</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">’t best wat ik er op weet – voor de lijst – is eenige raampjes van die grootte te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> dan kunnen we zien wat het best uitvalt.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many thanks for your letter and 200 francs enclosed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Thanks for letting me know the size of the frame, for which I’m thinking of making a little woman spinning, after the large study.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I was pleased to hear good reports about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> for once.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> As you know, the last impressions that I had of him were rather unfavourable as a consequence of 3 large canvases that I saw at his place and in which I literally saw nothing that one could locate either in reality or in an imaginary world.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Still, a few watercolours he was working on at the time — horses in the dunes — were better, although very sketchy.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And I saw in them things that mean I can readily understand that the painting you talk about is good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">As to the drawing society:<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> first, I’d utterly forgotten about it because I was painting those particular figures; secondly, now that your letter prompts me to think about it again, I have very little inclination for it since, as I already said to you in the summer, I wouldn’t expect anything other than a rejection of my application for membership, which rejection one can, however, regard as a sort of necessary evil that would be redressed another year, and as such the step acquires a <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi> if need be. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But besides, since it completely slipped my mind, I don’t have a single watercolour in hand and would have to start new ones in a hurry, if it’s not already too late for this year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And when I tell you that I’m just now absorbed in two new large studies of weavers’ interiors, you’ll understand that I’m not in the mood for it. Particularly since it could involve all sorts of unpleasantnesses were I to apply again to the gentlemen in The Hague.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">As to these two weavers — one is a section of the loom with the figure and a little window.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The other an interior with 3 little windows that look out on the yellowish foliage, which contrasts with the blue of the cloth that’s being woven on the loom and the weaver’s smock, which is another blue again.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But for want of a good model I haven’t yet started on what has most struck me in nature these last few days. At present the half-ripe wheatfields have a dark, golden blond tone, ruddy or golden bronze. This is brought out to maximum effect by opposition with the broken cobalt tone of the sky.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Imagine female figures against such a background, very crude, very energetic, faces and arms and feet bronzed by the sun, with dusty, coarse indigo clothes and black caps in the shape of a beret on their close-cropped hair — 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> while they go to their work on a dusty path of ruddy violet with some green weeds among the wheat, with hoes on their shoulders, or a loaf of rye bread under their arms, a pitcher or a copper coffee-pot. These last few days I’ve repeatedly seen that same subject, time and again, in all sorts of variants. And I assure you that it was thoroughly authentic, very lush and yet very sober, most perfectly artistic.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And it preoccupies me greatly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The state of my paint bill is such, however, that I have to be a bit careful about starting new things in a larger size, and all the more so because it will cost me a fair amount in models if I could ever get suitable models of precisely the type I have in mind (coarse, flat faces with low foreheads and thick lips, not that sharp look, but full and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>-like) and with those very clothes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">For this is very precise work, and one isn’t at liberty to depart from the colours of the costume, since the effect lies in the analogy of the broken indigo tone and the broken cobalt tone, heightened by the mysterious elements of orange in the ruddy bronze of the wheat.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">It would be something that expresses <hi rend="italics">Summer</hi> well — in my view summer isn’t easy to express. Usually, or often at least, a summery effect is either impossible or ugly  that’s my feeling, at least — it’s offset by the twilights, though.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But I mean it isn’t easy to find the effect of a summer sun that’s as lush and as simple and as pleasant to look at as the characteristic effects of the other seasons. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The spring is tender green (young wheat) and pink (apple blossom).</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The autumn is the contrast of the yellow leaves against violet tones.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">The winter is the snow with the little black silhouettes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">But if the summer is the opposition of blues against an element of orange in the golden bronze of the wheat, this way one could paint a painting in each of the contrasts of the complementary colours (red and green, blue and orange, yellow and violet, white and black) that really expressed the mood of the seasons.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Well, I’m very eager to hear how things are going with your trip to London<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> etc.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> is still not making much progress with her walking. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs>’s gone to Noordwijk, and that’s a good thing.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> has been here, but I thought that her work hadn’t progressed — she still hasn’t learnt to use her eyes and to make what she really saw or felt. It’s stuck at I don’t know what kind of hackneyed half-sentimental, half-religious view.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> But it can still change in time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Regards, and thanks again for your letter and the enclosure.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">The best I can think of — for the frame — is to take some little stretching frames of that size, then we can see what works out best.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Because Vincent thanks his brother for the money he sent – this must have been for July (<ref target="#n-8">see n. 8</ref>) – the letter is dated on or about Wednesday, 2 July 1884.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s visit to Nuenen at Whitsun <ref target="let448.xml">(448)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mrs van Gogh’s broken leg <ref target="let423.xml">(423)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This ‘large’ painting of a woman spinning must be the same one referred to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let449.xml">letters 449</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let450.xml">450</ref>. The ‘little woman spinning’ may have been the woman spinning that is under <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The parsonage garden in the snow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2492">F 194 / JH 603</rs>), which measures 59 x 78 cm. For an X-ray image of this see exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 172. Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let466.xml">letter 466</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> stayed in Paris, where he met Theo, from June to November 1884. See Hefting 1970, p. 75.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>See for these three large works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs>, one of which was probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_635">Charge of the hussars</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let361.xml#n-22">letter 361, nn. 22</ref><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let361.xml#n-22">-24.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>We do not know which watercolours Van Gogh means.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>See for De Hollandsche Teeken-maatschappij: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let256.xml#n-8">letter 256, n. 8.</ref> Van Gogh’s name does not appear in the minutes for 1884-1885, nor is he listed among the absentees (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">GAH</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver near an open window</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2472">F 24 / JH 500</rs>), which measures 67 x 93.2 cm. In the same week – on 5 July 1884 – <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘Vincent is still working on weavers. A pity, one might say, that he doesn’t choose a landscape for a change’ (FR b2253).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Weaver, interior with three small windows</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2473">F 37 / JH 501</rs>), which measures 61 x 93 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘uitgelezen’ (exquisitely).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The plan was that Theo would go to London on 4 August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let452.xml">see letter 452</ref>). His <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> wished him bon voyage on 17 July (FR b2254). We know that he travelled back via the Netherlands, because on 22 August the family was able to look back with great pleasure on his visit to Nuenen (FR b2256).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> was on holiday with her sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Joan van Houten</rs> and their family in a boarding house in Noordwijk aan Zee, between The Hague and Haarlem. Theo had provided the funds for this (FR b2254 and b2255).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Their sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Elisabeth</rs> had aspirations as a writer. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote this month about Vincent’s surly attitude: ‘Vincent is working hard but he’s not pleasant; all the same I’m easier in my mind than if he were in The Hague’ (FR b2254, 17 July 1884).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The idea is that Vincent will send works without stretching frames which Theo will mount on the stretching frames – there would then be a single frame that could be used for all the works.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    