<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Monday, 22 and about Sunday, 28 September 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let461"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b413 a V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>461</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>379</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>464</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-09-22">between about Monday, 22 and about Sunday, 28 September 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0413 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0413 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000546_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Mijn laatsten brief kon ik niet in een anderen vorm krijgen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Maar weet dat het mij altijd voorkomt dat het meer een noodlottig geschil is tusschen U en mij dan een waaraan we zelf alleen schuld hebben. En zoo met Pa ook<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ge zegt er komt binnen kort een expositie van ’t werk van Delacroix<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Goed – daar zult ge zeker wel zien een schilderij <hi rend="italics">La barricade</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dat ik alleen ken uit levensbeschrijvingen van Delacroix. ’t is geschilderd meen ik in 1848.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Gij kent bovendien een lithographie door de Lemud meen ik – indien niet door hem dan door <hi rend="italics">Daumier</hi><c type="kk">/</c> voorstellende ook de barricade van 1848.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ik wou gij U eens kondt voorstellen dat gij en ik hadden geleefd in dat jaar 1848 – of dergelijke periode<c type="kk">/</c> want bij den coup d’état van Napoleon is er ook weer iets geweest.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik zal U geen hatelijkheden zeggen – dat is ook het doel nooit geweest – ik tracht U duidelijk te maken in hoeverre ’t verschil dat tusschen ons gekomen is in verband staat met algemeene stroomingen in de maatschappij<c type="kk">/</c> en als zoodanig iets heel anders is dan expres er op aangelegde hatelijkheden.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Neem dus dien tijd 1848.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wie stonden toen tegenover elkaar die men als typen kan nemen van al de rest<c type="kp">_</c> Guizot – minister van Louis Philippe eenerzijds<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Michelet en Quinet met de studenten aan den anderen kant<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik begin met Guizot en Louis Philippe<c type="kp">_</c>– Waren die slecht of tiranniek? Niet precies – ’t waren lui<c type="kk">/</c> naar ik ’t zie<c type="kk">/</c> als b.v. Pa en grootvader<c type="kk">/</c> den ouden Goupil<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> (personen enfin die er almagtig eerwaardig uitzien – diep – ernstig – doch bekijkt men ze een beetje scherp en van digt bij<c type="kk">/</c> hebben ze iets lugubers<c type="kk">/</c> dofs<c type="kk">/</c> flaauws zelf<c type="kk">/</c> dermate men er wee van wordt<c type="kp">_</c>– Is dit te veel gezegd???)<c type="kk">/</c> behoudens variatie van positie zelfden geest<c type="kk">/</c> zelfde karakter. Is dat mis gezien van mij???</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Quinet nu b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> of Michelet of V. Hugo (<hi rend="italics">later</hi>)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> was ’t verschil tusschen hen en hun tegenpartij almagtig groot<c type="kp">_</c>– Ja – maar oppervlakkig zou men dat niet gezegd hebben. ik zelf heb <hi rend="italics">in der tijd</hi> tegelijk een boek van Guizot en een boek van Michelet even mooi gevonden. Doch in mijn geval<c type="kk">/</c> naarmate ik er dieper in kwam zag ik onderscheid en <hi rend="italics">tegenstrijdigheid</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wat meer is! Enfin dat het eene <hi rend="italics">dood</hi>loopt<c type="kk">/</c> vaag verdwijnt<c type="kk">/</c> en integendeel in ’t andere iets <hi rend="italics">oneindigs</hi> blijft<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Er is sedert veel gebeurd<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar ik houd het er voor dat als gij en ik <hi rend="italics">toen</hi> geleefd hadden gij aan den kant van Guizot waart geweest en ik aan den kant van Michelet. En beiden consequent blijvende<c type="kk">/</c> met een zekere melankolie ons regtlijnig als vijanden tegenover elkaar hadden kunnen bevinden<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. op zoo’n barricade<c type="kk">/</c> gij er vóór als soldaat van ’t gouvernement<c type="kk">/</c> ik er achter als revolutionnair of rebel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">Nu</hi> in 1884 – <hi rend="italics">toevallig zijn de cijfers net dezelfde</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">slechts even omgedraaid</hi> – staan we <hi rend="italics">weer</hi> tegenover elkaar – doch barricades zijn er nu wel is waar niet<c type="kp">_</c>– De geesten die ’t niet eens kunnen worden echter wel degelijk. Le moulin n’y est plus mais le vent y est encore<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> En we zijn – mijns inziens – in verschillende kampen tegenover elkaar – daar is niets aan te doen<c type="kp">_</c>– En of ge wilt of niet<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> moet voort<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> moet voort<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch wegens we broers zijn<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons ’t coupeeren elkaar dood te schieten b.v. (in figuurlijken zin)<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Doch elkaar <hi rend="italics">helpen</hi> kunnen we niet dermate als twee lui die in ’t zelfde kamp aan elkaars zij staan. Neen<c type="kk">/</c> komen we in elkaars nabijheid<c type="kk">/</c> we zouden in elkaars vuur loopen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12"><hi rend="italics">Mijn</hi> hatelijkheden zijn kogels niet op U – die mijn broer zijt – gericht<c type="kk">/</c> maar wel in ’t algemeen op de partij waar ge nu eenmaal in zijt<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> hatelijkheden beschouw ik ook niet als expres gemikt op mij maar – <hi rend="italics">ge schiet op de barricade</hi> (en meent U daarmee verdienstelijk te maken)<c type="kk">/</c> en ik ben nu eenmaal daarin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Denk hier eens over als ge wilt – want ik geloof niet dat ge erg veel kunt afdingen hierop<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan niet anders zeggen dan dat ik geloof ’t ± zoo in elkaar zit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb nu meenen te zien dat terwijl ik vroeger gehoopt had gij anders zoudt uitvallen en we aan een zelfde zij zouden staan<c type="kk">/</c> het zich beslist heeft we in tegenstrijdige kampen verzeild zijn geraakt<c type="kp">_</c> En gij – uwerzijds hebt misschien gehoopt ik veranderen zou dermate dat wij zamen aan de kant waar ge U nu bevindt<c type="kk">/</c> teregt gekomen zouden zijn. Maar ge ziet, daar heb ik geen plan op<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik moet schieten<c type="kk">/</c> Uw kant uit – ik zal echter trachten U niet te raken<c type="kp">_</c> Gij moet schieten<c type="kk">/</c> mijn kant uit – doe ’t zelfde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik hoop gij dit wat ik in figuurlijken zin zeg<c type="kk">/</c> vatten zult. Noch gij noch ik bemoeien ons met de politiek maar wij zijn in de wereld<c type="kk">/</c> in de maatschappij<c type="kk">/</c> en <hi rend="italics">vanzelf</hi> groepeeren zich gelederen van menschen. Kunnen de wolken er zelf <hi rend="italics">heel</hi> veel aan doen of ze tot de eene donderbui of tot de andere hooren? of ze dragers zijn van positieve of negatieve electriciteit?– Doch nu is het ook weer waar menschen geen wolken zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Men maakt als individu een deel uit van ’t geheel dat de menschheid uitmaakt<c type="kp">_</c>– In die menschheid zijn partijen. In hoeverre is ’t eigen wil<c type="kk">/</c> in hoever fataliteit der omstandigheden<c type="kk">/</c> dat men tot de eene of tot de er tegenoverstaande partij hoort?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Enfin ’t was toen 48<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is nu 84<c type="kp">_</c> le moulin n’y est plus<c type="kk">/</c> le vent y est encore. Tracht echter voor U zelf te weten waar ge eigentlijk in zijt zooals ik voor me zelf dat tracht te weten. Gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I couldn’t get my last letter into a different form.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">But understand that it always seems to me that it’s more an ill-fated quarrel between you and me than one for which we ourselves are solely to blame. And the same with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You say there’s soon to be an exhibition of Delacroix’s work.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Very well — you’ll certainly see a painting there, <hi rend="italics">The barricade</hi>, that I only know from biographies of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>. I think it was painted in 1848.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> You also know a lithograph by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1167">De Lemud</rs>, I think — if not by him then by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs></hi>, also depicting the barricade of 1848.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I wish that you could just imagine that you and I had lived in that year, 1848 — or a similar period, for there was also something of the kind with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_496">Napoleon</rs>’s coup d’état.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I won’t say anything nasty to you — that’s never been the aim — I’m trying to make clear to you the extent to which the difference that has come between us is related to general tendencies in society, and as such is something very different from expressly intended nastiness. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">So take the 1848 period.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Who were facing each other then whom one can take as prototypes of all the rest? <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_620">Guizot</rs> — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_171">Louis-Philippe</rs>’s minister on one side,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_720">Quinet</rs> with the students on the other side.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I’ll start with Guizot and Louis-Philippe. Were they bad or tyrannical? Not exactly — they were people, as I see it, like, say, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_398">Grandfather</rs>, old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_436">Goupil</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> (people in short who look almighty respectable — profound — serious — yet if one looks at them a bit sharply and at close quarters, there’s something lugubrious, dull, even feeble about them, to such a degree that they make one sick. Is this going too far???), aside from a difference in position, same mind, same character. Have I got this wrong???</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_720">Quinet</rs> now, say, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">V. Hugo</rs> (<hi rend="italics">later</hi>),<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> was the difference between them and their opponents almighty great? Yes — but on the surface one wouldn’t have said so. <hi rend="italics">At the time</hi> I myself, at one and the same time, found a book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_620">Guizot</rs> and a book by Michelet equally good. Yet in my case, as I got deeper into it, I saw a difference and, what’s more, <hi rend="italics">contradiction</hi>! In short, that the one <hi rend="italics">peters out</hi>, disappears vaguely, while in contrast something <hi rend="italics">infinite</hi> remains in the other. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Much has happened since then. But I believe that if you and I had lived <hi rend="italics">then</hi>, you would have been on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_620">Guizot</rs>’s side and I on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s side. And both remaining consistent, could with a certain sadness have found ourselves directly opposed to each other as enemies, on just such a barricade, say; you in front of it as a soldier of the government, I behind it as a revolutionary or rebel.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"><hi rend="italics">Now</hi> in 1884 — <hi rend="italics">by chance the figures are exactly the same, just reversed</hi> — we’re facing each other <hi rend="italics">again</hi> — although there are no barricades now, it’s true. The minds that can’t agree, however, are real. The mill is there no longer, but the wind’s still there.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> And we are — in my view — opposite each other in different camps — it can’t be helped. And whether you like it or not, <hi rend="italics">you</hi> must go on, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> must go on. Yet because we’re brothers, let’s stop short of shooting each other dead, say (figuratively speaking). 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Yet we can’t <hi rend="italics">help</hi> each other as much as two people standing side by side in the same camp. No, if we come in each other’s vicinity, we’d walk into each other’s fire.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><hi rend="italics">My</hi> nasty remarks are bullets directed not at you — who are my brother — but in general at the party to which you belong. Likewise I don’t regard <hi rend="italics">your</hi> nasty remarks as being expressly aimed at me, but — <hi rend="italics">you’re shooting at the barricade</hi> (and believe that you’re thereby making yourself useful) and I happen to be inside it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"> Think about this if you will — for I don’t believe that you can contradict very much of it; all I can say is that I believe this is pretty much how it is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’ve now realized that while I used to hope that you’d turn out differently and we’d be on the same side, it has been decided that we’ve ended up in opposing camps. And you — for your part, perhaps hoped that I’d change to the extent that we’d have fetched up together on the side where you are now. But you see I have no intention of that. I have to shoot in your direction — I’ll try not to hit you, though. You have to shoot in my direction — do the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I hope you’ll take what I’m saying in a figurative sense. Neither you nor I concern ourselves with politics, but we do live in the world, in society, and ranks of people do form groups<hi rend="italics"> as a matter of course</hi>. Can the clouds themselves do <hi rend="italics">very</hi> much about whether they belong to one thunderstorm or the other? Whether they are carriers of positive or negative electricity? But it’s also true that people aren’t clouds. As an individual one is part of the whole that makes up humanity. Within this humanity there are parties. To what extent is it free will, to what extent the fatefulness of circumstances, that one belongs to one opposing party or the other?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Anyway, it was 48 then, it’s 84 now. The mill is there no longer, the wind is still there. However, try to know for yourself where you actually are, as I try to know it for myself. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Assuming that the opening shot in this letter refers to <ref target="let458.xml">letter 458</ref>, in which Vincent explicitly says that his opinion about a man’s responsibility to a woman differs fundamentally from Theo’s, this letter must have been written after about 21 September. It must, moreover, be earlier than <ref target="let463.xml">letter 463</ref> of 30 September, since the question of the ‘barricade’ between Theo and Vincent introduced at the beginning of the present letter is repeated there. We therefore date this one between about Monday, 22 and about Sunday, 28 September 1884.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">It remains odd that Van Gogh used the word ‘soon’ in association with the upcoming exhibition of Delacroix’s work, since it was not due to open until March 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">A sheet had previously been added to the end of this letter which, on the grounds of content, we regard as part of <ref target="let464.xml">letter 464</ref>. See under <hi rend="italics">Arrangement </hi>there.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Margot Begemann is in Utrecht <ref target="let456.xml">(456)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let458.xml">letter 458</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exposition Eugène Delacroix au profit de la souscription destinée à éléver à Paris un monument sa mémoire. Ecole Nationale des Beaux-Arts </hi>(Eugène Delacroix<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>Exhibition to benefit the subscription intended to raise a monument to his memory in Paris), Paris (Ecole Nationale des Beaux-Arts) 6 March to 15 April 1885. See Johnson 1981-1989, vol. 1, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xxxiv</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La barricade</hi> (The barricade), or: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Liberté guidant le peuple </hi>(Liberty guiding the people), 1830 (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_64">Ill. 64</rs>. Van Gogh is mistaken (but he does write ‘I think’): the painting depicts the July revolution of 1830, not the popular uprising in June 1848. Delacroix also spoke of a barricade in his letters: ‘I have embarked on a modern subject, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A barricade</hi>’ (‘J’ai entrepris un sujet moderne, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Une barricade</hi>’). See Johnson 1981-1989, vol. 1, pp. 144-151, cat. no. 144.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This may be a lithograph of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_476">The Revolution of 1848. A family on the barricades</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let305.xml#n-6">see letter 305, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_496">Louis Napoleon Bonaparte</rs>, who became President of France on 20 December 1848, violated the constitution and forced through a ten-year presidency after the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">coup d’état</hi> of 2 December 1851. A year later he had himself proclaimed Emperor Napoleon <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">iii</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_620">François Guizot</rs> took part in the July revolution of 1830 and then became one of the pillars of the July monarchy of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_171">King Louis Philippe I</rs>. He gradually became more conservative, and was appointed premier in 1847. His accommodating attitude towards the king provoked the February revolution of 1848. Louis Philippe I initially ruled as a citizen king but grew ever more authoritarian; his regime became corrupt. He too was brought down by the revolution that ushered in the Second Republic (1848-1852).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_720">Edgar Quinet</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, both of whom held liberal views, rebelled against <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_620">Guizot</rs>’s conservative and ultramontane policy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_436">Adolphe Goupil</rs>, founder of the firm of Goupil &amp; Cie.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs> wrote several novels in which the Revolution featured, among them <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi> (1862), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_278">Quatre-vingt-treize</ref></hi> (1874), and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_307">Histoire d’un crime</ref></hi> (1877-1878).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This line is taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_307">Les misérables</ref></hi>, book 1, chapter 10. See Hugo 1951, p. 67. It is said by a former revolutionary (‘le conventionnel’) in a conversation with Bishop Bienvenu about the achievements of the French Revolution: ‘We brought down the ancien régime in deeds, we did not entirely succeed in doing away with it in ideas.’ (Nous avons démoli l’ancien régime dans les faits, nous n’avons pu entièrement le supprimer dans les idées.) This idea ties in directly with what Van Gogh asserts before the quotation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    