<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 14 November 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let469"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b419 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>469</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>385</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>471</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-12-14">on or about Friday, 14 November 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0419 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0419 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000560_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0419 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0419 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000561_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">’t zal U zeker wel interesseeren hoe het staat met ’t beroep n. Helvoirt dat Pa heeft ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Pa heeft tot de lui in Helvoirt gezegd dat hij het <hi rend="italics">zeker niet</hi> in overweging kon nemen zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij tractement H. in ’t evene werd gebragt met tractement Nuenen<c type="kp">_</c>– En dit ’t verschil in tractement opmaken – ze moeten er een f<c type="kp">_</c> 150 bij leggen geloof ik – schrijft Pa heden dat zij niet veel bezwaar schijnen tegen te maken<c type="kp">_</c>– Dus ofschoon niets is beslist – gegeven de bereidwilligheid der brave inboorlingen van Helv. – er is wel degelijk kans op dat Pa het nu ingevolge van zijn eigen woorden in zeer serieuse consideratie zal dienen te nemen<c type="kp">_</c>– Dit is voor mij belangrijk om reden ik <hi rend="italics">zeker niet</hi> trek zou hebben naar Helv. mede te gaan<c type="kp">_</c>– Hoe die zaak staat wou ik U eens precies zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dezer dagen ben ik ondanks het hier vrij terdeeg vriest nog buiten aan ’t werk aan een nogal groote studie (meer dan 1 meter) van een ouden watermolen te Gennep<c type="kk">/</c> aan den anderen kant van Eindhoven.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik wil dat geheel buiten afwerken – maar ’t zal ook wel ’t laatste zijn dat ik dit jaar buiten schilder. Sedert ik U schreef ben ik bovendien aan andere studies doende – onder anderen twee koppen van polderwerkers<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">ik heb nu <hi rend="italics">3</hi> lui in Eindhoven die schilderen willen leeren en die ik stillevens leer maken<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik durf gerust beweren ik in techniek van schilderen en in kleur sedert Uw bezoek<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ben gevorderd<c type="kp">_</c> En dat dit nog toe zal nemen ook<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">il y a les premiers pas qui coûtent<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> in ’t schilderen – ’t is later meer meegaande en ik heb <hi rend="italics">sommige</hi> troeven in de hand<c type="kp">_</c>– En ik geloof dat daar slagen mee te halen zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu weet ge dat ik een demarche gedaan heb<c type="kk">/</c> op nieuw bij Mauve en Tersteeg<c type="kk">/</c> om te redresseeren wat vroeger is gepasseerd<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Die demarche heb ik geen spijt van<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar ze hebben geweigerd zich er mee in te laten – “zeer stellig” geweigerd<c type="kp">_</c>– Dit decourageert me niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik beschouw het als iets dergelijks als dat men een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> naar een expositie stuurt en geweigerd wordt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Men moet eerst eens of meermalen zelfs oppositie hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Dus nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb geen spijt van mijn demarche en zal die hoogst denkelijk herhalen – niet precies direct – maar over niet al te langen tijd<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Nu wou ik U zeggen dat het mij zeer aangenaam zou zijn als gij niet maar neutraal U hieldt in dezen – doch integendeel medehielpt om er door te krijgen wat ik wil<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb tegenover Mauve niet alleen doch ook tegenover T. ongelijk bekend<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Te eer omdat ik geloof later ze zelf in zullen zien zij van hun kant dingen radicaal <hi rend="italics">mis</hi> verstaan hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Wat ze nu nog niet zien<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Dus van mijn kant heb ik ditmaal door zoo ver te gaan van heel royaal gedecideerd ongelijk te bekennen over vroeger<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">verder</hi> eenvoudig hun<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> <hi rend="italics">werk</hi> te laten zien naar gelang het <hi rend="italics">beter</hi> wordt<c type="kk">/</c> en ben van eventueele excuses maken verder quand bien même af<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi>Eens</hi> <hi rend="italics">is</hi> <hi>voldoende</hi>, en <hi rend="italics">hoefde</hi> ik desnoods niet eens in zóó ver als ik ’t gedaan heb, namelijk – <hi rend="italics">onvoorwaardelijk</hi>. Hun <hi rend="italics">royaal</hi> te krijgen van <hi rend="italics">hun</hi> kant – is nu een tweede – werk gij daaraan mee <hi rend="italics">als ge lust hebt</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Anders – laat maar waaijen doch dan ga ik over een tijd er toch alleen op nieuw op door<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik weet niet hoe gij mijn laatsten brief zult hebben opgenomen – die toch niet kwaad gemeend was<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="italics">Mijn zaken kunnen goed gaan</hi> en in ons beider belang wou ik we de kracht waar we over disponeeren kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> concentreerden<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb <hi rend="italics">en</hi> Tersteeg <hi rend="italics">en</hi> M. ook met een kort woord geantwoord op hun weigering<c type="kk">/</c> om hun te zeggen dat “<hi rend="italics">ik het met Tersteeg eens was betrekkelijk</hi> <hi rend="italics">dat het voor mij </hi><hi>beter</hi><hi rend="italics"> was nieuwe lui te zoeken dan oude relaties</hi> <hi rend="italics">te zoeken te vernieuwen</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> dat zulks wel degelijk mijn</hi> <hi rend="italics">eigen idee ook is doch dat buiten en behalve dat</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> ik toch</hi> <hi rend="italics">vertrouwen genoeg in de toekomst heb dat ik het</hi> <hi>niet<hi rend="italics"> </hi>ligt</hi><hi rend="italics"> zal opgeven ook </hi><hi>zelfs</hi><hi rend="italics"> oude relaties te herwinnen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">beter dan vroeger zelfs</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c> Dit is mijn antwoord aan T. geweest<c type="kp">_</c>– En is ook mijn woord aan U – ik geloof dat het mogelijk is ook met U – op <hi rend="italics">beter</hi> voet te komen dan den tegenwoordigen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Maar – ronduit gezegd – de laatste <hi rend="italics">1 1/2</hi> of twee jaar vind ik gij te neutraal zijt geweest jegens mij en wensch ik meer <hi rend="italics">hartelijkheid</hi> vooral en was de vriendschap me te koel en te weinig geanimeerd<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vind dit pedant van me <hi rend="italics">als ge wilt</hi> – doch het is niet <hi rend="italics">pedant</hi> maar ’t is uit grondige praktische redenen dat ik U hier op vroeger wees en nog eens wijs<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Margo Begemann komt dezer dagen te Nuenen terug<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – ik ben altijd goede vrienden met haar gebleven en ’t is op mijn aanraden dat zij <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> toegegeven heeft aan haar zusters die lieten merken dat ze maar liever hadden ze weg bleef en die haar nahouden dat zij huns inziens het verbruid heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– Integendeel heeft haar familie verpligtingen aan haar en heeft zij in der tijd haar eigen geld in de zaak gegeven toen haar broer<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> failliet is geweest<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">De zaak is hier dat indien zij en ik verkiezen van elkaar te houden, aan elkaar gehecht zijn – trouwens al lang geweest zijn – is dit geen <hi rend="italics">kwaad</hi> van ons of iets wat men ons verwijten mag<c type="kp">_</c>– ’t Zij aan haar ’t zij aan mij<c type="kp">_</c>– En in mijn oog is het iets absurds dat de lui meenden zich hierover ’t hoofd te moeten opwinden – nog wel – in <hi rend="italics">hun</hi> meening – in mijn of in haar belang<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat was een slechte dienst<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Iedereen moge dit doen met de beste intenties – doch – – – Louis Begemann – die had ook zijn bezwaren maar <hi rend="italics">was</hi> zóó en <hi rend="italics">bleef</hi> zóó dat en zij en ik met hem konden praten<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>en dat het nog niet <hi rend="italics">veel erger</hi> afliep is juist doordat hij humaan en bedaard was en toen dat met haar gebeurde, waar ik alleen van wist, kon hij <hi rend="italics">helpen</hi> en al de anderen <hi rend="italics">hinderden slechts</hi><c type="kp">_</c> En in de maatregelen toen te nemen zijn we ’t volkomen eens geweest<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Drie dagen te <hi rend="italics">voren</hi> trouwens had ik hem al gewaarschuwd en gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben bezorgd over je zuster<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Zeer zeker is het dat <hi rend="italics">zij</hi> vroeger of later zoowat <hi rend="italics">al</hi> de lui hier in de buurt meer of minder goedheid en diensten heeft bewezen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij in ziekte ’t zij als ze in een of andere ongelegenheid waren.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">En zij en ik zijn juist gehecht geworden tijdens de ziekte van Moe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Zij schrijft mij nu nog pas: als er soms zieken zijn in Nuenen<c type="kk">/</c> ga gij er dan toch eens kijken en zie of er iets te helpen is<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin – er zijn duizend dingen in haar van dien aard.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">En dat er hier een zeer deplorabel misverstand heeft plaats gehad<c type="kk">/</c> dat is het <hi rend="italics">allerzachtst</hi> wat men er van zeggen kan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Ik geloof van U dat van achteren beschouwd gij <hi rend="italics">nu niet meer</hi> <hi rend="italics">zóó zoudt spreken als op dien</hi> <hi rend="italics">avond</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Dat gold <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> alleen – en <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> kon er tegen<c type="kk">/</c> dus er is geen sprake van verwijt mijnerzijds tegen U in deze zaak<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Alleen tot <hi rend="italics">explicatie</hi> voor U zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">even als gij spraakt tot mij die er</hi> <hi rend="italics">tegen kan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> spraken haar zusters<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> <hi rend="italics">tot haar</hi> die bleek er radeloos door te worden. Gij hebt <hi rend="italics">part nog deel hieraan</hi> want ge spraakt tot <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> die er tegen op kan en ge spraakt <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> tot <hi rend="italics">haar</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Maar de <hi rend="italics">eigentlijke schuld</hi> ligt aan haar zusters<c type="kk">/</c> of liever vooral <hi rend="italics">één der</hi> <hi rend="italics">zusters</hi> die te verharder blijkt daar zij eigentlijk nog <hi rend="italics">mokt</hi> en rancune heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Gij – zoudt <hi rend="italics">me zelf moeten herzeggen</hi> dat ge rancune houdt – eer ik er U van zou verdenken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Zooveel als dit laatste mijnerzijds tot U<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">You’ll certainly be interested in how things stand with the call to Helvoirt that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> received.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Pa told the people in Helvoirt that he <hi rend="italics">certainly couldn’t</hi> even consider it unless the H. stipend was brought up to the level of the Nuenen stipend. And Pa writes today that they don’t seem to be raising any objections to making up the difference in stipend — they have to add 150 guilders to it, I believe. So although nothing has been decided — given the willingness of the good natives of Helvoirt — there’s a real chance that as a result of his own words Pa will have to consider it very seriously. This is important to me, because I would <hi rend="italics">certainly not</hi> want to go to Helvoirt with them. I just wanted to tell you exactly how things stand.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">These last few days, although it’s freezing quite hard here, I’ve been working outdoors on a rather large study (more than 1 metre) of an old water mill in Gennep, on the other side of Eindhoven.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I want to finish the whole thing outdoors — but it will definitely be the last that I paint outdoors this year. Since I wrote to you I’ve also been working on other studies — among them two heads of polder workers.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I now have <hi rend="italics">3</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449 bio.xml#_475 bio.xml#_816">people</rs> in Eindhoven who want to learn to paint and whom I’m teaching to paint still lifes.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I can safely say that I’ve progressed in painting technique and in colour since your visit.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> And that this will continue to improve, too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">In painting, it’s the first steps that count<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — it gets easier later, and I have <hi rend="italics">some</hi> trumps in my hand. And I think there are tricks to be taken with them. Now you know that I made an approach to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> again, to put right what happened in the past.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I don’t regret that approach.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But they’ve refused to have anything to do with it — ‘very definitely’ refused. This doesn’t discourage me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I regard it as something like sending a painting to an exhibition and having it rejected.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">One has to encounter opposition at first, or even several times.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">So again, I don’t regret my approach, and shall most likely repeat it — not straightaway, exactly — but before too long. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I wanted to tell you now that I’d be very pleased if you didn’t just stay neutral in this matter — but on the contrary helped me to get what I want. I’ve admitted I was wrong, not just to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> but to<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787"> T.</rs> as well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">All the more because I believe that later on they themselves will realize that for their part they totally <hi rend="italics">misunderstood</hi> things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Which they don’t see yet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">So for my part, by going so far this time as to very generously and decidedly admit I was wrong in the past, <hi rend="italics">moreover </hi>to simply show them <hi rend="italics">work</hi> as it gets <hi rend="italics">better</hi>, in any event I won’t have to make any more apologies in future. <hi>Once</hi> <hi rend="italics">is</hi> <hi>enough</hi>, and I didn’t necessarily even <hi rend="italics">have to</hi> go as far as I did, namely — <hi rend="italics">unconditionally</hi>. Getting them to be <hi rend="italics">generous</hi> for <hi rend="italics">their</hi> part — is another thing – you could assist in this <hi rend="italics">if you want to</hi>. If not — don’t bother about it, but then after a while I’ll return to it again on my own. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t know how you’ll have taken my last letter — which wasn’t meant angrily. <hi rend="italics">My affairs can prosper</hi>, and in both our interests I wish that we could concentrate the strength we have at our disposal. I’ve replied briefly to <hi rend="italics">both</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> <hi rend="italics">and</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">M.</rs> about their refusal, to tell them that ‘<hi rend="italics">I rather agree with Tersteeg that it would be </hi><hi>better</hi><hi rend="italics"> for me to seek out new people than to try to renew old relationships, that this really is my own idea, too, but above and beyond that, that I nonetheless have enough faith in the future that I will </hi><hi>not<hi rend="italics"> </hi>lightly</hi><hi rend="italics"> give up regaining </hi><hi>even</hi><hi rend="italics"> old relationships, even better than before</hi>’. This has been my answer to T. And is also what I tell you — I believe that it’s possible — to get on <hi rend="italics">better</hi> terms than the present ones — with you, too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">But — speaking bluntly — I think that you’ve been too neutral towards me the last <hi rend="italics">1 </hi> <hi rend="italics">1/2</hi> or two years, and I wish above all for more <hi rend="italics">warmth</hi>, and the friendship was too cool and not animated enough for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Find this pedantic of me <hi rend="italics">if you will</hi> — yet it isn’t <hi rend="italics">pedantic</hi> but it’s for sound practical reasons that I pointed this out to you before and point it out again.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">Margot Begemann</rs> is coming back to Nuenen one of these days<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — I’ve always remained good friends with her, and it’s on my advice that she did <hi rend="italics">not</hi> give in to her sisters, who let it be seen that they’d rather she stayed away and who keep telling her that in their view she has made a hash of things. On the contrary, her family has obligations towards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">her</rs>, and in the past she put her own money into the business when her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_268">brother</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> went bankrupt.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">The issue here is that if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">she</rs> and I choose to love each other, be attached to each other — indeed have been for a long time — this is no <hi rend="italics">wrongdoing</hi> on our part nor something for which people may blame us. Either her or me. And in my view it’s absurd that people felt they should get worked up about it — and then — in <hi rend="italics">their</hi> opinion — in my interest or in hers. That was a bad turn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Anyone may do this with the best intentions — yet — — — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_268">Louis Begemann</rs> — he had his objections, too, but <hi rend="italics">was</hi> such and <hi rend="italics">remained</hi> such that both <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">she</rs> and I could talk to him, 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> and it was precisely because he was humane and calm that it didn’t turn out <hi rend="italics">much worse</hi>, and when that happened with her, which only I knew about, he could <hi rend="italics">help</hi> and all the others <hi rend="italics">only hindered</hi>. And we were in complete agreement about the steps to be taken then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Three days <hi rend="italics">before</hi>, after all, I had already warned <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_268">him</rs> and said, I’m concerned about your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">sister</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Most certainly, at some time <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">she</rs></hi> has done greater or lesser good turns for pretty well <hi rend="italics">all</hi> the people here in the neighbourhood, either in sickness or when they were in some trouble or other. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">she</rs> and I actually became attached during <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s illness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">She</rs> has just written to me: should there be any people sick in Nuenen, do go and visit them and see if anything can be done to help. Well, there are a thousand things of that nature in her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">And to put it very <hi rend="italics">mildly</hi>, one can say that there has been a most deplorable misunderstanding here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I think that, with hindsight, you <hi rend="italics">would now no longer speak as you did on that evening</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">That concerned <hi rend="italics">me</hi> alone — and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could take it, so there’s no question of my reproaching you in this matter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Only as an <hi rend="italics">explanation</hi> for you, I say, <hi rend="italics">just as you spoke to me, who can take it</hi>, so her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_270 bio.xml#_271 bio.xml#_272">sisters</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> spoke <hi rend="italics">to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">her</rs></hi>, who was made distraught by it. You have <hi rend="italics">nothing to do with it</hi>, because you spoke to <hi rend="italics">me</hi>, who can take it, and you did <hi rend="italics">not</hi> speak to <hi rend="italics">her</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">But the <hi rend="italics">real fault</hi> lies with her sisters, or rather <hi rend="italics">one of the sisters</hi> in particular, who proves to be very hard, since she’s actually still <hi rend="italics">sulking</hi> and bearing a grudge.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">You — would <hi rend="italics">have to tell me again yourself</hi> that you bear a grudge — before I would suspect you of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">So much on my part to you.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh refers to his father’s discussions in Helvoirt about his call to go and serve there. We know in any event that these took place some days after 11 November 1884, since on the evening of Tuesday, 11 November 1884 Mr van Gogh told Theo that he was thinking of going to Helvoirt in the next few days to talk about his possible appointment (FR b2261). In view of the distribution of the other three letters that Vincent wrote to Theo in November (<ref target="let470.xml">470</ref>, <ref target="let471.xml">471</ref> and <ref target="let472.xml">472</ref>), and in view of the cold snap that set in on 12-13 November – Van Gogh says that ‘it’s freezing quite hard’ <ref target="#l-16">(ll. 16-17)</ref> – we have dated the present letter on or about Friday, 14 November 1884 (<hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi>). See also under <hi rend="italics">Date</hi> in the notes to the following letters this month.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter is unsigned, so it may be incomplete.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Efforts to resume contacts with Mauve and Tersteeg <ref target="let468.xml">(468)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Margot Begemann is in Utrecht <ref target="let456.xml">(456)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This call had already been alluded to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let465.xml">letter 465</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Water mill at Gennep</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2490">F 125 / JH 525</rs>); the work measures 87 x 151 cm. The mill is about 8 km from Nuenen (now South of Eindhoven). Probably in exchange for tobacco, Van Gogh gave his sketch of the water mill to Jansje van den Broek, who ran a tobacconist’s near Jan Baijens’s paint shop, where Van Gogh bought his paint (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Telegraaf</hi>, 3 July 1969).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>These two heads of polder workers are not known; several male heads have survived, Hulsker dates them to late 1884, early 1885.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>These ‘3 people’ were the goldsmith <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Antoon Hermans</rs>, the tanner <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Anton Kerssemakers</rs> and the telegraph operator <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_816">Willem van de Wakker</rs>. On 11 November <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> told Theo: ‘Vincent is very hard at work and is being greatly encouraged by Gentlemen in Eindhoven’ (FR b2261).</p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> had already written to him on 27 October 1884: ‘Vincent ... also goes to Eindhoven often, still for that business for that Mr Hermans and then he has another acquaintance there who draws, but is actually a telegrapher; at bottom I think he’s still depressed though. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> is a quiet one but very hard-working ... I think Vincent would like to go out sometimes after Rappard’ (FR b2259).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo had been in Nuenen in August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let453.xml">letter 453</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The saying is ‘Il n’y a que le premier pas qui coûte’; it is attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_56">Marie de Vichy-Chamrond</rs>, Marquise du Deffand, who is supposed to have said it to Cardinal Polignac in 1763 (John Bartlett, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Familiar quotations</hi>. 10th ed. Boston 1919).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘aan hen’ (to them).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mrs van Gogh</rs> told Theo on 11 November: ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">Margot</rs>’s homecoming is approaching’ (FR b2262), but it was postponed. On 25 March 1885 she wrote: ‘Margot is coming home next week, may she be wise and may both of them find distraction in their work. She has been ill again and stretched her absence out as long as she could’ (FR b2268).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_268">Louis Begemann</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>During Theo’s visit there had been a serious clash about Vincent’s conduct: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let456.xml">see letters 456</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let458.xml">458</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_267">Margot</rs> had three <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_270 bio.xml#_271 bio.xml#_272">sisters</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let457.xml#n-2">see letter 457, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    