<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 17 November 1884. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let470"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b420 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>470</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>386</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>472</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-12-17">on or about Monday, 17 November 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0420 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0420 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000562_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0420 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000563_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000563_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0420 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000563_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000563_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">gisteren avond las ik uw laatste schrijven aan Pa en Moe<c type="kk">/</c> waarvan ik den toon goed en serieus vond<c type="kp">_</c>– Gisteren bragt ik juist ’t huis die studie van den watermolen te Gennep<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik met pleizier aan heb gewerkt<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – en die me te Eindhoven een nieuwe kennis<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> bezorgd heeft die met alle geweld wil leeren schilderen en bij wie ik een bezoek gebragt heb<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en we toen zamen op slag zijn begonnen<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodat hij s’avonds een stilleven er op had staan en ik de belofte van hem heb hij er een 30tal zal zien te maken dezen winter<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik telkens naar zal komen kijken en hem er mee helpen. ’t is een looier die tijd heeft en geld en circa 40 jaar<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> is<c type="kk">/</c> dus kan dit iets doenlijkers worden dan Hermans<c type="kk">/</c> die evenwel zijn ambitie wel degelijk behoudt en nog even hard werkt als den eersten dag<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. haast <hi rend="italics">al</hi> zijn tijd er aan geeft<c type="kp">_</c>– Deze nieuwe kerel heb ik idee spoedig kleur zal leeren zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb echter plan om gaandeweg de lui iets te laten betalen – maar niet in geld doch hun te zeggen <hi rend="italics">ge moet me tubes</hi> <hi rend="italics">verf geven</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Want ik wil veel schilderen – aanhoudend<c type="kk">/</c> en ik wil er doorkrijgen dat ik niet met <hi rend="italics">halve</hi> kracht meer hoef te werken – doch van s’morgens tot s’avonds schilderen kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ge moet niet denken dat ik zoo heel graag zou hebben de lui allen mijn werk en in ’t algemeen mijn doen en laten goed vonden<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> op dit moment bij voorbeeld ben ik haast meer in mijn schik dat Mauve en Tersteeg me afgewezen hebben dan als ’t andersom geweest ware<c type="kp">_</c>– Begrijp me wel! het is – omdat ik de kracht in me meen te voelen ondanks alles hun <hi rend="italics">toch</hi> te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zou ook als ik niet voelde dat ik een vast punt heb<c type="kk">/</c> doordat ik in de laatste jaren op het abc van teekenen en van schilderen heb geblokt<c type="kk">/</c> harder dan zij veronderstellen – ik zou<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> me niet tot hun gewend hebben op nieuw en een nieuwen strijd geentameerd indien ik niet een vaste meening had die te <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> winnen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De <hi rend="italics">zekerheid</hi> van te winnen heb ik evenwel geenszins maar de <hi rend="italics">kans</hi> durf ik op speculeeren en ga dus ook niet achteruit nu ik begonnen ben ’t publiek aan te klampen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">ik zal juist in de worsteling zelf sterker worden en door critiek<c type="kk">/</c> door onwil en tegenkanting zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> meer leeren dan door berusting<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het geen ik U echter schreef<c type="kk">/</c> daar moet ik bepaald<c type="kk">/</c> bepaald op aandringen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ik heb me een zeker aantal studies voor<c type="shy">-</c>gesteld die<c type="kk">/</c> hoe ik ’t ook bereken<c type="kk">/</c> ik geld voor te kort kom en die ik om geen reden ter wereld <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> uitstellen<c type="kp">_</c> Het nieuwejaar is in ’t verschiet<c type="kk">/</c> tegen dien tijd moet ik eenige dingen betalen en heb deze maand ook zelfs reeds afgedaan. Maar ik kom te kort zoodoende voor mijn werk en als ik niet een meevaller vind<c type="kk">/</c> verlies ik een maand werk – en in de gegevenen <hi rend="italics">mag</hi> dat niet<c type="kp">_</c> en tracht een uiterste poging te doen mij een extra frs 100 te bezorgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zal van mijn kant er op werken van de lui die ik les geef ook een bijdrage voor verf te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik hoop dat gij voelen zult dat juist wegens ik Mauve en T. heb aangeklampt en ze weigeren<c type="kk">/</c> ik – en dat binnen <hi rend="italics">heel</hi> kort – direct of indirect moet laten zien ik weer iets heb uitgevoerd – en dat alle energie nu geconcentreerd moet blijven en er <hi rend="italics">full</hi> speed moet worden gewerkt<c type="kk">/</c> al zou ’t iets duurder uitkomen<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat <hi rend="italics">zal</hi> terugkomen en wat ik zeide daar blijf ik bij<c type="kk">/</c> we moeten zien van nu af van het er ingestoken kapitaal een goede <hi rend="italics">rente</hi> althans te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Er <hi rend="italics">is</hi> sedert ge hier waart<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> een verandering in mijn kleur gekomen – waar ik toen reeds een voorgevoel van had<c type="kk">/</c> toen ge hier waart – en <hi rend="italics">gij zult zien dat met nog een aantal studies</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">die waarover ik U nu schrijf die</hi><ptr target="#note-t-a"/><hi rend="italics">in een paar maanden</hi> <hi rend="italics">af moeten</hi><c type="kk">/</c> mijn studies onweerlegbaar zullen bewijzen dat ik juist op ’t gebied van kleur iets weet<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik kan ’t niet helpen maar ik kom momenteel te kort – juist omdat ik meer geschilderd heb dan eigentlijk er af kon – en er <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> nu niet bezuinigd worden – want met nu ’t ijzer te smeden terwijl ’t heet is kunnen we belangrijke punten winnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik herinner me in mijn vorigen brief gezegd te hebben “dat ik Uw opinie niet meer telde”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ik bedoel dat zoo niet in ’t barre zooals ’t klinkt – ik bedoel alleen dat in sommige punten ik besloten ben door te zetten meer met hartstogt dan met voorzigtigheid omdat het zóó in mijn karakter ligt en ik mij toch niet t’huis kan voelen in het koelere rekenen. En toch <hi rend="italics">reken ik ook</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Hetgeen ik extra vraag<c type="kk">/</c> vraag ik ook niet in eens – doch ziehier hoe – Tracht omstreeks 20 Nov<c type="kp">_</c> f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 20 extra te sturen – 1 December ’t gewone<c type="kk">/</c> omstreeks 20 December weer f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 20 extra en in Januarij ’t zelfde<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Dan ben ik gedekt voor de einden dier maanden en hoef geen dagen te stoppen als ’t werk eischt ik geen moment verlieze<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Kan ’t iets meer zijn<c type="kk">/</c> tant mieux<c type="kk">/</c> doch tracht dat wat ik hierboven vroeg althans gebeure<c type="kp">_</c> En ik zal van mijn kant misschien nog wat van dien nieuwen kennis kunnen krijgen in den vorm van tubes verf<c type="kp">_</c>– Hermans is tot in ’t bespottelijke gierig of liever beestachtig egoist<c type="kk">/</c> niet alleen tegen mij doch met iedereen<c type="kk">/</c> overigens hij is iemand met wie ik toch goede vrienden voornemens ben te blijven – ter wille van dat hij bepaald curieus zijn best doet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">ik geloof niet dat ik mij vergis ten opzigte van Tersteeg en Mauve als ik durf zeggen er wel degelijk een kans is om hun te raken en over te halen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zij zijn over te halen door <hi rend="italics">de kleur</hi> en ik zie kans om<c type="kk">/</c> met me moeite te geven<c type="kk">/</c> overtuigend hun te wijzen ik begrip en gevoel van kleur heb. En dan – er worden meer en meer portretten gevraagd – en er zijn er zoo heel veel niet die dat kunnen en ik wil probeeren om een kop met karakter te leeren weergeven. Ik ben in den laatsten tijd er juist warm voor geworden omdat mijn begrip van kleur vaster wordt. Gij hoeft U niet <hi rend="italics">nu direkt</hi> in die kwestie met Tersteeg en Mauve te mengen – <hi rend="italics">spaar U</hi> <hi rend="italics">liever</hi><c type="kk">/</c> maar als ik b.v. in eind Januarij die 50 koppen die ik maken ga klaar heb<c type="kk">/</c> dan bij voorbeeld – kan ’t goed zijn <hi rend="italics">gij onverwachts</hi> hun eens een woordje zegt<c type="kp">_</c>– Hermans heeft après tout <hi rend="italics">bepaald me beloofd</hi> me vrij te houden voor een reisje doch met een <hi rend="italics">retour</hi> ergens naar toe<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="italics">Als</hi> ik eens naar Antwerpen wil <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ik hem aan zijn woord houden en van den winter zal ik wel zien een poging te doen om daar eenige relaties te krijgen – al lukt ook dat niet de <hi rend="italics">eerste</hi> keer<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het komt me voor dat het met Cor al bijzonder goed gaat – hij ziet er veel energieker uit en krijgt iets mannelijks<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c>– Zie ge tegen 20 Nov. me om ’t eind van deze maand te dekken f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 20 althans zendt<c type="kp">_</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">b. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vincent </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I read your last letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> yesterday evening; I thought the tone of it good and serious. Just yesterday I brought home the study of the water mill at Gennep, which I enjoyed working on<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — and which brought me a new <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">acquaintance</rs> in Eindhoven,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> who passionately wants to learn to paint and whom I paid a visit,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and then we immediately got down to work together. So that by the evening he had a still life down, and I had his promise that he’ll make 30 of them this winter, which I’ll come and look at and help him with each time. He’s a tanner who has time and money, and is about 40,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> so this can become something more feasible than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs>, who nonetheless is really sustaining his ambition and is still working just as hard as on the first day, in other words spends almost <hi rend="italics">all</hi> his time on it. I have an idea that this new fellow will soon learn to see colour.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I have a plan, though, to gradually get people to pay something — not in money, however, but by telling them <hi rend="italics">you must give me tubes of paint</hi>. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Because I want to paint a lot — continually, and I want to get to a position where I no longer have to work at <hi rend="italics">half</hi> speed — but can paint from morning till night.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You mustn’t think that I’m so very eager for people to approve of all my work and my doings in general.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> On the contrary, at this moment, for example, I’m almost more pleased that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> refused me than if it had been the opposite. You must understand me! It’s — because I think I can feel the power in me to bring them round <hi rend="italics">anyway</hi>, despite everything. I should not, even if I hadn’t felt that I have a fixed goal, because in the last few years I’ve slogged away at the abc of drawing and painting, harder than they imagine — I should not, I say, have turned to them again and engaged in a new battle if I hadn’t had a firm conviction that I <hi rend="italics">could</hi> win it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I have no <hi rend="italics">certainty</hi> whatsoever of winning it, though, but I dare to gamble on the <hi rend="italics">chance</hi>, and so I won’t retreat now that I’ve started to approach the public. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’ll become stronger in the very struggle itself, and learn more through criticism, through unwillingness and even resistance, than through resignation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">What I wrote to you, though, I must definitely, definitely insist upon.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I’ve resolved to make a certain number of studies for which, however I calculate it, I don’t have enough money and which I <hi rend="italics">may</hi> not postpone for any reason in the world. The New Year is in prospect, around that time I have to pay some things, and have actually already paid some this month. But this means that I haven’t enough for my work and, if I don’t have a stroke of luck, I’ll lose a month’s work — and that <hi rend="italics">may</hi> not happen in the circumstances. And try to make the utmost effort to let me have an extra 100 francs. For my part, I’ll see about getting a contribution for paint from the people I’m giving lessons to.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I hope that you’ll feel that precisely because I approached <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">T.</rs> and they refuse, directly or indirectly I must show — and that <hi rend="italics">very</hi> soon — that I’ve done something again — and that all energy now has to remain concentrated and work has to proceed at <hi rend="italics">full</hi> speed, even if it were to work out slightly dearer. That <hi rend="italics">will</hi> be returned and I stand by what I said, from now on we must see to it that we at least get good <hi rend="italics">interest</hi> on the capital invested in it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">There <hi rend="italics">has</hi> been a change in my colour since you were here<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — which I already had a presentiment about when you were here — and <hi rend="italics">you’ll see that with some more studies, those I’m writing to you about now should be finished in a few months</hi>, my studies will irrefutably prove that I really do know something about colour. I can’t help it, but I’m short at the moment — precisely because I’ve painted more than could actually be afforded — and there <hi rend="italics">can </hi>be no economizing now — because by striking now, while the iron’s hot, we can win important points. I recall having said in my last letter ‘that I didn’t value your opinion any more’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I don’t mean that as severely as it sounds — I just mean that I’ve decided to press on in some respects more with passion than with prudence, because this is in my character and I really can’t feel at home in cooler calculation. And yet <hi rend="italics">I calculate too</hi>. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The extra I’m asking for I’m not asking for all at once — but here’s how. Try to send 20 francs extra around 20 Nov. — 1 December the usual, around 20 December another 20 francs extra, and the same in January.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Then I’m covered for the ends of those months and won’t have to stop for days when the work demands that I don’t lose a moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">If it can be a little more, so much the better, but try to do at least what I asked above. And for my part I’ll perhaps also be able to get something from this new <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">acquaintance</rs> in the form of tubes of paint. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> is preposterously miserly or rather beastly selfish, not just to me but with everyone; all the same, he’s someone with whom I intend to remain good friends — because he’s quite remarkably doing his best.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I don’t think I’m mistaken about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> when I dare say that there really is a chance of getting at them and winning them over. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">They can be won over by <hi rend="italics">colour</hi> and I see a chance, by taking pains, to demonstrate to them convincingly that I understand and have a feeling for colour. And then — there’s more and more demand for portraits — and there aren’t so very many who can do that, and I want to try to learn to render a head with character. I’ve become particularly keen on this recently because my grasp of colour is becoming sounder. You don’t have to involve yourself in the question with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> <hi rend="italics">right now</hi> —<hi rend="italics"> don’t bother, rather</hi>, but if, say, I have the 50 heads I’m going to get ready by the end of January, then for instance — it might be good if <hi rend="italics">you</hi> were <hi rend="italics">unexpectedly</hi> just to say a word to them. After all, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> has <hi rend="italics">definitely promised me</hi> that he’ll pay for a trip for me somewhere, but with a <hi rend="italics">return</hi>. <hi rend="italics">If</hi> I should want to go to Antwerp, I <hi rend="italics">can</hi> hold him to his word, and in the winter I’ll see about making an attempt to get some contacts there — although that, too, won’t succeed the <hi rend="italics">first</hi> time.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">It seems to me that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> is doing extremely well — he looks much more energetic and is getting a manly air.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Regards. Try to send at least 20 francs by 20 Nov. to cover the end of this month. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes ‘Try to send 20 francs extra around 20 Nov.’ <ref target="#l-107">(l. 107)</ref>. For Theo to be able to accede to this request, the letter must have been written around Monday, 17 November 1884. As Vincent brought the painting of the mill in Gennep home ‘yesterday’ <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>, it is likely that some days have elapsed since he reported starting work on it in <ref target="let469.xml">letter 469</ref> of about 14 November. We have therefore dated the present letter on or about Monday, 17 November 1884.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">Van Gogh’s reference to ‘the study of the water mill’ implies that Theo would know what he was talking about: after all, he had already mentioned it in <ref target="let469.xml">letter 469</ref>. We have therefore placed the present letter after that one, even though he also talks here of his ‘last’ letter, by which he must nonetheless mean <ref target="let468.xml">letter 468</ref> (cf. <ref target="#n-6">n. 6</ref> below). The three letters were written and sent in quick succession, which could explain the error.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh paints with acquaintances in Eindhoven <ref target="let469.xml">(469)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Efforts to resume contacts with Mauve and Tersteeg <ref target="let468.xml">(468)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Water mill at Gennep</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2490">F 125 / JH 525</rs>). See also under <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This new acquaintance was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Anton Kerssemakers</rs>, who made a gouache of the same mill.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs> lived at number 283 Kloosterdijk (district B), opposite the then station and outbuildings (De Brouwer 1984, p. 56, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs> was 38.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>That <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> had his reservations emerges from a confidential letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> to Theo: ‘Vincent goes to Eindhoven a lot. He made 6 paintings for Mr Hermans, who is copying them. He only paid the expenses of the ingredients used. He is an art lover. But he still finds a great deal to criticize and comment on, including Vincent’s views. But you mustn’t write this. It troubles this Gentleman that he just comes out with it and says he has broken with religion’ (FR b2258, Monday, 27 October 1884).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>A reference to <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let468.xml">letter 468</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Theo had been in Nuenen in August (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let453.xml">letter 453</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Dat die’ (that they).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let468.xml#l-11">letter 468, l. 11</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh did not actually go to museums in Antwerp with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs> until around the middle of August 1885 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let527.xml">see letter 527</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This remark about their brother <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> refers to the decision, which Vincent had previously mentioned, not to send him to the high school (HBS) for another two years but to have him taught a trade instead: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let443.xml">see letter 443</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    