<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 24 November 1884. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let471"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b423 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>471</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>387</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>473</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-12-24">on or about Monday, 24 November 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0423" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000566_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000566_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0423" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000566_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000566_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000566_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">ge weet zeker reeds dat Pa bedankt heeft voor Helvoirt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ze hebben Pa hier een cadeau van ongeveer f<c type="kp">_</c> 200.- gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> dat is wel aardig en ben ik blij om voor hen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">De decisie was mij niet onverschillig – daar in geen geval ik mede naar H. zou zijn gegaan<c type="kk">/</c> en of hier in mijn atelier zou zijn gebleven – of naar Antwerpen zou zijn vertrokken<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu – voor zoover ik zien kan<c type="kk">/</c> is en blijft het ’t beste voor mij eenvoudig door te gaan zoo als het is – en hier te blijven<c type="kp">_</c> Het gaat me waarachtig in den laatsten tijd niet zoo slecht. Het is waar dat ik van mijn werk hier niets maken kan in ’t finantieele – doch ik krijg werkelijk goede vrienden hier – en die ik geloof nog beter zullen worden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik heb verleden week dag in dag uit stillevens geschilderd<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> bij de lui die schilderen te Eindhoven<c type="kp">_</c> Die nieuwe kennis – den looier – waar ik U van verteld heb<c type="kk">/</c> doet buitengewoon zijn best<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar ik van mijn kant moet er ook wel iets voor doen om het goed met hun te houden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Maar ik kan niet inzien ik er bij verlies daar ik pleizieriger werk door dat ik wat conversatie heb<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Hermans heeft zóó veel mooie voorwerpen – als oude kruikjes en andere antiquiteiten –</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">dat ik U eens vragen wil of ik U pleizier zou kunnen doen met voor Uw kamer een stilleven van eenige van die voorwerpen – b.v. gothieke zaken<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – te schilderen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Die welke ik tot heden met Hermans maak zijn meer eenvoudig<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch hij heeft me juist heden gezegd dat als ik voor me zelf eens een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> wil maken van dingen die voor hem nog te moeielijk zijn om als studie te doen<c type="kk">/</c> ik de voorwerpen naar ’t atelier kan medenemen<c type="kp">_</c>– Antwoord me s.v.p<c type="kp">_</c> hier eens op – en als gij dat wilt dan zal ik het voor U maken en zal ik echte dingen uitzoeken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb een kleintje<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> klaar reeds overigens. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wat nu betreft wat ik U gevraagd heb om zoo mogelijk het eind van deze maand te dekken door me er frs 20 bij te sturen<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou gij dat doen kondt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het wordt beter voor mij – maar mijn onkosten worden er niet minder op – doch juist door nu zeer hard door te werken schieten we bepaald op<c type="kp">_</c>– Help me dus met wat ik gevraagd 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>heb als ’t U eenigermate doenlijk is<c type="kp">_</c> Want anders wordt het dezer dagen zeer lastig en lijdt het werk meer dan ergens toe dient<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En ik zal het U in mijn werk terug geven. Meer woorden kan ik er ook niet over zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik zal in alle geval die voorwerpen van Hermans vragen – en U er iets van maken – ge zult zelf zien wat ik U zeide van de kleur<c type="kk">/</c> dat die beter wordt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik heb ook weer een aquarel onder handen van den watermolen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Cor is niet wel geweest een paar dagen<c type="kk">/</c> en ’t huis<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – maar hij is weer beter.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik <hi rend="italics">weet</hi> dat het voor U een moeielijken tijd is – maar we <hi rend="italics">moeten</hi> vooruit en het zal wel een beetje ten goede veranderen – dat zult ge zien<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I suppose you already know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> has turned down Helvoirt.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The people here gave <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> a present of about 200 guilders, that’s most kind and I’m pleased for them.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">The decision wasn’t a matter of indifference to me — since I wouldn’t have gone with them to H. in any case, and would either have stayed here in my studio — or would have left for Antwerp. Now — as far as I can see, the best thing for me is simply to carry on as things are — and stay here. It has truly not been going too badly for me lately. It’s true that I can’t make anything financially from my work here — but I’m making really good friends here — and I believe they’ll become even better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Last week I painted still lifes day in and day out<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> with the people who are painting in Eindhoven. The new acquaintance — the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">tanner</rs> — whom I told you about, is really doing his best.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But for my part, I also have to do something to keep on good terms with them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But I can’t see that I lose by it, since I work more enjoyably because I have some conversation. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> has so many beautiful objects — like old jars and other antiques — that I wanted to ask you whether I could oblige you by painting a still life for your room of some of these objects — Gothic things, for instance.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The ones I’ve been making with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> so far are simpler. But just today he said to me that if I ever want to make a painting for myself of things that are still too difficult for him to do as a study, I can take the objects with me to the studio. Please let me have an answer to this — and if you would like it, I’ll make it for you and shall select really nice things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">By the way, I’ve already finished a small one.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Now, as to what I asked you about covering the end of this month if possible by sending me 20 francs extra, I wish you could do that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It’s getting better for me — although my expenses aren’t getting any smaller — but we’re definitely making progress just by working very hard now. So help me with what I asked 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> if it’s at all feasible for you. Because otherwise it will soon become very difficult, and the work will suffer more than necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And I’ll give it back to you with my work. That’s all I can say about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">At all events I’ll ask <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs> for those objects — and make something for you with them — you’ll see for yourself what I told you about the colour, that it’s getting better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m also working on a watercolour of the water mill.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> was unwell for a few days, and at home<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — but he’s better now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I <hi rend="italics">know</hi> that it’s a difficult time for you — but we <hi rend="italics">must</hi> progress and it will change a little for the good — you’ll see.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes ‘Last week I painted still lifes day in and day out with the people who are painting in Eindhoven’ <ref target="#l-19">(ll. 19-20)</ref>. He mentioned the plan to go and paint still lifes with Kerssemakers in <ref target="let470.xml">letter 470</ref>, which was written on or about Monday, 17 November. Assuming that the still lifes painted ‘last week’ were done in the week of 17 to 22 November, it would mean that the present letter dates from the week of Sunday, 23 to Saturday, 29 November 1884. Van Gogh moreover repeats the request he made in <ref target="let470.xml">letter 470</ref>, that is for an extra 20 francs to cover ‘the end of this month if possible’ <ref target="#l-48">(l. 48)</ref>. This remark implies that the letter must have been written at least a few days before the end of the month, otherwise Theo would not have had time to accede to the request. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Monday, 24 November 1884.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh paints with acquaintances in Eindhoven <ref target="let469.xml">(469)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had received a call to serve in Helvoirt (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let469.xml">see letter 469</ref>). He wrote to Theo: ‘We did write to you about the gift that the congregation gave me when I turned down Helvoirt; 210 guilders in a wallet so I can choose for myself?’ (FR b2263, 9 December 1884).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>There are nine known still lifes dating from the period November 1884-April 1885. Cf. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 78-83, cat. no. 9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>By ‘Gothic things’ Van Gogh must be referring to old-fashioned, typical artefacts and objects, possibly in the gothic style; later in the letter he talks of ‘really nice things’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-45">(l. 45)</ref>. A number of items from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_449">Hermans</rs>’s collection are listed in cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 81, n. 12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The nine smaller still lifes from this period all measure about 30 x 40 cm, which makes it difficult to determine which one Van Gogh meant. In view of the ‘antiquities’ depicted in them and the stylistic similarities, Vellekoop links this point in the text with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_442">F 52 / JH 535</rs>; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_959">F 58 / JH 531</rs>; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_960">F 64 / JH 537</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_961">F 178r / JH 528</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 81-82, and n. 12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Water mill at Gennep</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2489">F 1144a / JH 523</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Their brother <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> had been apprenticed to Egbert Haverkamp Begemann’s machine works in Helmond; he was also boarding there: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let443.xml#n-3">see letter 443, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    