<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 23 January 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let479"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b430 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>479</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>392</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>482</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-01-23">on or about Friday, 23 January 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0430" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000575_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000575_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0430" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000575_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000575_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000575_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Hierbij nog eenige krabbels van koppenstudies<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Van t’huis hoorde ik ge een goed jaar hadt gehad – en een aanbieding van frs 1000 per maand – die ge geweigerd hadt.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Ik kan me begrijpen dat bij G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> eenmaal zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> ge er blijft – ’t is een van de eerste groote huizen geweest – welnu – ’t zou ook nog welligt verscheiden concurrenten kunnen overleven<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Echter ik blijf ’t er voor houden dat het met ’t jaar moeielijker zal worden de routine die den schilderijhandel tot heden volhoudt<c type="kk">/</c> door te voeren<c type="kk">/</c> en een nieuwe taktiek van zaken doen nu te vinden<c type="kp">_</c> zal ’t gebeuren? misschien wel niet. En toch – tenzij er een nieuwe taktiek komt – dreigt dan niet met den dag meer ’t gevaar dat door den val van ’t een of ander groot huis b.v. sommige dingen dalen en die daling een paniek in alles ten gevolge hebbe<c type="kp">_</c>– Werkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> dat gevaar is geloof ik niet precies maar ingebeeld<c type="kp">_</c>– Betrekkelijk in zeer korten tijd zijn de prijzen tot de tegenwoordige hoogte gestegen – in laat ons zeggen een jaar of 40 hoogstens<c type="kp">_</c> En zou er meer tijd dan dat noodig zijn om den berg weer af te rollen? in den regel gaat het anders makkelijker &amp; sneller berg af dan berg op<c type="kp">_</c>– En toch – er is iets in de kunst dat maakt dat er altijd wel – een kans althans tot uitbreiding van ’t publiek dat koopt<c type="kk">/</c> mogelijk is<c type="kp">_</c>– Alleen nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> zal men dat nieuwe publiek créeeren<c type="kp">_</c>– indien niet dan vrees ik voor mij dat ’t even snel dalen zal als ’t gerezen is<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Haast geen jaar begon ik dat een somberder aspect had<c type="kk">/</c> in een somberder stemming<c type="kk">/</c> en ik verwacht dan ook geen toekomst van succes doch – een toekomst van strijd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het is buiten triest – de velden een marmer van klonten zwarte aard en wat sneeuw<c type="kk">/</c> meestendeels enkele dagen daar tusschen van mist en slijk – de roode zon s’avonds en s’morgens – kraaien<c type="kk">/</c> verdord gras en verlept rottend groen, zwarte boschjes<c type="kk">/</c> en de takken van de populieren en de wilgen nijdig als ijzerdraad tegen de trieste lucht<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dit<c type="kk">/</c> ik zie ’t in ’t voorbij gaan en ’t is alleen in harmonie met de binnenhuizen<c type="kk">/</c> erg somber in deze donkere winterdagen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het is ook in harmonie met de physionomies van boeren en wevers<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">de laatsten hoor ik niet klagen maar ze hebben ’t bar<c type="kp">_</c>– Een wever die hard doorwerkt maakt een stuk van 60 el b.v. in de week<c type="kp">_</c> Terwijl hij weeft moet een vrouw voor hem zitten spoelen<c type="kk">/</c> dat is de klossen garen winden – dus zijn er <hi rend="italics">twee</hi> die werken en er van leven moeten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Op dat stuk wint hij netto b.v. f<c type="kp">_</c> 4.50 in die week<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – en als hij ’t naar den fabrikant brengt krijgt hij menigmaal tegenwoordig de boodschap dat hij pas over 8 of 14 dagen een nieuw stuk kan mee nemen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dus loon laag niet alleen<c type="kk">/</c> maar werk vrij schaarsch<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Er is dan ook dikwijls iets gejaagds en onrustigs in de lui<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">’t is een andere stemming dan die van de charbonniers die ik bijwoonde in een jaar van grèves en veel ongelukken<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Dat was nog wel erger – maar toch<c type="kk">/</c> het is hier nu ook dikwijls navrant – de lui zijn stil en letterlijk <hi rend="italics">nergens</hi> hoorde ik iets wat naar oproerige redenaties geleek<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Maar ze kijken evenmin vrolijk als de vigelante paarden<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> of de schapen die per stoomboot naar Engeland worden getransporteerd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Gegroet – ik hoop dat ge zult kunnen sturen<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb niet heelemaal een gulden meer en moet vandaag nog eenige uren model hebben<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Dus morgen zit ik weer vast<c type="kk">/</c> doch welligt komt uw brief<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Herewith a few more scratches of studies of heads.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I heard at home that you’d had a good year — and an offer of 1,000 francs a month — which you had refused.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I can understand that once with G&amp;Cie, you’ll stay there — it was one of the first large houses — well then — it should still probably be able to outlive various competitors.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">However, I continue to maintain that it will become more difficult by the year to go on with the routine that the art trade has sustained so far, and to find a new tactic for doing business now. Will it happen? Perhaps not. And yet — unless there’s a new tactic — doesn’t the danger become more threatening by the day that, as a result of the collapse of one or other of the large houses, for instance, some things will drop and this drop will result in a panic all round? I really believe this danger isn’t just imaginary. Prices have risen to their present heights in a very short time, relatively speaking — in, let’s say, 40 years or so at most. And would it need more time than that to roll down the mountain again? As a rule, it’s easier and quicker to go downhill than uphill. And yet — there’s something in art which means that it’s always possible — there’s at least a chance to increase the numbers of the buying public. But again, will people create that new public? If not, I fear for my part that it will fall as quickly as it rose. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve hardly ever begun a year that had a gloomier aspect in a gloomier mood, and so I don’t expect a future of success, but — a future of struggle.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">It’s dismal outdoors — the fields a marble of clods of black earth and some snow, usually a few days of fog and mud in between — the red sun in the evening and in the morning — crows, shrivelled grass and withered, rotting vegetation, black bushes, and the branches of the poplars and willows vicious as wire against the dismal sky.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">This, I see it in passing, and it’s quite in harmony with the interiors, very gloomy in these dark winter days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">It’s also in harmony with the physiognomies of peasants and weavers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I don’t hear the latter complain, but they have a hard time of it. A weaver who works hard makes a piece of 60 ells, say, in a week. While he weaves, a woman has to spool for him; that is winding yarn on to the bobbins — so there are <hi rend="italics">two</hi> who are working and have to live on it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">On that piece he makes a net profit of, say, 4.50 guilders in that week<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — and nowadays when he takes it to the manufacturer he’s often told that he can only bring a new piece in a week or a fortnight’s time. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So not only wages low, but work fairly scarce.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">There’s consequently often something harried and restless in these people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It’s a different mood from that of the miners I lived with in a year of strikes and many accidents.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> That was even worse — but all the same, it’s often heart-rending here too — the people are quiet, and literally <hi rend="italics">nowhere</hi> have I heard anything resembling inflammatory arguments.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But they look as little cheerful as the cab-horses or the sheep that are transported by steamer to England.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Regards — I hope you’ll be able to send; I have less than a guilder left and must have a model for several more hours today.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">So tomorrow I’ll be stuck again, but possibly your letter will come.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh writes: ‘I’ve hardly ever begun a year that had a gloomier aspect’ <ref target="#l-32">(ll. 32-33)</ref>. This places the letter in January 1885. Vincent hopes that Theo will send some money soon – ‘possibly your letter will come’ <ref target="#l-76">(ll. 76-77)</ref>, because he has almost nothing left. The money he was looking out for must have been the extra allowance for January. In this letter he appears to be responding to information that Theo told his parents in a letter of 20 January (<ref target="#n-2">see n. 2</ref>). Since Mr van Gogh did not yet know on 21 January whether Theo had had a good year financially (FR 2265), whereas Vincent can now tell his brother: ‘I heard at home that you’d had a good year’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, Theo’s letter was probably received on the 22nd. On these grounds, and because the next letter must have been written on or about Monday, 26 January (<ref target="let480.xml">letter 480</ref>), we have dated the present letter on or about Friday, 23 January 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See for the scratches that may have been sent: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let475.xml#n-1">letter 475, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>One of Theo’s clients must have offered him a job at 1000 francs a month. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo about this on 24 January 1885 – in reply to Theo’s letter of 20 January – and warned him to be cautious: ‘You write again about the Gentleman who had made you an offer to go to work for him. But you had turned down that proposal.. but now you return to this, and call him your client? Someone who works in electricity and could become …. one of the richest people. And who still seems to want to take you into his office. You also say that you are involved in spite of yourself but don’t know yet whether he will be successful. I wanted to come back to this again. Although my opinion is biased and I know no more of his plans than your letter reveals, I still want to advise you to be careful. Should you perhaps consult <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Cent</rs>? He is a man who has a clear view of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">business </hi>and also courage enough to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">take a risk</hi> ... Does the Gentleman also need things for his company that belong to your present firm?’ There is a postscript in the margin: ‘We will not talk to Vincent about this business of yours. Do as you wish about that’ (FR b2266). Theo’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> had obviously not stuck to this intention.</p>

<p rend="indent">The annual profits payment was worked out after the inventory was compiled in January of the following year, and then paid out by the head office. For 1884 Theo was entitled to an annual share of the profits worth 6,943.65 francs; in total he had earned an average of 912 francs a month in 1884 (FR b2123). See also Account book 2002, pp. 15-16.</p>

<p rend="indent">We do not know who is meant by ‘Someone who works in electricity’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For a comparison of the size of wages in the second half of the nineteenth century: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Introduction</hi>, III.3.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Strikes had broken out in April 1879 after a mining accident in the Borinage, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let151.xml#n-3">see letter 151, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Paarden die voor een (huur)rijtuig worden ingespannen. (Horses harnessed to a (hackney) carriage.)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    