<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 26 January 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let480"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b431 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>480</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>393</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>483</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-01-26">on or about Monday, 26 January 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0431" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0431" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000576_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Ge zoudt mij een zeer groot genoegen doen met nog voor me te zien te krijgen</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Illustration N<hi rend="super">o</hi> <hi rend="italics">2174</hi></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">24 Octobre 1884.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">’t Is reeds een oud N<hi rend="super">o</hi> doch aan ’t bureau zal men ’t nog wel geven. Er staat in een teekening van Paul Renouard – een grève van wevers te Lyon<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ook een uit eene serie over de Opera – waarvan hij ook etsen heeft uitgegeven<c type="kk">/</c> naar er staat – <hi rend="italics">le Harpiste</hi><c type="kk">/</c> die ik erg mooi vind<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dan heeft hij nu ook nog pas gemaakt <hi rend="italics">le monde judiciaire</hi><c type="kk">/</c> die ik van Rappard kreeg – ge kent die waarschijnlijk uit de Paris illustré van Dumas.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Maar de teekening van de wevers vind ik ’t mooist van allen en er is zooveel corps en volheid in dat me dunkt die teekening zich goed zou houden bij Millet<c type="kk">/</c> bij Daumier<c type="kk">/</c> bij Lepage<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Als ik denk hoe hij tot die hoogte is gekomen<c type="kk">/</c> door van ’t begin af naar de natuur te werken zonder andere lui te volgen<c type="kk">/</c> en hoe toch hij in harmonie is met de heele knappe lui<c type="kk">/</c> ook wat techniek betreft<c type="kk">/</c> al heeft hij van ’t begin af zijn eigen manier van doen gehad<c type="kk">/</c> dan vind ik hem alweer een bewijs van dat als men maar doorgaat met zich aan de natuur te houden<c type="kk">/</c> het met ’t jaar beter wordt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Waar met den dag meer ik van overtuigd wordt<c type="kk">/</c> is dat die lui er <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> komen die van het worstelen met de natuur geen hoofdzaak maken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik vind dat men als men de meesters met aandacht heeft getracht na te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> men hen allen terugvindt<c type="kk">/</c> op zekere momenten<c type="kk">/</c> diep in de werkelijkheid<c type="kp">_</c> Ik bedoel – wat men noemt hunne <hi rend="italics">scheppingen</hi> – zal men ook zien in de werkelijkheid naarmate men – soortgelijke oogen – soortgelijk sentiment – heeft – als zij<c type="kp">_</c>– En ik geloof dan ook dit – indien de critici of kenners meer met de natuur vertrouwd waren<c type="kk">/</c> hun oordeel zou beter wezen dan nu ’t de routine is slechts in schilderijen te leven en die onderling te vergelijken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat natuurlijk als zijnde één kant van de kwestie in zijn verband <hi rend="italics">goed</hi> is<c type="kk">/</c> doch solide basis mist als men de natuur gaat vergeten en niet diep doorkijkt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Kunt gij niet begrijpen dat ik hierin misschien geen ongelijk heb – en om nog duidelijker te zeggen hoe ik het meen<c type="kk">/</c> is het niet jammer dat gij b.v. zelden – of haast nooit meer – komt in die binnenhuizen of omgaat met die menschen<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>of die stemmingen in ’t landschap ziet die in de schilderijen welke ge ’t mooist vindt worden geschilderd. Ik zeg niet dat in uw werkkring ge dit <hi rend="italics">kunt</hi> doen – juist omdat men veel en lang moet kijken op die natuur eer men tot de overtuiging komt dat wat de groote meesters voor meest aangrijpend hebben geschilderd toch zijn grond in ’t leven en de werkelijkheid zelf heeft. Een basis van solide poezij die eeuwig als daadzaak bestaat en gevonden kan worden als men diep genoeg graaft en zoekt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ce qui ne passe pas dans ce qui passe<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> dat bestaat.– En wat Michel Ange in een almagtig mooie beeldspraak zeide<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> dat vind ik Millet gezegd heeft zonder beeldspraak – en door Millet kan men ’t best leeren kijken misschien en “een geloof” krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Als ik later <hi rend="italics">mooier</hi> werk maak zal ik toch niet <hi rend="italics">anders</hi> werken dan nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik bedoel het zal den zelfden appel zijn doch rijper – ik zal zelf niet omdraaien in wat ik van ’t begin af heb gedacht<c type="kp">_</c>– En dit is de reden waarom ik van mijn kant zeg<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik nu niet deug<c type="kk">/</c> deug ik later ook niet – maar indien later dan ook nu. Want koren is koren al lijkt het voor stedelingen op gras in ’t begin – en ook omgekeerd.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">In elk geval – of de lui goed of niet goed vinden wat en hoe ik doe<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij weet geen anderen weg dan zoolang worstelen met de natuur tot zij haar geheim zegt.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik ben steeds werkende aan diverse koppen en – handen – ik heb er ook weer een aantal geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> misschien zoudt ge er wat in vinden – misschien ook niet – wat kan ik er aan doen<c type="kp">_</c>– Nog eens – ik weet geen anderen weg.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Maar ik kan me van U dat niet begrijpen<c type="kk">/</c> dat gij zegt – <hi rend="italics">misschien vinden we later</hi> <hi rend="italics">moois ook in de dingen van nu</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als ik U was zou ik zooveel zelfvertrouwen en zelfstandige opinie er op na houden dat ik wist of ik <hi>nu</hi> kon zien wat er in een ding was al dan niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Enfin – weet<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> dat soort van dingen voor U zelf<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">De maand is nog wel niet geheel om maar mijn beurs is wel geheel leeg – ik werk door zoo hard ik kan<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en ik geloof voor me zelf dat juist door aanhoudend ’t model te bestudeeren ik mijn roer wel regt zal houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik wou ’t U mogelijk was eenige dagen vóór den eersten reeds te zenden – om die zelfde reden dat de einden der maanden me altijd zwaar zijn<c type="kk">/</c> waar<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> ’t werk me veel kost en ik er niets van verkoop. Dit zal echter niet altijd zoo duren want ik werk te hard &amp; te veel dan dat ik althans ’t niet zoo ver brengen zal ik er mijn kosten uithale zonder in afhankelijke positie te zijn. En voor de rest<c type="kk">/</c> de natuur buiten en de binnenhuizen<c type="kk">/</c> ze zijn prachtig van stemming hier tegenwoordig<c type="kk">/</c> ik doe mijn best den tijd niet te verliezen. Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">You would do me a very great favour if you could manage to get hold of</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">L’Illustration No. <hi rend="italics">2174</hi></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">24 October 1884</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">for me. It’s already an old No, but they’ll still give it out at the office. There’s a drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Paul Renouard</rs> in it — a weavers’ strike in Lyon.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Also one from a series about the Opera — of which he’s also published etchings, it says — <hi rend="italics">The Harpist</hi>, which I think very good.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And then he’s also just made <hi rend="italics">The legal world</hi>, which I got from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> — you probably know it from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_585">Dumas</rs>’s Paris Illustré.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But I find the drawing of the weavers the finest of them all, and there’s so much body and breadth in it that it seems to me this drawing could well hold its own beside <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, beside <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, beside <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_124">Lepage</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">When I think how he reached this height, by working from nature from the start without imitating other people, and how he’s still in harmony with the very clever people, as far as technique is concerned too, although he had his own way of doing things from the start, then I find him another proof that if one just persists in sticking to nature, it gets better every year.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">What I’m more persuaded of every day is that those people who don’t make wrestling with nature the main consideration do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> get there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I think that if one has tried to follow the masters attentively, one encounters them all at certain moments, deep in reality. I mean — what are called their <hi rend="italics">creations</hi> — one will also see in reality to the extent that one — has — similar eyes — similar sentiment — to them. And so I also believe this — if the critics or connoisseurs were more familiar with nature, their judgement would be better than now, when it’s the routine to live only among paintings and to compare them with one another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Which, of course, is <hi rend="italics">right</hi> in its context as one side of the question, but lacks a solid basis if one forgets nature and doesn’t look deeply into it. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Can’t you understand that I may not be wrong in this — and to say even more clearly what I mean by it, isn’t it a pity, for instance, that you seldom — or hardly ever now — go into those interiors, or associate with those people, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> or see those moods in the landscape that are painted in the paintings you find most beautiful? I don’t say that you <hi rend="italics">can</hi> do this in your position — just because one has to look long and hard at nature before one arrives at the conviction that what the great masters painted most movingly still has its foundation in life and in reality itself. A basis of solid poetry that exists eternally as a fact, and can be found if one digs and searches deep enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">What does not pass in what passes,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> that exists. And what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs> said in an almighty beautiful metaphor,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I think that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> said without a metaphor — and one can perhaps best learn to see through Millet, and get ‘a faith’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">If I make <hi rend="italics">better</hi> work later, I still won’t work <hi rend="italics">otherwise</hi> than now; I mean it will be the same apple only riper — I myself won’t turn from what I’ve thought from the start. And this is why I say for my part, if I’m no good now, I won’t be any good later either — but if later, then now too. For wheat is wheat, even if it looks like grass at first to townsfolk — and the other way round too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">In any event — whether people like or don’t like what I do and how I do it, for my part I know no other way but to wrestle with nature until such time as she reveals her secret.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’m still working on various heads and — hands — I’ve also drawn some more, perhaps you’ll see something in them — then again, perhaps not — what can I do about it? Again — I know no other way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">But I can’t understand you when you say — <hi rend="italics">perhaps we’ll also find something good later in the things you’re doing now</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">If I were you, I would have enough self-confidence and independent opinion to know whether or not I could see <hi>now</hi> what there was in a thing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">In short — decide that sort of thing for yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">The month isn’t yet wholly over but my purse is wholly empty — I keep working as hard as I can,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and I believe for my part that I’ll stay on course just by constantly studying the model.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I wish it were possible for you to send a few days <hi rend="italics">before</hi> the first — for the same reason that the ends of the months are always difficult for me, because the work costs me a lot and I don’t sell any of it. This won’t go on for ever, though, because I work too hard and too much not to get at least to the point where I can cover my expenses without being in a dependent position. And for the rest, the mood of nature outdoors and the interiors here is magnificent at present; I’m doing my best not to waste time. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says he is working on hands and heads, which places the letter at the end of January 1885. The letter follows <ref target="let479.xml">letter 479</ref>, when Van Gogh still had a little money – now he has nothing at all <ref target="#l-91">(l. 91)</ref>. He also writes: ‘I wish it were possible for you to send a few days before the first’ <ref target="#l-95">(ll. 95-96)</ref>. If this request were to have any effect it must have been written some days before the end of the month; we have therefore dated the letter on or about Monday, 26 January 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh is mistaken in the date of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> by one day: no. 2174 of volume 42 came out on Saturday, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">25</hi> October 1884. It contains <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Paul Renouard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La crise industrielle à Lyon – Sans travail</hi> (The industrial crisis in Lyon – Out of work) (p. 268), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1513">Clément Edouard Bellenger</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_399">Ill. 399</rs>. Theo sent this issue in February; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let483.xml">see letter 483</ref>. Van Gogh noted the details of this issue of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> in one of his sketchbooks. See Van der Wolk 1987, pp. 54, 287-288.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1262">Paul Renouard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’harpiste</hi> (The harpist), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1762">Henri Dochy</rs>, was on p. 273 in the same issue. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_389">Ill. 389</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for the theme issue of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le monde judicaire </hi>(The legal world) of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Paris Illustré</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let475.xml#n-3">letter 475, n. 3.</ref> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_585">F.-G. Dumas</rs> was ‘directeur artistique’ of the magazine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>This quotation is taken from the introduction to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_237">La mascarade humaine</ref></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let294.xml#n-7">see letter 294, n.7</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>It is not clear what metaphor Van Gogh is referring to here. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs> suggested the idea that sculptures transcend time in a series of three madrigals and a sonnet: ‘Here art would have lived on / In just a living stone’. See Gilbert Creighton, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Complete poems and selected letters of Michelangelo</hi>. Princeton, New Jersey 1980, pp. 133 (sonnet 237), 133-134 (madrigal 238, quotation), 134 (madrigal 239) and 135 (madrigal 240).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘bepaal’ (decide).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo on 24 January 1885: ‘It’s a pity that Vincent doesn’t have some fun skating. However, he is hard at work’ (FR b2266).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘aangezien, omdat’ (since, because).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    