<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Friday, 30 January 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let481"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b425 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>481</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>388a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>484</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-01-30">on or about Friday, 30 January 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0425" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0425" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000570_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">ik ben erg wachtende op het geld, ik had gehoopt het U mogelijk geweest ware eenige dagen vroeger te zenden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb U lang &amp; breed er over geschreven hoe het schilderen van een 50tal koppen dat ik me heb voorgenomen<c type="kk">/</c> maakt ik nog meer onkosten dan anders heb te maken. En daar ge zelf door te schrijven dat gij jegens mij achterdochtig waart er aanleiding toe gaaft<c type="kk">/</c> ontstemt het mij als ik bedenk dat waarschijnlijk het meer daaraan is toe te schrijven als aan iets anders als ik soms in verlegenheid zit. Dat ik niet verkoop zou me niet kunnen schelen als het werk zelf evenwel met volle kracht kon worden doorgezet<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin ik doe wat ik kan en ik vorder er ook après tout mede.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Gij zult dat ook terug te nemen hebben wat ge me schreeft over Uw achterdochtigheid<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wanneer – dat zult ge wel zelf moeten weten – doch alleen waarschuw ik U dat juist de ergste misverstanden door achterdochtigheid komen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik voor mij ben er soms beroerd over dat uw karakter zich in een plooi schijnt vast gezet te hebben waarvan ik geloof dat ge voor U zelf er later onrust door zult kunnen hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Maar wat geeft praten er over. ’t geen ik bedoel is een familiekwaal mijns inziens.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik verbeeld me altijd dat te Zundert en nog een paar jaar verder<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> er een betere stemming in ’t algemeen bij ons t’huis was<c type="kp">_</c> Sedert vind ik ’t er niet beter op werd<c type="kp">_</c>– Tegenwoordig – – –</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar wat ik niet weet is of dat eerste – dat het te Zundert beter was – slechts verbeelding van me is – dat kan ook wel<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Doch nu is ’t in alle geval zeker niet <hi rend="italics">datte</hi>. Enfin. gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Onwillekeurig stel ik me U sedert dezen zomer altijd voor met uw zwartglas lorgnet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dit verandert een mensch zoo zeer niet<c type="kk">/</c> zult ge zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Kan wel – maar mijn impressie is dat in een anderen zin dan den letterlijken in Uw doen en denken ge misschien zoo’n zwartglas U hebt aangeschaft<c type="kp">_</c>– Achterdocht b.v.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Van den anderen kant denk ik evenwel dat het <hi rend="italics">iets</hi> is goed zijn Parijs te kennen – dat als gij<c type="kk">/</c> er eenmaal zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> door en door Parijzenaar wordt – analyseerend<c type="kk">/</c> staalachtig<c type="kk">/</c> en wat men malin noemt – ik niet zoo kleingeestig wil zijn om dit te veroordeelen. Zoo ben ik niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Wees en blijf Parijzenaar – ook al goed<c type="kk">/</c> als ge wilt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Er zijn verschillende dingen in de wereld die <hi rend="italics">groot</hi> zijn – de zee met de visschers – de voren en de boeren – de mijnen en de charbonniers<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">En zoo vind ik ook groot</hi> de trottoirs van Parijs en de lui die goed hun Parijs kennen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Nu echter begaat gij een fout indien van uw kant gij niet begrijpen kunt dat achterdocht van U jegens mij bepaald niet te pas komt. Zeer zeker denk ik anders<c type="kk">/</c> voel ik anders<c type="kk">/</c> doe ik anders<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Doch in zijn verband heeft het zijn reden van zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">En waar gij me schreeft<c type="kk">/</c> in Drenthe toen ik U raadde nog schilder te worden<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik uit de verte sprak over Uw zaken en ik zulks ook toegaf<c type="kk">/</c> zeer zeker is ’t omgekeerde ook zoo<c type="kk">/</c> dat n.l. gij betreffende mijn doen &amp; laten slechts in de lucht grijpen kunt. Houdt Uw achterdocht dus voor U want ze komt eenvoudig niet te pas<c type="kp">_</c>– En in den goeden voortgang van mijn werk is juist ’t middel gelegen om<c type="kk">/</c> wat er ook zij van meer of van minder sympathie voor elkaar<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">althans</hi> <hi rend="italics">onschadelijk</hi> te zijn voor elkaar<c type="kk">/</c> ook waar de wegen in vrij tegengestelde rigting loopen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’m really waiting for the money; I had hoped it might have been possible for you to send it a few days earlier.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve written to you at length about how my intention of painting 50 or so heads means that I have to incur even more expenses than usual. And since you yourself gave cause by writing that you were suspicious of me, I’m put out when I think that it’s probably more due to this than to anything else that I’m sometimes embarrassed. I wouldn’t mind that I don’t sell, if the work itself could carry on at full speed anyway. Still, I do what I can, and I’m making progress with it after all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You’ll also have to take back what you write to me about your suspiciousness.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5"> When — you’ll have to decide that for yourself — but I just warn you that the very worst misunderstandings come about because of suspicion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">For my part, I’m sometimes upset that your character seems to have set fast in a form which I believe could cause you disquiet later. But what’s the use of talking about it? What I mean is a family ailment, it seems to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I always imagine that in Zundert and for a few years afterwards there was generally a better atmosphere at home. Since then, I don’t feel it’s got any better. These days —  But what I don’t know is whether that former — that it was better in Zundert — is just my imagination — it could well be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But now, in any event, it’s certainly not <hi rend="italics">that</hi>. Anyway. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Since this summer I can’t help always visualizing you with your lorgnette with dark lenses.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This doesn’t change a person very much, you’ll say.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Maybe so — but my impression is that you have perhaps, in a sense other than the literal one, acquired dark glasses in what you think and do. Suspicion, for instance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">On the other hand, though, I think that it’s <hi rend="italics">something</hi> to know Paris well — that if, once there, you become a Parisian through and through — analytical, steely, and what they call shrewd — I don’t want to be so petty-minded as to condemn it. I’m not like that. Be a Parisian, remain one — that’s fine, if it’s what you want.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">There are various things in the world that are <hi rend="italics">great</hi> — the sea with the fishermen — the furrows and the peasants — the mines and the colliers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">And likewise I think</hi> the pavements of Paris and the people who know their Paris well <hi rend="italics">are also great</hi>.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Now, though, you’re making a mistake if for your part you can’t understand that your suspicion of me is downright inappropriate. Most certainly I think differently, I feel differently, I act differently.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">But in its context it has its reason for being.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">And whereas you wrote to me in Drenthe, when I advised you to become a painter, that I was speaking of your affairs from a distance and I conceded as much, most certainly the reverse is also the case, namely that you can only guess at what I’m doing. So keep your suspicion to yourself, because it’s simply inappropriate. And it’s precisely in the good progress of my work that the means lie, whatever may happen about being more or less in sympathy with each other, of being <hi rend="italics">at least harmless</hi> to each other, even where the ways lie in quite opposite directions.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In his previous letter (of about 26 January) Van Gogh asked Theo to send the money for February a few days early. He now notes to his regret that Theo has not been able to accede to that request. This letter must therefore have been written on Friday, 30 January 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This relates to Theo’s ‘mistrustfulness’, to which Vincent had responded in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let473.xml">letter 473</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘daarna’ (afterwards).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    