<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 2 February 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let482"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b426 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>482</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>388b</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>485</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-02-02">on or about Monday, 2 February 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0426" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0426" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000571_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dat gij mijn laatste schrijven “al bij<c type="shy">-</c>zonder onaangenaam” noemt<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik nog al heel wat op te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Vooreerst dit – een tijd geleden schrijft <hi rend="italics">gij</hi> mij diverse onaangenaamheden<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – die ik van U en anderen nu ruim 15 jaar al hoor – dat’s een heele tijd – over de verhouding t’huis<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Met dit nog speciaal er bij “dat ge achterdochtig zijt”. Indien ’t nu alleen ’t eerstgenoemde was had ik er waarschijnlijk niet meer op geattendeerd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Het toevoegsel van uw achterdocht echter<c type="kk">/</c> dat was me wat bar en heb ik herhaaldelijk U verzocht terug te nemen of te expliceeren<c type="kk">/</c> want zoo iets laat ik ook niet zeggen zonder inlichting te vragen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">En in mijn laatsten brief heb ik in ’t algemeen achterdocht vergeleken met een zwartglas waardoor men kijkt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En gezegd dat de leelijkste misverstanden erdoor ontstaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En dat is waar<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Indien ge <hi rend="italics">dit nu omdraait</hi> en mij schrijft: “ge doet me denken aan de oude menschen die zeggen dat het in hun jongen tijd beter was dan nu<c type="kk">/</c> er bij vergetende dat ze zelf veranderd zijn”<c type="kk">/</c> zoo brengt me dit niet van mijn stuk<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Hetgeen waar we ’t over hadden is achterdocht<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">die niet ik doch ge zelf noemt</hi><c type="kk">/</c> van U tegen mij<c type="kp">_</c> pas dat van de oude menschen primo daarop toe en zie <hi rend="italics">daarna</hi> of ’t verder ook op mij slaat<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Past het <hi rend="italics">daarna</hi> ook op mij – dan heb ik me te veranderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wat ik schreef over een zekere stemming t’huis die ik meer dan me lief is gelegenheid had te observeeren<c type="kk">/</c> is vrees ik 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>maar al te waar<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Indien ge in uw brief me vraagt hoe het komt dat ge me nooit hoort zeggen “ik wou zus of zoo zijn” – is – omdat ik meen dat wie ’t meest te koop loopen met “ik wou zus of zoo zijn” ’t minst doen om zich zelf te verbeteren<c type="kp">_</c> Wie ’t zeggen die doen ’t meestal niet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Indien ik me uitliet over zulke wenschen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zou <hi rend="italics">niet ligt</hi> wezen in een stemming als nu tusschen ons is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Dus dat komt daarvan – en waar ik me moeite geef om mijn werk te verbeteren hoef ik niet telkens in verzuchtingen te vervallen. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het spijt me ge dat N<hi rend="super">o</hi> Illustration niet hebt gestuurd<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb Renouard nog al gevolgd en heb van jaren lang wat hij voor de illustr. heeft gemaakt.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> En dit is een van de allermooisten waar ik geloof ge zelf ook schik in zoudt hebben gehad<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De oude N<hi rend="super">o</hi>’s<c type="kk">/</c> als men ze in den boekhandel bestelt ten minste hier<c type="kk">/</c> krijgt men niet<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wou wel ge het kondt krijgen. Is ’t je echter te veel moeite<c type="kk">/</c> laat het daar<c type="kk">/</c> doch het is toch waarachtig zooveel moeite niet.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">En – après tout – weet wel dat wat die achterdocht betreft &amp; ’t geen ik er op gerepliceerd heb<c type="kk">/</c> niet zoozeer is omdat ik U of anderen niet desnoods net alles wat ge wilt van me wil laten denken<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik heb U gewaarschuwd dat het U weinig satisfactie zou geven indien Uw karakter dien plooi zou aannemen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Waar ge herhaaldelijk zegt dat ge mij beter kent dan anderen &amp; ’t draait dan op achterdocht neer<c type="kk">/</c> is zulks echter serieus genoeg dan dat<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> ik bepaald er tegen protesteer<c type="kk">/</c> én tegen ’t een van dat “zoo goed kennen” én tegen ’t ander<c type="kk">/</c> die achterdocht. Zoo’n historie heb ik met Pa achter den rug en – een Pa II<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> begin ik niet aan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Als ik met Pa er van begin af bij geweest was en niet maar stilgezwegen<c type="kk">/</c> was er veel niet gebeurd<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Neem me dus niet kwalijk ik nu vierkantweg zeg hoe ’k er over denk.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Dat’s beter voor beiden. Overigens kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof ik wat te hard werk dan dat ’t heel lang kan duren of ik zal 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>den last in ’t finantieele voor U wel wat kunnen verminderen. Het moge me langer duren dan ik prettig vind voor U of voor mij<c type="kk">/</c> doch doorwerken is een weg die bezwaarlijk geheel en al falen kan. En waar ik er op aandring er kracht achter te zetten<c type="kk">/</c> is om aan de mogelijkheid tot twisten een eind te maken<c type="kp">_</c> Want de <hi rend="italics">mogelijkheid</hi> zelfs tot twisten houdt direkt op als ik een middel vind om me in ’t finantieele te dekken. Dan is mijn werk er niet langer mee gemoeid en nu nog wel. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">En daarom niet gedesespereerd. Maar ’t is nu beroerd voor beiden. en voor mij is ’t werk kostbaar<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet veel schilderen en ik heb voortdurend model er bij noodig, maar reden te meer waarom in een tijd waarin ’t werk moeielijk en inspannend is en ondankbaar tevens<c type="kk">/</c> het vrij beroerd is dan achterdocht er voor te krijgen.– Enfin ’t is een periode die ik door moet en men schildert niet voor zijn gemak.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Dank voor ’t gezondene. Gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I have a great deal to say about your calling my last letter ‘particularly unpleasant’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">First of all this — some time ago <hi rend="italics">you</hi> wrote various unpleasant things to me<ptr target="#note-t-1"/>  which I’ve been hearing from you and others for the past 15 years and more — that’s a long time — about relations at home.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">With this specially added, ‘that you are suspicious’. Well, if it had only been the former, I probably wouldn’t have given it any more attention.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">That addition of your suspicion, though, that was a bit too much for me, and I repeatedly asked you to take it back or to explain it, because I don’t allow something like that to be said without asking for enlightenment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And in my last letter I compared suspicion in general with a dark glass one looks through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And said that the nastiest misunderstandings arise because of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And that’s true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">When you now <hi rend="italics">turn this round</hi> and write to me, ‘you remind me of the old people who say that things were better in their young days than now, forgetting meanwhile that they themselves have changed’, this doesn’t upset me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">What we were talking about is suspicion, <hi rend="italics">which not I but you yourself mention</hi>, by you of me. First apply the thing about the old people to that, and <hi rend="italics">after that</hi> see whether it also applies to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">If it also applies to me <hi rend="italics">after that</hi> — then I’ll have to change.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">What I wrote about a certain atmosphere at home, which I had more opportunity to observe than I cared to, is, I fear, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> all too true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">When you ask me in your letter how it is that you never hear me say, ‘I’d like to be thus or so’ — is — because I believe that those who make the greatest parade of ‘I’d like to be thus or so’ do the least to improve themselves. Those who say it, usually don’t do it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Were I to express myself about such wishes, it would <hi rend="italics">not be easy</hi> to do so in an atmosphere like the one that now exists between us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">So that’s the reason — and since I take pains to improve my work, I don’t have to keep lapsing into lamentations.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’m sorry you didn’t send me that No. of L’Illustration; I’ve been following <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs> a good while, and have what he’s done for L’Illustration going back for years.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And this is one of the very finest, which I think you would also have been delighted with yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">One can’t get the old Nos. if one orders them in the bookshop, at least not here. I do wish you could get it. If it’s too much trouble for you, leave it, although it’s really not that much trouble after all.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">And — after all — take note that as far as that suspicion is concerned and what I replied to it, it isn’t so much because I won’t allow you or others, if need be, to think of me exactly as you will, but I’ve warned you that it would give you little satisfaction if your character were to set in that mould.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Since you repeatedly say that you know me better than anyone else and yet it still all ends in suspicion, though, this is serious enough for me to decidedly object to it, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> to that ‘know so well’, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> to the other thing, that suspicion. I’ve a history like that behind me with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> — I’m not starting on a Pa II.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">If I’d kept on top of things with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> from the start and not simply stayed silent, a great deal wouldn’t have happened.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">So don’t take it amiss that I now say foursquare what I think about it.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> That’s better for both of us. For the rest, old chap, I think I’m working rather too hard for it to be too long before I can 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> reduce the financial burden on you somewhat. It may take me longer than I’d like for you or for me, but keeping on working is a path that can hardly fail altogether. And when I insist on pressing on with it, it’s in order to put an end to the possibility of quarrelling. Because even the <hi rend="italics">possibility</hi> of quarrelling ceases to exist as soon as I find a means of covering myself financially. Then my work will no longer be at issue, and at present it still is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">And therefore don’t despair. But now it’s wretched for both of us. And for me the work is expensive; I have to paint a lot and I constantly need a model for it; just all the more reason why, at a time when the work is difficult and exacting, and at the same time thankless, it’s quite wretched to get suspicion for it. Never mind, it’s a period I have to go through, and one doesn’t paint for one’s comfort.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Thanks for what you sent. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent had lashed out savagely at Theo in his letter of about Friday, 30 January 1885 <ref target="let481.xml">(481)</ref>. Theo responded to this – he found it ‘particularly unpleasant’, as we see from the present letter which is a reply to that one. In passing Vincent thanks Theo for the money he sent <ref target="#l-93">(l. 93)</ref>, which must have been the allowance for February. There is no reason to think that the regular remittance was delayed, so we have dated the letter on or about Monday, 2 February 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent refers again here to Theo’s letter (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let481.xml">letter 481</ref>), in which he expressed his ‘mistrust’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let473.xml">see letter 473</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Vincent had asked for a special issue of this periodical (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let480.xml">letter 480</ref>), which Theo did in fact send shortly after this (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let483.xml">see letter 483</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘om te maken dat’ (to make me).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh introduced the comparison ‘Pa II’ in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let474.xml">letter 474</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>Later in the month <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> expressed himself frankly to Theo about the difficult relationship with Vincent. Although he said he did not want to burden Theo with the matter, he did inform him of it. On 19 February 1885 he wrote: ‘Pity that Vincent doesn’t join in any more. It’s as if he is increasingly becoming estranged from us ... His short temper prevents any talking and that in itself is enough to prove that he isn’t normal. It’s certainly not easy for me to be passive. And yet previous experience has taught me that one doesn’t win by opposition and it doesn’t improve matters ... We feel so sorry for him; because such a relationship can’t give him any pleasure. We place our hope in God and pray for light and wisdom and for him, oh if only it could be! some happiness in life. But I mustn’t burden you too much.’ In a postscript written the following day he added: ‘I did speak to Vincent again this morning after all. He was quite responsive and said that there was nothing in particular to make him feel depressed – We will just have to wait and see’ (FR b2267).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    