<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 2 March 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let484"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b433 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>484</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>395</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>488</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-03-02">on or about Monday, 2 March 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0433" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0433" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000578_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor de spoedige zending van het geld van deze maand, dat trouwens spoedig komende mij meer helpt. Dank ook voor de prachtige houtsnee naar l’Hermitte – een van de <hi rend="italics">weinige</hi> dingen die ik van hem ken want ik zag slechts deze – een troep meisjes in ’t koren<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – een oude vrouw in de kerk<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – en een mijnwerker of zoo iemand in een kroegje<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en la moisson<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> van hem en anders nooit iets<c type="kk">/</c> en niets ooit zoo teruggevende zijn eigentlijke manier van doen dan deze houthakkers<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Indien de monde illustré iedere maand een compositi<supplied>e</supplied> van hem geeft – dit maakt deel uit van eene serie “les mois rustiques” – dan zou ’t me magtig veel genoegen doen die serie in zijn geheel bij te houden en heb ik steeds erg graag dat ge ze zendt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Want ik zie hier natuurlijk nooit iets en ik heb het toch noodig nu en dan eens iets heel moois te zien<c type="kk">/</c> en dus houd gerust de een of andere keer b.v. frs 20 af maar stuur me zulk soort van dingen als ze in de illustraties voorkomen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wat nu betreft dat ge schrijft dat<c type="kk">/</c> als ik iets klaar had dat ik dacht goed was<c type="kk">/</c> gij wildet probeeren ’t in te zenden voor den Salon – ik apprecieer ge dit doen wilt<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dit op den voorgrond – en er bij verder dat als ik ’t 6 weken eer geweten had<c type="kk">/</c> ik getracht zou hebben U voor dit doeleinde iets te zenden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Nu heb ik echter niets dat ik zelf lust zou hebben in te zenden. ik heb zoo als ge weet den laatsten tijd bijna uitsluitend koppen geschilderd<c type="kp">_</c> En dat zijn <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> in den eigentlijken zin van ’t woord – n.l. ze zijn voor ’t atelier bestemd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Toch ben ik dadelijk heden begonnen om er eenigen te maken die ik U sturen zal<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Omdat ik het mogelijk acht het zijn nut kan hebben gij<c type="kk">/</c> als ge bij gelegenheid van den Salon ligt nog al lui ontmoet<c type="kk">/</c> iets – zij het slechts <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> – kunt laten kijken.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ge zult zoodoende ontvangen een oude en een jonge vrouwekop en waarschijnlijk meer dan een van die twee modellen. Gegeven wat ge me schrijft over uw gevoelens betreffende diverse opvatting van koppen<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik dat deze die regelregt uit een hut met bemost stroodak komen, al zijn ’t studies, en niets anders, U niet absoluut ontoepasselijk zullen voorkomen. Als ik ’t 6 weken eer geweten had zou ik een spinster of spoelster – geheel figuur – er van hebben gemaakt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Om even terug te komen op die kwestie van de vrouwekoppen genre Jaquet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> niet van vroeger doch van tegenwoordig<c type="kp">_</c>– De reactie daar tegen – zeker gemotiveerd – van lui die koppen schilderen van meisjes zooals b.v. onze zusters – ik kan me best begrijpen dat er schilders zijn die zulks doen – Whistler deed het verscheiden keeren goed – Millais<c type="kk">/</c> Boughton – om slechts te spreken van lui van wie ik in der tijd zoo iets zag<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Fantin Latour</hi> ken ik weinig maar wat ik zag vond ik <hi rend="italics">erg best</hi>. <hi rend="italics">Chardin achtig</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– En dat’s veel<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik voor mij echter ben geen persoonlijkheid die veel kans heeft om met dat soort meisjes op genoegzaam intiemen voet te komen dat 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>ze poseeren willen<c type="kp">_</c>– Speciaal met mijn eigen zusters niet<c type="kp">_</c>– En ben welligt ook vooringenomen tegen vrouwen die japonnen dragen<c type="kp">_</c>– En is mijn territoor meer die jakken en rokken dragen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Doch wat ge er van zegt vind ik waar – namelijk dat het heel goed <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> ze te schilderen – en ’t als reactie tegen de Jaquets van nu en v. Beers<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> raison d’être heeft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Alleen dit toch – Chardin (laat ons in zijn naam zamenvatten het streven dier reactie<c type="kk">/</c> dat zou althans Fantin Latour goedvinden)<c type="kk">/</c> Chardin was Franschman en schilderde <hi rend="italics">Francaises</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– En de <hi rend="italics">Hollandsche</hi><c type="kk">/</c><hi rend="italics"> fatsoenlijke</hi> vrouwen als onze zusters missen m.i. al heel erg bijzonder dikwijls het charme dat de fransche meermalen hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Gevolgelijk ’t zoogenaamd fatsoenlijk deel van de <hi rend="italics">hollandsche</hi> vrouwen is niet zoo heel erg aantrekkelijk – om te schilderen of over te denken.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Maar zekere gewone dienstmeiden daarentegen zijn weer erg Chardin achtig<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Ik schilder tegenwoordig niet alleen zoolang ’t licht is doch zelfs s’avonds bij de lamp in de hutten<c type="kk">/</c> als ik ter naauwernood iets op mijn palet kan onderscheiden<c type="kk">/</c> om zoo mogelijk iets te vatten van de eigenaardige effekten van verlichting s’avonds. met b.v. een groote slagschaduw op den muur.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Zeker heb ik in een paar jaar tijds niets zoo moois gezien als die houtzagers van <hi rend="italics">l’Hermitte</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Wat zijn zijn figuurtjes in die compositie gevoeld en gewild<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Nogmaals dank er voor<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Het Chardinachtige is dunkt me een eigenaardige expressie van <hi rend="italics">eenvoud</hi> en van <hi rend="italics">goedheid</hi> – beiden <hi rend="italics">door en door</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en dat men dat in b.v. onze zusters<c type="kk">/</c> een van beiden<c type="kk">/</c> zou vinden ben ik ietwat ongeloovig in<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar als Wil francaise er bij was in plaats van dominesdochter zou ze ’t <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> hebben. Maar verzeilt <hi rend="italics">zoo goed als altijd</hi> naar de tegenovergestelde windstreek.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for the prompt dispatch of the money for this month, arriving promptly like that actually helps me more. Thanks, too, for the splendid woodcut after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> — one of the <hi rend="italics">few</hi> things by him that I know, for I saw only these — a troop of girls in the wheat<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — an old woman in church<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — and a miner or some such in a little bar,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and Harvest<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> by him, and otherwise never anything, and nothing ever as much reflecting his actual manner as these woodcutters.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">If Le Monde Illustré prints a composition by him every month — this is part of a series of ‘Rural months’ — it would give me mighty great pleasure to collect this whole series, and I’d really like you to send them every time.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Because obviously I never see anything here, and after all I do need to see something really beautiful now and then, and so another time feel free to keep back 20 francs, say, but send me things like this when they appear in the illustrated magazines.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now as to when you write that if I had something ready that I thought was good, you would try to enter it for the Salon — I appreciate your wanting to do this.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">This in the first place — and then further that if I’d known it 6 weeks earlier, I would have tried to send you something for this purpose.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Now, though, I don’t have anything that I would care to send in. Recently, as you know, I’ve painted heads almost exclusively. And they are <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> in the true meaning of the word — that is, they’re meant for the studio.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Nonetheless, this very day I’ve started to make some that I’ll send you.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Because I think it possible that it might be of use, when you meet a good many people on the occasion of the Salon, if you had something you could show — albeit only <hi rend="italics">studies</hi>.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So you’ll receive heads of an old and a young woman, and probably more than one of these two models. Given what you write of your feelings about various conceptions of heads, I think that these, which come straight out of a cottage with a moss-grown thatched roof, won’t appear to you to be absolutely inappropriate, although they’re studies and nothing else. If I’d known 6 weeks earlier, I would have made a woman spinning or spooling yarn — full length — of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">To return for a moment to that question of the female heads in the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1115">Jacquet</rs> genre,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> not the earlier ones but of the present day. The reaction against them — certainly with a motive — by people who paint heads of girls like our sisters, for instance — I can well understand that there are painters who do such things — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1444">Whistler</rs> did it well several times — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_878">Boughton</rs> — to mention only people by whom I saw something of the sort in the past. I know little by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1015">Fantin-Latour</rs></hi>, but what I saw I thought <hi rend="italics">very good</hi>. <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs>esque</hi>. And that’s a lot. For my part, though, I’m not the sort of character who has much chance of getting on a sufficiently intimate footing with girls of that sort that 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> they’re willing to pose. Particularly not with my own sisters. And am possibly also prejudiced against women who wear dresses. And my province is more those who wear jackets and skirts.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Though I think what you say about it is true — namely that it’s perfectly <hi rend="italics">possible</hi> to paint them — and it has a <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi> as a reaction against the present-day <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1115">Jacquet</rs>s and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_427">Van Beers</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Just this, though — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs> (let’s sum up the aim of the reaction in his name, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1015">Fantin-Latour</rs>, at least, would approve), Chardin was a Frenchman and painted <hi rend="italics">French women</hi>. And in my view, <hi rend="italics">respectable Dutch</hi> women like our sisters really do extraordinarily often lack the charm that the French frequently have.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Consequently, the so-called respectable element among <hi rend="italics">Dutch</hi> women isn’t really so very attractive — to paint or to think about.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> But certain common servant girls, on the other hand, are very <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs>esque.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">At present I’m painting not just as long as there’s light, but even in the evening by lamplight in the cottages, if I can somehow make things out on my palette, in order to capture if possible something of the singular effects of lighting at night, for instance with a large shadow cast on the wall.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’ve certainly not seen anything in the last few years as fine as those woodcutters by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs></hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">How his little figures in that composition are felt and wanted.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Thanks again for it.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs>esque is, it seems to me, a singular expression of <hi rend="italics">simplicity</hi> and of <hi rend="italics">goodness</hi> — both <hi rend="italics">through and through</hi>, and I find it a little hard to believe that one would find it in our sisters, say, either one of them. But if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> were a Frenchwoman rather than a minister’s daughter, she <hi rend="italics">could</hi> have it. But <hi rend="italics">as good as always</hi> sails to the opposite point of the compass.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the ‘prompt dispatch of the money for this month’ <ref target="#l-1">(ll. 1-2)</ref>. It is clear from his efforts to make progress with the work on the heads and Theo’s question as to whether Vincent could send something for the Salon that the month must be March, 1885. The words ‘prompt’ and ‘this’ tell us that the allowance came on time – furthermore Theo sent an engraving that was in the 28 February issue of <hi rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi>. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Monday, 2 March 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Probably a reproduction of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La moisson </hi>(The harvest), 1874 (Carcassonne, Musée des Beaux-Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2095">Ill. 2095</rs>. See Le Pelley Fonteny 1991, p. 90, cat. no. 6.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_220">The grandmother</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml#n-1">letter 333, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_211">The inn</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let467.xml#n-7">see letter 467, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_217">The harvest</rs></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let343.xml#n-5">letter 343, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Les bûcherons </hi>(The woodcutters), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1513">Clément Edouard Bellenger</rs>, is the month of February in the series ‘Les mois rustiques’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 29 (28 February 1885), Supplement to no. 1457. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_216">Ill. 216</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>On ‘Les mois rustiques’ (Rural months): Le Pelley Fonteny 1991, p. 36. See for the prints for the months of March and April: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let496.xml">letter 496</ref>; for May (published in June): <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let506.xml">letter 506</ref>; for July and August: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let531.xml">letter 531</ref>; for September: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let533.xml">letter 533</ref>; for October and November: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let545.xml">letter 545</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Vincent had rejected Theo’s previous proposal – in March 1884 – to submit work to the de Salon. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let436.xml">See letter 436</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>It is not certain whether Vincent actually carried out his intention (we know of no confirmation and in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let485.xml">letter 485</ref> he writes ‘I have a few of the heads I promised you ready, but not completely dry yet ... so as soon as they’re completely dry and I can varnish them, I’ll send you a few heads’). See for the works that Theo took with him later in the month: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let489.xml#n-4">letter 489, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the charming, slickly painted portraits by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1115">Gustave Jaquet</rs> (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let515.xml">letter 515</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_427">Jan Maria Constantijn van Beers</rs> painted many portraits of wealthy Frenchwomen, of the type Van Gogh is talking about here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh added ‘or to think about’ (om te ... denken) later.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>There are four paintings of peasant men and women at work dating from this period in which shadows like these can be seen: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman peeling potatoes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_559">F 145 / JH 653</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sewing</hi> ( <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_560">F 126a / JH 655</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman sweeping the floor</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_561">F 152 / JH 656</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man making a basket</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_562">F 171 / JH 658</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    