<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Saturday, 4 April 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let489"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b435 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>489</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>397</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>492</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-04-04">on or about Saturday, 4 April 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0435" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000580_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000580_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0435" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000580_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000580_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Het is mij gegaan als U<c type="kk">/</c> in zoover dat als ge schrijft de allereerste dagen het werken nog niet als gewoonlijk ging<c type="kk">/</c> ik dezelfde ondervinding had<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het zijn dan ook dagen geweest die ons allen heugen zullen en toch is de totaalindruk niet verschrikkelijk maar alleen ernstig.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Het leven is voor niemand lang en de kwestie is maar – iets er mee te doen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Van daag ging ’t schilderen weer beter, de eerste twee koppen mislukten mij – die van heden is een kop van een jong meisje<c type="kk">/</c> bijna een kinderkop<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wat kleur betreft is het een tegenstelling van schel rood met flets groen tegen de kleur van het gezigtje<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als er reeds een kop is bij die ge mede naamt<c type="kp">_</c> Ik wil wel eens vernemen of die opgerolden goed zijn overgekomen.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als ik dacht dat C.M. het meende dat hij vroeg naar kinder<c type="shy">-</c>koppen<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik hem deze wel kunnen sturen van van daag<c type="kk">/</c> maar..... ik kan niet zeggen ik animo gevoel (tenzij hij meer bepaald iets vrage) in correspondentie te treden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Het kan evenwel geen kwaad hij eens op ’t atelier was. Ik wil ook wel eens een nieuw stilleven beginnen van die judaspenningen en dorre blaren tegen blaauw<c type="kk">/</c> omdat hij daar ook iets van zeide<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik ben natuurlijk van plan hard door te zetten maar het is erg noodig ik mijn verfrekening in ’t gelijk breng zoo dra mogelijk. Het is alle andere jaren geweest dat ik omstreeks dezen tijd heb kunnen gelijk maken<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> en mij wat nieuw gereedschap aanschaffen. En dit jaar heb ik de laatste maanden zooveel geschilderd dat ik er eigentlijk nog meer behoefte aan heb dan anders.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik wou er toen ge hier waart niet over doorpraten of U veel tegenspreken – maar als ge zeidet dat ik nog wel eens veranderen zou en evenmin als Mauve altijd in Bloemendaal gebleven was<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ik ook niet altijd hier zou blijven – kan wezen – maar – ik zie anders voor me zelf geen heil in van woonplaats veranderen<c type="kk">/</c> omdat ik hier een goed atelier heb en de natuur hier zeer mooi is<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Vergeet niet dat ik bepaald overtuigd ben een boerenschilder niet beter kan doen dan een voorbeeld nemen aan Barbizon – Wonen en leven goed midden in ’t geen men schildert. want het is buiten iederen dag nieuw en anders<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Kortom de twee redenen vóór het buiten wonen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> dat men er meer werken kan en minder onkosten heeft.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Tusschen nu en den tijd dat ge van den zomer weer hier komt<c type="kk">/</c> liggen<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> een maand of 3<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Als ik dag aan dag hard werk kan ik tegen dien tijd weer een 20tal studies voor U hebben en bovendien een twintigtal anderen om als gij wilt eens mee naar Antwerpen te gaan<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch – het is hoog noodig ik zoodra mogelijk mijn verfrekening eens afdoe<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge weet<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb noch in Februarij noch in Maart er U een woord meer over gesproken<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Maar ik heb ’t niet makkelijk gehad die maanden<c type="kk">/</c> dat kan ik U wel zeggen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het is hier weer guurder geworden<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoodra we een paar mooie dagen hebben zal ik iets van het kerkhof maken.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het kopje dat ik vandaag maakte is dunkt me zeker zoo goed als die gij hebt met een groote witte muts die zoowat is als dit<ptr target="#note-t-9"/><hi rend="italics"><supplied>After ‘this’ (dit) Van Gogh drew a little arrow pointing to the sketches</supplied></hi></p>
      <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En zou er als pendant voor kunnen dienen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Als ge die twee op verguld bristol zet zouden ze misschien goed in het goud staan, beter doen dan op zich zelf.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gegroet, met een handdruk &amp; nog dikwijls denkend aan Uw bezoek</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I felt as you did, in so far as when you write that the work didn’t yet proceed as usual the very first few days, I had the same experience.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">They have therefore been days that none of us will forget, and yet the overall impression isn’t terrible but only grave.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Life isn’t long for anyone, and the question is just — to do something with it.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">The painting went better again today; the first two heads went wrong — today’s is a head of a young girl, almost a child’s head.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">As to colour, it’s a contrast of bright red and pale green against the colour of the little face; there’s already a head like it among those you took with you. I’d like to hear sometime whether those rolled-up ones arrived safely.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If I thought that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">C.M.</rs> meant it when he asked for heads of children, I could send him this one I did today, but..... I can’t say I feel much inclined to enter into correspondence (unless he asks for something more specifically).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">It can do no harm, though, that he’s been to the studio. I don’t mind starting a new still life of those honesty heads and dry leaves against blue either, because he said something about that too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Of course I intend to keep working hard, but it’s very necessary for me to square my paint bill as soon as possible. Every other year, I’ve been able to get square at about this time and buy myself some new equipment. And this year I’ve painted so much the last few months that I actually need it more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I didn’t want to keep talking about it or contradict you much when you were here — but when you said that I would change some day and, no more than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> stayed in Bloemendaal for ever,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> would I stay here for ever either — maybe — but — I don’t see any advantage myself in moving, because I have a good studio here and the countryside here is very beautiful.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Don’t forget that I’m definitely convinced that a painter of peasant life can do no better than follow the example of Barbizon – dwelling and living right in the midst of what one is painting, for it’s new and different outside every day.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">In short, the two reasons <hi rend="italics">for</hi> living in the country are that one can do more work and has fewer expenses.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">There are about 3 months, let’s say, between now and the time you come back here in the summer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">If I work hard day after day, I can have another 20 or so studies for you by then, and moreover another twenty or so to take to Antwerp if you want. But — it’s very necessary for me to pay off my paint bill as soon as possible. You know I didn’t say another word to you about it either in February or in March.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But I didn’t have it easy in those months, I can tell you that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">It has become colder again here. As soon as we have a few fine days, I’ll make something of the churchyard.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I think the little head I made today is certainly as good as the one you have with a large white cap, which is something like this<ptr target="#note-t-9"/><hi rend="italics"><supplied>After ‘this’ (dit) Van Gogh drew a little arrow pointing to the sketches</supplied></hi></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">And could serve as a pendant to it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">If you mount these two on gilded Bristol they might perhaps look good in the gold, do better than by themselves.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Regards, with a handshake, and still thinking often of your visit</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo went back to Paris on Wednesday, 1 April 1885 (<ref target="#n-1">see n. 1</ref>), and had meanwhile written that ‘the work didn’t yet proceed as usual the very first few days’ <ref target="#l-3">(ll. 3-4)</ref>. Vincent responds to this in the present letter. On this basis and in view of the fact that the next letter was written on Monday, 6 April <ref target="let490.xml">(490)</ref>, we have dated the present one on or about Saturday, 4 April 1885. This is borne out by what Van Gogh says about the weather, which had ‘become colder’ <ref target="#l-64">(l. 64)</ref>; the temperature dropped significantly in the first few days of April compared with 31 March and 1 April (<hi rend="italics">KNMI</hi>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The death of Mr van Gogh <ref target="let486.xml">(486)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was buried on Monday, 30 March; Theo went back to Paris on the afternoon of Wednesday, 1 April. This emerges from a letter – undated, but written shortly after that day – from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan van Gogh</rs> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Aunt Cornelie</rs>. On 28 March he informed his sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_90">Maria (Mietje) Johanna van Gogh</rs>: ‘Vincent behaves well enough, obviously rather withdrawn but bearable all the same, apart from that a tendency to cool reasoning’ (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum Documentation, bd 15. Nebbeling/Weenink Ladies Collection, De Bilt).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Elisabeth van Gogh</rs> later recalled: ‘When <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs> died and Mrs Poots wanted to see Father once again, Vincent stood beside her and said: “yes, Mrs Poots, dying is hard, but living is harder still”’ (FR b2002). See Pickvance 1992, p. 68.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2500">F 160 / JH 722</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 94-95.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo took several works with him, among them <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman (Gordina de Groot)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2496">F 130 / JH 692</rs>) – letter sketch A corresponds with this – and probably also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2501">F 69 / JH 724</rs>), which in type and colouration is akin to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2500">F 160 / JH 722</rs>). The batch also included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Honesty in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2491">F 76 / JH 542</rs>), as we know from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let490.xml">letter 490</ref>. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_563">F 80a / JH 682</rs>) is the only other portrait of an old woman in Theo’s collection, and could therefore probably be identified with the head of an old woman Vincent had intended to send Theo in March (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let484.xml">letter 484</ref>) Cf. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 11-13, 94-95, 98-99, 238-239.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘vereffenen’ (settle).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This remark relates to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s apprenticeship in 1855-1857 with P.F. van Os in Haarlem, near Bloemendaal. Cf. Saskia de Bodt, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Anton Mauve en de Haagse School</hi>. The Hague 1997, p. 11 (Openbaar Kunstbezit 4).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In the mid-nineteenth century a group of painters worked in the French village of Barbizon in the Forest of Fontainebleau. They are known as the Barbizon School – their intimate scenes and sedate landscapes were usually painted outdoors.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Theo had probably given Vincent his allowance for April in person.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was later to depict the church in the field with the peasants’ churchyard in Nuenen many times. At the beginning of June this resulted in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>), which was painted over another scene and had been preceded by three watercolours. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 152-159, cat. no. 28. Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let259.xml#n-6">letter 259, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>See notes 4 and 3 respectively for the paintings after which the letter sketches <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(both <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_141 artwork.xml#_142">F- / JH 723</rs>) were done.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    