<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Monday, 6 April 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let490"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b436 a-b V/1962 (sheets 1, 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>490</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>398</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>493</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-04-06">Monday, 6 April 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0436 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0436 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000581_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0436 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000582_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000582_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0436b V/1962" xml:id="surf-extra-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000582_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000582_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Nog steeds ben ik zeer onder den indruk van het pas gebeurde – ik heb deze twee zondagen ook maar doorgeschilderd<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Hierbij nog een krabbel van een manskop<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en een van een stilleven met judaspenningen<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> in den zelfden trant als dat wat ge meenaamt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Het is echter wat grooter – en de voorwerpen op den voorgrond zijn een tabakszakje en een pijp van Pa.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Als ge ’t soms hebben wilt kunt ge ’t natuurlijk regt graag krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Moe ziet er goed uit en het veel brieven schrijven geeft voorloopig nog al afleiding. Maar natuurlijk nog erg bedroefd<c type="kp">_</c>– Cor is weer naar Helmond gegaan zooeven.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik weet niet of ge U nog herinnert dat ik in Januarij<c type="kk">/</c> toen de sneeuw op de akkers lag en de zon rood opkwam in den nevel<c type="kk">/</c> U schreef dat ik haast nooit een jaar in somberder stemming had aangevat.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Zeker is het dat er nog heel wat zal komen kijken voor ons allen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Natuurlijk zult ge wel begrijpen het niet voor mijn gemak is dat ik in ’t atelier zal gaan wonen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Voor mij worden zoodoende de dingen al weer nog moeielijker<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Doch ik ben overtuigd het in hun voordeel is dat ik wegga<c type="kk">/</c> bepaaldelijk met het oog op ’t voornemen van Moe om zoo mogelijk dezen zomer iemand in de kost te nemen die voor gezondheid buiten zou wenschen te zijn – of indien dit welligt tegen mogt vallen<c type="kk">/</c> dan zijn zij nog vrijer met logés &amp;.c.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik blijf echter zeer betreuren het incident met Anna<c type="kk">/</c> dat mij decideerde in dit opzigt<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Wat zij tot U zeide veranderde niets aan wat zij mij verweet<c type="kk">/</c> en hoe absurd die verwijten ook waren en haar ongemotiveerde presumpties omtrent dingen die nog in de toekomst liggen – zij heeft ze niet teruggenomen tegenover mij. Nu – ge begrijpt hoe voor zulke dingen ik eenvoudig mijn schouders ophaal – en trouwens<c type="kk">/</c> meer en meer laat ik iedereen net precies alles van mij denken wat ze willen en zeggen en doen desnoods ook<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Maar ik heb geen keus zoodoende – bij zoo’n begin moet men maatregelen nemen voor ’t vervolg al dat soort dingen te voorkomen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik ben dan ook geheel besloten<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het is wel te voorzien dat Moe<c type="kk">/</c> Wil en Cor ’t volgende jaar naar Leiden zullen gaan<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Dan zal ik de eenige zijn die nog van ’t huis in Brabant blijft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En mij is ’t gansch niet onwaarschijnlijk ik er de rest van mijn leven blijven zal ook. Trouwens ik begeer niets anders dan goed diep in ’t boerenland te zitten en ’t boerenleven te schilderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik voel dat ik er me een werkkring kan scheppen en dus ik zal bedaard mijn hand aan mijn ploeg houden<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en mijn voor doortrekken<c type="kp">_</c> Ik geloof dat gij anders er over dacht en dat welligt gij mij liever een anderen weg zoudt zien gaan wat woonplaats betreft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Maar ik denk wel eens dat gij meer oog hebt voor wat men in stad kan doen doch van den anderen kant ik buiten meer me <hi rend="italics">t’huis</hi> gevoel.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Doch het zal mij nog heel wat moeite kosten voor ik mijn schilderijen in ’t hoofd van de lui zal inprenten<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Intusschen<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben geenszins van plan me te laten decourageeren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik dacht nog aan wat ik las van Delacroix<c type="kp">_</c> 17 schilderijen van hem werden geweigerd<c type="kk">/</c> “<hi rend="italics">dix sept de refusés</hi>” vertelde hij zelf vierkantweg aan zijn vrienden<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Ik dacht van daag dat het toch almagtig dappere kerels waren<c type="kk">/</c> die baanbrekers<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Maar ook nu moet de strijd worden voortgezet<c type="kk">/</c> en met zoo veel en zoo weinig als ik waard ben wil ik voor mij ook vechten. En dus – Theo, wat we nu weer begonnen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop dat van weerskanten we er mee doorgaan<c type="kp">_</c>– in afwachting van of liever terwijl ik tob op meer importante composities stuur ik U de studies zoo als ze regelregt uit de hutten komen<c type="kp">_</c>– De lui zullen natuurlijk spreken van niet af of van leelijk &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> maar – mijns inziens – <hi rend="italics">toch laten kijken</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> Ik voor mij heb een vast geloof dat er enkele lui zijn die<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t stadsleven verzeild en gebonden<c type="kk">/</c> onuitwischbare indrukken houden van buiten en die hun leven lang een heimwee blijven voelen naar het veld en de boeren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Zulke liefhebbers worden wel eens getroffen door sinceriteit en hun hindert niet wat anderen afstuit<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-b"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik zelf weet hoe ik vroeger in stad uren rondliep langs de vitrines om ergens een of ander kijkje op n’importe quoi van buiten te zien<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Wij zijn nu in ’t begin van het laten kijken<c type="kk">/</c> dat gaandeweg wij er enkele lui voor zullen vinden<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof het vast en zeker<c type="kp">_</c>– De omstandigheden dringen ons en langzamerhand zullen we ook nog wel beter dingen kunnen wijzen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Nu op ’t oogenblik preoccupeert mij sterk het afdoen van mijn verfrekening en bovendien heb ik doek<c type="kk">/</c> verf<c type="kk">/</c> penseelen noodig.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Daar gij door ’t overlijden van Pa voor t’huis buitengewone dingen hebt moeten doen<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik ’t volgende gedacht.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Gesteld dat gij U niet bij magte gevoelt mij te geven wat andere jaren in ’t voorjaar en zomer ik extra ontving en wat trouwens ik niet missen kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Zoudt ge in dat geval ’t niet billijk vinden ik bij de regeling van de zaken mij eene som van b.v. f<c type="kp">_</c> 200 voorbehoud van mijn aandeel<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik overigens regt graag aan de jongeren laat.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> En ook in zijn geheel zal kunnen overlaten indien gij mij helpen kunt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ik beschouw het trouwens niet dat <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> mijn aandeel aan hun laat – doch ook dat het door U is dat zij het mijne houden kunnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Als ik in ’t atelier ga wonen is het onvermijdelijk ik er b.v. een kast laat timmeren want ik heb nu geen bergplaats hoegenaamd en ik zal ook het licht nog verbeteren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Verhuizen zou voor mij even erg zijn als brand – en ik geloof trouwens dat we er wel boven op blijven zullen met volharding en inspanning.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ik zal denk ik s’avonds – zoodra ik in ’t atelier woon – geregeld gaan aquarelleeren – hier thuis in de kamer kan dat niet goed<c type="kp">_</c>– Tot zoo lang blijf ik ook s’avonds naar ’t model werken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Wat Anna betreft – ge moet niet denken ik zoo iets kwalijk blijf nemen of er rancune over houd – maar alleen<c type="kk">/</c> het is jammer dat ze meenen Moe met zoo iets dienst te doen – dat’s jammer – en dat’s dom en onverstandig<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoolang Moe en Wil hier zijn zal er tusschen hun en mij niets hatelijks voorvallen<c type="kk">/</c> dat geloof ik niet. Alleen het is zeker dat Moe ten eenemale geen begrip zich vormen kan van dat schilderen <hi rend="italics">een geloof</hi> is en dat het <hi rend="italics">den pligt</hi> meebrengt van zich niet te storen aan de publieke opinie – en dat men er in overwint door <hi rend="italics">volharding</hi> maar niet door <hi rend="italics">toegeven</hi><c type="kp">_</c> En – “’t geloof kan ik u niet geven” is tusschen HEd<c type="kp">_</c> en mij ook ’t geval – zoo als zulks met Pa ook was en bleef<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Enfin – ik heb plan deze week te beginnen aan dat geval van die boeren rond een schotel aardappels s’avonds<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> of – misschien zal ik er daglicht van maken, of beiden<c type="kk">/</c> of – “geen van beiden” – zult ge zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar ’t zij ’t gelukke ’t zij ’t mislukke<c type="kk">/</c> ik ga aan de studies voor de verschillende figuren beginnen. Gegroet, met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Vincent</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’m still very much under the impression of what has just happened — I just kept painting these two Sundays.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Herewith another scratch of a man’s head<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and one of a still life with honesty<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> in the same style as the one you took with you.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> It’s rather larger, though — and the objects in the foreground are a tobacco pouch and a pipe of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> If you think you’d like it, of course you’re right welcome to have it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> looks well, and writing many letters provides some distraction for the time being. But, of course, still very sad. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> has just gone back to Helmond.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I don’t know whether you still remember that in January, when the snow was lying on the fields and the sun rose red in the mist, I wrote to you that I’d almost never started a year in a gloomier mood.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> It’s certain that there’ll be a whole lot more trouble for all of us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Of course you’ll understand that it’s not for my convenience that I’ll go and live in the studio.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">It will make things even more difficult for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But I’m convinced that it’s to their advantage for me to leave, particularly in view of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s intention to take in a lodger this summer, if possible, who wanted to be in the country for his health — or should this not come about, then they’re still freer with regard to guests &amp;c.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">However, I still very much regret the incident with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> that decided me in this respect.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> What she said to you changed nothing of what she reproached me for, and however absurd those reproaches were and her unfounded presumptions about things that are still in the future — she hasn’t told me she takes them back. Well — you understand how I simply shrug my shoulders at such things — and anyway, I increasingly let people think of me just exactly what they will, and say and do too, if need be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But consequently I have no choice — with a beginning like that, one has to take steps to prevent all that sort of thing in the future.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">So I’m absolutely decided.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">It’s likely that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> will go to Leiden next year.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Then I’ll be the only one of us who’s still in Brabant.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And I think it by no means unlikely that I’ll stay here for the rest of my life, too. After all, I desire nothing other than to live deep in the country and to paint peasant life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I feel that I can create a place for myself here, and so I’ll quietly keep my hand to my plough<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and cut my furrow. I believe that you thought differently about it, and that you would perhaps rather see me take another course as regards where I live.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">But I sometimes think that you have more idea of what people can do in the city, yet on the other hand I feel more <hi rend="italics">at home</hi> in the country.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">All the same, it will still take me a great deal of effort before I imprint my paintings in people’s heads.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Meanwhile, I have no intention whatsoever of allowing myself to be discouraged.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I was thinking again of what I read about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> — 17 of his paintings were rejected; ‘<hi rend="italics">dix-sept de refusés</hi>’, he himself told his friends straight out.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I was thinking today that they really were almighty brave fellows, those pioneers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">But the battle has to be continued even now, and for my part I also want to fight for as much and as little as I’m worth. And so — Theo, I hope that we can continue on both sides what we’ve now started again. Awaiting or, rather, while I toil away on more important compositions, I’m sending you the studies as they come straight from the cottages. Of course people will say they’re not finished or they’re ugly &amp;c. &amp;c., but — in my view — <hi rend="italics">show them anyway</hi>. For my part, I have a firm belief that there are a few people who, ending up in and tied to the city, retain indelible impressions of the country, and continue to feel homesick for the fields and the peasants all their lives.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Art lovers like this are sometimes struck by sincerity, and not put off by what deters others.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I know how I used to walk round the city for hours, looking in the shop windows, to see some little view of the country somewhere, no matter what.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">We’re now at the beginning of letting people see; I believe absolutely and utterly that little by little we’ll find a few people for it. Circumstances compel us, and gradually we’ll also be able to show better things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Now, at this moment, I’m very much preoccupied with paying off my paint bill, and moreover I need canvas, paint, brushes.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Since you’ve had to do exceptional things for the people at home because of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s death, I’ve come up with the following idea.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Suppose that you don’t feel you’re in a position to give me the extra I received in spring and summer in other years, and which, by the way, I can’t do without.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Wouldn’t you think it fair in that case if, when settling affairs, I were to reserve for myself a sum of, say, 200 francs of my share, which I’ll otherwise right willingly let the youngsters have?<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> And would be able to let them have altogether if you can help me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">By the way, I don’t see it as <hi rend="italics">my</hi> letting them have my share — but rather that it’s because of you that they can keep my portion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">If I go to live in the studio, I’ll inevitably have to have a cupboard built, for instance, because at present I have nowhere at all to store things, and I’ll also improve the light.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">To me, moving would be as bad as a fire — and anyway I think that we’ll stay on top of things with perseverance and effort.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">I think I’ll start painting in watercolour regularly in the evenings — as soon as I’m living in the studio — it can’t really be done in the living room here at home. Until then, I’ll go on working from the model in the evenings too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">As to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> — you mustn’t think that I’ll continue to take something like that amiss or hold a grudge about it — but only, it’s a shame that they think to do <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> a service with something like that — that’s a shame — and that’s stupid and unwise. As long as Ma and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> are here, nothing unpleasant will happen between them and me; I don’t think so. Only it’s certain that Ma simply cannot comprehend that painting is <hi rend="italics">a faith</hi> and that it brings with it <hi rend="italics">the duty</hi> to pay no heed to public opinion — and that in it one conquers by <hi rend="italics">perseverance</hi> and not by <hi rend="italics">giving in</hi>. And — ‘I can’t give you faith’ is also the case between Her Hon. and me — just as it was and remained with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Anyway — I plan to make a start this week on that thing with the peasants around a dish of potatoes in the evening,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> or — perhaps I’ll make daylight of it, or both, or — ‘neither one’ — you’ll say. But should it succeed or should it fail, I’m going to start on the studies for the different figures. Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The previous letter was written on or about 4 April <ref target="let489.xml">(489)</ref>. In the present one Van Gogh says he is still very much affected by ‘what has just happened’ and that he ‘just kept painting these two Sundays’ <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref> – we assume that by the two Sundays he means Easter Sunday and Monday. He also writes that Cor ‘has just’ left <ref target="#l-14">(l. 14)</ref>. Cor was due to be admitted as a member of the congregation at the church on Easter Sunday, 5 April. It is likely that he left on Easter Monday. In view of these considerations, we have dated the letter Monday, 6 April 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The death of Mr van Gogh <ref target="let486.xml">(486)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>At this time, Easter Monday was regarded as a ‘Sunday’, a Christian holiday on which all sorts of festivities were organized. See J. ter Gouw, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De volksvermaken</hi>. Haarlem 1871, pp. 205-218.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This enclosed sketch of a man’s head is not known, nor is the painting after which it was made. It is therefore no longer possible to identify which of the surviving heads this is.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh painted <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of apples</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2529">F 99 / JH 930</rs>) over the painting after which the enclosed sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Honesty in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_143">F - / JH 726</rs>) was done (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-5">see n. 5</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo had taken <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Honesty in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2491">F 76 / JH 542</rs>) with him; it measures 42.5 x 32.5 cm; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let489.xml#n-4">see letter 489, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The still life with honesty, tobacco pouch and a pipe can be seen on an X-ray of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of apples</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2529">F 99 / JH 930</rs>); it measures 45.0 x 60.4 cm. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2134">Ill. 2134</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 76-77, 177 (ill.).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> was an apprentice at Haverkamp Begemann’s machine works; he also boarded there: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let443.xml#n-3">see letter 443, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh said this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let479.xml">letter 479</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan van Gogh</rs> wrote about this to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423 bio.xml#_853">Uncle Vincent and Aunt Cornelie</rs>: ‘Vincent told me and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Stricker</rs> of his intention not to live with his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> any longer, but to settle by himself in the village. He also discussed the matter with his brother Theo, and will now, I think, go to the house where he was previously already accustomed to do his drawing and painting. Vincent was of the opinion that by doing so he would avoid all the difficulties with his sister.’ A piece has been cut out of the letter at this point. (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum Documentation, bd 16, undated letter, but written shortly after 1 April; Nebbeling/Weenink Ladies Collection, De Bilt). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-9">n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> later wrote to her friend <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_129">Line Kruysse</rs> about this incident with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>: ‘[Vincent’s] disappointments often embittered him and made him not a normal person. That was a difficult thing for my parents, who could not always follow him and often misunderstood him. My <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> was a stickler for the proper form, and he [Vincent] never concerned himself with all that; naturally that often caused clashes, and neither of the parties readily forgot words that were spoken in anger. So for the last eight years Vincent had been a problem to many people, and because of the outward appearances they all too often forgot the great deal of good that was in him. The last few years he worked at home with us; after my father’s death Anna thought it would be more peaceful for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> if he were not to live at home any longer and contrived that he left us. He took that so badly that we have heard nothing from him since then and we only know about him through Theo. I do so hope that he will gradually forget his grievances, for it is such a sad relationship, and something like this so easily leads to discord’ (FR b4536. Breda, 26 August 1886).</p>

<p rend="indent">In a memoir of her sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs>, Anna wrote (probably in 1923): ‘The summer that Pa died I spent several weeks at the parsonage with the two children and the nursemaid, and I saw and noticed a great deal that was bad. He gave in to all his desires, and spared nothing and no one. How Pa must have suffered. Although I, too, admire his art, I despise his person. Theo must also have suffered so much’ (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum Documentation, bd57).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This plan did not go ahead: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> did not go to live in Leiden until 1889; she left Nuenen on 30 March 1886 and went to Breda first. Her daughter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> lived in Leiderdorp, near Leiden.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Cf. Luke 9:62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh derived this from what <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Jean Gigoux</rs> says about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi> (Gigoux 1885, p. 68). Van Gogh refers to it again in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let515.xml">letter 515</ref>. Theo had sent Vincent the book, which contains numerous anecdotes about artists: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let485.xml">see letters 485</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let492.xml">492</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Gij moet ze toch laten zien’ (you must show them anyway).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘afschrikt’ (put off).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>On the day of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>’s death Theo had withdrawn 1000 francs from his current account (FR b2123).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>By ‘settling affairs’ Vincent means winding up <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>’s estate. A minister’s widow was entitled to go on living in the parsonage for a year – but it was necessary to determine the size of the estate (see exhib. cat. ’s-Hertogenbosch 1987, pp. 86-89). The ‘f’ must refer to francs, not guilders.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh did cede his share of the inheritance; interestingly, in March 1889 it was these very ‘youngsters’ – <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> – who made their shares available to Vincent when he was ill (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let506.xml#n-21">see letter 506, n. 21</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let749.xml#n-1">letter 749, n. 1</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>This is the first specific mention of Van Gogh’s plan to paint potato eaters. Given the use of the words ‘that thing’, Vincent must have discussed it with Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    