<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 2 June 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let506"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b448 V/1962 and b446 c V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>506</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>410</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>509</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-06-02">on or about Tuesday, 2 June 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0448" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0448" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000599_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0446 c" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0446 c" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000597_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor de spoedige zending van het geld voor deze maand. Hetgeen ge schrijft over ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> de aanmerking die zij maakten<c type="kk">/</c> Portier &amp; Serret<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat zij toch er goede dingen in vonden<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik content over<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zelf heb er ook critiek op en serieuser dan de hunnen – dat van de torsen<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – dus ik begeer niet dat zij het geheel zouden goedkeuren. Als ge hun eens spreekt<c type="kk">/</c> zeg hun dan eens dat het best wezen kan ik terugkom van de koper- en groene zeep<c type="shy">-</c>achtige toonen van nu<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat dit terugkomen er van <hi rend="italics">hoop ik</hi> <hi>tweeledig</hi> zal wezen<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat ik er sommigen hoop te schilderen in lichter gamma<c type="kk">/</c> meer vleesch en bloed – maar evenzeer zoek naar iets dat <hi rend="italics">nog meer</hi> groene zeep- en koperachtig is<c type="kp">_</c> In de werkelijkheid zie ik dagelijks in de sombere hutten effekten tegen ’t licht in of s’avonds in de schemering<c type="kk">/</c> die zóó curieus zijn dat tot nog toe mijn werk me nog te licht voorkomt voor die effekten in kwestie<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. die ik vergelijk bij groene zeep en de koperkleur van een versleten 10 centime stuk<c type="kk">/</c> faute de mieux<c type="kk">/</c> en ze met die kleuren schilder<c type="kk">/</c> faute de mieux. Maar ik wou dat ik ook aan den somberen kant slaagde. waar ik al meer over heb gesproken: le paysan peint avec la terre qu’il ensemence<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik hoop deze week aan Uw adres te verzenden een kistje gemerkt <hi rend="italics">V2</hi><c type="kk">/</c> inhoudende</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">1 Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> la chaumière<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">1 aquarel d<hi rend="super">o</hi><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">1   ,,    Vente pour cause de démolition<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">12 Etudes peintes<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">bij laatst genoemden zult ge een kop vinden dien ik onwillekeurig schilderde na het lezen van Germinal<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">“Est ce que je t’ai conté comment elle est morte? Qui donc? Ma femme là-bas en Russie. Etienne eut un geste vague, étonné du tremblement de la voix, de ce besoin de confidence, chez ce garçon impassible d’habitude<c type="kk">/</c> dans son détachement stoïque des autres &amp; de lui-même<c type="kp">_</c> il savait seulement que la femme c’était une maîtresse et qu’on l’avait pendue à Moscou.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Souvarine reprit: – le dernier jour sur la place j’étais là... il pleuvait – les maladroits perdaient la tête, dérangés par la pluie battante<c type="kp">_</c>– ils avaient mis 20 minutes pour en pendre 4 autres. Elle était debout à attendre. Elle ne me voyait pas<c type="kk">/</c> elle me cherchait dans la foule<c type="kp">_</c> Je suis monté sur une borne et elle m’a vu, nos yeux ne se sont plus quittés<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Deux fois, j’ai eu envie de crier, de m’élancer par-dessus les têtes, pour la rejoindre. Mais à quoi bon, un homme de moins<c type="kk">/</c> un soldat de moins<c type="kk">/</c> et je devinais bien qu’elle me disait non<c type="kk">/</c> de ses grands yeux fixes<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’elle rencontrait les miens”.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ge zult er een variatie bij vinden – profiel – een fonds van: “la plaine rase des champs de betteraves sous la nuit sans étoiles<c type="kk">/</c> d’une obscurité et d’une épaisseur d’encre”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Daartegen uit een kop van een “herscheuse” – of sclôneuse met iets als een koe die loeit<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Wat expressie aangaat – een individu uit: – la campagne était grosse d’une race d’hommes qui poussaient<c type="kk">/</c> une armee noire<c type="kk">/</c> vengeresse<c type="kk">/</c> qui germait lentement dans les sillons – grandissant pour la recolte des siècles futurs et dont la germinaison allait bientôt faire éclater la terre.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Doch de expressie van dat laatste is m.i. beter in de studie welke ik gemerkt heb en die ik maakte nog <hi rend="italics">vóór</hi> ik ’t las<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">zonder om Germinal te denken dus</hi><c type="kk">/</c> eenvoudig een boerin die van ’t aardappel zetten terug kwam nog vol stof van den akker.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik ben eigentlijk van plan om ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van de hut nog eens te herhalen<c type="kp">_</c> Het geval trof mij buitengewoon<c type="kk">/</c> die twee hutten half vergaan onder één zelfde rietdak deden mij denken aan een paar oude afgeleefde luidjes die maar één wezen uitmaken en die men elkaar ziet steunen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">want ge ziet<c type="kk">/</c> het zijn twee woningen en de schouw is dubbel. Dat ziet men trouwens hier telkens<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik heb den tijd niet<c type="kk">/</c> anders zou ik heel veel willen zeggen van Germinal<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik prachtig vind.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Een passage toch: du pain! du pain! du pain! Imbéciles! répéta M. Hennebeau, est ce que je suis heureux? une colère le soulevait contre ces gens qui ne comprenaient pas. Il leur en aurait fait cadeau volontiers, de ses gros appointements, pour avoir, comme eux, le cuir dur, l’accouplement facile et sans regret. Que ne pouvait-il les asseoir à sa table, les empâter de son faisan tandis qu’il irait forniquer derrière les haies, culbuter des filles, en se moquant de ceux qui les avaient culbutés avant lui! Il aurait tout donné, son éducation, son bien-être, son luxe, sa puissance de directeur, s’il avait pu être, une journée, le dernier des misérables qui lui obéissaient, libre de sa chair, assez goujat pour gifler sa femme et prendre du plaisir sur les voisines. Et il souhaitait aussi de crever de faim, d’avoir le ventre vide, l’estomac tordu de crampes ébranlant le cerveau d’un vertige: peutêtre cela aurait-il tué l’éternelle douleur. Ah! vivre en brute<c type="kk">/</c> ne rien posséder à soi, battre les blés avec la hercheuse la plus laîde, la plus sâle et être capable de s’en contenter.– Imbeciles<c type="kk">/</c> ces songe creux de revolutionnaires<c type="kk">/</c> ils élargiraient même le malheur de la terre – ils feraient un jour hurler jusqu’aux chiens de desespoir<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’ils les auraient sortis de la tranquille <hi rend="italics">satisfaction</hi> des instincts<c type="kk">/</c> pour les hausser à la souffrance <hi rend="italics">inassouvie</hi> des passions.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Wat nu betreft ’t geen ge over Portier schrijft<c type="kk">/</c> “hij is misschien meer enthousiast dan koopman”<c type="kk">/</c> en dat ge betwijfelt of hij met mijn werk iets doen kan<c type="kk">/</c> me dunkt dat noch gij noch ik noch hij op ’t moment dat al kunnen beslissen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Maar als ge hem ziet<c type="kk">/</c> zeg hem eens franchement dat mijn idee is<c type="kk">/</c> ik – als ik<c type="kk">/</c> na de sympathie welke hij uitte aangaande mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> mijn uiterste best doe om te sturen en dus voet bij stek houd – bepaald er op reken dat hij met standvastigheid mijn werk zal laten zien. Zeg hem dat mijn idee is dat een gedeelte van ’t publiek te Parijs niet op den duur dupe is van conventie<c type="kk">/</c> hoe verleidelijk ook<c type="kk">/</c> maar integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> dat ’t geen<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> ’t meest stof van de hutten of van ’t veld nog in zit<c type="kk">/</c> ’k weet zelf niet waarom of hoe<c type="kk">/</c> er enkele zeer trouwe vrienden vindt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Dat hij dus niet gaauw den moed moet opgeven want dat gij en ik gecombineerd<c type="kk">/</c> het hem niet kwalijk zullen nemen als ’t langeren of korteren tijd mislukt<c type="kk">/</c> doch dat hij maar moet doorgaan met laten kijken. en dat ik zal doorgaan met sturen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Dat als hij me eens zijn aanmerkingen schrijven wil<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof dat ze mij nuttig zullen zijn. en hij zich niet moet geneeren. Ik voeg hier nog bij dat ik soms wel eens heel erg verlangen kan de Louvre en Luxembourg eens terug te zien en dat ik de techniek en kleur van Millet<c type="kk">/</c> Delacroix<c type="kk">/</c> Corot en anderen<c type="kk">/</c> vroeger of later nog wel eens dien te bestudeeren<c type="kp">_</c> Onmiddelijke haast is daar echter geenszins mede mijns inziens<c type="kk">/</c> hoe meer ik werk hoe meer ik er aan hebben zal <hi rend="italics">als</hi> het eens gebeuren kan. Het is maar<c type="kk">/</c> men heeft <hi rend="italics">en</hi> de natuur <hi rend="italics">en</hi> de schilderijen noodig. Het is vooral die kwestie van de gamma waar ze in gezet zijn en het breken en tegen elkaar over stellen der kleuren<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik dagelijks over denk<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Is de maand mei van L’Lhermitte er reeds.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Ingevolge van ’t postscriptum van uw brief ben ik dadelijk weer eens t’huis aangegaan en van tijd tot tijd zal ik dat ook geregeld volhouden<c type="kk">/</c> al is ’t mijn voornemen bepaald niet om het druk te maken. Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Ik weet niet of gij hebt opgemerkt dat er een heel klein woordje over “enthousiasme” staat in de artikels van Mantz<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> hoe verder er iets staat van “le grain de folie qui est <hi rend="italics">le meilleur</hi> de l’art”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik weet dat gij schreeft “hij is misschien meer enthousiast dan koopman<c type="kk">/</c> wat misschien beter is”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Dus dat is van uw kant zachtmoedig genoeg gezegd<c type="kp">_</c> Ik voor mij denk dat enthousiasme gansch niet onvereenigbaar is met handelaar zijn echter<c type="kp">_</c>– En herinner U eenvoudig aan Mouret en Bourdoncle<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Mantz spreekt ook heel even en heel diep raak over “cette maladie qu’on appelle la sagesse”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Wat zal ik U zeggen – de toekomst en ondervinding zal het nog wel eens zeggen – dat waar ik geen geschikte woorden voor vinden kan<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik bedoel – dat enthousiasme soms beter rekent dan zelfs de rekenaars die er zich “boven verheven” achten. En instinkt – inspiratie – impulsie – geweten – juister geleiden dan velen wel denken. En wat er ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij ben het er mee eens<c type="kk">/</c> mieux vaut crever de passion que de crever d’ennui.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Het is toch iets zonderlings dat ik nog steeds uw tegenwoordige zienswijs <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> als uw <hi rend="italics">definitieve</hi> beschouw<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Deze week kwam het stuk betreffende de nalatenschap<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-21"/> ik heb me gehouden aan wat ik toen dadelijk heb gezegd<c type="kp">_</c>– Moe scheen het op haar naam te willen doch daar kan ik niets aan doen – ik heb me gehouden aan wat ik gezegd heb.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Er komt nu naar ik verneem eene dame inwonen<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> – ge begrijpt wel dat het noch voor hun pleizierig is ik er dikwijls kom<c type="kk">/</c> noch voor mij om er dikwijls heen te gaan. Een enkele keer van tijd tot tijd is voldoende. Ik vind hen (ik weet – tegen uw opinie in en tegen hun eigen opinie) te huis zeer verre<c type="kk">/</c> zeer verre van opregt<c type="kk">/</c> en waar bovendien ik nog meer andere dingen er op tegen heb om <hi rend="italics">m.i.</hi> gegronde redenen, vind ik het overlijden van Pa en de schikking betreffende de nalatenschap een punt waarop ik heel bedaard me er uit retireeren kan. waar ik voorzie de karakters van de 3 zusters (alle drie) met der tijd er niet beter op zullen worden maar wel erger en me nu althans ten eenemale onsympathiek zijn. Herinner U met hoeveel sympathie ik U over Wil heb geschreven tijdens de ziekte van Moe<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Welnu het is een zoo korte vlaag geweest – en het is weer bevroren<c type="kp">_</c>– Hebt ge “l’Évangéliste” van Daudet wel eens gelezen?<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Indien ja – dan vindt ge daar beter woorden voor wat ik zeggen wil dan de mijnen.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Ik zie wel gij Uw best doet om ons te verzoenen<c type="kk">/</c> doch mijn beste kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik wensch haar immers geen kwaad toe en ik doe hun immers geen kwaad. Alleen ik begeer niet invloed op hun uit te oefenen<c type="kk">/</c> daar zij zelve vooreerst niet begrijpen maar tweedens ook niet willen begrijpen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">De oude toren wordt volgende week afgebroken! de spits is er reeds af – ik ben aan een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> er van bezig.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> De figuren begin ik in deze nieuwe teekeningen met den romp en het komt mij voor zij daardoor voller en breeder worden. Als 50 niet genoeg is zal ik er 100 teekenen en als ’t dan niet genoeg is nog meer<c type="kk">/</c> tot ik solide heb wat ik wil<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk dat alles rond is en er als ’t ware begin noch eind ergens aan den vorm is doch die één harmonisch levend geheel uitmaakt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Ge weet dat dit juist die kwestie is waarover sprake was in ’t boek van Gigoux<c type="kk">/</c> “ne pas prendre par la ligne mais par le milieu”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Mantz zegt: le modelé est la probité de l’art<c type="kk">/</c> en wat hij verandert aan ’t woord van Ingres is dat Ingres zeide “le dessin est la probité de l’art” en er bijvoegde<c type="kk">/</c> je voudrais marquer le contour d’un fil de fer<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> Hebert had wat hij noemde “l’horreur de la ligne”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-28"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">En dan zijn er ook weer lui die beweeren dat alle dogma’s uit den aard der zaak absurd zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Jammer dat dit juist ook weer zelf een dogma is<c type="kp">_</c>– Men moet het dus maar doen zoo als men het doet<c type="kk">/</c> zien er iets van te maken<c type="kk">/</c> zoeken het te laten leven<c type="kp">_</c> Als men Thijs Maris niet te beroerd en te melankoliek gemaakt had om te werken<c type="kk">/</c> misschien had hij iets verbazends gevonden<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-29"/> Ik denk zoo dikwijls om dien kerel Theo<c type="kk">/</c> want wat is zijn werk wonderbaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Het is droomerij – maar wat een meester! God! als die kerel nu eens was zooals hij begon! wat zou hij een centrum worden!– Want de Hollandsche school van nu heeft het noodig dat er nieuwen bij komen die iets kunnen<c type="kp">_</c> Men moet niet werken “<hi rend="italics">in duizend vreezen</hi>”<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> en dat doen er velen die zóó in angst zijn om hun toonen en kleuren te snappen dat door den angst zelf zij laauw water<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> worden. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> en dat doen de eigentlijke lui<c type="kk">/</c> Israels of Maris of Mauve of Neuhuys<c type="kk">/</c> heel anders want die zeggen “smeer het er maar op”. Welnu – omdat men enthousiasme heeft uitgedoofd zal men “faire hurler jusqu’aux chiens de désespoir”<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> als niemand meer enthousiasme heeft en niemand meer robust durft. We zijn nog zoover niet – dat weet ik<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zeg maar – laat het enthousiasme blijven want anders bereiken wij dat maximum van wijsheid dat <hi rend="italics">pruiketijd</hi> heet<c type="kp">_</c> Men hoeft de geschiedenis van de oude schilderscholen maar na te gaan om te zien dat het zoo gaan kan. Wat was artikel 4 van Mantz – het laatste<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> – ernstig en bitter en net wat noodig is<c type="kp">_</c>– Let vooral op de L’Hermittes als zij uitkomen. Wat is dat mooi. Ik heb tante Cornelie even gesproken<c type="kk">/</c> die beweerde gij zeker dezen zomer nog kwaamt<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-32"/> ik zal tegen dien tijd heel wat figuren geteekend hebben zoo als ik er nu mee ben begonnen. Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for sending the money for this month so promptly. I’m satisfied with what you write about the painting,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> the comments that they made, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1354">Serret</rs>, but that they still found good things in it. I myself have criticisms of it, and more serious ones than theirs — that about the torsos<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — so I don’t wish them to approve of the whole. When you speak to them, just tell them that it may very well be that I draw back from the present copper and green soap-like tones, but that this drawing back will, <hi rend="italics">I hope</hi>, be <hi>twofold</hi>, namely that I hope to paint some in a lighter spectrum, more flesh and blood — but equally am searching for something that’s <hi rend="italics">even more</hi> green soap and coppery. In reality, every day in the gloomy cottages I see effects against the light or in the evenings in the dusk that are <hi rend="italics">so</hi> curious that so far my work still seems to me too light for the effects in question, that is, those I compare to green soap and the copper-colour of a worn 10-centime piece, for want of anything better, and paint them with those colours, for want of anything better. But I wanted to succeed on the gloomy side too. What I’ve talked about before: the peasant painted with the soil he sows.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">This week I hope to send to your address a little crate marked <hi rend="italics">V2</hi>, containing</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">1 painting, The cottage<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">1 watercolour ditto<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">1 ,, Auction because of demolition<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">12 painted studies<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">among the latter you’ll find a head that I couldn’t help painting after reading Germinal.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">‘Did I tell you how she died? Who do you mean? My wife, over there in Russia. Etienne made a vague gesture, surprised at the trembling of the voice, at that need to confide, in this usually impassive youth with his stoical detachment from others and from himself. He knew only that the wife was a mistress, and that she had been hanged in Moscow.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Souvarine went on: on the last day, in the square, I was there... It was raining — the bunglers were losing their nerve, put off by the torrential rain. They had taken 20 minutes to hang 4 other people. She was standing waiting. She couldn’t see me, she was looking for me in the crowd. I stood up on a stone bollard and she saw me, and we did not take our eyes off one another again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Twice I wanted to shout out, to throw myself over people’s heads in order to reach her. But what was the point, one man less, one soldier less, and I could clearly see that she was saying “no”, with her great steady eyes, when she met mine’.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You’ll find a variation among them — profile — a background of: ‘the flat expanse of fields of beet under the starless night sky, as dark and thick as ink’.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Standing out against this the head of a female coal-pit drawer — or female thrutcher with something of a cow that’s lowing.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> As to expression — an individual from: — The land was big with a race of men growing like crops, a black avenging army slowly germinating in the furrows — growing taller to be harvested in future centuries and whose germination would soon make the earth explode.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Yet to my mind the expression of that last is better in the study that I’ve marked, and which I made <hi rend="italics">before</hi> I read it, <hi rend="italics">in other words without thinking about Germinal</hi>, simply a peasant woman who came back from planting potatoes, still covered in dust from the field.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I’m actually planning to repeat the painting of the cottage once more. The thing struck me greatly; those two cottages, half decayed under one and the same thatched roof, reminded me of a couple of worn-out old folk who make up just one single being and whom one sees supporting each other.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">For you see, they are two dwellings and the chimney is double. One sees that here a lot, by the way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t have time, otherwise I’d like to say a very great deal about Germinal, which I think splendid.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Just one more passage: bread! bread! bread! Fools! repeated M. Hennebeau, am I happy? He was stirred to anger against these people who did not understand. He would gladly have made them a gift of his high salary, in order to have, like them, a thick skin, an easy way of mating, with no regrets. Why could he not sit them down at his table, fatten them on his pheasant while he went off to fornicate behind hedges, tumbling lasses while jeering at those who had tumbled them before him! He would have given everything, his up-bringing, his comforts, his wealth, the power of his position as manager, if one day he could have been the lowest of the wretches who obeyed his orders, free in his fleshly existence, enough of a boor to slap his wife and take his pleasure with the neighbour-women. And he also wished to be starving with hunger, to have an empty belly, a stomach knotted with cramps that made him dizzy in the head; perhaps that would have killed the interminable pain. Ah! to live like a beast, to possess nothing of one’s own, to flatten the corn with the ugliest, dirtiest female coal-pit drawer, and to be able to be happy with that. Fools, these head-in-the-air revolutionaries; they would actually increase the world’s misery — they would one day make the very dogs howl with despair, when they had brought them out of the peaceful <hi rend="italics">satisfaction </hi>of their instincts, in order to raise them to the <hi rend="italics">unsatiated</hi> suffering of the passions.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Now as to what you write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs>, ‘he is perhaps more of an enthusiast than a salesman’, and that you doubt whether he can do anything with my work, it seems to me that neither you, nor I, nor he can already decide that at the moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">But when you see him, just tell him frankly that my idea is — if, after the sympathy which he expressed concerning my work, I do my utmost to send work and thus stick to my guns — I’m certainly counting on his persevering in showing my work. Tell him that my idea is that in the long run a part of the public in Paris won’t be fooled by convention, however seductive, but on the contrary that that which still has in it the most dust from the cottages or from the field will, I don’t know how or why myself, find a few very loyal friends.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">That he must therefore not lose heart too soon, because you and I combined won’t take it amiss of him should it not succeed for a longer or shorter time, but that he must just go on showing. And that I’ll go on sending.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">That if he would write down his comments for me, I believe they’ll be useful to me. And he mustn’t be embarrassed. I add here, too, that I can sometimes very much long to see the Louvre and the Luxembourg once again, and that sooner or later I really should study the technique and colour of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> and others. There’s absolutely no immediate hurry, though, to my mind; the more I work the more benefit I’ll derive from it <hi rend="italics">if</hi> it can happen sometime. It’s just that one needs <hi rend="italics">both</hi> nature <hi rend="italics">and</hi> paintings. It’s above all the question of the spectrum in which they’re set, and the breaking and opposing of colours, which I think about every day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>’s month of May out already?<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> In accordance with the postscript to your letter, I called in at home again straightaway, and I’ll also keep it up regularly from time to time, although it certainly isn’t my intention to go there often. Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I don’t know whether you noticed that there’s a tiny bit about ‘enthusiasm’ in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs>’s articles,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> how there’s also something about ‘the grain of madness that is <hi rend="italics">the best</hi> of art’.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I know that you wrote ‘he is perhaps more of an enthusiast than a salesman, which is perhaps better’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">So that’s said mildly enough on your part. For my part, though, I think that enthusiasm is certainly not irreconcilable with being a dealer. And simply remind you of Mouret and Bourdoncle.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs> also speaks very briefly and profoundly to the point about ‘this illness that they call good sense’.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">What shall I say to you? — some day the future and experience will say — what I can’t find the right words for. I mean — that enthusiasm sometimes counts for more than even the calculating types who consider themselves ‘above it all’. And instinct — inspiration — impulse — conscience — guide more truly than many people think. And be that as it may, for my part I agree with it, better to die of passion than to die of boredom.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> It’s really curious that I still do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> regard your current view as your <hi rend="italics">final</hi> one.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">The document about the estate came this week.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> I’ve stuck to what I said straightaway at the time. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> appeared to want it in her name, but I can’t do anything about that — I’ve stuck to what I said.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">I hear that a lady is coming to lodge<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> — you’ll understand that it’s not pleasant for them if I’m there often, nor for me to go there often. Occasionally, from time to time, is sufficient. I find them at home (I know — contrary to your opinion and contrary to their own opinion) very far, very far from sincere, and since there are moreover several other things I can’t stand with good reasons, <hi rend="italics">I believe</hi>, I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s death and the settlement of the estate is a point at which I can withdraw very calmly, since I foresee that the characters of the 3 sisters (all three) will get worse not better with time, and to me at least they’re utterly disagreeable as it is. You remember with how much warmth I wrote to you about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> when Ma was ill.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Well now, it’s been such a short burst — and it’s frozen again. Have you ever read ‘L’évangéliste’ by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>?<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> If you have — then you’ll find better words in it than mine for what I’m saying.
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I can see that you’re doing your best to reconcile us, but my dear chap, I really don’t wish her any harm, and I really don’t do them any harm. Only I don’t want to exert any influence on them, since firstly they don’t understand themselves, but secondly don’t want to understand either.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">The old tower is being pulled down next week! The spire’s already off — I’m working on a painting of it.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> In these new drawings I’m starting the figures with the torso, and it seems to me that they’re fuller and broader as a result. If 50 aren’t enough, I’ll draw 100 of them, and if that’s still not enough, even more, until I’ve got what I want solidly, that’s to say that everything is round, and there is as it were neither beginning nor end anywhere on the form, but it constitutes a single, harmonious, living whole.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">You know that this is precisely the question that was discussed in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Gigoux</rs>’s book, ‘do not start from the line but from the middle’.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs> says: modelling is the integrity of art, and what he changes in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1102">Ingres</rs>’s words is that Ingres said, ‘drawing is the integrity of art’, and added, I would like to show the outline of a wire.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/> Hebert had what he called ‘a horror of the line’.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">And then there are also fellows who maintain that all dogmas are absurd by the very nature of the thing. Pity that this is just another dogma itself. One simply has to do it as one does it, take care to make something of it, seek to get it to live. If people hadn’t made <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs> too wretched and too melancholy to work, perhaps he would have found something amazing.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> I think about that chap so often, Theo, for his work is truly marvellous.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">It’s a pipe dream — but what a master! God! If only that chap was still as he was when he began! What a focus he would become! For the present-day Dutch school needs new people who can do something in order to come along. One shouldn’t work <hi rend="italics">in the grip of fear</hi>, and many do, who are so anxious to understand their tones and colours that the fear itself makes them insipid. Well, the real fellows, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Maris</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_154 bio.xml#_1248">Neuhuys</rs>, do that very differently, for they say ‘just slap it on’. Well then — because people have snuffed out enthusiasm, they’ll ‘make the dogs howl with despair’<ptr target="#note-t-30"/> when no one has any enthusiasm left and no one dares to be robust any more. We’re not at that point yet — I know that, but I’m just saying — let’s retain enthusiasm, for otherwise we’ll achieve that maximum of wisdom that’s called the <hi rend="italics">periwig age</hi>. One only has to look at the history of the old schools of painting to see that this can happen. How serious and bitter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs>’s article 4 — the last one<ptr target="#note-t-31"/> — was, and just what’s needed. Look out particularly for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>s when they come out. How fine they are. I spoke to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Aunt Cornelie</rs> briefly; she insisted that you would certainly be coming this summer.<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> By then I’ll have drawn a great many figures in the way I’ve now begun. Regards.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo ‘for sending the money for this month so promptly’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). In view of the comments about the reactions to Vincent’s work, this must have been the month of June. The second sheet cannot possibly have been written before Monday, 1 June 1885 since there is a reference in it to an article that had appeared in <hi rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> on Sunday, 31 May and had been sent to Nuenen (see <hi rend="italics">Arrangement</hi>). We have therefore dated the letter on or about Tuesday, 2 June 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The second sheet was previously placed with <ref target="let502.xml">letter 502</ref> of about 22 May 1884. However, Van Gogh refers in it to ‘article 4’ by Paul Mantz <ref target="#l-252">(ll. 252-253)</ref>, which was not published until 31 May 1885. Since he moreover goes back to a line from the Zola passage he quotes in the present letter <hi rend="italics">and</hi> repeats ‘more of an enthusiast than a salesman’ (see <ref target="#l-102">ll. 102-103</ref> and <ref target="#l-148">ll. 148-149</ref>), we assume that this sheet must have been part of <ref target="let506.xml">letter 506</ref>. See also exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 191 (n. 1).</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Portier’s opinion of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let494.xml">(494)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2510">F 82 / JH 764</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had already pointed this out about the torsos in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let502.xml">letter 502</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh took this expression from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238"><hi rend="italics">La vie et l’oeuvre de J.F. Millet</hi></ref>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let495.xml#n-9">see letter 495, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This watercolour of a cottage is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sale of building scrap</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2511">F 1230 / JH 770</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
      
<p>It is impossible to establish exactly which 12 painted studies these are. There were in any event some heads among them; Van Gogh had previously written that he had finished seven (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let505.xml">letter 505</ref>). They probably included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman (Gordina de Groot)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2515">F 141 / JH 783</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2516">F 86 / JH 785</rs>) (see <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-10">nn. 10</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-12">12</ref>), and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a man</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2495">F 163 / JH 687</rs>). It is not clear whether <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2514">F 388r / JH 782</rs>) was also part of the shipment. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 239.</p>

<p rend="indent">It also appears that as well as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>) there was another cottage – this painting was roughly the same size as <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>, which measures 64 x 78 cm (according to <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let513.xml">letter 513</ref>). Two cottages that could fit the bill are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cottage and woman with a goat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3025">F 90 / JH 823</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cottage with a man coming home</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2520">F 170 / JH 824</rs>), which measure 60 x 85 and 64 x 76 cm respectively. Since Van Gogh later wrote that he had another four cottages this size (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let513.xml">letter 513</ref>), it is not possible to make a precise identification.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Taken, with some discrepancies, from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi> (see Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, p. 1525).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Taken from the opening sentence of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The terms ‘herscheuse’ and ‘sclôneuse’ (terms for women who worked in the pits) are found in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi>; Van Gogh also used them in his Borinage period. The description must refer to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2516">F 86 / JH 785</rs>). See also Sund 1992, p. 98.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>These are the closing lines of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi> (see Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, p. 1591).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman (Gordina de Groot)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2515">F 141 / JH 783</rs>); Van Gogh ‘marked’ (signed) this painting in the upper left corner. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let505.xml">letter 505</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>This is probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_965">F 92a / JH 806</rs>) in which the cottage also has two doors. The tree in the foreground does not, however, appear in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Taken from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi> (see Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, pp. 1439-1440). The word ‘Imbeciles’ he wrote in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-97">l. 97</ref> is not in the original text, and Van Gogh omitted several lines after ‘révolutionnaires’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-98">(l. 98)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘datgene waar’ (that which).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le mois de Marie à Chartèves</hi>, planned for the month of May in the series ‘Les mois rustiques’, was unexpectedly dropped. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let502.xml#n-19">See letter 502, n. 19.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh is referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Paul Mantz</rs>’s  article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_582">Le Salon <hi>iv</hi></ref>’ about the Salon in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> of 31 May 1885. Mantz writes: ‘Mr Lucas is perhaps an enthusiast’ (M. Lucas est peut-être un enthousiaste); a little later he talks about ‘enthusiastic fervour and luminous architecture’ (des élans enthousiastes et des architectures lumineuses) (p. 1).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>In ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_582">Le Salon <hi>ii</hi></ref>’, published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> of 17 May 1885, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs> says at the end of his discussion of Rochegrosse: ‘He preserved that which was best in his art and in ours, a grain of madness’ (Il garderait ce qu’il y a de meilleur dans son art et dans le nôtre, un grain de folie) (p. 2).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Mouret and Bourdoncle are characters in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_275">Au bonheur des dames</ref></hi>: Van Gogh contrasted them in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let464.xml">letter 464</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>This quote in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> of 17 May 1885, p. 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>A quotation from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_275">Au bonheur des dames</ref></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let464.xml#n-12">see letter 464, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            
      
<p>This inventory was drawn up on 21 May by the notary Abraham Schutjes of Nuenen. Van Gogh relinquished his share of the estate: as it says in the deed, he had ‘withdrawn during the inventorization without giving reason therefor’. See exhib. cat. ’s-Hertogenbosch 1987, pp. 86-89 (quotation on p. 89) and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let490.xml#n-14">see letters 490, n. 14</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let749.xml#n-1">749, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>We do not know who this was.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>’s exemplary care of her <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let432.xml">letter 432</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_384">L’évangéliste</ref></hi>, a novel about hypocrisy and deceit: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let464.xml#n-14">letter 464, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>). This was also enclosed (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let507.xml">see letter 507</ref>). On the demolition of this tower: De Brouwer 2000.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Gigoux</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let494.xml#n-2">see letter 494, n. 2.</ref> Van Gogh formulates this endeavour anew in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let508.xml">letter 508</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs> says in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> of 31 May 1885 (‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_582">Le Salon</ref>’): ‘The public perhaps does not know enough about this honest draughtsman, who, changing Mr <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1102">Ingres</rs>’s words somewhat, would freely admit: modelling is the integrity of painting’ (Le public ne connait peut-être pas assez ce<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>dessinateur loyal, qui, changeant quelque chose au mot de M. Ingres, dirait volontiers: Le modelé est la probité de la peinture) (p. 2).</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh could have derived his knowledge of Ingres from various sources, among them <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1747">Henri Delaborde</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_414">Ingres. Sa vie, ses travaux, sa doctrine, d’après les notes manuscrites et les lettres du maître</ref></hi>. Paris 1870, pp. 123-126, 138-139, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_922">Cassagne</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_212">Traité d’aquarelle</ref></hi> (Cassagne 1875, p. 89). The ‘wire’ (fil de fer) occurs in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_742">Silvestre</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_415">Eugène Delacroix</ref></hi> (Silvestre 1864, p. 38). He also repeated this description in his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_416">Histoire des artistes vivants français et étrangers</ref></hi> (1853) (see Silvestre, Histoire, p. 53). See also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ingres raconté par lui-même et par ses amis – Pensées et écrits du peintre</hi>. 2 vols. Vésenaz-Genève 1947-1948, vol. 1, pp. 56, 60, 76.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>Probably an oral survival; the saying has not been found in writing.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            

<p>The lack of response to his work had caused <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Maris</rs> to turn increasingly in on himself; he had become something of a recluse. Cf. Heijbroek 1975.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Dutch saying; it means: ‘in gevaarvolle situaties, in nood’ (in dangerous situations, in fear).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Means: ‘krachteloos, zonder vuur’ (insipid, without fervour).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>Previously quoted in the passage from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_413">Germinal</ref></hi>: see <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-99">l. 99</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>The last one was published in ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_582">Le Salon <hi>iv</hi></ref>’ as ‘Feuilleton du Temps’ in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Temps</hi> of 31 May 1885; Theo also sent the previous issues of 10 May and 17 May. In his article, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Mantz</rs> is highly critical of the standard of French painting at the Salon; a few portraits are all that receive his approval. He regrets that the art of portraiture, ‘the sublime art’ (l’art superbe) of Raphael, Holbein, Rembrandt and Velázquez, is not valued at its true worth and is regarded as ‘second-rate art’ (art de second rang) when the medals are awarded.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Cornelia van Gogh-Carbentus</rs> had been to see Theo. He wrote to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>: ‘As always, Aunt was very kind to me, she invited me to dine with her in the hotel several times and brought me such nice things’ (FR b901, 19 May 1885).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    