<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 9 June 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let507"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b449 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>507</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>411</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>510</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-06-09">on or about Tuesday, 9 June 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0449 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0449 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000600_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0449 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000601_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000601_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0449 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000601_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000601_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Heden heb ik afgezonden het bewuste kistje<c type="kk">/</c> inhoudende behalve wat ik U reeds schreef nog 1 Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Cimetière de paysans</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik heb eenige details weggelaten – ik heb willen zeggen hoe die ruine aantoont aldaar <hi rend="italics">sedert eeuwen</hi> de boeren ter ruste worden gelegd in de akkers zelve<c type="kk">/</c> welke zij bij hun leven doorwroeten – ik heb willen zeggen hoe doodeenvoudig het sterven &amp; begraven gaat<c type="kk">/</c> doodleuk als ’t afvallen van ’t herfstblad – niets dan een beetje aard omgewoeld – een houten kruisje<c type="kp">_</c> De akkers er om heen – zij maken waar ’t gras van ’t kerkhof eindigt<c type="kk">/</c> over ’t muurtje een laatste lijntje tegen den horizon – als een horizon van een zee. En nu zegt die ruine tot mij hoe een geloof en godsdienst vermolmde<c type="kk">/</c> al was ze hecht gegrondvest – hoe echter het leven &amp; sterven der boertjes al mee ’t zelfde is en blijft<c type="kk">/</c> gelijkmatig uitspruiten en verwelken als ’t gras en de bloempjes die daar wassen op dien kerkhofsgrond. Les religions passent<c type="kk">/</c> Dieu demeure<c type="kk">/</c> is een woord van Victor Hugo<c type="kk">/</c> die ze ook pas begraven hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik weet niet of ge iets in deze twee gevallen vinden zult – de hut met mosdak<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> deed me denken aan een winterkoningennestje<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin ge moet maar eens kijken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu moet ik U bij deze gelegenheid toch nog eens uitleggen – waar ik er nieuwe<c type="kk">/</c> duidelijke woorden voor vond – waarom ik U schreef en schrijf dat ik nog ver van secuur ben of uw tegenwoordige zienswijs uw definitieve overtuiging is.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Het huis G.&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> is geen goede leerschool om schilderijen<c type="kk">/</c> laat staan schilders te leeren kennen. Ik zeg U dit als mijn meening – dat men er niet vrij leert kijken zelfs<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wie hebben ze er groote eer bewezen? Paul Delaroche<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">’k hoef U niet te zeggen hoe Delaroche een van de lui was die bitter slecht steek hielden – er is eenvoudig niemand meer die zijn partij op neemt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Wie ook <hi rend="italics">geen steek houden zal</hi> – al is hij <hi rend="italics">beter</hi> – ofschoon toch eens of twee keer hij iets heel moois maakte – wie ook <hi rend="italics">zakken</hi> zal – dat is – Gerome.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zijn Prisonnier<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> evenwel<c type="kk">/</c> zijn Berger Syrien<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> is <hi rend="italics">gevoeld</hi> en ik vind ze zoo mooi als wie dan ook en van harte en gaarne<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Doch verreweg meestal is hij een Delaroche II<c type="kp">_</c> Elk hunner<c type="kk">/</c> met <hi rend="italics">den lijst</hi><ptr target="#note-t-a"/><hi rend="italics"> van den tijd rekening houdende</hi><c type="kk">/</c> is van gelijke waarde. Wat ik nu beweer is – dat ik het ten allerzeerste waarschijnlijk acht dat de heele entourage u <hi rend="italics">met het jaar meer</hi> <hi>vervelen</hi> zal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat ik verder beweer is dat men én anderen én speciaal ook zich zelven er een slechten dienst mede bewijst zich te vervelen. Bij mij heeft het ondanks veel wijze leeringen er nooit van harte in gewild het zijn goeden<c type="kk">/</c> praktischen kant kan hebben zich “om bestwil” te vervelen. Een MASSA lui nu hebben zich op een leeftijd van ± 30 jaar nog eens herzien en zeer aanmerkelijk gewijzigd.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Denk in zachtmoedigheid hier eens over na – ik zeg U dat van wat ik geleerd heb en gehoord heb bij G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> over kunst <hi>niets</hi> steek hield. Hoe als men omdraait de algemeenheden die daar in tel zijn als doodslaanders om kunst te beoordeelen – 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>n.l. den ouderen of hedendaagschen Delaroche kant op te hemelen en de onregtzinnigen verdacht te maken – als<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> men zekere gezegdes <hi rend="italics">omkeert</hi> dan – haalt men in reiner lucht adem<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin – kerel – er zijn in toestanden en zaken zulke curieuse wendingen mogelijk – niet alleen<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> – maar ook den regel<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is toch mal – dat ik tevens après tout betwijfel of ge in den handel blijft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ge hoeft niet hierop te attendeeren of er op te antwoorden – ik zeg het U als zoo maar eens rondweg mijn idee te uiten<c type="kk">/</c> niet om onvruchtbare woordenwisselingen te beginnen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Maar het is er – une terre enchantée<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – waar men niet vrij is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Enfin – ik hoor wel eens of gij het kistje hebt ontvangen en of ge er iets in vindt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Morgen ga ik schilderen een geval op een ander dorp – ook een hut – in kleiner formaat. Ik heb het ll. Zondag gevonden op een grooten togt die ik in gezelschap van een boerenjongen<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> deed – om een nest van een winterkoninkje magtig te worden<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Wij vonden er <hi rend="italics">6</hi><c type="kk">/</c> het was een plek waar Bodmer mede zou hebben gedweept zonder twijfel.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> En het waren allen nesten waar de jongen reeds uitgevlogen waren zoodat men zonder al te veel gewetensknaging ze mee kon nemen. Het was zoo echt<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb ook nog andere prachtige nesten. Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf eens spoedig<c type="kp">_</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">b. à. t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Vóór ge het aan Portier of Serret laat zien<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik erg graag hebben gij de beide sch<hi rend="super">ijen</hi> een vernis gaaft.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vooral het boerenkerkhof is erg ingeschoten omdat het eerst heel anders op het doek stond en ik het eerste <hi rend="italics">geheel</hi> heb afgeschrapt<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Het was me eerst totaal mislukt – toen heb ik korte wetten gemaakt<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> en van voren af begonnen<c type="kk">/</c> aan een anderen kant gaan zitten en s’morgens geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> vroeg<c type="kk">/</c> in plaats van s’avonds. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> en het andere – dat van de hut – was oorspronkelijk een schaapherder.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> De schapen werden verl. week geschoren<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb ’t gezien – in een schuur op een tafel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Ik ben er blij om dat ik nu deze keer aan Portier weer iets heel anders kan laten kijken. Ik ben overigens druk aan het teekenen om over een tijdje een paar heele figuren te zenden. Doch aan de buitenhuizen – misschien zult ge zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> imitaties van Michel<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> ofschoon ze ’t toch niet zijn – werkende en gevallen zoekende<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik zulke mooie hutten gevonden dat 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>ik nu toch nog een stuk of wat variaties van deze “<hi rend="italics">menschennestjes</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> die me zoo doen denken aan de nesten van winterkoninkjes – moet uithalen<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. ze schilderen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Och – men moet niet twijfelen – wie tegenwoordig de boeren schildert en hart heeft voor zijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> die wint – althans een deel<c type="kk">/</c> en niet het slechtste al is ’t nog niet ’t grootste – van ’t publiek<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Dat neemt niet weg dat mijn einde of tweede helft van de maand – nog al merkwaardig schraal kan uitvallen<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch zulks gebeurt de boerenjongens ook en – ze amuseeren zich toch<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Ik wou ge er Zondag bij waart geweest toen wij dien togt hebben gemaakt. Ik kwam geheel bemodderd terug want wij hadden wel een half uur door een beek moeten baden. Maar ’t schilderen wordt nu voor mij animeerend <hi rend="italics">en</hi> <hi rend="italics">capiteux</hi> als de jagt – het is een jagt dan trouwens ook op modellen en mooie plekken. nogmaals gegroet en ’t beste U toegewenscht.– Het is al laat en ik moet om 5 uur op ’t punt zijn<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> dus – adieu<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Today I sent off that little crate, containing 1 other painting, <hi rend="italics">Peasant cemetery</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> besides what I already told you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve left out some details — I wanted to say how this ruin shows that <hi rend="italics">for centuries</hi> the peasants have been laid to rest there in the very fields that they grubbed up in life — I wanted to say how perfectly simply death and burial happen, coolly as the falling of an autumn leaf — no more than a bit of earth turned over — a little wooden cross. The fields around — where the grass of the churchyard ends, beyond the little wall, they make a last fine line against the horizon — like the horizon of a sea. And now this ruin says to me how a faith and religion mouldered away, although it was solidly founded — how, though, the life and death of the peasants is and will always be the same, springing up and withering regularly like the grass and the flowers that grow there in that churchyard. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, whom they’ve also just buried, said Religions pass, God remains.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I don’t know whether you’ll see anything in these two things — the cottage with the mossy roof<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> reminded me of a wren’s nest. Anyway, you must just look at them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now I must take this opportunity of explaining to you again — which I found new, clear words for — why I wrote and write to you that I’m still far from sure whether your present view is your definite conviction.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> The firm of G&amp;Cie isn’t a good school for getting to know paintings, let alone painters. I tell you this as my opinion — that one doesn’t even learn how to look independently there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Who did they greatly honour? <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Paul Delaroche</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I don’t have to tell you how <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs> was one of the people who really didn’t stand up to scrutiny — there’s simply no one left who takes his part.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Someone else who <hi rend="italics">won’t stand up to scrutiny</hi> — even though he’s <hi rend="italics">better</hi> — although he did make something very fine once or twice — who will also <hi rend="italics">fail</hi> — that is — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">His Prisoner,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> though, his Syrian shepherd<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> are <hi rend="italics">felt</hi>, and I think them as fine as anybody, and readily and willingly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But by far the most often he’s a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs> II. Each of them, <hi rend="italics">taking into account the context of their age</hi>, is of equal worth. What I’m now asserting is — that I consider it highly likely that the whole situation will <hi>bore</hi> you <hi rend="italics">more by the year</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What I further assert is that one does both others and especially oneself too a disservice by being bored. In spite of many wise lessons, I’ve never seriously granted that being bored ‘for one’s own good’ can have its good, practical side. Now a MASS of people have reformed themselves at the age of about 30 and changed very considerably.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Just think calmly about this — I tell you that <hi>nothing</hi> of what I learnt and heard about art at G&amp;Cie stood up to scrutiny. How if one reverses the generalities that count there as the conversation killers in judging art — 
      <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> namely praising the old or present-day <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs> to the skies and discrediting the unorthodox — if, I say, one <hi rend="italics">reverses</hi> certain maxims, then — one takes a breath of fresh air. In short — old chap — such curious turns in situations and affairs are possible — not only that — but even the rule. It’s funny, isn’t it — that, after all, I still doubt whether you’ll stay in the trade.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">You don’t have to take any notice of this or reply to it — I say it to you just to express my idea frankly, not to start futile exchanges of words.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But it’s — an enchanted land<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — where one isn’t free.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Anyway — I’ll hear sometime whether you’ve received the little crate and whether you find anything in it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Tomorrow I’m going to paint a thing in another village — also a cottage — in a smaller size. I found it last Sunday on a long trip I made in the company of a peasant <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_57">boy</rs><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> — in order to get hold of a wren’s nest.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> We found <hi rend="italics">6</hi>; without doubt it was a place that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_867">Bodmer</rs> would have adored.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And they were all nests from which the young had already flown, so that one could take them without too many pangs of conscience. It was so real; I also have some other splendid nests. Regards, write soon, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I’d like you to give both the paintings a varnish before you show them to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1354">Serret</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">The peasant cemetery has sunk in particularly badly, because it was very different on the canvas at first and I scraped the first thing off <hi rend="italics">completely</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> It was a total failure at first — then I gave it short shrift and started from the beginning, went and sat on another side and painted early in the morning instead of in the evening. Well, and the other — the one of the cottage — was originally a shepherd.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> The sheep were shorn last week; I saw it — on a table in a barn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I’m glad that this time I can show <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> something very different again. I’m busy drawing, by the way, so as to send a few full-length figures in a little while. But working on the cottages — perhaps you’ll say imitations of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1228">Michel</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> although they aren’t — and searching for subjects, I’ve found such splendid cottages that 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> I now really must go bird’s nesting with a number of variations of these ‘<hi rend="italics">people’s nests</hi>’, which remind me so much of the nests of wrens — that’s to say, paint them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Oh — one mustn’t doubt — anyone who paints the peasants nowadays and has his heart in his work, he wins — at least a part, and not the worst although it’s not the largest — of the public.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">This doesn’t alter the fact that my end or second half of the month — can still work out remarkably meagre. But the same happens to the peasant lads too, and — they still have fun.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I wish you’d been here on Sunday when we went on that trip. I came back covered in mud because we had to spend a good half hour wading through a stream. But for me painting is now becoming as stimulating <hi rend="italics">and enticing</hi> as hunting — it is a hunt, after all, for models, and beautiful places too. Regards again, and best wishes to you. It’s already late and I have to be at the place<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> at 5 o’clock, so — adieu.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In his previous letter, written on or about Tuesday, 2 June <ref target="let506.xml">(506)</ref>, Van Gogh wrote that he hoped to send a small crate of paintings ‘this week’. This crate was sent, he says here, ‘today’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>). Since he moreover says in <ref target="let508.xml">letter 508</ref>, which dates from Monday, 15 June: ‘In all likelihood you’ll have received the little crate in the last few days’, we have dated the present letter on or about Tuesday, 9 June 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh sends a small crate of paintings to Paris <ref target="let506.xml">(506)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Portier’s opinion of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let494.xml">(494)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>See for the contents of the little crate: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let506.xml#n-4">letter 506, nn. 4</ref><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let506.xml#n-7">-7.</ref> It emerges from the present letter that Van Gogh also added <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs> died on 22 May 1885; on 31 May his body was placed under the Arc de Triomphe and on 1 June he was buried in the Panthéon, watched by large crowds. The newspapers and magazines devoted an extraordinary degree of attention to this story.</p>
      
<p rend="indent">See for this <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">dictum</hi>, taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La sorcière</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let294.xml#n-6">letter 294, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let506.xml">letter 506</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Both <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs> had become big names as a result of Goupil’s promotional activities.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_132">The prisoner</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let418.xml#n-1">letter 418, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>There were two versions of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Jean Léon Gérôme</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le troupeau en marche (Le berger syrien à cheval) </hi>(The flock on the move (The Syrian shepherd on horseback)), 1865, but both have been lost. See Ackerman 1986, pp. 216-217, cat. nos. 153-154. The <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Berger syrien</hi> was no. 357 in Goupil’s series ‘Galerie Photographique’. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_128">Ill. 128</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘het kader, de context’ (the frame of reference, the context).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘en dat niet alleen’ (and not only that).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Most probably an allusion to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_558">Bunyan</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let407.xml#n-4">see letter 407, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This peasant boy was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_57">Driek Dekkers</rs>. See De Brouwer 1984, pp. 92, 109.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>There are several eyewitness accounts by boys whom Van Gogh paid to get bird’s nests for him at this time, including those of the said <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_57">Driek Dekkers</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_108">Piet van Hoorn</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs> and Vincent’s sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Elisabeth</rs> remembered the nest collection – wren’s nests were rare. See De Brouwer 1984, pp. 109-112, and cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 198-203, cat. nos. 38-39.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_867">Karl Bodmer</rs> made numerous depictions of birds in and around their nests, but not of individual bird’s nests. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1045">Hector Giacomelli</rs>, though, did. His illustrations appeared in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_133">L’oiseau</ref></hi>. Paris 1881. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 201.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
      
<p>Traces of this earlier version can be seen on an X-ray photograph of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 157.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            
            
<p>Variant of ‘korte metten maken’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>This shepherd can be seen on an X-ray photograph under <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The cottage</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2149">Ill. 2149</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 148.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>A reference to the quarrel that had blown up when Theo described Vincent’s work as <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1228">Michel</rs> imitations: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let432.xml">see letter 432</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means ‘ter plekke zijn’ (being on the spot), that is to say near the cottage he just mentioned <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-88">(ll. 88-89)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    