<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Monday, 6 July 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let512"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b454 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>512</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>416</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>519</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-07-06">Monday, 6 July 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0454" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0454" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000606_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor het geld<c type="kk">/</c> uw schrijven en catalogus Raffaelli. De teekeningen die daarin staan  vind ik meesterlijk.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Wat hij zelf verder zegt over “<hi rend="italics">le caractéristique</hi>” is interessant.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Zijn schrijven is een mengsel van zeer eenvoudige woorden die uit het hart en uit een nerveus artistiek gevoel komen – die zijn treffend – en verder – uit woorden die denk ik Raffaelli zelf evenmin begrijpt als wie het lezen moet<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is een geschrijf dus vol heele mooie dingen en vol fouten – dat lees ik liever dan iets anders. Hetgeen waar hij ’t over heeft is dan ook magtig ingewikkeld<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Het <hi rend="italics">geheel</hi> van wat hij zegt – als men ’t gelezen heeft – voldoet echter dunkt mij – en met al zijn zonderlinge uitvallen zegt hij toch <hi rend="italics">iets gezonds</hi> en <hi rend="italics">waars</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Theo ge moet niet denken dat als ik het Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van Uhde zelf zag<c type="kk">/</c> ik de impressie verliezen zou welke ik ontving<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik zeg nog eens dat ik geloof het met dezen man gaan zal als met Knaus en Lobrichon – dat n.l. na eenige dingen vol karakter <hi rend="italics">juist de techniek</hi> hem een poets zal bakken<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat hij hoe langer hoe correcter zal gaan werken – en – hoe langer hoe drooger<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Ik vind b.v. <hi rend="italics">Raffaelli</hi> een schilder die <hi rend="italics">veel hooger</hi> staat – dan Uhde<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ge hoort me ook geen pessimistische twijfelingen hebben omtrent l’Lhermitte niet waar? Dus ik ben niet iemand die altijd twijfelt<c type="kp">_</c>– Integendeel in sommige lui heb ik een zeer vast geloof<c type="kp">_</c>– Van Raffaelli had ik nooit iets gezien dan die twee smids toen ik U er over schreef reeds<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <hi rend="italics">Raffaelli</hi><c type="kk">/</c> vooral echter juist <hi rend="italics">L’Hermitte</hi><c type="kk">/</c> hebben dat waar Raffaelli over spreekt<c type="kk">/</c> “<hi rend="italics">conscience</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Ik vrees dat daar ’t zwakke punt van Uhde zal zitten. dat hij niet meer weten zal wat hij wil<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu zegt ge dat het zilverachtig grijs van Uhde zoo mooi is – en dat als ik ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> zag ik er anders over denken zou<c type="kp">_</c>– Neen kerel – ik heb al zoo almagtig veel grijs gezien dat met een beetje zilvergrijs ik niet zóó makkelijk te verleiden meer ben als vroeger. Het grijs schilderen <hi rend="italics">als systeem</hi> wordt onverdragelijk. en we krijgen er nog een <hi rend="italics">revers de la medaille</hi> van! Toch heb ik<c type="kk">/</c> om U te overtuigen ik het goede er van wensch te zien blijven en niet er op <hi rend="italics">tegen</hi> ben<c type="kk">/</c> juist nu ook een grijs geval staan.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">We zullen – onwillekeurig over deze dingen het nog wel eens hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Vergeet er echter niet bij dat ofschoon ik jegens Uhde zekere bezwaren heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik op den voorgrond stelde ik <hi rend="italics">dit</hi> sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> wel degelijk – wat het voornaamste betreft<c type="kk">/</c> dat 3/4 van ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> is – de kinderen – zeer mooi vind.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik moet er op uit – wilde niet langer wachten<c type="kk">/</c> ben alle dagen zoo moe als een hond omdat ik heel wijd weg in de hei zit<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Ik heb ook weer figuren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het spijt me wel wat ge schrijft over het geld<c type="kk">/</c> dat ge zelf krap zult zitten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het schilderen is soms zoo verdomd duur en in den tegenwoordigen tijd komt het er juist zoo op aan dat men zijn eigen idee coûte qui coûte volgt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Il nous faut un art de <hi rend="italics">force vive</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zegt Raffaelli<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> en om in figuur daartoe te komen heeft men zooveel moeite met modellen te vinden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">De tijd is er niet meer<c type="kk">/</c> en ik klaag daar niet over<c type="kk">/</c> dat het genoeg is een figuur volgens de akademie conventioneel in elkaar zitte<c type="kk">/</c> of eigentlijk<c type="kk">/</c> al verlangen velen <hi rend="italics">juist dat</hi><c type="kk">/</c> er komt toch reactie – en ik hoop die leven in de brouwerij zal geven<c type="kp">_</c> De artisten roepen om karakter<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>wel – ’t publiek zal het ook doen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik verzeker U dat ik de Christus van Uhde al <hi rend="italics">bijzonder</hi> ongelukkig vind<c type="kk">/</c> die kan er niet door – de kinderen zijn goed<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik houd zooveel van L’Hermitte – van Raffaelli omdat het door en door <hi rend="italics">gedacht</hi> is<c type="kk">/</c> verstandig en eerlijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik heb hier liggen een paar figuren<c type="kk">/</c> een vrouw met een schop op den rug gezien<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> eene andere die bukt om aren op te rapen<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> – eene andere van voren met ’t hoofd haast aan den grond<c type="kk">/</c> die wortelen uitsteekt<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik heb 1 1/2 jaar hier op die boerenfiguurtjes nu geloerd en op hun actie<c type="kk">/</c> juist om er wat karakter in te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Dan kan ik zulk een sinterklaas als Uhde daar in dat schooltje – het schooltje is anders zoo mooi toch! – niet goed uitstaan. Uhde zelf – wel ik wed dat hij ’t ook weet – en het ter wille van dat de brave burgers uit dat land alwaar hij woont “sujet” en “iets conventioneels te denken” verlangen<c type="kk">/</c> en hij anders honger lijden moet – heeft gedaan. Als ik dezer dagen nog een oogenblikje vind dat ik niet te moe ben om te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik U nog weleens trachten te zeggen hoe <hi rend="italics">uitmuntend</hi> goed ik sommige dingen vind in Raffaelli<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for the money, your letter and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> catalogue. I think the drawings in it are masterly.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> What he himself also says about ‘<hi rend="italics">character</hi>’ is interesting.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">His writing is a mixture of very simple words that come from the heart and from a nervous artistic emotion — they’re moving — and further — of words that I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> himself understands as little as one who has to read them. Thus it is writing full of very fine things and full of mistakes — I would rather read that than anything else. For what he’s talking about is mightily complicated.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">It seems to me, though, that the <hi rend="italics">totality</hi> of what he says satisfies — when one has read it — and with all his strange outbursts he nonetheless says <hi rend="italics">something sound</hi> and <hi rend="italics">true</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Theo, you mustn’t think that if I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>’s painting itself I would lose the impression I got of it.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I say again that I believe this man will go the same way as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1131">Knaus</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1172">Lobrichon</rs> — namely that after a few things full of character, <hi rend="italics">the very technique </hi>will play a dirty trick on him, that’s to say he’ll start working more and more correctly — and — more and more drily. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I find <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs></hi>, say, a painter who stands <hi rend="italics">much higher</hi> — than Uhde.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">You don’t hear me having any pessimistic doubts about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>, do you? So I’m not someone who always doubts. On the contrary, I have a very firm faith in some people. I had never seen anything by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> besides those two blacksmiths<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> when I wrote to you about it. <hi rend="italics">Raffaëlli</hi>, and above all specifically <hi rend="italics">Lhermitte</hi>, though, have what Raffaëlli’s talking about, ‘<hi rend="italics">conscience</hi>’.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I’m afraid that that’s where <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>’s weak spot will be. That he’ll no longer know what he wants.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Anyway. Now you say that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>’s silvery grey is so beautiful — and that if I saw the painting I’d think differently about it. No, old chap. I’ve already seen so almighty much grey that I’m not so easily seduced by a bit of silvery grey as I once was. Painting grey <hi rend="italics">as a system</hi> is becoming intolerable, and we’ll get the<hi rend="italics"> other side of that coin</hi>! All the same, to convince you that I want to go on seeing the good in it and am not <hi rend="italics">against</hi> it, I have a grey thing going right now.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">We’ll — inevitably talk about these things again sometime.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Don’t forget, though, that although I have certain reservations about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>, I said at the outset that I really do think <hi rend="italics">this</hi> painting — as far as the main part is concerned, which is 3/4  of the painting — the children — very fine.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I must get going — didn’t want to wait any longer; am dog-tired every day because I’m so far away on the heath.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’ve got some more figures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’m sorry about what you write about the money, that you’ll be short yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Painting is sometimes so damned expensive, and nowadays it just comes down to following one’s own idea at all costs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">We need an art with <hi rend="italics">strength and vigour</hi>, says <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and in achieving this in the figure one has so much difficulty finding models.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">The time has passed, and I’m not complaining about it. Although it’s enough for a figure to be put together conventionally, academically – or actually, although many people want <hi rend="italics">precisely that</hi>, there’ll be a reaction nonetheless — and I hope that will stir things up. The artists are calling for character, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> well — the public will do the same. I assure you that I find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>’s Christ <hi rend="italics">extraordinarily</hi> unfortunate, it won’t do — the children are good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’m so fond of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> — because it’s <hi rend="italics">thought out</hi> through and through, sensible and honest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’ve got a few figures here, a woman with a spade seen from behind,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> another one bending over to glean ears of corn<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> — another one from the front with her head almost on the ground, digging up carrots.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I’ve been spying on these peasant figures here for 1  1/2  years and on their activities, precisely to get some character into it. So I really can’t stand a Santa Claus like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs> put there in that little school — the little school itself is so fine, though! Uhde himself — well, I wager that he knows it too — and that he did it on account of the fact that the good citizens of that country where he lives desire a ‘subject’ and ‘something conventional to think about’, and otherwise he’d have to starve. If I find another moment one of these days when I’m not too tired to write, I’ll try to tell you how <hi rend="italics">outstandingly</hi> good I find some things in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written after <ref target="let510.xml">letter 510</ref> of 28 June. In that one Vincent thanks his brother for sending reproductions after Uhde and Raffaëlli, which he elaborates on here. The money he thanks Theo for was therefore the allowance for July. Vincent apparently waited a few days before replying <ref target="#l-56">(ll. 56-58)</ref>. Since Jo van Gogh-Bonger gave the date as 6 July in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, and she may have had a postmark to go on, we have dated the letter Monday, 6 July 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Catalogue illustré des oeuvres de Jean-François Raffaelli, exposées 28 bis, avenue de l’Opéra. Suivi d’une étude des mouvements de l’art moderne et du beau caractériste</hi>. Paris 1884. Facsimile printed in: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exhibitions of Impressionist Art <hi>ii</hi></hi>. New York and London 1981. This exhibition ran from 15 March to 15 April 1884; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> was responsible for organizing it. One of the categories was ‘Portraits-types de gens du bas peuple’ (Portrait heads of the lower classes). The catalogue contains five illustrations followed by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>’s lengthy essay, titled ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_550">Etude des mouvements de l’art moderne et du beau caractériste</ref>’ in which he puts into words what makes up the essence of art for him (pp. 21-70). Theo handled several works by Raffaëlli from 1886 onwards.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>One of the main themes of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>’s essay is the concept of ‘character’; expressing this well in the work of art is the most important task of the modern artist; the concept is discussed in particular on pp. 21-30, 43, 66-68. The piece begins with a number of pithily formulated contentions: ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Character</hi> is the essential beauty, in a positivist era. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Characteristic beauty</hi> must at the same time be natural beauty, intellectual beauty and artistic beauty, finally leading to moral beauty. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Characteristic beauty</hi> must be a means of judicial action in all manifestations of freedom.’ (Le <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">caractère</hi> est le beau essentiel, à une époque positiviste. Le <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">beau caractériste</hi> doit être en même temps le beau naturel, le beau intellectuel, et le beau artistique, menant comme fin au beau moral.– Le <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">beau caractériste</hi> doit être un mode d’action judiciaire de toutes les manifestations de la liberté) (p. 21). Cf. also Schinman Fields 1979, pp. 60, 102-118.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>See for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2141">Suffer the little children to come unto me</rs></hi>by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1387">Uhde</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let500.xml#n-25;">letter 500, n. 25;</ref> Theo had sent a reproduction of it: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let510.xml">see letter 510</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The blacksmiths</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let510.xml#n-18">letter 510, n. 18.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In this essay, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> explores the concept of ‘conscience’ (specifically on pp. 43, 47-48, 69).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh painted cottages there, as becomes clear in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let513.xml">letter 513</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The sentence from which this quote is taken reads: ‘We need art with strength and vigour which addresses issues by reproduction and by considering new, poetic, critical, natural and scientific manifestations; whether damnable or praiseworthy.’ (Il nous faut un art de force vive s’adressant à l’idée par la reproduction et par l’attention portée à des spectacles nouveaux, poétiques, critiques, naturels, scientifiques; condamnables ou à louanger (p. 25).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman digging </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2521">F 1255 / JH 826</rs>). From <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let515.xml">letter 515</ref> it emerges that these are drawings.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>A stooping woman picking up ears of corn occurs in several drawings of this period, so it is not possible to identify the specific drawing Van Gogh is referring to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman stooping, with a spade </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2522">F 1691 / JH 835</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    