<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 13 July 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let514"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b8384 a-b V/2006</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>514</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>R52</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>513</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-07-13">on or about Monday, 13 July 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anthon van Rappard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8384 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8384 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001644_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8384 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 8384 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001645_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Rappard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">het een en ander dat gepasseerd is maakt dat als ik er toe kom U te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> het meer is om duidelijk te zijn dan omdat ik het voor mijn pleizier doe<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat betreft dat ik U uw vorig schrijven kortaf heb teruggezonden<c type="kk">/</c> twee redenen waren er voor<c type="kk">/</c> ieder voor zich dit m.i. motiveerende<c type="kp">_</c>– Vooreerst – gesteld uwe aanmerkingen over de lithografie welke ik U zond<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> waren juist<c type="kk">/</c> gesteld ik had er niets tegen te zeggen – ook dan niet waart ge gerechtigd al mijn werk op zoo beleedigende manier te veroordeelen<c type="kk">/</c> of liever te negeeren als ge deedt<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">En tweedens – waar ge niet alleen van mij maar ook van mijn familie meer vriendschap hebt gehad dan gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> kunt ge zeker niet <hi rend="italics">aanspraak maken</hi> er op dat bij eene gelegenheid als ’t overlijden van mijn vader men iets anders <hi rend="italics">verpligt</hi> zij te zenden dan een circulaire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Vooral <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> niet<c type="kk">/</c> waar reeds vóór dien tijd ge geen antwoord hadt gezonden op een brief van mij. Vooral <hi rend="italics">ik</hi> niet<c type="kk">/</c> waar bij die gelegenheid van het overlijden van mijn vader gij wel een teeken van belangstelling geeft in een schrijven aan mijne moeder gerigt – doch een zoodanig dat toen dit arriveerde er nog sprake van geweest is t’huis<c type="kk">/</c> wat de reden was waarom ge aan mij niet schreeft toen – waar ik echter niet begeerig naar was<c type="kk">/</c> ook niet ben.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Gij weet – ik ben jaren lang met t’huis niet in de beste overeenstemming geweest. Bij het overlijden van mijn vader heb ik de eerste dagen <hi rend="italics">moeten</hi> correspondeeren met de naaste familie<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch overigens heb ik zoodra familie arriveerde me geheel er van onttrokken<c type="kp">_</c>– En regardeeren eventueele verzuimen niet mij doch de familie. En ik moet U zeggen dat in zoover gij nog een uitzondering maakt<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik t’huis vroeg of men U een berigt had gezonden en het bleek het vergeten was. Veel meer dan genoeg hierover<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De reden dat ik U weder schrijf is geenszins om te antwoorden op uwe aanmerking dienaangaande<c type="kp">_</c> Ook niet om te herhalen wat ik U zeide over uw spreken over schilderen<c type="kp">_</c> ge hebt uw eigen brief kunnen herlezen – als ge dien juist zijt blijven vinden<c type="kk">/</c> als ge dan inderdaad meent dat “als ge er u toe zet ge U weerga’s juist uitdrukt” – wel – dan is het ’t best U in dien waan eenvoudig te laten<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Om ter zake te komen – de reden waarom ik U schrijf is eenvoudig dat ik U te lang heb gekend dan dat ik – ofschoon niet ik U maar wel gij mij in de eerste plaats hebt beleedigd – dit nog geen reden<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> acht om 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>alle kennis af te breken<c type="kp">_</c>– Hetgeen ik U te zeggen heb is als een schilder tot een schilder en – zoolang gij en ik schilderen – blijft dat ook – ’t zij we elkaar kennen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Er was sprake over <hi rend="italics">Millet</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Best – ’k zal je antwoorden amice<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ge schrijft mij “en dat durft Millet en Breton aanroepen”<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik antwoord U daarop dat ik U ten ernstigste in overweging geef – eenvoudig <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> met mij te vechten<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik voor mij – ga mijn eigen gang – ziet ge – maar ik zoek twist met niemand – met U ook nu <hi rend="italics">niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zou U ook alles laten praten wat ge wildet – als ge meer zulke uitdrukkingen hadt – en ’t zou me van mijn koude kleeren afdruipen zonder meer<c type="kp">_</c>– Zooveel echter voor ’t oogenblik – dat ik om den vorm van ’t figuur niet geef<c type="kk">/</c> wat ge al meer hebt gezegd – het is beneden me er op te attendeeren en – kerel – het is beneden U om iets zóó ongemotiveerds te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge hebt mij jaren lang gekend nu reeds – hebt ge me ooit anders gezien dan werkende naar ’t model en me de soms zoo zware kosten ervan getroostende<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik arm genoeg toch ben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Wat ge niet in den laatsten doch wel herhaaldelijk in vorige brieven mij tot mijn verveling schreeft<c type="kk">/</c> en reden was van den brief waarop gij niet antwoordet<c type="kk">/</c> is over “<hi rend="italics">techniek</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c> Wat ik U daarop heb geantwoord en nogmaals antwoord is – de conventioneele beteekenis welke men aan het woord techniek meer en meer geeft<c type="kk">/</c> en de eigentlijke beteekenis <hi rend="italics">wetenschap</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Welnu – Meissonnier zelf zegt:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">“<hi rend="italics">la science – nul ne l’a</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">“la science” nu is niet hetzelfde als “de la science”<c type="kk">/</c> dat vooreerst en dat zult ge niet tegenspreken.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Maar ook dat is ’t nog niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Haverman b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> van dien zegt men – ook gij – dat hij zooveel <hi rend="italics">techniek</hi> heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar niet alleen Havermann<c type="kk">/</c> hoeveel anderen – hebben iets dat gelijkstaat met die soort kennis die H. van de kunst heeft – onder de Fransche schilders – Jacquet b.v. en die is <hi rend="italics">beter</hi>.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Mijne beweering is eenvoudig deze – dat akademisch correct een figuur teekenen – dat een gelijkmatigen beredeneerden penseelstreek weinig te maken hebben – althans minder dan men in ’t algemeen meent – met de behoeften – de dringende behoeften – van den tegenwoordige tijd op ’t gebied schilderkunst.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Indien in plaats van te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> H<c type="kp">_</c> heeft veel “techniek”<c type="kk">/</c> ge zeidet<c type="kk">/</c> H. heeft veel “metier”<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik voor eens U gelijk geven<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge zult misschien begrijpen wat ik bedoel als ik zeg dat als Havermann zit voor een mooi meisjes/dameskopje<c type="kk">/</c> hij het mooier maken zal dan bijna iedereen<c type="kk">/</c> maar zet hem voor een boer – en – hij zal er niet eens aan beginnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Zijne kunst – voor zoover mij bekend – blijkt vooral toepasselijk te zijn op motieven welke niet diegenen zijn waar behoefte aan is – is vooral toepasselijk op motieven die zoowat geheel en al tegenvoeterig zijn tegen Millet of lhermitte – en veeleer met Cabanel evenwijdig loopen – die met al zijn wat ik noem – metier – weinig heeft verteld dat bleef – of vooruit hielp<c type="kp">_</c>– En – wat ik U bidden mag – <hi rend="italics">verwar</hi> dit niet met de wijze van schilderen van een Millet of l’Hermitte<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Het geen ik zeide en nog zeg – het woord – techniek – wordt maar al te veel gebruikt in een conventioneele beteekenis – en – het wordt maar al te veel niet te goeder trouw gebezigd<c type="kp">_</c>– Van al die italjanen en spanjaarden prijst men de <hi rend="italics">techniek</hi><c type="kk">/</c> en ’t zijn menschen die meer conventioneel zijn<c type="kk">/</c> meer slechs routine hebben – dan iemand anders<c type="kp">_</c>– En bij zulken als Havermann wordt zoo gaauw<c type="kk">/</c> vrees ik<c type="kk">/</c> het “metier” – “routine”. En dan – wat is ’t dan waard?</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Wat ik U nu te vragen heb – wat is nu eigentlijk de reden dat gij met mij hebt gebroken–?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">De reden waarom ik aan U weder schrijf is juist uit liefde voor Millet<c type="kk">/</c> voor Breton en voor <hi rend="italics">allen</hi> die de <hi rend="italics">boeren</hi> en ’t <hi rend="italics">volk</hi> schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> waaronder ik U reken<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zeg het niet omdat ik als vriend veel aan U had – amice – want – ik had bitter weinig aan U – en neem me niet kwalijk ik voor ’t eerst en ’t laatst U dit eens vierkant zeg – ik ken geen drooger vriendschap dan de uwe<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar – vooreerst doe ik ’t <hi rend="italics">daarom</hi> niet – tweedens<c type="kk">/</c> ook dat had beter kunnen worden – maar zelf gelegenheid me gemaakt hebbende om modellen &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> te vinden<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik zoo kleingeestig niet om dat stil te houden<c type="kp">_</c>– Integendeel – indien welk schilder dan ook hier in de buurt kwam<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik hem graag en inviteeren en den weg wijzen. Juist omdat modellen te vinden die poseeren willen niet altijd even makkelijk gaat – en een pied à terre ergens te hebben niet voor iedereen een onverschillige zaak is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">En ik zeg het U daarom<c type="kk">/</c> dat als gij hier wilt schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> ge U niet geneeren moet om reden dat we ongenoegen hadden<c type="kp">_</c>– En ge zelfs – al woon ik nu op me zelf in mijn werkplaats – logeeren kunt ook<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Welligt echter dat – uit de hoogte – ge zegt dit U niets scheelen kan<c type="kp">_</c>– Wel<c type="kk">/</c> dan ook goed<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik ben zóó gewoon aan beleedigingen dat zij werkelijk zóó ten eenemale langs mijn koude kleeren afdruipen – dat – iemand als gij – waarschijnlijk zich moeielijk begrijpen kan hoe ten eenemale koel me b.v. zulk een brief laat als den uwen<c type="kp">_</c>– En ongevoelig er voor zijnde – even als een paal heb ik ook geen rancune<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar wel – genoeg helderheid en sereniteit om er op te antwoordden als ik nu doe<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Wilt gij breken – best<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Wilt gij hier blijven schilderen – ge hoeft U niet te storen aan dit beetje geharrewar in correspondentie<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Hetgeen gij de laatste keer gemaakt hebt hier<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – had en heeft mijn volle sympathie – en – amice Rappard – het is omdat ge zoo verdomd goed toen de laatste keer hebt gewerkt en ik bij me zelf denk dat ge misschien mogt verlangen de gelegenheid hier zoo bleef als die was<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik je schrijf<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Weet het voor U zelf – ik zeg het vierkantweg – ik heb van den eenen kant – behoudens alle waardeering van uw schilderen – eenige zorgen voor <hi rend="italics">later</hi><c type="kk">/</c> of ge ’t ook zóó volhouden zult – ik vrees soms dat door de invloeden waaraan gegeven uw maatschappelijke positie en stand ge niet anders kunt dan blootgesteld zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ge misschien op den duur niet zoo goed zult blijven als ge op ’t moment zijt – als schilder juist in uw schilderen – de rest bemoei ik me niet mee<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Als een schilder tot een schilder zeg ik U dus dat als ge hier schilderijen wilt zoeken <hi rend="italics">het net blijft als vroeger</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Ge kunt hier komen en al woon ik op mezelf net zoo goed logeeren als vroeger<c type="kp">_</c>– Ziet ge – ik dacht dat misschien gij er iets aan gehad hadt en hebben kondt en ik wilde dit U nog zeggen – Kunt ge elders net zoo goed uit den weg – welnu – ik heb geen reden om te treuren<c type="kk">/</c> en dan<c type="kk">/</c> adieu<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Gij schreeft me niets over <hi rend="italics">Uw</hi> werk<c type="kk">/</c> ik U nu ook niets over ’t <hi rend="italics">mijne</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Geloof me – twist met mij niet over Millet – Millet is iemand over wie ik niet wil twisten<c type="kk">/</c> al weiger ik niet er over te spreken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">All that has passed means that when I come to write to you it’s more in order to be clear than because I do it for my pleasure. As to my having returned your last letter to you forthwith, there were two reasons for it, each in its own right, to my mind, providing a motive. Firstly — suppose that your comments on the lithograph I sent you<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> were correct, suppose I had nothing to say against them — even then, you wouldn’t have been justified in condemning my work in such an insulting manner, or rather in ignoring it as you did.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And secondly — whereas you have had more friendship than you have given, not just from me but from my family too, you certainly cannot <hi rend="italics">claim</hi> that on an occasion such as my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>’s death we were <hi rend="italics">obliged</hi> to send something other than a printed notice.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Particularly not <hi rend="italics">me</hi>, since before that time you hadn’t replied to a letter from me. Particularly not <hi rend="italics">me</hi>, since on the occasion of my father’s death you did send an expression of sympathy in a letter addressed to my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> — but such a one that when it arrived there was comment at home about what reason there might be for not writing to me then — which I didn’t want, however, nor do I.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You know — I haven’t been on the best of terms with them at home for years. In the first few days after my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> died, I <hi rend="italics">had</hi> to correspond with the immediate family. But otherwise, as soon as family arrived, I withdrew from it all completely. And regarding any omissions, not me but the family. And I have to tell you that in so far as it goes, you’re an exception, that I asked them at home if they’d sent you word and it appeared that it had been forgotten. Much more than enough about that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The reason I’m writing to you again is in no way to respond to your comment in that regard. Nor to repeat what I said about your remarks about painting. You’ve been able to re-read your own letter. If you still believe that was justified, if you still really think that ‘if you put your mind to it, you can deuced well express yourself correctly’ — well — then it’s best simply to leave you to your delusions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">To get to the point — the reason why I’m writing to you is simply that — although it was you who insulted me in the first place, not I you — I’ve known you too long for me to consider this a reason 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> to break off all acquaintance. What I have to say to you is as a painter to a painter and — so long as you and I paint — it will remain so — whether we know each other, whether we don’t. There was mention of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs></hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"> Very well — I’ll answer you, my dear friend.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">You wrote, ‘you dare to invoke <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Breton</rs>’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">My reply to that is that I seriously invite you to consider — simply <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to fight with me. For my part — I go my own way — you see — but I don’t seek a quarrel with anyone — <hi rend="italics">not</hi> with you now either. I’d also let you say anything that you wanted — if you had any more such expressions — and it would just be like water off a duck’s back. So much for the present, though. That I don’t care about the form of the figure, which you’ve said before — it’s beneath me to take any notice of it and — old chap — it’s beneath you to say something <hi rend="italics">so</hi> unfounded. You’ve known me for years now — have you ever seen me do anything other than work from the model and resign myself to the sometimes great expense of it, even though I’m poor enough as it is?
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What you didn’t write in your last, but did repeatedly and ad nauseam in previous letters, and was the reason for the letter to which you didn’t reply, is about ‘<hi rend="italics">technique</hi>’. What I replied to you then and reply once more is — the conventional meaning that people increasingly give to the word technique, and the actual meaning, <hi rend="italics">knowledge</hi>. Well then. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs> himself says,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">‘<hi rend="italics">the knowledge — nobody has it</hi>’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Well, ‘the knowledge’ isn’t the same as ‘knowledge’, that first of all, and that you won’t deny.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> But even that still isn’t it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Take <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1072">Haverman</rs>, for instance; people — you too — say of him that he has so much <hi rend="italics">technique</hi>. But not only Haverman, how many others — have something that’s equivalent to the sort of knowledge that H. has of art — among the French painters — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1115">Jacquet</rs>, say, and he’s <hi rend="italics">better</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">My assertion is simply this — that drawing a figure academically correctly — that an even, reasoned brushstroke have little — at least less than is generally thought — to do with the needs — the urgent needs — of the present day in the field of painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">If, instead of saying <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1072">H.</rs> has a lot of ‘technique’, you were to say H. has a lot of ‘craftsmanship’, I would have agreed with you for once. You will perhaps understand what I mean when I say that when Haverman sits in front of the head of a beautiful girl/woman, he’ll make it more beautiful than almost anyone, but put him in front of a peasant — and — he won’t even make a start on it. His art — as far as I know — proves chiefly applicable to subjects which aren’t the ones that are needed — is above all applicable to subjects that are pretty much completely and utterly opposite to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> — and sooner run parallel to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_917">Cabanel</rs> — who for all his what I call — craftsmanship — has said little that lasted — or contributed to progress. And — this I beg of you — don’t <hi rend="italics">confuse</hi> this with the way a Millet or Lhermitte paints.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">What I said and still say — the word — technique — is all too often used in a conventional sense — and — it’s all too often not used in good faith. People praise the <hi rend="italics">technique </hi>of all those Italians and Spaniards, and they’re fellows who are more conventional, have more sheer routine — than anyone else. And with such as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1072">Haverman</rs>, I fear, ‘craftsmanship’ so soon becomes — ‘routine’. And then — what’s it worth then?
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">What I want to ask now — what’s the real reason that you’ve broken with me —?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">The reason I’m writing to you again is just out of love for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Breton</rs> and for <hi rend="italics">everyone</hi> who paints the <hi rend="italics">peasants</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">people</hi>, among whom I count you. I don’t say it because I got a lot from you as a friend – my dear friend – because — I got precious little from you — and don’t take it amiss of me for saying this to you straight out for the first and last time — I know of no drier friendship than yours. But — firstly <hi rend="italics">that’s</hi> not why I’m doing it — secondly, that might have improved too — but having created my own opportunities to find models &amp;c., I’m not so petty as to keep it quiet. On the contrary — were any painter, no matter who, to come to this district, I would be glad both to invite him home and to show him the way. Precisely because it’s not always easy to find models who are willing to pose — and having a pied-à-terre somewhere isn’t a matter of indifference to everyone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">And this is why I say to you that, if you want to paint here, you mustn’t be embarrassed because we had a disagreement. And — although I’m living on my own in my studio now — you can even stay too. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">It may be, though, that — superciliously — you’ll say that this is of no consequence to you. Well, that’s all right. I’m <hi rend="italics">so</hi> accustomed to insults that they really are <hi rend="italics">so </hi>like water off a duck’s back — that — someone like you — probably finds it hard to understand just how cold a letter like yours, say, leaves me. And being indifferent to it — I have no more resentment than a post. But I do have — enough clarity and serenity to reply as I do now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">If you want to break with me — very well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">If you want to go on painting here — you don’t have to take any notice of this little bit of bickering in our correspondence.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">What you did the last time you were here<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — had and has my full sympathy — and — my dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> — it’s because you worked so damned well that last time, and I think to myself that you might perhaps want things here to remain as they were, that I’m writing to you.
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Make up your own mind — I say frankly — from one point of view — in spite of all my appreciation of your painting — I have some concerns about whether you’ll be able to keep it up like this <hi rend="italics">later </hi>— I sometimes fear that, because of the influences to which you cannot but be exposed given your social position and standing, you may not remain as good in the long run as you are at the moment — just as a painter in your painting — I don’t concern myself with the rest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">So I say to you, as a painter to a painter, that if you want to look for paintings here, <hi rend="italics">it will stay just the same as before</hi>. You can come here and, although I live on my own, stay just the same as before. You see — I thought that perhaps you had got and could get something out of it, and I just wanted to tell you this. If you can get on as well elsewhere — well then — I’ll have no reason to grieve about it, and then, adieu.
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">You’ve told me nothing about <hi rend="italics">your</hi> work, so I likewise say nothing about <hi rend="italics">mine</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Believe me — don’t argue with me about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> — Millet is someone I won’t argue about, although I don’t refuse to talk about him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter is a justification for the return of Van Rappard’s letter about <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> of 24 May 1885 (<ref target="let503.xml">503</ref> and <ref target="let504.xml">504</ref>). Some time must have elapsed between that letter and the present one because Van Gogh assumes that Van Rappard has broken with him <ref target="#l-117">(ll. 117-118)</ref>. From <ref target="let516.xml">letter 516</ref> of about 15 July it appears that Van Rappard had not written about a breach, so that Van Gogh’s assumption must have been based on the prolonged absence of a response. Since it is also clear from that same letter that Van Rappard replied to the present letter and Van Gogh wrote back immediately, we have dated <ref target="let514.xml">letter 514</ref> on or about Monday, 13 July 1885. See also <ref target="let515.xml">letter 515</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s reaction to the lithograph of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let503.xml">(503)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The death of Mr van Gogh <ref target="let486.xml">(486)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2135">F 1661 / JH 737</rs>). We do not know which one <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had. Cf. Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 97-98.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘een reden’ (a reason).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Taken from the article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_434">Meissonier. A propos de l’exposition récente de ses oeuvres</ref>’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1808">G. Dubufe</rs> fils, which was published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Nouvelle Revue</hi> 6, November-December 1884, vol. 31, pp. 116-132. An admirer had written in an ode: ‘You have the knowledge’ (Vous avez la science), whereupon <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs> wrote him a letter, saying: ‘No! I do not have the knowledge, one never has it!) (Non! je n’ai pas la science, on ne l’a jamais!) (quotation on pp. 131-132). Van Gogh read this periodical in his parents’ house (FR b2268). The expression is repeated in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let516.xml#n-6">letter 516, n. 6</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh means that people may claim to have some knowledge, but not that they know <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">everything</hi>, have ‘the’ knowledge.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>That is, during <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s stay in Nuenen in October 1884.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    