<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anton Kerssemakers. Nuenen, on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let518"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b880 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>518</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>517</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-07-16">on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anton Kerssemakers</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0880" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0880" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001174_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Mijnheer Kerssemakers,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Het is met genoegen dat ik met Wenkebach heb kennis gemaakt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik acht het niet alleen mogelijk maar vrij denkelijk dat niet alleen hij maar ook Rappard van tijd tot tijd hier zullen blijven komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ten minste<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb Rappard zoo lang gekend en zoo goed gekend dat ik geneigd ben het er voor te houden hij terug zal komen van zeker misverstand<c type="kk">/</c> dat maakte dat wij een tijd koel waren. Ik heb hem zoo even geschreven maar ik verlang algeheele terugname en zonder voorbehoud van zekere dingen die hij van mijn figuren zeide en die ik beweer niet te verdienen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Wat ik zeggen wilde in verband met Uw nieuwe studies is dat ter wille van de voorgronden vooral<c type="kk">/</c> die steeds te onsolide mij voorkomen en maken er niet genoeg ruimte in komt<c type="kk">/</c> is dat het<c type="kk">/</c> stel ik me voor<c type="kk">/</c> heel goed zou wezen dat U het ook eens met een perspectiefraam probeerdet. Want er is niets dat zoo <hi rend="italics">leert</hi> <hi rend="italics">kijken</hi> en de perspectief <hi rend="italics">zoo leert voelen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>De fout is bij U zóó dat als U er één enkele met ’t perspectiefraam maakt<c type="kk">/</c> U het dadelijk voelen zult<c type="kk">/</c> anders dan ik het in woorden zeggen kan. Om iets te <hi rend="italics">voelen</hi> moet men het <hi rend="italics">weten</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">goed en lang</hi> <hi rend="italics">kennen</hi> zóó dat er overtuiging is<c type="kp">_</c>– Wenkebach zei mij dadelijk dat hij vond U “<hi rend="italics">heel veel</hi> teekenen” moest.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">De kwestie welke hij echter niet oplost is “<hi rend="italics">hoe</hi>?” <hi rend="italics">Hoe?</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wanneer het wenschelijk is den aller kortsten weg in te slaan en Uw geval eenigzins anders<c type="kk">/</c> heel anders dan dat van iemand die op zijn zeventiende jaar begint en dan niets anders te doen heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En ik zie er geen heil in om het U <hi rend="italics">al te</hi> moeielijk<c type="kk">/</c> al te <hi rend="italics">hard</hi> en <hi rend="italics">bar</hi> te maken. In tegenoverstelling en tegenspraak met veel anderen beweer ik men<c type="kk">/</c> op later leeftijd beginnende<c type="kk">/</c> ook nog bepaald iets goeds kan leeren schilderen en daar blijf ik bij<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik wou echter we meer zamen konden werken – ik vind dat<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> bepaald noodig – en 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>ongelukkigerwijs is er altijd zoowel voor U als voor mij vrij veel tijd mee gemoeid om bij elkaar te komen. De oude schilders hebben het perspectiefraam altijd veel gebruikt<c type="kk">/</c> het <hi>is</hi> de kortste weg<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En tenzij men de dingen <hi rend="italics">afsluit</hi><c type="kk">/</c> moet men als beginner wel in den war gebragt worden door allerlei dingen in de omgeving waar men niet naar hoeft te zien<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs <hi rend="italics">niet mag</hi> kijken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik kan daar ook niet te sterk dus op aan dringen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik wil U hier ook nog bij zeggen dat hetzelfde model dat ik U gisteren liet zien<c type="kk">/</c> ook binnenskamers te gebruiken is – als men het vastzet in een <hi rend="italics">blok</hi> door middel van een schroef<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En U kunt het dan ook gebruiken om koppen te schilderen of te teekenen en voor figuren buiten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">En ik geloof dat het U zóó praktisch helpen zou<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof dat U er zooveel nieuwe idees door zoudt krijgen en zoo veel meer voelen dat U U zelf er een heel eind verder mee brengen kunt<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>dat ik regt gaarne de eerste keeren er eens voor tot U kom<c type="kk">/</c> al is ’t een heelen dag<c type="kk">/</c> om U goed op dreef er mee te brengen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Wil mij dus laten weten of ik er hier een voor U bestellen zal of dat U er t’huis een zelf wilt maken<c type="kk">/</c> wat U wel kunt met behulp van eenige schroeven alleen. Dan kunt U ’t mijne als model krijgen als U ’t noodig mogt hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Mijn indruk van Wenkebach is zeer gunstig maar toch vraag ik me af<c type="kk">/</c> waarom in godsnaam zitten landschap<c type="shy">-</c>schilders in stad<c type="kk">/</c> waarom doen ze niet als de Franschen en gaan vierkant<c type="shy">-</c>weg zich buiten installeeren<c type="kp">_</c>– En hij voor één zou er wel bij varen<c type="kp">_</c>– U zaagt misschien wel dat ik hem even afsnaauwde toen hij zeide dat wat anderen mij ook reeds zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> dat Stengelin “een zonderling mensch” was. Dat is een Franschman die midden op de hei in Drenthe zich een atelier heeft ingerigt<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – ik heb hem niet getroffen toen ik in Drenthe was maar zijn voorbeeld vind ik zóó goed en praktisch dat ik het ellendig vind dat de Hollandsche schilders die hem bezocht hebben allerlei tegen hem te zeggen hadden.– Na groete<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">b<c type="kp">_</c> à v<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Mr Kerssemakers</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">It was with pleasure that I made <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs>’s acquaintance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I regard it as not only possible but quite likely that not only he but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, too, will continue to come here from time to time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">At least, I’ve known <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> so long and so well that I’m inclined to believe that he’ll retract a certain misunderstanding which meant that we were cool for a while. I’ve just written to him, but I want total retraction, and without reservation, of certain things that he said about my figures and that I insist I do not deserve.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">What I wanted to say in connection with your new studies is that for the sake of the foregrounds, in particular, which always seem to me to be too insubstantial and prevent there being enough space in them, is that I suggest it would be very good if you also gave it a try with a perspective frame. For there’s nothing like it <hi rend="italics">for teaching one to look</hi> and <hi rend="italics">teaching one to feel</hi> perspective. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> The mistake you make is such that if you do just one with the perspective frame you’ll feel it instantly, other than how I can put it into words. In order to <hi rend="italics">feel</hi> something, one must <hi rend="italics">know</hi> it, <hi rend="italics">be very familiar with it</hi> so that there’s conviction. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs> told me straightaway that he thought you should ‘do <hi rend="italics">a great deal</hi> of drawing’.</p>
<p rend=" indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The question that he doesn’t solve, though, is ‘<hi rend="italics">how</hi>?’ <hi rend="italics">How?</hi> when it’s desirable to take the very shortest route and your case is rather different, very different from that of someone who begins when he’s seventeen and so has nothing else to do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And I see no benefit in making it <hi rend="italics">too</hi> difficult, too <hi rend="italics">hard</hi> and <hi rend="italics">tough</hi> for you. In contrast to and contradicting many others, I maintain that one can definitely still learn to paint something good beginning at a later age, and I stand by that. I do wish we could work together more, though — I would say that I find that really necessary — and 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> unfortunately our getting together always involves rather a lot of time both for you and for me. The old painters always used the perspective frame a lot; it <hi>is</hi> the shortest way.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And unless one <hi rend="italics">blocks</hi> things <hi rend="italics">out</hi>, as a beginner one is inevitably thrown into confusion by all sorts of things in the surroundings which one oughtn’t to see, in fact <hi rend="italics">may not</hi> look at.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">So I therefore can’t urge it strongly enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I also want to tell you that the same model I showed you yesterday can be used indoors as well — if one fixes it in a <hi rend="italics">block</hi> by means of a screw.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And then you can also use it to draw or to paint heads, and for figures outdoors.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And I think it would be of <hi rend="italics">such</hi> practical help to you, I think that you would get so many new ideas from it, and feel so much more that you can get yourself a great deal further with it, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> that I’d be very happy to come to you for it the first few times, even if it’s a whole day, so as to help you get the hang of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">So let me know whether I should order one for you here or whether you want to make one yourself at home, which you can do with no more than a few screws. Then you can have mine as a model should you need it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">My impression of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1442">Wenckebach</rs> is very favourable, but all the same I wonder why for God’s sake landscape painters are in the city, why don’t they do what the French do, and firmly install themselves in the country? And he, for one, would be the better for it. You may have noticed that I just bit his head off when he said what others had already said to me, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1361">Stengelin</rs> was ‘a strange person’. He’s a Frenchman who has set up a studio in the middle of the heath in Drenthe<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — I didn’t meet him when I was in Drenthe, but I find his example <hi rend="italics">so</hi> good and practical that I think it despicable that the Dutch painters who visited him had all sorts of things to say against him. Sincerely, with a handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">We have dated the letter on or about Thursday, 16 July 1885. See for this <ref target="let515.xml">letter 515</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>. <ref target="let517.xml">Letters 517</ref> and <ref target="let519.xml">519</ref> were also written this day.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Meeting with Wenckebach <ref target="let516.xml">(516)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Rappard’s reaction to the lithograph of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let503.xml">(503)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let517.xml">letter 517</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for the perspective frame, which was in use as long ago as the Renaissance: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let235.xml#n-10">letter 235, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>There are various drawings of perspective frame designs in Van Gogh’s Nuenen sketchbook; he may have shown these to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs>. See Van der Wolk 1987, pp. 50, 53, 60, 75-76, 79.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1361">Stengelin</rs> and Drenthe: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let473.xml#n-6">letter 473, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    