<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Friday, 21 and about Wednesday, 26 August 1885</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let530"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b462 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b1035 V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>530</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>422</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>531</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-08-21">between about Friday, 21 and about Wednesday, 26 August 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0462" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0462" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000619_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1035" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001204_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001204_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1035" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001204_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001204_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw schrijven en ingesl. f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 20 heb ik in orde ontvangen &amp; dank U er voor. Nu kan ik U berigten mijne kist aan Leurs verzonden te hebben met 7 stuks verschillende gevallen en om het wat compleeter te maken nog 12 kleinere geschilderde studies.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik heb ook aan Wisselingh geschreven dat ik deze zending deed &amp; hem verzocht ze te gaan zien. Echter blijft het mij spijten dat deze zending niet liever naar U is gegaan<c type="kp">_</c> Als wij Leurs afbetaald hadden en gij deze zending hadt genomen en we hadden dan<c type="kk">/</c> als gij er te veel van een zelfde soort kreegt<c type="kk">/</c> uit de verschillende zendingen een &amp; ander uitgeschoten om in Holland te probeeren<c type="kk">/</c> ware mijns inziens zoodoende steeds hetgeen bij U bleef het beste geweest en eene kern om gaandeweg uit te breiden naarmate we vorderen. Gedane zaken<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als ge zegt<c type="kk">/</c> nemen echter geen keer. Om nu voorloopig te antwoorden op hetgeen gij schreeft betreffende teekeningen van figuren met entourage<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik heden er eenigen afgezonden.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Of die voor het doel van ze te encadreeren geschikt zijn betwijfel ik – en ik zal er als ik in ’t veld wat gelukkig ben om iets beters te vinden<c type="kk">/</c> nog wel spoedig eenige nieuwen zien bij te voegen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wat betreft dat gij schrijft overtuigd te wezen <hi rend="italics">nog niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">te</hi> <hi rend="italics">ver</hi> <hi rend="italics">gegaan</hi> <hi rend="italics">te zijn in het bezuinigen</hi><c type="kk">/</c> kan uit Uw kasboek<c type="kk">/</c> in geval uitgaven grooter zijn dan inkomsten<c type="kk">/</c> U blijken<c type="kp">_</c>– Mogelijk ja<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch de reden???</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu ja – t’huis – <hi rend="italics">kerel</hi> <hi>gij kunt</hi> <hi>het niet volhouden zóó als gij het nu doet</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <hi rend="italics">Ik</hi> lijd er onder – dat kan ik U wel verzekeren – maar ik wil het desnoods goedvinden dat ik het er <hi rend="italics">nog</hi> armer door gekregen heb dan andere jaren<c type="kp">_</c> Maar worden zij er t’huis gelukkiger door en gaan zij er op vooruit en – – – de gevolgen voor later<c type="kk">/</c> voor henzelf en voor U<c type="kk">/</c> zult gij er gelukkig mede zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Waarlijk – als ik in mijn eigen ervaring terugdenk<c type="kk">/</c> als ik nadenk dat eenige jaren G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> <hi rend="italics">eindigden</hi> met een mij zeer sterk getrokken voelen naar t’huis<c type="kk">/</c> als ik denk hoe er voor mij een crisis op volgde<c type="kk">/</c> verbijsterend<c type="kk">/</c> en waarin ik zoo heel gaauw geheel alleen stond en <hi rend="italics">alles</hi> en <hi rend="italics">allen</hi> waar ik vroeger van gemeend had het blijven zou<c type="kk">/</c> veranderde en niets er van steek hield<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Als ik aan die trieste tijden terugdenk vrees ik zoo zeer beslist dat het tegenwoordige voor U geen <hi rend="italics">vasten</hi> bodem onder uw voeten zal blijken.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En dan voel ik mij gedrongen – niet als verwijt<c type="kk">/</c> niet om U te verschrikken<c type="kk">/</c> niet om U den moed te benemen maar als een woord van harde waarheid – dat te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> dat mijne meening is de zon voor U kan ondergaan – ja – aan het ondergaan is<c type="kp">_</c> Dat wat ik er bij voeg – Vernieuw U maar zoek die vernieuwing <hi rend="italics">in het hart van het</hi> <hi rend="italics">vak</hi>: schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> en handelen ook maar met <hi rend="italics">eigen</hi> zaken<c type="kk">/</c> is bewijs genoeg ik het niet verwijtenderwijs of beleedigenderwijs bedoel. Ik spreek als hebbende zelf strijd gekend en als midden in mijn gevecht zijnde<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>– Met ieder jaar dat men vordert in het leven schijnt de tijd sneller te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> gebeurt er meer – hebben de dingen meer vaart. Dat ik het ronduit zeg<c type="kk">/</c> is opdat ingeval er iets voor U verandert ge weten moogt ik het een natuurlijke<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>zeer begrijpelijke zaak zou vinden<c type="kk">/</c> en wel verre van het U te verwijten U zou voorstellen slechts om meer zamen te doen en geen van beiden ons te laten overdonderen. Beiden integendeel te toonen dat er pit en energie – en liefde tot de kunst van een degelijk<c type="kk">/</c> ernstig gehalte in ons zit<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Het is met mij zelf telkens zoo dat ik met vrij serieuse bezwaren te kampen heb<c type="kk">/</c> wel verre van voorspoedig te zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Goed – maar naarmate het uitwendige ongunstiger wordt neemt het inwendige<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. de lust in het werk<c type="kk">/</c> toe. En openen zich – indien al geen nieuwe ressources<c type="kk">/</c> toch nieuwe – <hi rend="italics">vernieuwde</hi> – <hi rend="italics">kansen</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Zooals gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> bij deze kleine zending teekeningen voegde ik een paar nieuwen maar ik zal trachten er deze maand verscheiden bij te maken in het formaat van die erwtendopster<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> die de laatste was welke ik maakte<c type="kp">_</c> Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Neem het mij niet kwalijk dat al is het het kostbaarste<c type="kk">/</c> ik bij de <hi rend="italics">figuren</hi> vooral blijf<c type="kp">_</c>– Hoe moeielijker de tijden zouden worden<c type="kk">/</c> hoe meer ik zou zoeken juist dat meester te worden<c type="kp">_</c> Want het is voorzien dat als de animo om te koopen niet grooter wordt<c type="kk">/</c> de lui die nog koopen blijven<c type="kk">/</c> hooger eischen stellen en dan is het boerenfiguur iets wat nu nog terdeeg kans heeft om te <hi rend="italics">blijven</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En wat den Haag betreft – ik acht het mogelijk dat sommige lui die ik ken en die nu tegen me zijn<c type="kk">/</c> te overtuigen zullen wezen<c type="kp">_</c>– En al moest het lang duren<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal zoo ligt het niet opgeven<c type="kk">/</c> vooreerst<c type="kk">/</c> dat kan ik U verzekeren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Het Ingres teekent heel prettig – en ik ben blij met die schetsboeken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het boek van Bracquemond heb ik nog gehouden omdat bij eerste lezing ik hetgeen hij zegt van chaud et froid niet begrepen nog heb<c type="kk">/</c> maar 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>ik geloof het iets belangrijks is dat hij van het licht zegt.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Dat is waar ik ’t mijne nog nader van hebben moet en dien te herlezen<c type="kp">_</c> De andere hoofdstukken zijn ook belangrijk en zijn definities goed doordacht.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter and 20 francs enclosed in good order, and thank you for them. Now I can inform you that I’ve sent my crate to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_491">Leurs</rs> with 7 different things and, to make it more complete, another 12 smaller painted studies.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’ve also written to tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs> that I’ve sent this batch and asked him to go and see them. I’m still sorry that this batch didn’t go to you instead, though. If we’d paid off Leurs and you’d taken this batch and then, if you were getting too many of the same kind, we had picked out this and that from the different batches to try in Holland, then the ones that still remained with you would, to my mind, have been the best and a nucleus to gradually expand as we progressed. As you say, though, it’s no use crying over spilt milk. Now as a provisional answer to what you write about drawings of figures in their surroundings, I sent a few off today.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I doubt whether they’re suitable for framing purposes — and if I have a bit of luck in finding something better in the fields, I’ll see about adding a few new ones very soon.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">As to what you write about being convinced <hi rend="italics">that the economizing hasn’t gone far enough yet</hi>, you may be seeing this in your ledger, if the outgoings are greater than the income. Possibly so. But the reason???</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Well yes — the people at home — <hi rend="italics">old chap</hi>, <hi>you can’t carry on as you’re doing now</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <hi rend="italics">I’m</hi> suffering because of it — I can assure you of that — but if need be I’m prepared to accept that I’m <hi rend="italics">even</hi> poorer than in other years because of it. But are they any happier for it at home, and is it making them any better off — — — the consequences later on, for them and for you, will you be happy about them?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Truly — when I think back to my own experience, when I consider that several years at G&amp;Cie <hi rend="italics">ended</hi> by my feeling very strongly drawn towards home, when I think how a crisis ensued for me, bewildering, and in which I so very soon stood entirely alone, and <hi rend="italics">everything</hi> and <hi rend="italics">everyone</hi> I had previously thought would endure, changed, and none of it stood fast. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">When I think back to those sad times, I’m so very much afraid that the present situation won’t prove to be <hi rend="italics">firm</hi> ground under your feet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And so I feel compelled — not in reproach, not to frighten you, not to dishearten you, but as a piece of harsh truth — to tell you that my view is that the sun can set for you — indeed — is setting. That what I add — renew yourself, but seek this renewal <hi rend="italics">in the heart of the profession</hi>: painting, and dealing too, but in <hi rend="italics">our own</hi> things — is proof enough that I don’t mean it reproachfully or insultingly. I speak as having known strife myself and as being in the middle of my battle. Anyway. With every year that one gets on in life, the time seems to go faster, more happens  things pick up speed. The fact that I say it straight out is so that you know that, should something change for you, I’d find it a natural, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> very understandable matter and, far from reproaching you for it, would simply suggest doing more together and not allowing either one of us to be overwhelmed. Both, on the contrary, to show that we have vigour and energy — and a love of art of a sound, serious standard.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">In my case I always have to contend with quite serious obstacles, far from being prosperous. Very well — but the more unfavourable the outward becomes, the more the inward, that is the passion for the work, increases. And — even if they aren’t new resources, new — <hi rend="italics">renewed </hi>—<hi rend="italics"> opportunities</hi> — do still open up. Anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">As I said, I added a couple of new ones to this small batch of drawings, but this month I’ll try to make several the size of that woman shelling peas,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> which was the last one I made. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Don’t take it amiss of me that I’m sticking primarily with the <hi rend="italics">figures</hi>, even though it’s the most expensive. The more difficult times were to get, the more I’d seek to master precisely that. For one can foresee that if the enthusiasm to buy doesn’t pick up, the people who do still buy will set higher standards, and then the peasant figure is something that still has a real chance of <hi rend="italics">lasting</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">And as regards The Hague — I consider it possible that some people whom I know and who are now against me, could be persuaded. And although it may have to take a long time, I shan’t give up easily as yet, that I can assure you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">The Ingres is very good to draw on — and I’m pleased with these sketchbooks.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’ve held on to the book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs> because at the first reading I didn’t understand what he’s saying about warm and cool, but 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> I think he’s saying something important about light.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">This is what I must get to the bottom of and should re-read. The other chapters are also important, and his definitions well thought out.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the 20 francs he sent, an extra allowance in August of which he was in dire need. It is not possible to say for sure at which point in the month it arrived. We estimate that the intention to make ‘several’ more drawings ‘this month’ <ref target="#l-88">(ll. 88-89)</ref> puts the <hi rend="italics">terminus ante quem</hi> at about five days before the end of the month. Vincent had moreover asked for money twice earlier in the month – the first time when the month was already well advanced and the second two days later (<ref target="let527.xml">letters 527</ref> and <ref target="let529.xml">529</ref> respectively), which we have dated on or about 17 and on or about 19 August (cf. <ref target="let527.xml">letter 527</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>). We therefore date the present letter between about Friday, 21 and about Wednesday, 26 August 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On a loose sheet, published for the first time in <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 as a separate letter (534 [-]), Vincent responds to what Theo wrote about drawing figures, and discusses the expense. The beginning consequently dovetails neatly with <ref target="let530.xml">letter 530</ref>, in which Vincent thanks Theo for his letter and says that he has sent some figure studies that day. Since, moreover, the comment about The Hague <ref target="#l-12">(l. 12)</ref> tallies with the shipment of nineteen works to Leurs’s shop in The Hague, we regard this small sheet as a continuation of <ref target="let530.xml">letter 530</ref>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
    
<p>The make-up of this consignment is difficult to reconstruct. In his previous letter Van Gogh wrote that he was planning to include a few cottages, a picture of the old tower and smaller figure studies. These works have not, however, been identified. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let529.xml#n-9">letter 529, nn. 9</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let529.xml#n-10">10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>There is a good chance that <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman lifting potatoes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_584">F 1273 / JH 909</rs>) was part of the batch for Theo: the drawing is signed and Vincent wrote in the lower left corner: ‘arracheuse de pommes de terre’. These ‘figures in surroundings’ may also have included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Man breaking up the soil</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_585">F 1325 / JH 903</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman stooping between wheat sheaves </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_586">F 1275a / JH 873</rs>); certainly Van Gogh made more of an effort with the backgrounds in them. Later in the letter he moreover refers to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman shelling peas </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2499">F 1214 / JH 702</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1997, pp. 248-249, cat. no. 194.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Theo supported several members of the family financially, including his mother, his sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> and his brother <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman shelling peas </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2499">F 1214 / JH 702</rs>); it measures 39.0 x 26.7 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In all probability Theo had brought <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Félix Bracquemond</rs>’s recently published <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_418">Du dessin et de la couleur</ref></hi> (On drawing and colour) (1885) with him when he came to Nuenen (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let526.xml">letter 526</ref>) – Vincent would like to keep it for a little while longer. The remarks links up with the statement that he had sent drawings to Paris. Bracquemond discusses the concepts of ‘warm’, ‘cool’ and ‘light’ in the chapter titled ‘Warmth – Cold. Relative aspects resulting from a light, a colour, a brightness’ (Chaleur – Froideur. Apparences relatives émanant d’une lumière, d’une couleur, d’une clarté) (see Bracquemond 1885, pp. 57-96). It is a textbook in which the artist Bracquemond explains numerous technical concepts.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    