<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Wednesday, 2 September 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let531"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b463 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>531</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>423</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>532</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-09-02">on or about Wednesday, 2 September 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0463" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0463" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000620_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor Uw brief en ingesl. frs 150.– Ik heb ook heden ontvangen de twee nieuwe Lhermittes<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Hij is het figuur de baas. hij weet er mede te doen wat hij wil – het ensemble opvattende noch van de kleur noch van den localen toon maar veeleer van het licht uitgaande – zooals Rembrandt deed – is er iets verbazend meesterachtigs in al wat hij doet – modeleerende vóór alle dingen voldoet hij volkomen aan de eisschen van eerlijk te wezen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Er is veel gesproken over – Poussin<c type="kp">_</c>– Bracquemond spreekt er ook over<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> De Franschen noemen Poussin hun allergrootsten schilder onder de ouden<c type="kp">_</c>– Wel is het zeker dat hetgeen van Poussin wordt gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> van wien ik zoo heel weinig ken<c type="kk">/</c> ik het terugvind in l’Hermitte &amp; in Millet<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar met dit onderscheid<c type="kk">/</c> dat het mij voorkomt Poussin de oorspronkelijke korrel is<c type="kk">/</c> de anderen de volle aar zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Ik voor mij stel dus die van heden <hi rend="italics">hooger</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb deze laatste 14 dagen erg veel last gehad van de eerwaarde heeren pastoors<c type="kk">/</c> die mij te kennen gaven – ook al met de beste bedoelingen en niet minder dan anderen meenende dat zij verpligt waren er zich mede te bemoeien – die mij te kennen gaven dat ik mij niet te familiaar moest maken met lieden beneden mijn stand – die het tot mij in zulke termen zeggende<c type="kk">/</c> tegen de “lieden van minderen stand” op een heel anderen toon zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. met dreigementen dat zij zich niet moesten laten uitschilderen<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ditmaal heb ik eenvoudig direkt het precies zoo verteld aan den burgemeester<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en er op gewezen hoe dit de pastoors niet raakt en die op hun eigen territoor van meer abstracte dingen moeten blijven<c type="kp">_</c>– In alle geval heb ik voorloopig geen tegenstand meer en ik acht het wel mogelijk het daarbij blijft ook<c type="kp">_</c>– Er moest een meid in de kraam die ik dikwijls geschilderd had en men zag er mij op aan hoewel ik het niet was<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Echter wetende hoe ’t geval in elkaar zat van de meid zelve en het een geval zijnde waarin een gemeentelid van den Nuenenschen pastoor 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>zich nog al bijzonder leelijk had gehouden<c type="kk">/</c> kunnen zij op mij, bij deze gelegenheid althans, geen vat krijgen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar gij ziet dat het niet makkelijk is om bij de lui aan huis te schilderen en in hun eigen gedoente te teekenen. Enfin – heel ligt zullen zij het in deze kwestie niet winnen en ik hoop dezen winter juist dezelfde modellen te houden<c type="kk">/</c> die door en door van oud Brabantsch ras zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Toch heb ik nog een paar nieuwe teekeningen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Maar in het veld kon<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ik nu dezer dagen onmogelijk iemand krijgen. Tot mijn geluk is de pastoor nog wel niet<c type="kk">/</c> maar begint toch te worden<c type="kk">/</c> vrij impopulair. Het is echter een leelijk ding en als het doorging zou ik denkelijk verhuizen.– Ge zult vragen<c type="kk">/</c> waar dient het toe een onaangenaam mensch te zijn – het moet soms<c type="kp">_</c>– Als ik zachtmoedig had geredeneerd hadden ze me zonder genade oversukkeld. En als zij me in mijn werk hinderen weet ik soms geen anderen weg dan oog om oog en tand om tand. De pastoor ging zoover dat hij de menschen geld <hi rend="italics">beloofde</hi> als zij zich niet lieten schilderen – de lui echter zeiden heel parmantig terug dat zij het liever aan mij verdienden dan bij hem iets te komen vragen<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar gij ziet<c type="kk">/</c> zij doen het niet dan ter wille van te verdienen en ik krijg <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> voor <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> hier gedaan<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Gij vraagt mij of Rappard ooit iets verkocht heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik weet hij het tegenwoordig ruimer heeft dan vroeger<c type="kk">/</c> dat hij b.v. een tijd lang dag aan dag naakt model nam<c type="kk">/</c> dat hij nu ter wille van een sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van een steenbakkerij een huisje op de plaats zelve huurde en het veranderde zoo dat hij licht van boven had –<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> ik weet dat hij een reis is gaan doen weer door Drenthe<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en dat hij tevens naar Terschelling gaat. Dat dit een &amp; ander vrij kostbaar is en het geld er voor <hi rend="italics">ergens</hi> vandaan moet komen<c type="kp">_</c> Dat ofschoon hij geld van zich zelf moge hebben<c type="kk">/</c> hij er beslist bij verdient want anders kon hij niet doen wat hij doet<c type="kp">_</c>– Het kan zijn dat zijn familie koopt of kennissen<c type="kk">/</c> dat wel<c type="kk">/</c> maar iemand toch<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Maar ik heb van avond te veel met de teekeningen van Lhermitte te doen dan dat ik over andere dingen verder doorschrijf<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Als ik aan Millet of aan Lhermitte denk – dan – vind ik de moderne kunst zoo groot – als Michel Ange en Rembrandt – het oude oneindig<c type="kk">/</c> het nieuwe ook oneindig – het oude <hi rend="italics">genie</hi><c type="kk">/</c> het nieuwe <hi rend="italics">genie</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Dit vindt iemand als Chenavard misschien niet<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> – maar ik ben voor mij zelf overtuigd – dat men in het tegenwoordige wat dat betreft gelooven kan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dat ik betreffende kunst een bepaald geloof heb maakt ook dat ik weet wat ik in mijn eigen werk wil krijgen en dat ik dat zal zoeken te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> ook al ging ik er zelf bij onder door. Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">b. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter and 150 francs enclosed. I also received the two new <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>s today.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> He’s a master of the figure. He’s able to do what he likes with it — conceiving the whole neither from the colour nor from the local tone, but rather proceeding from the light — as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> did — there’s something astonishingly masterly in everything he does — in modelling, above all things, he utterly satisfies the demands of honesty.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">A great deal is said about — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1277">Poussin</rs>. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs> talks about him, too.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> The French call Poussin their greatest ever painter among the old masters. Well it’s certain that what’s said about Poussin, whom I know so very little about, I find in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> and in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>. But with this distinction, that it seems to me Poussin is the original grain, the others are the full ear. For my part, then, I rate today’s <hi rend="italics">superior</hi>.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">This last fortnight I’ve had a great deal of trouble with the reverend gentlemen of the priesthood, who gave me to understand — of course with the best of intentions and, no less than others, believing that it was their duty to interfere — who gave me to understand that I shouldn’t be too familiar with people beneath my station — who, having spoken to me in those terms, spoke in a very different tone to the ‘people of lower station’, that’s to say with threats that they mustn’t allow themselves to be painted.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> This time I simply went straight to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_450">burgomaster</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and told him exactly what had happened, and pointed out that this was none of the priests’ business and that they should stick to their own province of more abstract things. In any event, I’m not encountering any more opposition for the time being, and I think it quite possible that that’s how it will remain. A girl I’d often painted was having a child and they thought it was mine, although it wasn’t me.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> However, knowing the facts of the matter from the girl herself and it being a case in which a member of the priest’s congregation in Nuenen 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> had behaved extremely badly, they can’t get their teeth into me, at least not this time. But you see that it isn’t easy to paint people at home and draw them as they go about their business. Anyway — they won’t easily win in this case, and this winter I do hope to keep the very same models, who are of the old Brabant stock through and through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Even so, I have a few more new drawings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But now, in the last few days, I could<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> not get anyone in the fields. Fortunately for me, the priest isn’t yet, but is nonetheless beginning to become, quite unpopular. It’s a bad business, though, and if it were to continue I’d probably move. You’ll ask what’s the point of being a disagreeable person — sometimes you have to be. If I’d discussed it meekly they’d have ground me down without mercy. And when they hinder me in my work, sometimes the only way I know is an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth. The priest went so far as to <hi rend="italics">promise</hi> the people money if they didn’t allow themselves to be painted — however, the people replied very pertly that they’d rather earn it from me than go cap in hand to him. But you see, they only do it for the sake of earning money and I don’t get <hi rend="italics">anything</hi> done for <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> around here. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">You ask me whether <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> has ever sold anything. I know he’s flusher at present than before, that for a long time, for instance, he had a nude model day after day, that for the purposes of a painting of a brickworks he’s now rented a small house actually on the spot and altered it so that he had light from above<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — I know that he’s been on another trip through Drenthe<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and that he’s also going to Terschelling. That all of this is pretty expensive, and the money for it has to come from <hi rend="italics">somewhere</hi>. That although he may have money of his own, he must be earning as well, because otherwise he couldn’t do what he’s doing. It may be that his family is buying or friends, that’s possible, but at any rate somebody must be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But this evening I’m much too occupied with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>’s drawings to go on writing any more about other things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">When I think about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> or about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs> — then — I find modern art as great — as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> — the old infinite, the new infinite too — the old <hi rend="italics">genius</hi>, the new <hi rend="italics">genius</hi>. Perhaps someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_943">Chenavard</rs> doesn’t see it like this<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> — but for my part I’m convinced — that in this regard one can believe in the present.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">The fact that I have a definite belief as regards art also means that I know what I want to get in my own work, and that I’ll try to get it even if I go under in the attempt. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the 150 francs he had sent, which must have been the allowance for September. This emerges from a remark about the reaction of the Nuenen clergy that Vincent makes here <ref target="#l-23">(ll. 23-24)</ref>, which Theo discussed in a letter to Mrs van Gogh on 8 September 1885 (FR b902). We have therefore dated the letter on or about Wednesday, 2 September 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let496.xml">letter 496</ref> Vincent expressed the hope that Theo would continue to watch out for the publication of ‘new months’ in this series. Since he had meanwhile received the months of February, March and April from ‘Les mois rustiques’, and was subsequently to get September, October and November, it is safe to assume that by the ‘new’ <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>s he meant the prints for the months of July and August (the month of June was not published).</p>
    
<p rend="indent">The months of July and August are Léon Augustin Lhermitte, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les fraises des bois </hi>(Wild strawberries), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1512">Charles Baude</rs> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2152">Ill. 2152</rs>), and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La soir dans la rivière</hi> (Evening on the river), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1513">Clément Edouard Bellenger</rs> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2153">Ill. 2153</rs>), in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi>. 29 (1 August 1885), Supplement to no. 1479 and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 29 (29 August 1885), Supplement to no. 1483.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Félix Bracquemond</rs> discusses <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1277">Nicolas Poussin</rs> in the chapter ‘Décoration, décorateur’ in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_418">Du dessin et de la couleur</ref></hi>, and examines the conflict between colour and line. He attaches a great deal of value to the line (drawing) and believes that colour plays a subordinate role. He insists that artists should draw from nature and then work these studies out in colour in the studio from memory and imagination, rather than copying the colours of nature (see Bracquemond 1885, pp. 203-209).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>They were <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_565">Andreas Pauwels</rs>, who was priest in Nuenen from 1880 to 1889, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_566">W. Beekmans</rs>, chaplain from 1882 to 1890. See De Brouwer 1984, p. 96.</p>

<p rend="indent">On 8 September 1885 Theo wrote about this matter to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>: ‘What bad luck for Vincent, he wrote to me about it too, is there anything those priests don’t interfere in? If only he could find something else suitable soon! All the painters I show his work to say that there’s a great deal in it and he must just keep going’ (FR b902).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The burgomaster of Nuenen was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_450">Johannes van Hombergh</rs> (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>, Administratief Archief Nuenen). Van Gogh wrote a note to Van Hombergh in September 1887 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let573.xml">letter 573</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This ‘girl’ was the unmarried <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_403">Gordina de Groot</rs>, who modelled for Van Gogh several times.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>It is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘kan’ (can) rather than ‘kon’ (could).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_331">Workers at the Ruimzicht brickyard</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let528.xml">letters 528</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let529.xml">529</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> returned to Drenthe not only in 1885, but in 1886 too. See Egbert Brink, ‘Ridder in het armenhuis. Anthon van Rappard in Drenthe’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Waardeel. Drents Historisch Tijdschrift</hi> 25-1 (2005), pp. 23-28, esp. 27.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh knew of the history painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_943">Paul Marc Joseph Chenavard</rs> through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Charles Blanc</rs>, who devoted a chapter to him in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_403">Les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>. Blanc believed that, unlike most contemporary French artists, Chenavard had not fallen prey to decadence and had made an extensive study of the old masters. According to Blanc they should show modern art the way (see Blanc 1876, pp. 191-198 and cf. the quotation from Blanc in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let449.xml">letter 449</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    