<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Saturday, 14 November 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let541"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b473 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>541</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>433</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>544</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-12-14">on or about Saturday, 14 November 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0473 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0473 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000638_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0473 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0473 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000639_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">In het boek van de Goncourt vond ik de volgende zin in het artikel over Chardin door U aangestreept. Na gesproken te hebben over ’t slecht betaald worden van de schilders zegt hij: “Que faire<c type="kk">/</c> que devenir. Il faut se jeter dans une condition subalterne ou mourir de faim<c type="kp">_</c>– On prend le premier parti”<c type="kp">_</c> zóó, zegt hij verder, behalve enkele <hi rend="italics">martelaars</hi><c type="kk">/</c> gaan de rest “schermmeester<c type="kk">/</c> soldaat of comediant worden”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Dat is au fond wel degelijk nog een waarheid gebleven<c type="kp">_</c>– Wegens gij het bovenstaande hadt aangeteekend achtte ik het mogelijk gij, vooral waar ik U juist berigt heb dat ik mijn tegenwoordige werkplaats heb opgezegd, kondt verlangen te weten wat ik me verder voorneem te doen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Geheel en al zijn de dagen van nu niet eender als die van Chardin<c type="kp">_</c>– En tegenwoordig zijn er een paar dingen moeielijk weg te redeneeren<c type="kp">_</c> Het aantal schilders is veel grooter<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu maakt het op het publiek direkt een fatalen indruk als een schilder “er iets bij doet”<c type="kp">_</c> Ik ben betrekkelijk daar geenszins boven verheven<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> schilder door<c type="kk">/</c> maak eens een honderd en als ’t niet genoeg is twee honderd studies<c type="kk">/</c> en kijk eens of dat niet U over ’t “iets er bij doet” heenzet<c type="kp">_</c>– Dan<c type="kk">/</c> zich wennen aan armoede<c type="kk">/</c> kijken hoe een soldaat of een sjouwer leeft en gezond blijft bij weer en wind met het gewone volkseten &amp; woning<c type="kk">/</c> is even praktisch als ’t een gulden of wat meer verdienen in de week<c type="kp">_</c> Men is toch voor zijn gemak niet in de wereld en hoeft het niet beter te hebben dan een ander<c type="kp">_</c> Dat helpt toch betrekkelijk <hi rend="italics">niets</hi><c type="kk">/</c> of men ’t wat beter heeft – onze jonge jaren kunnen we toch niet vasthouden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6"><hi rend="italics">Als</hi> <hi>dat</hi> kon – maar dus het eigentlijke wat gelukkig maakt<c type="kk">/</c> materieel gelukkig<c type="kk">/</c> jong zijn en lang blijven – wel dat is hier niet – dat is in Arabie of Italie niet eens<c type="kk">/</c> al is <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> daar beter dan hier<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">En ik voor mij ben van meening dat men ’t meest kans heeft om krachtig te blijven en zich te vernieuwen – onder den tiers etat<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> van nu. Enfin. Ik zeg dus dat ik in ’t schilderen ’t zoek te vinden<c type="kk">/</c> zonder bijgedachten<c type="kp">_</c> Maar – ik zal denk ik wel doen<c type="kk">/</c> het portretten maken in ’t oog te houden. als ik verdienen wil. Ik weet dat het lastig is ’t de lui naar den zin te maken met de “gelijkenis” en ik durf niet vooruit zeggen dat ik me zeker van mijn zaak voel<c type="kp">_</c> Geheel onmogelijk acht ik ’t echter zeker niet want de menschen hier zullen wel al mee zijn als de menschen elders. De boeren nu en de lui uit ’t dorp vergissen zich niet en zeggen grif<c type="shy">-</c>weg<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs <hi rend="italics">tegen me in als ik zeg dat ze ’t mis hebben</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> is Reinier de Greef<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> dat is Toon de Groot<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en dat is Dien van de Beek<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> En herkennen zelfs een figuur van achteren gezien somtijds<c type="kp">_</c>– In stad hechten de burgerluidjes<c type="kk">/</c> en zeker niet minder de cocottes<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">altijd</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wie ze ook zijn<c type="kk">/</c> aan portretten. En Millet – heeft ontdekt dat de scheepskapteins er “iemand om achten” zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> als hij dat kan (voor hun maitressen aan wal zijn die portretten denkelijk </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">bestemd)<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Dat is nog niet geexploiteerd<c type="kp">_</c>– Herinnert ge U dat uit Sensier. Ik heb het altijd onthouden hoe Millet zich zoodoende te Havre staande hield.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t ruwe is mijn plan om naar Antwerpen te gaan – hoe of wat<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik onmogelijk berekenen vooruit<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik ben te weten gekomen 6 adressen van kunsthandelaars<c type="kk">/</c> dus ik wou wat medenemen en verder heb ik voor ’t werk plan zoo dra ik er kom een paar gezigten van de stad te schilderen – redelijk groot – en die direkt te exposeeren ook<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Dus alles concentreeren om daar iets uit te rigten. En er arm naar toe gaande<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik er in geen geval veel verliezen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Nu wat hier betreft – ik ken de streek en de luidjes te goed en ik houd er te veel van dan dat ik zeker weet ’t geheel uit ware<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zal een vertrek zien te huren waar ik mijn boel berg en ben dan gedekt tevens in geval ik in Antwerpen me voor een tijd terug wil trekken – of ’t heimwee naar buiten mogt krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Wat betreft “’t iets er bij doen” – van begin af aan heeft b.v. Tersteeg me daar over <hi rend="italics">gezanikt</hi><c type="kp">_</c> En dat was <hi rend="italics">zaniken</hi><c type="kk">/</c> wat er ook overigens van Tersteeg zij. Die er ’t meest over praten zijn tevens niet bij magte te preciseeren wat dan<c type="kp">_</c>– En wat dat betreft<c type="kk">/</c> om in mijn geval het geheel op te helderen – als ik er “iets bij deed” dan zou het eenige wezen dat als ik ’t zij handelaars ’t zij schilders kende<c type="kk">/</c> ik eens iets met schilderijen zou doen eventueel<c type="kk">/</c> door b.v. eens voor hen naar Engeland te gaan &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Zulke dingen natuurlijk die bij ’t schilderen zich direkt aansluiten<c type="kk">/</c> maken een uitzondering<c type="kk">/</c> maar anders<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">in den regel</hi> een schilder moet geheel schilder zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vergeet ook niet dat ik niet voor melancolicus in de wieg ben gelegd<c type="kp">_</c> den bijnaam die ik hier in de buurt heb is algemeen ’t schildermenneke en het is niet ten eenemale zonder een dosis malice dat ik naar ginder ga<c type="kp">_</c> Nu heb ik echter ook gedacht aan Drenthe doch als bezwaarlijker uitvoerbaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Dat zou echter goed zijn voor ’t geval dat mijn werk uit het boerenland in Antw. mogt bevallen. Als de dingen van hier ’t zij nu ’t zij later bevallen<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik er op doorgaan en ze afwisselen met soortgelijken uit Drenthe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Doch de kwestie is dat ik maar één ding te gelijk kan doen<c type="kk">/</c> dat als ik druk in boerenschilderijen zit<c type="kk">/</c> ik met zaken in stad me niet kan bezig houden<c type="kp">_</c>– Het moment van nu is juist geschikt om er eens uit te breken daar ik gescharrel met het model nemen heb gehad en verhuizen ga in alle geval<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat dat betreft<c type="kk">/</c> in deze werkplaats vlak naast den pastoor en koster<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> zou er nooit een eind aan komen<c type="kk">/</c> dat is te voorzien<c type="kp">_</c>– Dus dat verander ik<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar overigens<c type="kk">/</c> het maakt op de lui geen <hi rend="italics">absoluten</hi> indruk en met een ander vertrek te huren en ’t een paar maanden te laten rusten<c type="kk">/</c> is de intrigue haar kracht aanmerkelijk kwijt<c type="kp">_</c> Kon ik nu de paar eerstvolgende maanden ginder zijn<c type="kk">/</c> December &amp; Januarij<c type="kk">/</c> was dat niet ’t beste<c type="kp">_</c>– In Amsterdam logeerde ik voor 50 cents in een volksgaarkeuken<c type="kk">/</c> dat zou ik ginder ook doen<c type="kk">/</c> of nog liever met een of ander schilder accoord maken om op zijn atelier te kunnen werken. Er komt nog een reden bij<c type="kk">/</c> dat het niet absoluut onmogelijk is ik ergens een gelegenheid vind om naakt te schilderen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Op de akademie zouden zij me niet willen<c type="kk">/</c> noch ook ik denkelijk – maar – bij een beeldhouwer b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> er moeten er zeker een paar wonen<c type="kk">/</c> kan men ligt eenige sympathie vinden. Het spreekt van zelf dat men met geld zooveel modellen kan krijgen als men wil<c type="kk">/</c> doch zonder dat is het een moeielijke kwestie<c type="kp">_</c>– Toch<c type="kk">/</c> er zullen ginder wel lui zijn die naakt model nemen en met wie men zich wat de kosten betreft combineeren kan<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb ’t voor veel dingen noodig.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Terwijl ik U schrijf ontvang ik Uw brief<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Ik wil wel desnoods eens naar v.d. Loo gaan<c type="kk">/</c> alleen gij weet dat de dokters soms niet alles zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> vooral in dubieuse gevallen. Begrijp ook wel dat wat ik zeg van dat zij wat beneveld is geweest<c type="kk">/</c> denkelijk wel nog eens weer worden zal<c type="kk">/</c> een ding is dat de meeste menschen die oud worden hebben<c type="kp">_</c> In alle geval vind ik het idee zeer praktisch om, ten zij ze <hi rend="italics">absoluut</hi> er op staat er bij te blijven, haar niet bij de verhuisdrukte te laten zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Overigens, kerel, geloof ik voor mij dat v<c type="kp">_</c>d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo alles<c type="kk">/</c> absoluut alles heeft geraden aan Moe wat te raden was<c type="kk">/</c> en niets nieuws zou zeggen. Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> hij zou reeds gewaarschuwd hebben als er een af te wenden gevaar dreigde<c type="kp">_</c> Maar als hij niets zegt is het een teeken dat al ware er iets<c type="kk">/</c> hij er niets aan doen kan en er niets aan gedaan moet worden<c type="kk">/</c> als hij de natuur aan zich zelf overlaat dan doet hij het omdat zulks ’t beste is – v.d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo is fameus secuur en – Zola achtig koel en leuk<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> Enfin – maar ik zal er Wil over spreken en ’t zij dat ik er eens heenga ’t zij dat Moe v<c type="kp">_</c>d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo eens 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>als hij op ’t dorp is tegenkomt<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> we zullen wel iets doen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ’t zal zijn loop moeten hebben zonder veel meer denk ik<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu<c type="kk">/</c> het <hi rend="italics">tobben</hi> en overbezorgd zijn in zulke gevallen<c type="kk">/</c> ge zult het met me eens zijn<c type="kk">/</c> is ondragelijk voor den patient <hi rend="italics">als die ’t merkt</hi>. En oude menschen<c type="kk">/</c> er is net niets van te voorspellen dikwijls<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat bij zooveel het hart niet normaal is<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. door vervetting<c type="kk">/</c> en dan kunnen ze net zoo goed in eens weg zijn als nog 5<c type="kk">/</c> nog 10 jaar blijven gaan<c type="kp">_</c>– Emotie dan kan natuurlijk influenceeren<c type="kk">/</c> maar daarom juist is er veel meer kans van leven blijven als de geest zoo heel bijster klaar niet meer is<c type="kk">/</c> dan in periodes van helderzien. Nog iets – bij Moe nu bepaaldelijk weet ik zeker dat er althans bij wijlen een ondergrond van diepe gedachten is (want haar inwendig<c type="kk">/</c> haar gemoedsleven is zoo tamelijk ingewikkeld en met verdiepingen of lagen) die zij noch zou willen noch zou kunnen zeggen. In veel gevallen was zij nog al zwijgend<c type="kk">/</c> dus – ik voor één<c type="kk">/</c> zeg liever dat ik niet altijd alles van haar af weet<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="italics">Juist nu ze</hi> <hi rend="italics">helder is haar zelf te laten doen zoo</hi> <hi rend="italics">als ze wil</hi><c type="kk">/</c> zeker ’t makkelijkst vooreerst voor haar zelf en tweedens het meest verantwoord voor ons<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Stilzwijgend begrijpende hoe het voor haar geenszins een ongeluk zou wezen indien het al ware dat zij niet heel lang meer leefde en zonder veel lijden heenging<c type="kk">/</c> is sereniteit in deze gemotiveerd<c type="kp">_</c> Sereniteit echter ook al ware het dat er nog jaren van betrekkelijk machinaal leven resteerden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ge ziet dat ik mijn gaan naar Antwerpen zoowat ter zelfder tijd wou schikken als hun reis<c type="kk">/</c> die in Februarij zoowat om is<c type="kp">_</c>– Tusschen dan en het definitieve verhuizen van hen ben ik of te Nuenen terug of – als er iets bijzonders me langer hield<c type="kk">/</c> toch steeds direkt bereid om als er iets gebeurde present te zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Deze moet weg<c type="kk">/</c> maar, ik schrijf U binnen een paar dagen wat ik met Wil afspreek. Ik zal haar voorstellen om vòòr de reis met Moe nog eens naar v.d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> dat is voor Moe zelf iets van zelf sprekends. Als v.d. Loo haar dan gezien heeft<c type="kk">/</c> is ’t voor ’t zij Wil<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij mij ’t moment om v<c type="kp">_</c>d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo kort en bondig te vragen of hij iets kan zeggen aangaande de kans die zij nog op ’t leven heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– Des noods<c type="kk">/</c> al naar mate gij en Wil er over denkt<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik bereid vóór dat bezoek van Moe v.d<c type="kp">_</c> Loo te prepareeren en zeggen wat wij gaarne zouden weten<c type="kk">/</c> opdat hij eens goed nog ’t heele gestel onderzoeke. Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Schrijf me eens spoedig wat ge denkt van dat naar Antw. gaan – ik geloof er niets tegen is.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I came across the following sentence that you’d underlined in the article on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs> in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>’s book. After speaking about painters being badly paid, he says: ‘What to do, what to become. He must abandon himself to the inferior occupations or die of hunger. The first course is adopted’. <hi rend="italics">So</hi>, he goes on to say, aside from a few <hi rend="italics">martyrs</hi>, the rest ‘become fencing masters, soldiers or comedians’.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">That really has remained fundamentally true. Seeing as you’d marked the above, I considered it possible you might want to know what I intend to do next, especially since I’ve just informed you that I’ve given notice on my current studio.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">The present day isn’t entirely the same as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs>’s, and nowadays there are a few things that are hard to argue away. The number of painters is much greater.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now it immediately makes a fatal impression on the public if a painter ‘does something on the side’. I’m not at all above that in this respect, I should say keep on painting, make a hundred studies, and if that’s not enough, two hundred, and just see if that doesn’t get you over ‘doing something on the side’. Then accustoming yourself to poverty, seeing how a soldier or a labourer lives and stays healthy in wind and weather with the ordinary people’s food and dwelling, is as practical as earning a guilder or a bit more a week. After all, one’s not in the world for one’s comfort and doesn’t have to be any better off than the next man. Being better off helps hardly <hi rend="italics">at all</hi> — after all, we can’t hold on to our youth.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><hi rend="italics">If</hi> <hi>that</hi> were possible — but the thing that really makes one happy, being young and staying so for a long time — well, that isn’t here — that isn’t even in Arabia or Italy, although <hi rend="italics">that</hi> is better there than here.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And for my part, I’m of the opinion that one has the greatest chance of staying strong and renewing oneself — in today’s third estate.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Anyway. So I’m saying that I seek to find it in painting, without ulterior motives. But — I’d do well, I think, to bear portrait painting in mind if I want to earn. I know it’s difficult to please people with a ‘likeness’, and I dare not say beforehand that I feel sure of my case. I certainly don’t consider it altogether impossible, though, because the people here will be much the same as people elsewhere. Well then, the peasants and the folk from the village aren’t mistaken and promptly say, even <hi rend="italics">contradicting me if I say they’re wrong, that</hi> is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_435">Renier de Greef</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> that’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_424">Toon de Groot</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and that’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_263">Dien van der Beek</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c. And sometimes even recognize a figure seen from behind. In town, the bourgeois folk, and certainly no less the tarts, no matter who they are, <hi rend="italics">always</hi> value portraits. And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> — discovered that ship’s captains actually ‘respect someone for it’ if he can do that (those portraits are probably intended for their mistresses ashore). 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> This hasn’t been exploited yet. Do you remember this in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>? I’ve always remembered how Millet kept himself going in Le Havre this way.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"> Well roughly, my plan is to go to Antwerp — I can’t possibly calculate the ins and outs beforehand.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’ve come by the addresses of 6 art dealers, so I’d want to take something with me and further, as to the work, I plan to paint a few views of the city as soon as I get there — reasonably large — — and show them straightaway too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">In other words concentrate everything on doing something there. And going there poor, at any rate I can’t lose much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Now as regards here — I know the area and the folk too well and love them too much to believe I’m going for good. I’ll see about renting a place to store my things, and then I’m also covered should I want to leave Antwerp for a while — or should become homesick for the country.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">As for ‘doing something on the side’ — right from the outset <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>, for instance, <hi rend="italics">nagged</hi> me about it. And that was <hi rend="italics">nagging</hi>, whatever else one may think of Tersteeg. Those who talk about it the most aren’t at the same time able to explain precisely what. And as to that, in order to clear the whole thing up in my case — if I did ‘something on the side’, then the only thing would be that, if I knew either dealers or painters, I would possibly do something with paintings, for instance by going to England for them &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Things like this, which are obviously directly related to painting, are an exception, but otherwise, <hi rend="italics">as a rule</hi>, a painter must be wholly a painter.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Don’t forget, either, that I’m not cut out to be a melancholic. The nickname I have around here is generally ‘the little painter fellow’, and it’s not entirely without a measure of malice that I’m going there. I’ve also thought of Drenthe, though, but as more difficult to bring about.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">That would be good, though, should my work from the countryside be liked in Antwerp. If the things from here were liked, either now or later, then I would continue with them, and vary them with similar things from Drenthe.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But the issue is that I can only do one thing at a time, that if I’m engaged in painting peasants, I can’t occupy myself with business in town. The present moment is ideal for breaking away, since I’ve had trouble getting models and am going to move in any case. As to that, it’s to be expected that there would never be an end to it in this studio right next door to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_565">priest</rs> and the sacristan.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> So I’m changing that.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">But anyway, it doesn’t make an <hi rend="italics">absolute</hi> impression on people, and by renting another room and letting things lie for a few months, the intrigue will lose a great deal of its force. Wouldn’t it be best if I could spend the next couple of months, December and January, there? In Amsterdam I lodged in a soup kitchen for 50 cents; I’d do the same there, or better yet reach agreement with some painter or other to be allowed to work in his studio. There’s another reason, too — that it’s not absolutely impossible I might find an opportunity somewhere to paint from the nude.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">They wouldn’t want me at the academy, nor probably would I — but — with a sculptor, say, there must surely be a few living there, one might readily find some sympathy. It goes without saying that people with money can get as many models as they want, but it’s a difficult matter without it. All the same, there must be people there who use nude models and with whom one could split the cost. I need it for many things.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I received your letter while I was writing to you.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I’m willing to go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_495">Van de Loo</rs> if need be, only you know that doctors sometimes don’t tell you everything, particularly in doubtful cases. You should also understand that what I said about her being rather in a fog will probably recur, is a thing that most people who are getting old have. In any event I think it a very practical idea not to let her stay in the midst of the upheaval of the removal, unless she <hi rend="italics">absolutely</hi> insists. For the rest, old chap, for my part I believe that Van de Loo has given <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> all, absolutely all the advice there was to give, and would say nothing new. I mean, he would already have given a warning if a danger that could be averted were threatening. But if he doesn’t say anything it’s a sign that, if there were something, he can’t do anything about it and nothing should be done about it; if he’s letting nature take its course, he’s doing it because that’s the best thing — Van de Loo is enormously scrupulous and — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>-like cool and calm. Anyhow — I’ll speak to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> about it, and either I may go there or Ma may come across Van de Loo sometime 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> when he’s in the village;<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> we’ll do something. But I think it will just have to take its course. Now in such cases, you’ll agree with me, <hi rend="italics">worrying</hi> and being overanxious is intolerable for the patient <hi rend="italics">if she notices it</hi>. And with old people there’s often no way of predicting it, precisely because in so many cases their hearts aren’t normal, because of fatty degeneration, say, and they can just as easily go off suddenly as carry on for another 5, another 10 years. Emotion can have an effect, of course, but precisely because of this there’s much more chance of staying alive if the mind is no longer all too clear, than in periods of lucidity. Something else — I’m quite sure that, from time to time at least, there’s definitely a substratum of deep thoughts in Ma (for her inner life, her life of the mind is fairly complicated and has levels or layers) that she neither wants to nor could express. In many cases she was rather silent, so — I for one would rather say that I don’t always know everything about her. <hi rend="italics">Particularly now that she’s lucid, letting her do as she wants</hi> is certainly the easiest, firstly for her and secondly the most sensible for us.
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Silently understanding how it would by no means be a misfortune for her were it to be that she didn’t live very much longer and departed without much suffering, serenity is justifiable in this regard. Serenity too, though, were it to be that years of relatively mechanical life remained.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">You see that I wanted to arrange my going to Antwerp at around the same time as their trip, which will be over around February. Between then and their final move, I’ll either be back in Nuenen or — if something exceptional detained me longer, nonetheless always ready to be present right away if something happened.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">This must go off, but I’ll write in a few days and tell you what I’ve arranged with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs>. I’ll suggest she goes to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_495">Van de Loo</rs> with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> before the trip; that would go without saying for Ma. Once Van de Loo has seen her, that will be the moment for either Wil or me to ask Van de Loo outright whether he can say anything about her life expectancy. For my part, depending on what you and Wil think about it, I’m willing to prepare Van de Loo before Ma’s visit, and tell him what we’d like to know, so that he gives her a really thorough examination. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Write soon and tell me what you think about my going to Antwerp — I don’t believe there’s anything against it.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let540.xml">letter 540</ref> Van Gogh wrote that he intended to give notice on his studio as of May; in the present letter he says that he had ‘just’ informed Theo of this <ref target="#l-12">(l. 12)</ref> – this establishes the sequence of the letters. The fact that the letter was written in November is also evident from the wording ‘Wouldn’t it be best if I could spend the next couple of months, December and January, there?’ <ref target="#l-130">(ll. 130-132)</ref>. See for the dating of this letter: <ref target="let539.xml">letter 539</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Opposition from the Catholic clergy <ref target="let531.xml">(531)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The impending move of Mrs van Gogh and Willemien <ref target="let540.xml">(540)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Taken from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_426">L’art du dix-huitième siècle</ref></hi> by the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>s: ‘What to do, what to become? One must throw oneself into some subordinate condition, where the door is open to poverty, or die of hunger. One chooses the former and, with the exception of about twenty people who come here every two years to exhibit themselves to fools, the others, equally unknown but perhaps less unfortunate, wear their breastplate at some fencing-master’s, or carry a musket on their shoulder in some regiment or tread the boards in stage costume’ (Que faire, que devenir? Il faut se jeter dans quelques-unes de ces conditions subalternes, dont la porte est ouverte à la misère, ou mourir de faim. On prend le premier parti; et à l’exception d’une vingtaine, qui viennent ici tous les deux ans s’exposer aux bêtes, les autres ignorés, et moins malheureux peut-être, ont le plastron sur la poitrine dans une salle d’armes, ou le mousquet sur l’épaule dans un régiment, ou l’habit de théâtre sur les tréteaux?) (see Goncourt 1881-1914, vol. 1, p. 151, and cf. Goncourt 1948, p. 147).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for the ‘Tiers état’, the lower classes: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let539.xml">letter 539</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_435">Renier de Greef</rs> was a farmer in Nuenen. Like Van Gogh, he lived in district F and modelled for him (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>, and De Brouwer 1984, p. 111 (with portrait)).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_424">Antonie (Toon) de Groot</rs> was a labourer in Nuenen; he lived in district F and modelled for Van Gogh (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_263">Ardina (Dien) van der Beek</rs>, no occupation, married to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_182">Franciscus Raaijmakers</rs>, modelled for Van Gogh. She lived in district E-F (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh bases this on what <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs> wrote about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s stay in Le Havre in 1845: ‘He did, in fact, everything: portraits of master mariners, shipowners, harbour masters and workers, even sailors. Amongst others, he painted a señora in a pink and blue silk dress reclining nonchantly on a sofa, specially commissioned by a captain. This painting delighted everyone. Millet was all the rage for a while... A public exhibition of his work was arranged in Le Havre and he did a few more portraits. Finally, when not without difficulty he had got together 900 francs, he left for Paris with his wife’ (Il fit, en effet, de tout: portraits de capitaines au long cours, d’armateurs, de commandants ou employés du port, voir même de matelots. Il peignit, entre autres, une señora en costume de soie rose et bleue, étendue nonchalamment sur un canapé, qu’un capitaine lui avait recommandée tout spécialement. Cette peinture plut à tous. Millet eut un instant de vogue ... On organisa une exposition publique de ses oeuvres au Havre, et il fit encore quelques portraits. Enfin, quand il eut, non sans peine, rassemblé 900 francs, il partit pour Paris avec sa femme) (see Sensier, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238">La vie et l’oeuvre de J.F. Millet</ref></hi> (1881), pp. 84, 87; also quoted in Burty 1877, p. 282. Cf. in this context <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml">letter 542</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The priest <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_565">Andreas Pauwels</rs> and the sacristan <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_667">Johannes Schafrat</rs>. Van Gogh rented his studio from Schafrat.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This must have been a letter in which Theo had asked about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs>’s health in response to <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let540.xml">letter 540</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘kalm’ (calm).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_495">Van de Loo</rs> lived in Eindhoven.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    