<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Saturday, 28 November 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let545"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b477 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>545</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>437</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>548</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-12-28">Saturday, 28 November 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0477" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0477" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000644_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Zaturdag avond</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Wilde U nog eenige impressies van Antwerpen schrijven. Van morgen heb ik een heel echte wandeling gemaakt in den plasregen<c type="kk">/</c> een togt die ten doel had om mijn goed van het douanenkantoor te halen.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> de verschillende entrepots en hangars aan de kaaien zijn erg mooi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Verscheiden keeren reeds ben ik op allerlei manieren langs die dokken &amp; kaaien gewandeld<c type="kp">_</c> Vooral wanneer men uit ’t zand en de hei &amp; de stilte van een boerendorp komt en lang niets anders dan in een stille omgeving is geweest<c type="kk">/</c> is het curieus als contrast<c type="kp">_</c> Het is een ondoorgrondelijken warboel<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Een van de spreekwoorden van de Goncourt was “<hi rend="italics">Japonaiserie</hi> <hi rend="italics">for ever</hi>”<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wel<c type="kk">/</c> die dokken zijn een fameuse <hi rend="italics">Japonaiserie</hi><c type="kk">/</c> grillig<c type="kk">/</c> eigenaardig<c type="kk">/</c> ongehoord – ten minste men kan ’t zoo zien<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ik zou er wel eens met U willen loopen om te weten of we ’t zelfde kijken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Men zou er alles kunnen maken<c type="kk">/</c> stadsgezigten – figuren van ’t meest uiteenloopend karakter – de schepen als hoofdzaak met water &amp; lucht van fijn grijs – maar vooral – <hi rend="italics">Japonaiseries</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> de figuren zijn er altijd in beweging<c type="kk">/</c> men ziet ze in de zonderlingste entourages<c type="kk">/</c> alles grillig<c type="kk">/</c> en er ontstaan vanzelf telkens interessante tegenstellingen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Een wit paard in den modder<c type="kk">/</c> in een hoek waar hoopen marchandises met zeildoek bedekt liggen – tegen oude<c type="kk">/</c> zwart berookte muren van ’t magazijn. Doodeenvoudig<c type="kk">/</c> maar een effekt van Black &amp; White<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Men zal door ’t raam van een zeer elegante engelsche kroeg uitzien op den vuilsten modder en op een schip waar b.v. liefelijke koopwaar als vellen en buffelhoorns uitgeladen worden door monstrueuse types van sjouwerlui of uitheemsche matrozen; daar naar<c type="kk">/</c> of naar iets anders<c type="kk">/</c> staat voor ’t raam een zeer blank<c type="kk">/</c> zeer fijn engelsch meisje te kijken<c type="kp">_</c> Het interieur met figuur gansch in toon<c type="kk">/</c> en als licht – de zilverachtige lucht boven dien modder en de buffelhoorns alweer een reeks van tegengestelden die nog al kras is. Er zullen vlaamsche matrozen met overdreven gezonde gezigten<c type="kk">/</c> met breede schouders<c type="kk">/</c> krachtig en vol en door &amp; door Antwerpsch<c type="kk">/</c> mosselen staan te eten en bier drinken<c type="kk">/</c> en met veel lawaai en beweging zal dat geschieden<c type="kp">_</c>– Oppositie – daar komt een zeer klein figuurtje in ’t zwart met de handjes tegen ’t lijf onhoorbaar aansluipen langs de grijze muren<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>In een encadrement van gitzwart haar een klein ovaal gezigtje<c type="kk">/</c> bruin? oranjegeel? ik weet het niet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Even slaat ze de oogleden op en kijkt met een scheeven blik uit een paar gitzwarte oogen. Het is een chineesche meid<c type="kk">/</c> geheimzinnig<c type="kk">/</c> stil als een muis<c type="kk">/</c> klein<c type="kk">/</c> wandluisachtig van karakter<c type="kp">_</c> Wat een contrast met de groep vlaamsche mosseleters<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Een ander contrast – men gaat door een zeer naauwe straat tusschen geducht hooge huizen<c type="kp">_</c> Magazijnen en bergplaatsen<c type="kp">_</c> Maar beneden aan straat kroegen voor alle natien met bijbehoorende mannelijke en vrouwelijke individus<c type="kp">_</c> Winkels van eetwaren<c type="kk">/</c> van zeemanskleeren<c type="kk">/</c> bont en woelig<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Die straat is lang<c type="kk">/</c> men ziet er telkens iets echts en het is bijwijlen een gewoel als er een standje is<c type="kk">/</c> krasser dan elders. b.v. ge loopt daar te kijken – en in eens gaat er een hoerah op en allerlei geschreeuw<c type="kp">_</c> Op klaar lichten dag wordt een matroos door de meiden uit een hoerekast gesmeten en door een woedenden kerel vervolgd en een sleep meiden<c type="kp">_</c> Waarvoor hij blijkbaar zeer bang is – ten minste<c type="kk">/</c> ik zag hem over een hoop zakken klauteren en door een raam in een magazijn verdwijnen. Heeft men nu genoeg van dat lawaai – aan ’t eind der aanlegplaatsen waar de Harwich en Havre booten liggen – ziet men – de stad achter zich hebbende<c type="kk">/</c> voor zich uit niets<c type="kk">/</c> absoluut niets dan een oneindigheid van vlak<c type="kk">/</c> halfoverstroomd weiland<c type="kk">/</c> verbazend triest en nat<c type="kk">/</c> golvend dor riet<c type="kk">/</c> modder – de rivier met een enkel zwart bootje<c type="kk">/</c> water op den voorgrond grijs<c type="kk">/</c> lucht mistig en koud<c type="kk">/</c> grijs – stil als de woestijn<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">’t Ensemble nu van de haven of een dok – nu eens is het meer verward en grillig dan een doornheg<c type="kk">/</c> verward zóó dat men geen rust vind voor het oog<c type="kk">/</c> zoo dat men duizelt<c type="kk">/</c> gedwongen wordt door het papillotteeren van kleuren en lijnen nu eens hier dan eens daar te kijken<c type="kk">/</c> zonder dat het bij lang kijken op een zelfde punt zelfs mogelijk is het een uit het ander te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Maar gaat men op een plek waar men een vaag terrein als voorgrond heeft – dan krijgt men weer de mooiste<c type="kk">/</c> stilste lijnen en die effekten die b.v. Mols dikwijls maakt. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Nu eens ziet men een meid die prachtig is van gezondheid en althans schijnbaar heel loyaal en naïf vroolijk<c type="kk">/</c> dan weer een aangezigt zóó geniept valsch dat men er een angst van krijgt als van een hyena. Niet te vergeten de van de pokken geschonden gezigten die een kleur hebben als gekookte garnaal<c type="kk">/</c> met fletsch grijze oogjes zonder wenkbraauwen en weinig<c type="kk">/</c> glad<c type="kk">/</c> dun haar<c type="kk">/</c> kleur van puur varkenshaar of iets geeler – Zweedsche of deensche types<c type="kp">_</c>– Om er te werken – ’t zou mooi zijn – maar hoe en waar<c type="kp">_</c> Want men zou al bijzonder gaauw ’t er te kwaad kunnen krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik ben toch een heele partij straten &amp; stegen doorkruist zonder avonturen<c type="kk">/</c> heb heel fideel met diverse meiden zelfs zitten praten<c type="kk">/</c> die mij blijkbaar voor een schipper hielden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Ik acht het niet onmogelijk dat door het maken van portretten ik nog eens aan goede modellen kom<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Vandaag heb ik mijn goed gekregen en gereedschap – waar ik hard naar verlangde. En ik heb mijn werkplaats dus in orde<c type="kp">_</c>– Als ik betrekkelijk kosteloos aan goed model kon komen dan was ik voor niets bang<c type="kp">_</c> Ik reken het ook niet erg dat ik geen geld heb zóóveel als noodig ware om door betalen te forceeren<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Misschien is het idee om portretten te maken en die met poseeren te laten betalen een secuurder weg. Want het is in stad niet zoo als bij de boeren<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin<c type="kp">_</c> Zeker is het dat Antwerpen voor een schilder zeer curieus en mooi is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Mijn werkplaats is nog al dragelijk. vooral omdat ik een partij japansche prentjes tegen de muren heb gespeld die mij erg amuseeren. Ge weet wel<c type="kk">/</c> van die vrouwenfiguurtjes in tuinen of aan ’t strand<c type="kk">/</c> ruiters<c type="kk">/</c> bloemen<c type="kk">/</c> knoestige doorntakken.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik heb er vrede mede dat ik gegaan ben – en hoop van den winter niet stil te zitten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> het is mij een rust dat ik een hokje heb waar ik bij slecht weer werken kan.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Dat ik nu deze laatste dagen niet in buitensporige weelde precies leven zal<c type="kk">/</c> hoort tot de begrijpelijke dingen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Zie dat gij den eersten Uw brief wegzendt want ik heb mij van brood voorzien tot dan<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zou verdere dagen in de rats zitten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Mijn kamertje valt me nog erg mede en het ziet er bepaald niet triest uit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Nu ik mijn 3 studies die ik medenam hier heb<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> zal ik ook eens naar de marchands de tableaux zien te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> die echter naar ’t schijnt meest in gesloten huizen wonen<c type="kk">/</c> geen etalage aan straat<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Het park<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> is ook mooi<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er nog op een morgen zitten teekenen<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Nu – ik heb dus in zoover geen tegenspoed<c type="kk">/</c> wat woning betreft ben ik geborgen want ik heb door nog een paar francs te laten schieten een kagchel en een lamp gekregen<c type="kp">_</c> Vervelen zal ik me niet ligt<c type="kk">/</c> dat verzeker ik U. Ik heb ook OCTOBRE van Lhermitte gevonden<c type="kk">/</c> vrouwen s’avonds op ’t aardappelveld<c type="kk">/</c> prachtig<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Novembre echter nog niet<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/>– Hebt gij die soms bijgehouden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb ook gezien dat er een Figaro illustré is met een mooie teekening <hi rend="italics">van Raffaelli</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Ge weet mijn adres is <hi rend="italics">194 Rue des images</hi><c type="kp">_</c> adresseer dus daar Uw brief s.v.p. en het tweede deel van de Goncourt<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> als ge ’t uit hebt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Gegroet.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">b. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Zonderling is het dat mijn geschilderde studies hier in stad donkerder doen dan buiten – komt dit omdat het licht in stad overal minder helder is? ik weet het niet – maar dat kan meer schelen dan men oppervlakkig zeggen zou<c type="kk">/</c> het heeft me gefrappeerd en ik zou me kunnen begrijpen dat dingen die bij U zijn ook donkerder lijkenen dan ik buiten meende ze waren<c type="kp">_</c> Toch<c type="kk">/</c> die welke ik nu medenam doen niet slecht met dat al – de molen – laan met herfstboomen en stilleven en een paar kleintjes.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Saturday evening</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Wanted to write to you with a few more impressions of Antwerp. This morning I went for a really good walk in the pouring rain, an expedition with the object of fetching my things from the customs office.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> The different entrepôts and hangars on the wharves are very fine.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve already walked in all directions around these docks and wharves several times. It’s a strange contrast, particularly when one comes from the sand and the heath and the tranquillity of a country village and hasn’t been in anything but quiet surroundings for a long time. It’s an incomprehensible confusion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">One of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>’s sayings was ‘<hi rend="italics">Japonaiserie for ever</hi>’.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Well, these docks are one huge <hi rend="italics">Japonaiserie</hi>, fantastic, singular, strange — at least, one can see them like that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’d like to walk with you there to find out whether we look at things the same way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">One could do anything there, townscapes — figures of the most diverse character — the ships as the central subject with water and sky in delicate grey — but above all — <hi rend="italics">Japonaiseries</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I mean, the figures there are always in motion, one sees them in the most peculiar settings, everything fantastic, and interesting contrasts keep appearing of their own accord.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">A white horse in the mud, in a corner where heaps of merchandise lie covered with a tarpaulin — against the old, black, smoke-stained walls of the warehouse. Quite simple — but a Black and White effect.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Through the window of a very elegant English inn one will look out on the filthiest mud and on a ship where such delightful wares as hides and buffalo horns are being unloaded by monstrous docker types or foreign sailors; by the window, looking at this or at something else, stands a very fair, very delicate English girl. The interior with figure wholly in tone, and for light — the silvery sky above that mud and the buffalo horns, again a series of contrasts that’s quite strong. There’ll be Flemish sailors with exaggeratedly ruddy faces, with broad shoulders, powerful and robust, and Antwerp through and through, standing eating mussels and drinking beer, and making a great deal of noise and commotion about it. Contrast — there goes a tiny little figure in black, with her small hands pressed against her body, slipping soundlessly along the grey walls. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> In a frame of jet-black hair, a little oval face, brown? Orange yellow? I don’t know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">She raises her eyelids momentarily and looks with a slanting glance out of a pair of jet-black eyes. It’s a Chinese girl, mysterious, quiet as a mouse, small, like a bedbug by nature. What a contrast to the group of Flemish mussel eaters.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Another contrast — people passing along a very narrow street between formidably tall houses. Warehouses and stores. But down at street level, alehouses for all nations with the corresponding male and female individuals. Shops selling food, sailors’ clothes, colourful and bustling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This street is long, one keeps seeing authentic scenes, and once in a while there’s a commotion, louder than usual, when a quarrel breaks out. For instance, you’re walking along, looking around, and suddenly a great cheer goes up and all sorts of shouting. In broad daylight a sailor is being thrown out of a brothel by the girls and pursued by a furious fellow and a string of girls. Of whom he is apparently terrified — at any rate, I saw him scramble over a pile of sacks and disappear through a window into a warehouse. Once one’s had enough of this racket — at the end of the berths where the Harwich and Le Havre boats lie — having the city behind one — one sees — in front of one, nothing, absolutely nothing but an infinity of flat, half-flooded pasture, incredibly sad and wet, undulating dry reeds, mud — the river with a single small black boat, water in the foreground grey, sky misty and cold, grey — silent as a desert.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">The overall effect of the port or of a dock — sometimes it’s more tangled and fantastic than a thorn-hedge, so tangled that one can find no rest for the eye, so that one gets dizzy, is forced by the flickering of colours and lines to look now here and now there, unable to tell one thing from another even after staring at a single spot for a long while.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">But if one goes to a place where one has an indistinct piece of land as a foreground — then one gets the most beautiful, quiet lines and those effects that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1223">Mols</rs>, for instance, often gets.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Now one sees a girl who is magnificently healthy and, at least seemingly, very sincere and innocently cheerful, then a countenance <hi rend="italics">so</hi> slyly malicious that one is frightened by it as if by a hyena. Not forgetting the faces ravaged by the pox, the colour of boiled shrimp, with little dull grey eyes and no eyebrows, and sparse, greasy, thin hair, colour of pure pig’s bristle or slightly yellower — Swedish or Danish types. It would be good to work there — but how and where? Because one could run into trouble there exceedingly quickly. All the same, I did roam around a whole lot of streets and alleys without mishap, even sat and talked very genially with various girls, who evidently took me for a bargee.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t consider it impossible that I might be able to come by some good models by painting portraits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Today I got my things and tools — which I was eagerly awaiting. And so I have my studio in order. If I could come by good models at virtually no expense I wouldn’t be afraid of anything. I don’t reckon it a bad thing, either, that I haven’t any money, as much as it would take to force things by paying.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Perhaps the idea of painting portraits and getting the sitters to pay for them by posing is a safer way. Because in the city it’s not like it is with the peasants. Anyway. One thing’s certain, Antwerp’s a very singular and beautiful place for a painter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">My studio’s quite tolerable, mainly because I’ve pinned a set of Japanese prints on the walls that I find very diverting. You know, those little female figures in gardens or on the shore, horsemen, flowers, gnarled thorn branches.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I’ve reconciled myself to having left — and hope not to be idle this winter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Well, it’s a relief to me to have a little cubby-hole where I can work in bad weather.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">It’s pretty obvious that I shan’t exactly be living in the lap of luxury these days.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">See that you send your letter off on the first, because I’ve got enough bread in until then, but after that I’d be in a real stew.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">My little room isn’t bad at all, and it definitely doesn’t look dreary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Now that I have the 3 studies I brought with me here,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I’ll set about going to the picture dealers, who mostly seem to live in private houses, though, no shop windows on the street.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The park<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> is beautiful, too. I sat there drawing one morning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Well — I’ve had no setbacks so far. I’m safe and sound as far as accommodation is concerned, for by forking out a few more francs I’ve acquired a stove and a lamp. I shan’t easily get bored, I assure you. I’ve also found OCTOBER by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Lhermitte</rs>, women in a potato field in the evening, magnificent.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Not yet November, though.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Have you kept up to date with that, by any chance? I’ve also seen that there’s a Figaro Illustré with a fine drawing <hi rend="italics">by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs></hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">You know my address is <hi rend="italics">194 rue des Images</hi>, so please address your letter there, and the second volume of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> when you’ve finished it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">It’s curious that my painted studies look darker here in the city than in the country — is this because the light isn’t as bright anywhere in the city? I don’t know — but it might differ more than one would say on the face of it. It struck me, and I could understand that things that are with you also appear darker than I thought they were in the country. Still, the ones I’ve brought with me now don’t look bad all the same — the mill — avenue of autumn trees and still life, and a few small ones.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written on ‘Saturday evening’ <ref target="#l-1">(l. 1)</ref> and continues Van Gogh’s report of his first thoughts about Antwerp (he gives ‘a few more impressions’, <ref target="#l-2*">l. 2*</ref>). It must moreover have been written before 1 December because he says in <ref target="#l-129">l. 129</ref>: ‘see that you send your letter off on the first’. The only possibility is therefore Saturday, 28 November 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>There were ‘Bureaux des douanes’ in three locations: 6 plaine Vanschoonbeke, 6 rue d’Egmont and Entrepôt; Van Gogh must have gone to the last of these (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboek</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">1885</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>A reference to the end of a letter that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_618">Jules de Goncourt</rs> wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1694">Philippe Burty</rs> from Trouville on 1 August 1867: ‘A revoir donc. Japonaiserie <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">for ever</hi>!’ Quoted in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_252">Maîtres et petits maîtres</ref></hi> (Burty 1877, p. 274). Van Gogh probably borrowed the book from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Kerssemakers</rs>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml#n-10">see letter 542, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This is the first time that Van Gogh writes about his interest in Japanese prints; see for this also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let587.xml#n-3">letter 587, n. 3.</ref> Japanese items had been on display at the World Exhibition that had run in Antwerp until 2 November and the dealers probably took advantage of the interest this had created to start selling Japanese prints.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had obviously rented a ‘cubby-hole’ as well as his room; on the floor plan of the house (as it was in 1922) there is a small room on the right at the front of the second floor, next to the main room; this is probably the ‘studio’ Van Gogh refers to. Cf. cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The three paintings Van Gogh took with him from Nuenen are: an unknown ‘mill’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Avenue of poplars</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2538">F 45 / JH 959</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with Bible</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2535">F 117 / JH 946</rs>) (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml#n-3">letter 542, nn. 3</ref><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml#n-5">-5</ref>); from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-162">l. 162</ref> it appears that he must also have taken ‘a few small ones’. It is not possible to say for sure which these were. They probably included some of the following works – although these could equally well have been sent in October (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let535.xml#n-1">see letter 535, n. 1</ref>): <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with three beer tankards</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_605">F 49 / JH 534</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with earthenware and bottles</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_607">F 53 / JH 538</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of apples</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_606">F 101 / JH 927</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with vegetables and fruit</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_615">F 103 / JH 928</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with a basket of apples and two pumpkins </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_592">F 106 / JH 936</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with birds’ nests</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_588">F 109r / JH 942</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with birds’ nests</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_589">F 112 / JH 938</rs>); <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The parsonage at Nuenen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_608">F 182 / JH 948</rs>); and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a woman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2514">F 388r / JH 782</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 239.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The Stadspark in the city centre, which was opened in 1869.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La récolte des pommes de terre </hi>(The potato harvest), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1513">Clément Edouard Bellenger</rs>, appeared as the month of October in de series ‘Les mois rustiques’, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 29 (21 November 1885), Supplement to no. 1495 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_219">Ill. 219</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>It would seem that Theo did manage to get hold of the engraving for Vincent: there is an example of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le semeur</hi> (The sower), engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1513">Clément Edouard Bellenger</rs> – the month of November in the series ‘Les mois rustiques’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Monde Illustré</hi> 30 (3 April 1886), no. 1514 – in the estate. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_218">Ill. 218</rs> (t*228).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les vieux officiers</hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Jean-François Raffaëlli</rs> was published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Figaro Illustré</hi> 6 (25 December 1885). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2169">Ill. 2169</rs>. It was after the panel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Les vieux officiers</hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">c</hi>. 1884, then in the W. Blumenthal Collection, now in the Van Gogh Museum under de title <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The veterans</hi>. Van Gogh was aware of the proposed publication because <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Figaro</hi> advertised it in countless advance announcements.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Volume 2 of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Jules and Edmond de Goncourt</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_426">L’art du dix-huitième siècle</ref></hi>. We learn from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let551.xml">letter 551</ref> that Theo did send it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    