<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Sunday, 6 December 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let546"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b478 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>546</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>438</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>549</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-12-06">on or about Sunday, 6 December 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0478 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0478 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000645_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0478 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000646_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000646_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0478 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000646_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000646_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000646_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Dank voor uw brief en ingesl. frs 150.– Wilde U zeggen dat ik blij ben naar hier gegaan te zijn. ik heb verl. week nog 3 studies geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> een met achterkanten van oude huizen – uit het raam bij mij gezien<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – twee in het park.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Een daarvan heb ik bij een marchand geexposeerd<c type="kp">_</c>– Verder heb ik ook bij twee anderen hetgeen ik van buiten medebragt in commissie gegeven.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> bij een vierde kan ik een gezigt op de kaai exposeeren zoodra ’t weer me toelaat het te maken<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> omdat hij een Mols had waar hij wel iets bij wilde hebben. Verder heb ik van dien laatstgenoemde nog een adres gekregen waar hij mij verzekerde ik goed ontvangen zou worden<c type="kp">_</c>– Nu zijn deze marchands niet de grootsten van Antwerpen maar toch zag ik bij allen<c type="kk">/</c> onder veel wat mij niet aanstond<c type="kk">/</c> zulke dingen als me bevielen<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. bij één een schij van v<c type="kp">_</c> Goyen en een studie van Troyon<c type="kk">/</c> bij den ander een Mols en kleine hollandsche schilderijtjes – bij een ander dat kleine sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> dat ik U zeide als Raffaelli was – het is van Moormans<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – en enkele goede aquarellen – bij een ander diverse goede marines van jonge belgen. Figuren zag ik er al heel weinig en ik ben voornemens te trachten wat figuren te maken daarom.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het adres dat die bewuste marchand me opgaf is juist van een van de groote handelaars (<hi rend="italics">Nicolié</hi>)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> die geen etalage hebben maar in een gesloten huis hun exposities houden. Ik wil daar echter met figuur komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Dan ik heb ook nuttige ressources ontdekt voor verf &amp;c. waar ik vrij goedkoop teregt zal kunnen. Ik heb ook Linnig<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> opgescharreld die gij mij van den zomer<c type="kk">/</c> toen ik U vroeg of ge in Antwerpen lui kendet<c type="kk">/</c> noemdet – maar hij heeft <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> dan wat miserable oude schilderijtjes<c type="kk">/</c> schildert zelf zoowat als Vertin<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> maar scheen mij toe een gedecourageerd man te zijn voor zoover hij ooit courage moge gehad hebben<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik niet op veel schat<c type="kp">_</c>– Al deze heeren klagen echter steen &amp; been over dat er niets omgaat. enfin dat is geen nieuws. Ik hoop binnen kort dat Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> waar ge over schrijft te gaan zien<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb het echter druk met heen &amp; weer loopen gehad<c type="kk">/</c> &amp; nog<c type="kk">/</c> om die lui op te sporen<c type="kk">/</c> en tevens ook de jagt op modellen. Dat laatste is steeds geducht bezwaarlijk maar ik heb ’t elders wel gevonden &amp; dus ik zal ook hier zien. Ik heb voor morgen afspraak met een prachtigen ouden man – zal hij komen???</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik heb heden mijn voorraad verf die ze uit Eindhoven me nastuurden gekregen &amp; betaald<c type="kk">/</c> over de frs 50<c type="kp">_</c> Het is hard<c type="kk">/</c> geducht hard te blijven werken als men niet verkoopt<c type="kk">/</c> en letterlijk zijn verf te moeten betalen van wat voor eten &amp; drinken &amp; wonen alleen niet veel te veel zou wezen<c type="kk">/</c> zuinig genomen<c type="kp">_</c> En dan bovendien de modellen. Enfin. Toch is er een kans en zelfs een goede<c type="kk">/</c> want er zijn er betrekkelijk weinig die tegenwoordig werken. Dit is hun m.i. maar <hi rend="italics">half</hi> (voor de andere helft <hi rend="italics">wel</hi>) kwalijk te nemen want het is soms te bar. Toch bouwt men rijksmuseums van honderdduizenden &amp; soortgelijke zaken maar de artisten creveeren bijwijlen. Maar wat er ook van dit alles zij<c type="kk">/</c> het was mij behoefte zelf eens weer in de dingen een kijkje te gaan nemen en de kans om iets te doen is niet minder<c type="kk">/</c> eer heel wat meer dan ik veronderstelde. Ik heb verscheiden photos naar Jan v<c type="kp">_</c> Beers gezien<c type="kp">_</c> Sommige dingen van hem zijn toch met veel karakter gedaan. Maar ik verbeeld me dat iemand als b.v. Manet zeer veel meer <hi rend="italics">schilder</hi> is dan v<c type="kp">_</c> Beers. en het mooier<c type="kk">/</c> artistieker doet.– Als ik hier wat meer bekend was<c type="kk">/</c> als ik de modellen die ik zag krijgen kon!– Gisteren was ik in het café concert Scala<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> iets als Folies bergère<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – ik vond het er saai en natuurlijk afgezaagd maar – ik heb mij geamuseerd met de toeschouwers. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Er waren prachtige vrouwenkoppen<c type="kk">/</c> werkelijk buitengewoon mooi<c type="kk">/</c> onder de brave burgerluidjes op de achterste banken<c type="kk">/</c> en in ’t algemeen vind ik het wel waar wat men van Antwerpen zegt<c type="kk">/</c> dat de vrouwen er mooi zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Ah! ik zeg het nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> als ik modellen naar mijn keus kon krijgen! Wat me zeer koel laat zijn de massa duitsche meiden<c type="kk">/</c> allen naar een model gefabriceerd zou men zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> die men bij de cafe concerts ziet. Dat zelfde ras ziet men<c type="kk">/</c> schijnt het<c type="kk">/</c> tegenwoordig overal<c type="kk">/</c> net als het beiersch bier<c type="kp">_</c> ’t schijnt een artikel te wezen dat en gros geexporteerd wordt. Ik vind al die duitsche elementen<c type="kk">/</c> die waar men ook komt zich tegenwoordig nestelen<c type="kk">/</c> zoo gloeijend vervelend. In Parijs zal ’t wel net eender zijn dat de moffen zich overal indringen. Enfin ’t is een vervelend ding om over te praten.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Door het zien van wat schilderijen van anderen heb ik allerlei idees voor als ik in ’t voorjaar weer buiten zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c> tevens in ’t algemeen versterkt zich mijn vertrouwen om met alle kracht die maar disponible is door te gaan. Antwerpen is mooi van kleur en alleen om de motieven is ’t de moeite waard.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik heb op een avond een bal populaire van matrozen &amp;c. gezien bij de dokken – dat was alleraardigst en het ging er <hi rend="italics">zeer fatsoenlijk</hi> toe. Dat zal echter niet op alle van die bals ’t geval zijn. Hier was niemand b.v. dronken of niemand dronk ook veel<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Er waren zeer mooie meiden<c type="kk">/</c> van welke de allermooiste leelijk<c type="kp">_</c> Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> een figuur dat mij frappeerde als een verbazend mooie Jordaens of Velasquez of – Goya – was een in ’t zwart zij<c type="kk">/</c> een of andere herbergierster denkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> met een gezigt leelijk en onregelmatig maar met een leven en piquant à la Frans Hals. Zij danste uitmuntend met ouderwetsche manieren – o.a<c type="kp">_</c> eens met een soort welgesteld boertje die een groote<c type="kk">/</c> groene parapluie onder den arm had<c type="kk">/</c> ook terwijl hij verbazend vlug walste. Andere meiden droegen gewone jakken &amp; rokken en roode doeken – de matrozen<c type="kk">/</c> kajuitsjongens &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> alleraardigst<c type="kp">_</c> Types van gepensioneerde scheepskapteins die kwamen kijken. Bijzonder echt. Het doet goed lui te zien die zich waarachtig amuseeren.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> gij ziet dat ik niet stil zit – maar hoe geducht bezwaarlijk het is court d’argent te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan ’t niet genoeg zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– Mijn beste kans is in figuur omdat er maar heel weinig betrekkelijk zijn die het doen en die kans moet ik werk van maken. Ik moet mij hier er in werken totdat ik met goede figuurschilders in relatie kom – <hi rend="italics">Verhaert</hi><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> </p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">en dan is portretten maken<c type="kk">/</c> stel ik me voor<c type="kk">/</c> ’t middel om wat te verdienen voor grootere dingen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">ik voel een kracht in me om wat te doen. ik zie dat mijn werk zich houdt tegen ander werk en dat geeft mij een verbazenden lust om te werken<c type="kk">/</c> en in den laatsten tijd dat ik buiten was<c type="kk">/</c> was ik beginnen te twijfelen juist omdat ik merkte dat Portier blijkbaar er niet meer om geeft.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Als ik het ruimer had dan zou ik er wel meer kunnen maken<c type="kp">_</c> Maar ik ben voor een deel afhankelijk van mijn beurs wat produceeren betreft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik heb ook een idee voor een soort enseignes<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> dat ik hoop uit te voeren. Ik bedoel b.v. voor een vischkooper stilleven van visschen<c type="kk">/</c> voor bloemen<c type="kk">/</c> voor groenten<c type="kk">/</c> voor restaurant<c type="kp">_</c>– Mij dunkt dat als men goed gearrangeerde motieven nam – groot – 1 meter bij 1/2 meter of 3/4 b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> zulk een doek mij 50 frs zou kosten<c type="kk">/</c> niet meer – desnoods 30 frs als ’t meevalt. en het te probeeren ware er eenigen te maken<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zooveel is zeker<c type="kk">/</c> ik wil gezien worden – later zullen we ons mogelijk moeten decourageeren 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>maar we zullen het erg uit zien te stellen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Als ge tijd hebt<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf mij nog weer eens. Het eind van de maand zou zeker bar zijn tenzij gij me dan nog wat kunt steunen<c type="kp">_</c> Er hangt voor mij zooveel misschien van af voet bij stek te kunnen houden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">En men mag er ook niet hongerig of beroerd uitzien. Integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> men moet zien mee te werken om leven in de brouwerij te brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter and 150 francs enclosed. Wanted to tell you that I’m glad to have come here. I painted 3 more studies last week; one of the backs of old houses — seen out of my window<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — two in the park.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve exhibited one of them at a dealer’s. Furthermore, I’ve also left what I brought with me from the country with two others on commission.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> At a fourth I can exhibit a view of the wharf as soon as the weather allows me to paint it,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> because he had a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1223">Mols</rs> that he wanted something to show alongside. Furthermore, I got another address from the last of them, where he assured me I’d be well received. Now these dealers aren’t the biggest in Antwerp, but all the same I saw at all of them, among much that I didn’t like, such things as appealed to me, for instance at one a painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1056">Van Goyen</rs> and a study by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1389">Troyon</rs>, at another a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1223">Mols</rs> and tiny little Dutch paintings — at another that little painting which I told you was like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs> — it’s by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1239">Moormans</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> — and some good watercolours — at another various good seascapes by young Belgians. I saw very few figures, and I consequently intend to try to paint some figures.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The address that the dealer in question gave me is actually that of one of the large dealers (<hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_529">Nicolié</rs></hi>)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> who don’t have a shop window but hold their exhibitions in a private house. I want to take figures there, though.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then I’ve also discovered useful sources for paint &amp;c., where I’ll be able to get things quite cheaply. I’ve also hunted out <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1178">Linnig</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> whom you mentioned in the summer when I asked you if you knew people in Antwerp — but he has <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> but a few miserable old paintings; paints himself rather like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1416">Vertin</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> but seemed to me to be a discouraged man in so far as he ever had any courage, which I reckon wasn’t much. All these gentlemen, though, are complaining bitterly that nothing’s moving. Still, that’s not news. I hope to go and see the painting you write about before long. I’ve been busy going backwards and forwards, though, and still am, tracking down those fellows, and at the same time hunting for models, too. That last is always terribly difficult, but I’ve done it elsewhere and so I’ll manage here too. I have an appointment for tomorrow with a splendid old man — will he come??? 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Today I got my stock of paint that they forwarded to me from Eindhoven and paid for it, more than 50 francs. It’s hard, terribly hard to keep working when people don’t buy, and literally to have to pay for one’s paint out of what wouldn’t be excessive just for food and drink and lodgings alone, living frugally. And on top of that, the models. Anyway. Still, there’s a chance, and a good one even, for there are relatively few people working at present. To my mind they’re only <hi rend="italics">half</hi> to blame for this (for the other half <hi rend="italics">they are</hi>) because it’s sometimes too tough. And yet they build national museums costing hundreds of thousands and similar things, but meanwhile the artists sometimes starve. But be all this as it may, I needed to look into things for myself, and the chance of doing something isn’t less but rather a great deal more than I’d imagined. I’ve seen various photographs of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_427">Jan van Beers</rs>’s work. Some of his things are done with a great deal of character. But I imagine that someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs>, say, is very much more of a <hi rend="italics">painter</hi> than Van Beers, and does it better, more artistically. If only I knew my way around here rather better, if only I could get the models I saw! Yesterday I was in the Scala café concert,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> something like the Folies Bergères<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> — I thought it was tedious and hackneyed, of course, but — I amused myself looking at the audience. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> There were magnificent women’s heads, really extraordinarily fine, among the worthy bourgeois folk in the back rows, and on the whole I find what they say about Antwerp true indeed, that the women are good-looking here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Ah! I’ll say it again, if I could only get the models I want! What leaves me quite cold are the mass of German girls, all manufactured from a single model one would say, that one sees at the café concerts. It seems that one sees that same breed everywhere nowadays, like Bavarian beer. It seems to be an article that’s exported in bulk. I’m bored to tears by all these German elements that lurk wherever one goes these days. It’s sure to be just the same in Paris, with the Boches worming their way in everywhere. Anyway, it’s a boring thing to talk about.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Seeing some paintings by other people has given me all sorts of ideas for when I’m back in the country in the spring; at the same time my confidence to carry on with all the strength at my disposal is being boosted in general. Antwerp is a beautiful colour, and it’s worthwhile for the subjects alone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">One evening I saw a popular dance for sailors &amp;c. down by the docks — it was quite charming and all <hi rend="italics">very respectable</hi>. That won’t be the case at all these dances, though. No one there was drunk, for instance, nor did anyone drink much. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">There were very good-looking girls there, the best-looking of whom was ugly. I mean, a figure that struck me like an amazingly beautiful <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1124">Jordaens</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1402">Velázquez</rs> or — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs> — was one in black silk, probably some inn landlady or other, with an ugly and irregular face, but with vivacity and piquancy à la <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Frans Hals</rs>. She danced excellently in an old-fashioned manner — among others, once with a well-to-do little farmer type who had a large green umbrella under his arm, even while he was waltzing amazingly fast. Other girls were wearing ordinary jackets and skirts and red scarves — the sailors, cabin-boys &amp;c., quite charming. Retired ship’s captain types who came to watch. Extraordinarily authentic. It does one good to see people who are really enjoying themselves.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Well, you can see that I’m not sitting idle — but I can’t stress enough how terribly difficult it is to be short of money. My best chance is in figures because there are relatively very few who do it, and I must make the most of this chance. I have to work my way in here, until I come into contact with good figure painters — <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1397">Verhaert</rs></hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> for instance, and then portrait painting, I imagine, will be the way to earn something for grander things.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I feel a power to do something within me. I see that my work holds its own against other work, and that gives me an incredible desire to work; and lately, when I was in the country, I was starting to have doubts precisely because I noticed that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> seemingly doesn’t care for it any more.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’d be able to do more if I were better off. But I’m partly dependent on my purse as far as production is concerned.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I also have an idea for a sort of shop sign<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> that I hope to carry out. I mean, for instance, still lifes of fish for a fishmonger, for flowers, for vegetables, for a restaurant. It seems to me that if one took well-arranged subjects — large — 1 metre by 1/2  a metre or 3/4, say, a canvas like that would cost me 50 francs, no more — even 30 francs with luck, and it would be worth trying to make a few.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">This much is certain, I want to be seen — we may have to lose heart later, 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> but we’ll manage to put it off for a long while.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Do write to me again if you have time. The end of the month would certainly be hard unless you can give me a little support then. For me, so much may depend on my being able to stick to my guns.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And one can’t afford to look hungry or wretched. On the contrary, one must see to it that one helps to liven things up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for the monthly allowance of 150 francs, which places the letter at the beginning of December. Since he refers to ‘last week’ in reference to three studies he has painted <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>, that must have been the week of 29 November to 5 December. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Sunday, 6 December 1885. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">View of the terrace near the Moulin de Blute-Fin </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_616">F 272 / JH 1183</rs>) of 1887 was painted over this work. Until now it has been assumed that it was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Houses seen from the back</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_617">F 260 / JH 970</rs>); however, there is snow on the roofs in that painting, whereas the first snowfall was on 9 December and Van Gogh says that he painted the works in question ‘last week’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>. See cat. Amsterdam 2011; cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let547.xml">letter 547</ref>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>These paintings of the park are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for the works that Van Gogh took with him from Nuenen: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let545.xml#n-4">letter 545, n. 4.</ref> We do not know who these three art dealers were.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>We do not know whether this plan was ever carried out. The notion that the intended work turned out to be the panel <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2542">F 211 / JH 973</rs>, as was long assumed on Tralbaut’s instigation, has proved to be incorrect (Tralbaut 1948): the panel is of the De Ruyterkade in Amsterdam and was painted on 6, 7 or 8 October 1885. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let534.xml#n-17">See letter 534, n. 17.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to a work in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1279">Raffaëlli</rs>’s style that he mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let544.xml">letter 544</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_529">Paul Emile Nicolié</rs>, painter and art dealer, who lived at Keizerstraat 8 (district 2). He also worked as a restorer at the Antwerp Museum, where he held the post of ‘expert’. (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">SAA</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adresboek 1885</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1178">Jan Theodor Jozef Linnig</rs>, art dealer at 35 Oude Koornmarkt in Antwerp, also a painter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1416">Petrus Gerardus Vertin</rs>, known for his cityscapes, painted in warm colours and with strong light effects.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Scala was a music-hall and ballroom in Anneessensstraat, which opened in December 1884; according to a tourist guide of the time it was a ‘theatre built in an exotic architectural style’. See R. Binnemans, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Atlas van Antwerpen; evolutie van een stedelijk landschap van 1850 tot heden</hi>. Antwerp 1991 (not paginated).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The Folies Bergères was and is a famous revue theatre in rue Richer in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The scene he describes resembles the little sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dance-hall</hi> from Van Gogh’s sketchbook of this period (now preserved as a separate drawing), in which ‘girls’ looking on wear red scarves. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2170">Ill. 2170</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1397">Pieter Verhaert</rs> was a teacher at the Antwerp Academy; as well as genre works and landscapes he also painted numerous portraits.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
      
<p>During the summer it had become clear that the Parisian art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Alphonse Portier</rs>’s initial enthusiasm for Van Gogh’s work had cooled; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let534.xml#n-30">letter 534, n. 30</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>‘Enseignes’ – the word Van Gogh uses here – literally means a shop sign; however since Van Gogh goes on to refer to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">canvas</hi> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-141">(l. 141)</ref>, he must have had in mind paintings for shop windows or interiors rather than advertising signs to go on shop fronts. Another possibility is that he was thinking of the canvases as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">designs </hi>for the signs.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    