<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Saturday, 19 December 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let549"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b481 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>549</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>441</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>552</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-12-19">Saturday, 19 December 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0481" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0481" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000650_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">ik heb vandaag nog weer een kop geschilderd<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – van een model dat ik echter niet kon betalen – maar ’t krijgen kunnende heb ik het toch genomen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ook is me nu voor vast beloofd dat ik een portret zal maken van iemand<c type="kk">/</c> en dan tot vergoeding twee studies voor mij<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik moet U echter zeggen dat het vuur me na aan de scheenen is – ik heb van mijn vijf francs die ik nog nagenoeg had – twee doeken moeten koopen voor die twee portretten en zooeven komt mijn waschgoed thuis<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo dat op ’t moment ik enkele centimes over heb<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Hetgeen ik U dus absoluut vraag is: wacht in vredesnaam niet met schrijven en stuur mij veel of weinig naarmate ge hebt – doch weet dat ik honger heb<c type="kk">/</c> letterlijk<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Wanneer ’t me lukt een 50tal koppen bijeen te krijgen is er nog een kans om werk te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. om te zien bij de photografen geemployeerd te worden<c type="kk">/</c> wat ik op den duur niet willen zou maar in tijd van nood wel. De photografen schijnen hier veel te doen te hebben. men ziet ook geschilderde portretten bij hen die zij blijkbaar op een door photografie verkregen fond bewerken<c type="kk">/</c> wat voor iemand die weet wat schilderen is natuurlijk en zwak en flaauw van effekt is<c type="kp">_</c> Het komt me nu voor dat men een heel wat beter coloriet zou kunnen krijgen indien men met studies direkt naar ’t leven geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> naar de photografies werkte welke men geschilderd verlangt te zien. En enfin dit is een van de kansen althans die men zou kunnen hebben om wat te verdienen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Maar wat ik ook beginnen wil en waar – ik moet dingen kunnen laten zien<c type="kk">/</c> dat spreekt van zelf.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Daar ik al mijn opgewektheid<c type="kk">/</c> al mijn werkkracht noodig heb – zie ik er tegen op<c type="kk">/</c> ronduit gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> om physiek slap me te voelen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik ben met mijn gezigt van ’t Steen nog naar een ander geweest<c type="kk">/</c> die het goed van toon &amp; kleur vond<c type="kk">/</c> die echter in een rommel zat van zijn inventaris op te maken en klein behuisd is<c type="kk">/</c> maar waar ik na Nieuwjaar kon<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> terugkomen. Het is een goed ding voor als er vreemdelingen zijn die een souvenir van Antwerpen willen hebben en om die reden zal ik in ’t zelfde genre van stadsgezigten er nog wel meer bij maken. Zoo teekende ik gisteren een paar studies<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> voor een geval waar men de cathedraal ziet. En zoo heb ik ook een kleintje van het Park<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Echter ik schilder liever de oogen van menschen dan cathedralen want er zit iets in de oogen wat in de cathedraal niet zit – al is die plegtig en al imponeert die – de ziel van een mensch<c type="kk">/</c> al is het een arme schooier of een meid van de straat<c type="kk">/</c> is in mijn oog interessanter. Ik geloof dan ook dat niets zóó direkt vooruit helpt als met model werken<c type="kp">_</c>– Als zeer zeker ’t een lastig bezwaar is om de modellen te moeten betalen – wij zijn in een tijd dat het op energie aan komt en 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>de schilderijen energiek zullen moeten zijn om koopers te vinden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Dat er hier wat te doen is – ’k geloof het zeker<c type="kp">_</c>– Er gaat blijkbaar veel om hier in stad in mooie vrouwen – en dat er te verdienen is met ’t zij vrouwenportretten ’t zij fantaisie vrouwen –</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">koppen en figuren – dat moet zoo zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Het is me een waar genot met wat beter soort penseelen te werken en cobalt en carmijn en goed jaune brillant en vermilloen te hebben.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Het duurste is nog soms ’t goedkoopste<c type="kp">_</c> Cobalt vooral – het is met geen ander blaauw te vergelijken wat de fijne toonen betreft die men er mee krijgen kan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">En de kwaliteit van kleur moge niet alles afdoen in een schij maar het is toch dat wat het leven geeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Wat betreft of ik al dan niet hier voor vast zou gaan wonen – gegeven dat het niet precies rooskleurig er uitziet in den kunst<c type="shy">-</c>handel – en er een zeker streven is onder de schilders om ieder voor zich zijn eigen handelaar te zijn – wat op den duur stel ik me voor nog toe zal nemen – ware ’t mogelijk verstandig een atelier hier te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Hebt gij gedachten daaromtrent of verlangens<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij voor ’t zij tegen<c type="kk">/</c> deel ze mij zoo ronduit mogelijk mede<c type="kp">_</c> Maar mij springt direkt in ’t oog dat – indien ooit na veel of weinig jaren gij er toe zoudt komen om voor Uzelf onafhankelijk van de Goupils te gaan werken – 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Antwerpen misschien een terrein zou kunnen wezen waar gegeven de trieste etalage van nu door goed etaleeren nog wel wat kan worden gedaan dat de andere huizen niet begrijpen<c type="kp">_</c> Verder – Het is betrekkelijk zoo makkelijk van hier naar Engeland heen &amp; weer te gaan.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Waarom – voor den handel – zijn alle schilderijen altijd in lijsten<c type="kp">_</c>– als handelsartikel is er toch soms veel voor dat iets ligt en makkelijk te hanteeren &amp; te verplaatsen zij<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">De handel is oud en... 3 maal vermolmd<c type="kp">_</c> Er moet vernieuwd worden – en de oude systeemen werken niet precies goed meer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">De prijzen – het publiek – alles heeft vernieuwing noodig<c type="kp">_</c>– En de toekomst is<c type="kk">/</c> goedkoop werken voor de burgers<c type="kk">/</c> misschien<c type="kp">_</c> althans – de gewone liefhebbers schijnen zelf al meer en meer vast te raken<c type="kk">/</c> hard te worden. Enfin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Met kapitaal te beginnen strekt zoo dikwijls slechts daartoe om eerst alles te verliezen en zoo ligt zijn moed &amp; werklust er bij<c type="kp">_</c> Terwijl beginnen met betrekkelijk niets alligt iemand beslist en vaster van karakter maakt. Enfin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Gegroet – maar zie dat gij me per ommegaande schrijft want ik heb een flaauw gevoel in ’t lijf daar ik me nog al ingespannen heb met een &amp; ander &amp; ik heb mijn kracht noodig<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I painted another head today<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — of a model whom I couldn’t pay, though — but being able to get it, I took it anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve also now had a definite promise that I’ll make a portrait of someone, and then two studies for me in return.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I have to tell you, though, that I’m really hard pressed now — out of the near enough five francs that I still had — I had to buy two canvases for those two portraits, and my laundry has just come back. So that at the moment I have a few centimes left.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">So what I’m urgently asking you is: for God’s sake don’t put off writing, and send me a lot or a little, such as you have — but know that I’m starving, literally.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If I succeed in getting 50 or so heads together, there’s a chance of getting work, that is to see about being employed by the photographers, which I wouldn’t want in the long run, but would do if needs must. The photographers seem to have plenty to do here. One also sees painted portraits in their shops, which they apparently work up on a background obtained by photography, which obviously has a weak, feeble effect to anyone who knows what painting is. It occurs to me now that one could get very much better colours if one worked with studies painted directly from life from the photographs that people want to see painted. And after all, at any rate this is one of the chances of earning something that one might have.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But whatever I want to begin and where — I have to be able to show things, that goes without saying.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Since I need all my high spirits, all my energy — putting it bluntly, I dread feeling physically weak.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’ve been to see someone else with my view of Het Steen, who thought the tone and colour good, who was in a state of confusion drawing up his inventory and is in small premises, though, but where I could<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> go back after the New Year. It’s a good thing for when there are foreigners who want to have a souvenir of Antwerp, and for this reason I’ll make a few more in the same genre of townscapes. Yesterday, for example, I drew a few studies<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> for a thing in which one sees the cathedral. And similarly I also have a small one of the Park.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> However, I’d rather paint people’s eyes than cathedrals, for there’s something in the eyes that isn’t in the cathedral — although it’s solemn and although it’s impressive — to my mind the soul of a person, even if it’s a poor tramp or a girl from the streets, is more interesting. I consequently believe that nothing helps one progress <hi rend="italics">so</hi> directly as working with a model. Of course it’s a great problem to have to pay the models  we’re at a stage where it comes down to energy and 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> the paintings will have to be energetic in order to find buyers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m convinced that something can be done here. There seem to be a lot of beautiful women in this city, and it has to be the case that there’s money to be earned with either women’s portraits or imaginary women — heads and figures.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">It’s a real pleasure for me to work with a rather better type of brush, and to have cobalt and carmine and a good brilliant yellow and vermilion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">The most expensive is still sometimes the cheapest. Cobalt especially — it can’t be compared with any other blue as regards the delicate tones that one can get with it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And the quality of the colour may not be everything in a painting, but all the same that’s what gives it vitality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">As to whether or not I’d live here permanently — given that things don’t look exactly rosy in the art trade — and there seems to be something of a tendency for each painter to be his own dealer — which I imagine will increase still further in the long run — it might be wise to keep a studio here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">If you have any thoughts or wishes about it, either for or against, let me know as frankly as possible. But it strikes me right away that — if you should ever get to the point of working for yourself, independently of the Goupils, either sooner or later — 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> Antwerp could perhaps be a place where, given the poor displays there are now, by exhibiting properly quite a lot could be done that the other houses don’t understand. Furthermore — It’s relatively easy to go back and forth to England from here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Why — for the trade — are all paintings always in frames? As a commercial article there’s surely sometimes a lot to be said for something’s being light and easy to handle and to move.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The trade is old-fashioned and... thrice mouldered. There has to be renewal — and the old systems don’t exactly work well any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">The prices — the public — everything needs renewing. And the future is working cheaply for the bourgeoisie, perhaps. At any rate — the ordinary art lovers themselves seem to be getting more and more set, becoming hard. Anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Starting with capital so often only leads to losing everything first, and thus one’s courage and zest for work, too. Whereas starting with virtually nothing at least makes someone more decisive and firmer of character. Anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Regards — but see that you write to me by return, for I have a faint sensation in my body because I’ve exerted myself rather a lot on this and that, and I need my strength.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">From <ref target="let550.xml">letter 550</ref> of 28 December 1885 it is clear that Theo responded to the urgent request for extra money in the present letter <ref target="#l-15">(ll. 15-18)</ref> and that Vincent left it several days before he wrote to thank him. Since Jo van Gogh-Bonger gave the date as 19 December in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914 and she may have had a postmark to go on, we have dated the letter Saturday, 19 December 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh tries to sell ‘View of ’t Steen’ (<ref target="let548.xml">letter 548</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This head is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
    
<p>We do not know which portrait this was; from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let550.xml">letter 550</ref> it is clear that Van Gogh did indeed paint the portrait and was able to make one study of the head in return. See for the two works to which this may have led: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let550.xml#n-3">letter 550, nn. 3</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let550.xml#n-4">4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This may read ‘kan’ (can) rather than ‘kon’ (could).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>There are two surviving drawings in which the cathedral in Antwerp can be seen: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Grote Markt</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_627">F 1352 / JH 975</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The spire of the Church of Our Lady</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_628">F 1356 / JH 974</rs>). Nothing is known of any working up of these drawings on canvas.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This picture of the park is not known; it must have been the Stadspark, near the Central Station.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    