<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh, Antwerp, on or about Thursday, 28 January 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let555"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b487 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>555</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>447</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>558</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-01-28">on or about Thursday, 28 January 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0487" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0487" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000659_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">ik heb reeds te lang gewacht om U de goede ontvangst van uw brief en het ingeslotene te berigten. Wat uw brief betreft<c type="kk">/</c> het is nog steeds ’t zelfde en gij steunt U te zeer mijns inziens als ge mij beoordeelt op algemeenheden en op prejugés die te oppervlakkig zijn en te zeer mis dan dat ik gelooven kan zij U steeds zullen bij blijven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">En daarom juist geloof ik dat <hi rend="italics">in geen geval</hi> het kwaad zal kunnen wanneer wij over een tijd elkaar eens te Parijs zien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Ik heb het gruwelijk druk gehad deze week omdat<c type="kk">/</c> behalve de schilderklas<c type="kk">/</c> ik s’avonds ook ga teekenen en dan daarna van half 10 tot half 12 nog naar ’t model ga werken op een club. Want ik ben van twee van die clubs zelfs lid geworden.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> En ik ken nu twee lui die m.i. mooi teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> beiden hollanders. Van deze week schilderde ik een groot ding met twee naakte torsen – twee worstelaars, een pose van Verlat<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> En dat bevalt mij uitmuntend.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En zoo ook het teekenen naar het antiek – ik heb nu twee groote figuren klaar<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> in alle geval heeft het twee dingen voor – vooreerst dat het me zeer interesseert<c type="kk">/</c> na jaren lang gekleed model te hebben geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> het naakt en het antiek terug te zien en dingen te verifieeren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Verder<c type="kk">/</c> juist om in Parijs ergens toegelaten te worden moet men ergens anders zijn geweest en zijn groensten bolster niet meer hebben<c type="kk">/</c> en heeft men altijd te doen met lui die reeds op een akademie hebben gewerkt, langer of korter<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Wat Verlat mij zegt is heel streng en zoo ook wat Vinck van de teekenklas mij zegt – en zij raden mij sterk aan<c type="kk">/</c> een jaar minstens<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">vooral</hi> te teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">desnoods niets anders</hi> dan teekenen naar antiek en naar naakt<c type="kk">/</c> en dat zulks de <hi rend="italics">kortste</hi> weg zou zijn<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik dan heel anders zal terugkomen op mijn ander werk buiten of mijn portretten<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En ik geloof dat het waar is – ik moet dus zien ergens te zijn waar ik en antiek en naakt model onder mijn bereik heb voor den eersten tijd.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">De beste van de klas heeft het ook zoo gedaan en hij zegt dat hij met iedere studie zich wat voelde vorderen<c type="kk">/</c> en ik heb dat zelf kunnen zien in dingen van vroeger en dingen van nu van hem.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik denk dat gij U zult herinneren:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">les Grecs ne prennent pas par le contour<c type="kk">/</c> ils prennent par les milieux<c type="kk">/</c> par les noyaux<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Gericault a pris cela à Gros qui lui l’avait pris des Grecs mais Gericault a voulu lui-même le prendre aux Grecs aussi et les a étudiés pour cela même – après Delacroix a fait comme Gericault.–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Die kwestie – Millet teekent ook zoo<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan iemand anders – is misschien de wortel van ’t heele figuur schilderen – hangt verbazend zamen juist met het modeleerend teekenen direct met ’t penseel<c type="kk">/</c> het – glad anders opvatten dan Bouguereau en anderen<c type="kk">/</c> die interieur modelé mankeeren<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">plat</hi> zijn vergeleken bij Gericault &amp; Delacroix en niet buiten de verf zijn.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Bij welke laatsten<c type="kk">/</c> Gericault &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> de figuren ruggen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> ook als men ze van voren ziet<c type="kk">/</c> lucht om de figuren heen – <hi rend="italics">buiten</hi> <hi rend="italics">de verf</hi>.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Het is om dat te zoeken – waar ik noch met Verlat noch met Vinck over zou willen praten zelfs – dat ik werk, er is geen nood dat <hi rend="italics">zij</hi> me dat zouden wijzen want hun beider fout zit in de kleur<c type="kk">/</c> die zoo als ge weet bij beiden niet het echte is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Het is curieus dat als ik mijn studie vergelijk bij die van andere lui<c type="kk">/</c> het bijna niets er mee gemeen heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– De hunnen hebben <hi rend="italics">dezelfde kleur als het vleesch</hi> zoo ongeveer – en doen dus van digt bij gezien heel precies – maar gaat men wat achteruit<c type="kk">/</c> wordt het pijnlijk en plat om te zien – al dat rose en fijn geel enz<c type="kp">_</c> enz<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> zacht op zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> geeft een hard effet produit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Zoo als ik het doe is het van digt bij groenachtig ros<c type="kk">/</c> geelgrijs<c type="kk">/</c> wit<c type="kk">/</c> zwart<c type="kk">/</c> en veel neutraal<c type="kk">/</c> en meest kleuren die men niet noemen kan<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar ’t wordt juist buiten de verf als men wat achteruit gaat – en dan is er lucht om heen en een sober golvend licht valt er op. Tevens<c type="kk">/</c> daarin spreekt het minste likje kleur waar men eventueel mee glaceere.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar wat er aan mankeert is – oefening – ik moet er een 50 zoo schilderen – ik geloof dat ik dan <hi rend="italics">iets</hi> hebben zal. Het <hi rend="italics">er opzetten van de verf</hi> is nu wat al te <hi rend="italics">moeielijk</hi> gedaan omdat ik er de routine nog niet genoeg van heb<c type="kk">/</c> te lang zoeken moet<c type="kk">/</c> het doodwerk. Maar dit is een kwestie van een tijd van doorschilderen, zoo dat de toets <hi rend="italics">in eens</hi> raak wordt naarmate men het meer in ’t hoofd heeft.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Er zijn eenige lui die mijn teekeningen hebben gezien – een is direkt begonnen om naar aanleiding van mijn boerenfiguren<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> op de naaktklas het model te teekenen met een krachtiger modelé<c type="kk">/</c> de schaduwen stevig aanzettende<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Hij heeft mij die teekening laten zien en we hebben er over gepraat. het was vol leven en het was de mooiste teekening die ik hier van de lui hier zag geworden. Weet ge nu hoe men daar over denkt<c type="kp">_</c>– de leeraar Sibert<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> liet hem opzettelijk bij zich komen en zeide dat als hij nog eens het op die manier durfde te doen<c type="kk">/</c> het zou beschouwd worden als hield hij den leeraar voor den gek<c type="kp">_</c>– En ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> het was de eenige teekening die <hi rend="italics">grassement</hi> <hi rend="italics">fait</hi> was<c type="kk">/</c> Tassaert- of Gavarni achtig.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Dus ge ziet hoe het gaat. Maar dat is niet erg echter en men moet er ook niet boos om worden en zich dom houden net als of men het heel graag zou afleeren<c type="kk">/</c> die slechte manier<c type="kk">/</c> maar ongelukkig er telkens in terugvalt.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">De figuren die ze teekenen – zijn zoo goed als altijd topzwaar en tuimelen voorover<c type="kk">/</c> hals over kop – geen een die op zijn voeten <hi rend="italics">staat</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">En dat <hi rend="italics">staan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dat moet <hi rend="italics">juist al in het eerste</hi> <hi rend="italics">schema zitten</hi>.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Enfin – ik blijf erg in mijn schik naar hier gegaan te zijn – hoe het ook ga of hoe het ook uitvalle – of ik goede of slechte vrienden 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>met Verlat worde<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik vind hier de wrijving van gedachten die ik zoek – ik krijg een frisch oog op mijn eigen werk<c type="kk">/</c> kan beter oordeelen waar de zwakke punten zitten en zoodoende vorderen om die te verbeteren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Wat ik U zeer dringend verzoek in het belang juist van het goed teregt komen van de dingen<c type="kk">/</c> is noch uw geduld, noch uw opgewektheid vooral, te verliezen<c type="kk">/</c> want wij zouden onze eigen glazen ingooien indien den moed ons ontzonk op het moment dat juist er zich toe prêteert om ons een zekeren invloed te geven<c type="kk">/</c> als wij toonen dat wij weten wat we willen<c type="kk">/</c> en iets durven en weten vol te houden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">En wat het geld betreft – dan wanneer ik op een atelier werk en dus de onkosten van model voor een goed deel vervallen<c type="kk">/</c> dan is frs 150 zeker ook dan niet veel want het schilderen is zeer duur – maar het <hi>kan</hi><c type="kk">/</c> mits men zelfs op eten &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> bezuinige.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Moet er model af <hi rend="italics">dan is het gedecideerd </hi><hi>niet te doen</hi> van frs 150. en verliest men tijd &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Het is dus tevens ’t goedkoopst op een atelier te blijven – want voor meer doorwerkte naaktstudies vooral is het niet te doen ’t model zelf te bekostigen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Onmogelijk acht ik het niet dat op den duur<c type="kk">/</c> vooral als onwillekeurig andere lui krachtiger schaduwen gingen aanzetten<c type="kk">/</c> dat dan of Verlat of een ander een standje met mij zal <hi rend="italics">zoeken</hi><c type="kk">/</c> ook als ik systematisch het ontwijk<c type="kp">_</c> Wat ik systematisch doen zal omdat het in mijn voordeel is er wat te blijven<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Enfin – ik ben nieuwsgierig hoe het zal gaan met Uwe woning.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Wat echter mij betreft<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik er kom vind ik het volkomen goed ergens achteraf (Montmartre) een goedkoop kamertje te nemen of een mansarde in een hôtel. Maar dit is betrekkelijk bijzaak en wij zijn zoover nog niet<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons eerst hier wat blijven – en daarna<c type="kk">/</c> wie dan leeft wie dan zorgt. 31 Maart eindigt de wintercursus.– Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve already left it too long to confirm the safe receipt of your letter and the enclosure. As regards your letter, it’s still the same and, to my mind, when you judge me you rely too much on generalities and on prejudices that are too superficial and too wrong for me to be able to believe that you’ll always stick to them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And for this very reason, I believe that <hi rend="italics">in any event</hi> it can do no harm if we see each other again in Paris after a while.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve been dreadfully busy this week because, as well as the painting class, I also go drawing in the evenings, and then after that go on and work from a model at a club from half past 9 to half past 11. For I’ve become a member of no fewer than two of these clubs.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> And I now know two fellows who to my mind draw well, both Dutch. This week I painted a large thing with two nude torsos — two wrestlers, a pose set by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And I really like doing that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And the same is true of drawing from the antique — I’ve now finished two large figures.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> At any rate it has two things in its favour — firstly that it interests me greatly, after having drawn clothed models for years, to see the nude and the antique again and to verify things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Further, just to be admitted anywhere in Paris one has to have been somewhere else and have lost one’s rough edges, and one always has to contend with fellows who’ve already worked at an academy for some length of time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">What <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> tells me is very severe and so too is what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1419">Vinck</rs>, who takes the drawing class, tells me — and they strongly advise me <hi rend="italics">above all</hi> to draw, <hi rend="italics">if necessary do nothing else</hi> but draw from the antique and nudes for at least a year, and that this would be the <hi rend="italics">shortest</hi> way, that then I’ll return very differently to my other work outdoors or my portraits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And I think it’s true — so I have to see to it that I’m somewhere where I have access to both the antique and nude models at first.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The best one in the class has done it like this too, and he says that he felt himself progressing a little with each study, and I’ve been able to see that for myself in things he did before and his recent things.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I think you’ll remember:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The Greeks don’t start from the outline, they start from the centres, from the cores.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_606">Géricault</rs> took that from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1062">Gros</rs>, who took it from the Greeks, but Géricault himself wished to take it from the Greeks, too, and he studied them for that very thing — afterwards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> did the same as Géricault.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This question — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> draws like that too — more than anyone else — is perhaps the root of all figure painting — is extremely closely related to modelling by drawing directly with a brush — conceived totally differently from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_890">Bouguereau</rs> and others, who lack interior modelling, are <hi rend="italics">flat</hi> compared with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_606">Géricault</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, and who don’t go beyond the paint.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">In which latter, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_606">Géricault</rs> &amp;c., the figures have backs, even when one sees them from the front, air around the figures — <hi rend="italics">beyond the paint</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">It’s to search for this — which I wouldn’t want even to talk about with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> or with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1419">Vinck</rs> — that I’m working; there’s no risk that <hi rend="italics">they</hi> could show it to me, because the fault with both of them is in the colour which, as you know, isn’t true with either of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"> It’s strange that when I compare my study with those of other people, it has almost nothing in common with them. Theirs have more or less <hi rend="italics">the same colour as the flesh</hi> — and so look very accurate from close to — but if one steps back a bit, it becomes painful and flat to look at — all that pink and delicate yellow etc., etc., soft in itself, produces a hard effect.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The way I do it, from close to it’s greenish red, yellow-grey, white, black and a lot of neutral, and mostly colours one can’t put a name to. But if one steps back a little it’s indeed beyond the paint — and then there’s air around it and a restrained undulating light falls on it. At the same time, the least little lick of colour with which one might glaze it is telling.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But what’s lacking in it is — practice — I must paint 50 or so like that — I believe that I’ll have <hi rend="italics">something</hi> then. I make the business of <hi rend="italics">putting on the paint</hi> too difficult because I haven’t yet sufficiently got into the way of it, have to search too long, work it to death. But this is a question of keeping on painting for a while, so that the touch is effective <hi rend="italics">straightaway</hi> as one gets it more fixed in one’s mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">There are some fellows who’ve seen my drawings — after seeing my peasant figures<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> one of them immediately started drawing the model in the life class with more vigorous modelling, putting the shadows in strongly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">He showed me the drawing and we talked about it. It was full of life and it was the finest drawing that I’ve seen by any of the fellows here. Now do you know what they think about it? The teacher, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1351">Siberdt</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> purposely sent for him and said that if he dared to do it again in that manner it would be considered that he was making a fool of the teacher. And I tell you, it was the only drawing that was <hi rend="italics">generously done</hi>, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1379">Tassaert</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">So you see how it is. But it’s not bad, though, and one mustn’t get angry about it, and must keep quiet just as if one would really like to break oneself of it, that bad manner, but unfortunately keeps slipping back into it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">The figures that they draw — are virtually always top-heavy and topple forwards, headlong — there’s not one that <hi rend="italics">stands</hi> on its feet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">And this <hi rend="italics">standing</hi>, this really must <hi rend="italics">already be there in the initial design</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Anyway — I’m still really pleased that I came here — however it goes and however it turns out — whether or not I get along with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs>. 
    <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I find the friction of ideas that I’m looking for here — I’m getting a fresh eye for my own work, can judge better where the weak points are and thus make progress in order to correct them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">What I ask you very earnestly for the sake of things working out well, is not to lose your patience, nor above all your optimism, for we’d be cutting our own throats if our courage were to fail us precisely as the moment presents itself when we could acquire a degree of influence if we show that we know what we want, and dare to do something and manage to see it through.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">And as to the money — if I worked in a studio and so saved a good part of the cost of models, even then 150 francs still wouldn’t be much, because painting is very expensive — but it <hi>can be done</hi>, provided one economizes even on food &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">If models have to come out of it, <hi rend="italics">then it definitely </hi><hi>can’t<hi rend="italics"> </hi>be<hi rend="italics"> </hi>done</hi> on 150 francs, and one wastes time &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">So at the same time it’s cheapest to stay in a studio — because for more finished nude studies, above all, it’s not possible to pay the cost of the model oneself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I don’t consider it impossible that in due course, especially if some of the other fellows couldn’t help starting to put in more powerful shadows, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> or someone else will <hi rend="italics">seek</hi> a row with me, even if I systematically avoid it. Which I’ll do systematically because it’s to my advantage to stay here for a bit.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Anyway — I’m curious as to what will happen with your apartment.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> As to me, though, if I come I’ll be perfectly content to take a cheap little room or a garret in a hotel somewhere in an out-of-the-way quarter (Montmartre). But that’s pretty much by the way and we’re not there yet. Let’s stay here for a while first — and then, all in good time. The winter course ends on 31 March. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says ‘I’ve been dreadfully busy this week’, which would indicate that the letter was written late in the <hi rend="italics">second </hi>week of classes. He also apologizes for his lateness in responding to the money Theo sent which, if he had acceded to the request in <ref target="let554.xml">letter 554</ref>, must have arrived at the beginning of the week; the letter was thus written a few days after Monday, 25 January. We have therefore dated it on or about Thursday, 28 January 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh takes classes at the Academy (<ref target="let553.xml">553</ref>, <ref target="let554.xml">554</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>It has not proved possible to identify which drawing clubs Van Gogh belonged to. Tralbaut suggested a club in Reyndersstraat as one possibility; Persoons and Wilmer one on the Grote Markt. These unregulated drawing clubs – sometimes described as sketching clubs – were usually set up by students of the senior classes at the Antwerp Academy. For a small subscription, members could go there in the evening to draw from models, nude and clothed. See Tralbaut 1948, p. 172, and Persoons 1990, p. 23, n. 2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
    
<p>This work with nude torsos was overpainted by Van Gogh in Paris with <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with meadow flowers and roses</hi>, 1886 (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_989">F 278 / JH 1103</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3103">Ill. 3103.</rs> See Luuk Struick van der Loeff <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al.</hi>, ‘Rehabilitation of a flower still life in the Kröller-Müller Museum and a lost Antwerp painting by Van Gogh’, in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Van Gogh: New Findings. Van Gogh Studies 4</hi>. Zwolle and Amsterdam 2012, pp. 33-54.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>These large figures are not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
    
<p>A reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Jean Gigoux</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let494.xml#n-2">See letters 494, n. 2</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let526.xml#n-10">526, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>See for the expression ‘beyond the paint’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let439.xml#n-3">letter 439, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Glazing involves applying a thin coat of diluted paint that gives a transparent colour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to the ‘drawings of figures’ he took with him from Nuenen to Antwerp. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml">See letter 542</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1351">Eugène Siberdt</rs> had been teaching at the Antwerp Academy since 1883. During Van Gogh’s time there, Siberdt was one of those responsible for the elements <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dessin d’après la figure antique</hi> (‘Classical Statues’) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dessin d’àprès le model vivant</hi> (‘Life’) (Antwerp, Bibliotheek Koninklijke Academie, Register 1885-1891, inv. no. 289).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            
    
<p>Theo lived in an apartment at 25 rue Laval in Paris; he had probably already responded to Vincent’s possible arrival and an attendant move, and had let it be known that he thought his apartment was too small for the two of them. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let559.xml">letter 559</ref> Vincent writes: ‘What you say about the apartment is perhaps really rather expensive. I mean, I’d be just as happy if it weren’t quite as good’ (ll. 192-195). In the event, Vincent and Theo moved to Montmartre in June 1886 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let557.xml#n-1">see letters 557, n. 1</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let569.xml#n-9">569, n. 9</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    