<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Thursday, 4 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let558"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b489 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>558</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>449</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>560</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-02-04">on or about Thursday, 4 February 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0489 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0489 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000662_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0489 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000663_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000663_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0489 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000663_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000663_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000663_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">ik heb U eergisteren reeds geschreven dat aan den eenen kant ik bij lange na niet wel was maar dat van den anderen kant ik toch licht meende te zien.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Nog meer categorisch moet ik tot mijn spijt U echter melden dat zeer gedecideerd ik letterlijk uitgeput en overwerkt ben. Als ge nagaat dat ik 1 Mei in mijn eigen atelier ging wonen –<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> is het sedert misschien een keer of 6 of 7 geweest<c type="kk">/</c> tot nu toe<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik er mijn middageten heb afgenomen. Ik wil niet<c type="kk">/</c> om goede reden<c type="kk">/</c> dat gij aan Moe zegt dat ik niet wel ben – want zij zou er mogelijk over na denken dat het niet aardig was dat gebeurde wat gebeurde<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat ik er niet bleef – juist om deze gevolgen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik zal er niets van zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> zeg gij ook niets<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar ik heb toen geleefd<c type="kk">/</c> en sedert hier<c type="kk">/</c> niet<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> hebbende voor mijn eten omdat het werk me te veel kost en ik heb er te veel op gesteund dat ik het zoo wel uit zou houden.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Hetgeen de dokter mij zegt is <hi rend="italics">dat ik absoluut</hi> <hi rend="italics">sterker moet leven</hi> en dat ik totdat ik sterker ben mij moet ontzien met mijn werk.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Het is een verzwakking van <hi rend="italics">alles</hi>.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Nu heb ik het erger gemaakt door veel rooken<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik juist te meer aan deed omdat men zoodoende van zijn leege maag geen last heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Enfin men zegt – manger de la vache enragée<c type="kk">/</c> het is dat waar ik mijn part van heb.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Want het is niet alleen het eten<c type="kk">/</c> het is tevens al de zorg &amp; verdriet die men heeft<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ge weet dat door een en ander dien tijd in Nuenen lang niet zonder zorg voor me was<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Verder – hier – ik ben heel blij hierheen gegaan te zijn – maar het is ook een moeielijken tijd geweest toch<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Wat we moeten doen en waar het hem grootendeels schort – is dit<c type="kp">_</c>– Zelf de modellen betalen is te zwaar<c type="kk">/</c> men moet zoolang men geen geld genoeg heeft zich bedienen van de gelegenheden op de ateliers<c type="kk">/</c> zooals Verlat<c type="kk">/</c> zooals Cormon<c type="kp">_</c> En men moet in de artistenwereld zijn en verder werken op clubs waar men zamen de modellen betaald<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Nu is het zoo dat ik niet vroeger hier op heb gedacht of althans het niet gedaan – maar ik wou nu wel dat ik een jaar vroeger er mede was begonnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Kon het nu dat wij verder er iets op vonden om in dezelfde stad te wonen<c type="kk">/</c> het ware zeker verreweg het beste<c type="kk">/</c> althans voorloopig<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Alleen<c type="kk">/</c> naarmate ik er over denk verbeeld ik mij meer en meer dat het misschien beter is het <hi rend="italics">eerste jaar</hi> niet veel aan een atelier te besteden omdat ik dat eerste jaar grootendeels zal moeten teekenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Want van Cormon gesproken – ik stel mij voor hij me ongeveer ’t zelfde zou zeggen wat Verlat zegt – dat ik naakt of antiek moet teekenen een jaartje<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat ik altijd naar ’t leven heb geteekend<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Deze eisch is ook niet hard want ik zeg U dat er hier zijn die al <hi rend="italics">3 jaar</hi> er op zitten en er nog niet af mogen<c type="kk">/</c> die ook schilderen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">In dat jaar moet ik en ’t mannen- en ’t vrouwenfiguur<c type="kk">/</c> en in detail en als ensemble<c type="kk">/</c> repeteeren en – dan zal ik het als ’t ware van buiten kennen<c type="kp">_</c> Het teekenen op zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> technisch<c type="kk">/</c> is mij makkelijk genoeg – ik begin het te doen zoo als men schrijft<c type="kk">/</c> met ’t zelfde gemak<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar juist op die hoogte wordt het interessanter als men met de handigheid die men langzamer<c type="shy">-</c>hand krijgt <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> tevreden is maar goed degelijk zoekt naar oorspronkelijkheid en breedheid van opvatting<c type="kp">_</c>– Het teekenen der massas in plaats van de contours. Het solide modeleeren<c type="kp">_</c> En als nu lui zooals laat ons zeggen Verlat of Cormon dat eisschen van iemand<c type="kk">/</c> verzeker ik U dit geen slecht teeken is<c type="kp">_</c>– Want er zijn er genoeg die Verlat eenvoudig maar laat scharrelen omdat – het de lui voor ’t hoogere figuur toch niet zijn. Gij spreekt over de knappe lui op dat atelier Cormon<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Juist omdat ik verdomd graag er mee mee wou doen<c type="kk">/</c> stel ik me zelf uit eigen overtuiging reeds van tevoren dien eisch van te Parijs althans een jaar grootendeels aan teekenen te besteden van naakt en antiek<c type="kp">_</c>– Laat ons overigens doen wat de hand vindt om te doen<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> van schilderen als ons een effekt buiten treft of we eens een mooi model hebben &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">En meen niet dat dit de <hi rend="italics">lange</hi> weg is want het is de <hi rend="italics">korte</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Wie uit ’t <hi rend="italics">hoofd</hi> zijn figuurtje kan maken is veel productiever dan wie dat niet heeft<c type="kp">_</c>– En door die moeite me te geven van dat jaar teekenen – zult ge eens zien hoe productief we worden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">En meen ook niet dat de jaren dat ik buiten werkte weg zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Want het is juist een ding dat degenen die nooit ergens anders dan op akademies &amp; ateliers zijn<c type="kk">/</c> mankeert den blik op de werkelijkheid waar ze in zijn en het motieven kunnen vinden<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ware het nu niet verstandig als we het eerste <hi rend="italics">half</hi> <hi rend="italics">jaar althans</hi> het huren van een atelier nog daar lieten<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat het op ’t geld zoo aankomt. Maar anders heb ik er veel<c type="kk">/</c> zeer veel sympathie voor een atelier te stichten<c type="kp">_</c>– Zelfs zoo dat desnoods men zich combineerde met andere schilders om zamen modellen te nemen. Hoe meer energie hoe beter<c type="kp">_</c> En in een duren tijd<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – moet men juist het in de vriendschap zoeken en in het zamen werken.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Maar Theo het is nu bedonderd van die ongesteldheid – het spijt me gruwelijk – <hi rend="italics">maar</hi> <hi rend="italics">ik heb toch goeden moed</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Het zal zich redresseeren. Ge begrijpt dat als ik uitstelde er tegen te reageeren<c type="kk">/</c> het al erger en erger zou zijn geworden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Wat ik echter denk is dit – Men moet niet denken dat de lui wier gestel geabimeerd<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> is<c type="kk">/</c> heel of half<c type="kk">/</c> voor ’t schilderen niet deugen<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is wenschelijk men 60 jaar althans hale<c type="kk">/</c> en noodig men 50 jaar hale<c type="kk">/</c> als men omstreeks zijn 30<hi rend="super">ste</hi> begint<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Maar men hoeft volstrekt niet volmaakt gezond te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> men mag van alles mankeeren<c type="kp">_</c> Het werk lijdt er niet altijd onder – integendeel de zenuwachtige lui zijn gevoeliger en fijner<c type="kp">_</c> Maar Theo juist omdat het voor mij zich zoo beslist dat er aan de gezondheid nog al wat te kort komt – ik ben besloten mij toe te leggen juist op ’t hoogere figuur en mij te zoeken te verfijnen<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Het is mij betrekkelijk zoo onverwacht op ’t lijf gevallen – ik voelde mij wel slap en koortsachtig maar ik ging toch door<c type="kp">_</c>– Alleen het begon mij te verontrusten dat telkens en telkens er een tand afbrak<c type="kp">_</c>– En dat ik er slechter en slechter ging uitzien<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin wij zullen er ons zien uit te helpen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Ik geloof dat het herstellen van de tanden op zichzelf al helpen zal omdat<c type="kk">/</c> meestal pijn in den mond hebbende<c type="kk">/</c> ik mijn eten maar zoo gaauw mogelijk doorslikte.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">En het zal me ook ietwat althans helpen voor mijn uiterlijk misschien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">Wat deze maand betreft<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb mijn kamer vooruit betaald<c type="kk">/</c> frs 25, voor mijn eten frs 30 vooruit en frs 50 aan den dentist<c type="kk">/</c> verder een visite aan den dokter en nog teekengerij – resteert <hi rend="italics">frs 6.–</hi></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Nu is het de kwestie deze maand <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> ziek te worden<c type="kk">/</c> wat niet makkelijk op te lossen is – en wat best wel zou kunnen gebeuren<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar wij willen toch zien – ik geloof steeds dat ik een zekere taaiheid met de boeren gemeen heb<c type="kk">/</c> die ook niet veel bijzonders eten en toch blijven leven en doorwerken. Maak U er ook niet buitengewoon bezorgd over<c type="kp">_</c>– Kunt gij nog wat bij sturen<c type="kk">/</c> goed – maar kan het niet<c type="kk">/</c> dan blijf ik het kalm afwachten hoe het gaat<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>Wat mij niet bevalt is dat ik koortsachtig ben en ik redeneer er zoo over dat al moge ik verzwakt zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb toch een zekere zorg gehad om geen ongezond voedsel te gebruiken<c type="kp">_</c>– Overspanning is ook niet overmatig – omdat ik met opgewektheid hier ben steeds<c type="kk">/</c> onder alles door – dus het is door dat ik zwak ben dat het me overspant. <hi rend="italics">Mij dunkt het</hi> <hi rend="italics">moet losloopen</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Ge begrijpt dat echter <hi rend="italics">als</hi> het erger werd – en een <hi rend="italics">kwaadaardigen</hi> keer nam – men een typhus of typheuse koortsen althans zou kunnen door te maken hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">En eigentlijk zijn de <hi rend="italics">eenige</hi> redenen waarom ik dat niet zeker verwacht deze – <hi rend="italics">1</hi> dat ik veel buitenlucht heb gehad<c type="kk">/</c> en <hi rend="italics">2</hi> dat zoo als ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik ook als ik me blijkbaar niet krachtig genoeg heb gevoed<c type="kk">/</c> toch juist voorzigtigheidshalve het met heel eenvoudig voedsel heb gedaan inplaats van de vuiligheden der mindere restauraties – en 3 – dat ik een zekere kalmte en sereniteit heb tegen de dingen in<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">We moeten dus afwachten verder<c type="kp">_</c>– Maak U er niet ongerust over want ik ben ’t zelf niet eens – ik blijf daarbij dat stel ik kreeg eens koorts<c type="kk">/</c> ik te eenvoudig heb geleefd en me gevoed dan dat het erg kwaadaardig kan worden zoo heel ligt<c type="kp">_</c>– De dingen komen après tout niet van zelf en alles heeft zijn reden.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Schrijf mij echter eens spoedig want ik heb daar wel behoefte aan<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Wat het naar Nuenen gaan betreft ook – wil ik wel weten wat ge ’t best zoudt vinden<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Maar noodig ben ik er niet – want iemand als de tuinman Rijke<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> b.v. kan minstens even goed als ik het beredderen wat er van inpakken of verzenden te doen zal zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Tegen Maart echter<c type="kk">/</c> als ’t ergens goed voor mogt wezen<c type="kk">/</c> ben ik desnoods klaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I already wrote to you the day before yesterday that on the one hand I was far from well, but that on the other hand I nevertheless thought I could see some light.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">However, I regret that I have to tell you even more categorically that I’m most definitely literally exhausted and overworked. When you think that I went to live in my own studio on 1 May<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — since then it’s perhaps been a matter of 6 or 7 times, so far, that I’ve had my midday meal. For good reasons, I don’t want you to tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> that I’m not well — because she might possibly consider that it wasn’t nice that what happened, happened, that’s to say that I didn’t stay there — precisely because of these consequences. I shan’t say anything about it; don’t you say anything either. But I lived then, and since then, here, having nothing for my food because the work cost me too much and I relied too much on the idea that I could stick it out like this.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">What the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_330">doctor</rs> tells me is <hi rend="italics">that I absolutely must live better</hi>, and that I have to take more care of myself with my work until I’m stronger.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> It’s <hi rend="italics">total</hi> debilitation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Well I’ve made it worse by smoking a lot, which I did all the more because then one isn’t troubled by one’s empty stomach.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Anyway, they say — one has to experience lean times, and I’ve had my share of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Because it’s not just the food, it’s also all the worry and sorrow that one has.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">You know that for one reason or another the time in Nuenen was far from carefree for me. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> What’s more — here — I’m very pleased to have come here — but it’s been a difficult time all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">What we have to do and what is largely lacking — is this. Paying the models ourselves is too much; as long as one doesn’t have enough money, one must take advantage of the opportunities at the studios, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs>, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>. And one must be in the artists’ world and work at clubs where one shares the cost of the models.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now it’s true that I didn’t think of this before, or at least didn’t do it — but I wish now that I’d started on it a year earlier. If we could now find some way of living in the same city it would be far and away the best thing, at least for the time being.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Only, the more I think about it, the more and more I fancy that it might be better not to spend much on a studio in the <hi rend="italics">first year</hi>, because I’ll mostly have to draw in that first year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Because speaking of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs> — I imagine he would tell me much the same as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> says — that I have to draw nudes or plaster casts for up to a year, precisely because I’ve always drawn from life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This isn’t really a harsh requirement, because I tell you that there are people here who’ve been in the class for <hi rend="italics">3 years</hi> and are still not allowed to stop, who also paint. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">In that year I have to practise the male and the female figure, both in detail and as a whole, and — then I’ll know it by heart, as it were. Drawing in itself, technically, is easy enough for me — I’m beginning to do it the way one writes, with the same ease. But precisely at this level it becomes more interesting, as one is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> satisfied with the facility that one gradually acquires but really looks for originality and breadth of conception. Drawing the masses rather than the outlines. Solid modelling. And I can assure you it’s not a bad sign if people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>, let’s say, demand that of someone. For there are enough of them that Verlat simply leaves to get on with it because — they just aren’t the fellows for the loftier figure. You talk about the clever fellows at Cormon’s studio.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Precisely because I damned well want to be one of them, I’m setting myself in advance, out of my own conviction, the requirement of spending at least a year in Paris mainly drawing from the nude and plaster casts. For the rest, let’s do whatsoever our hand finds to do<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> in the way of painting, if an effect out of doors strikes us or we happen to have a good model &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">And don’t think that this is the <hi rend="italics">long</hi> way, because it’s the <hi rend="italics">short</hi> one. Someone who can draw his figures from <hi rend="italics">memory</hi> is much more productive than someone who can’t. And by my taking the trouble to spend that year drawing — you’ll just see how productive we become. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And don’t think either that the years I worked out of doors were wasted. For it’s the very thing that people who’ve never been anywhere else but at academies and studios lack, that view of reality in which they live, and finding subjects. Anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Might it not be wise if we put off renting a studio <hi rend="italics">at least for the first six months</hi>, precisely because it all comes down to the money? But otherwise I like the idea of setting up a studio a great deal, a very great deal. Even, if need be, such that one could combine with other painters to take models together. The more energy the better. And in hard times<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — one must especially seek a way out in friendship and collaboration.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But Theo, it’s so rotten about this indisposition — I’m dreadfully sorry — <hi rend="italics">but I’m still in good spirits</hi>. It will get better. You understand that it would have got worse and worse if I’d delayed doing something about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">What I think, though, is this — one mustn’t think that people whose constitution is damaged, wholly or half, aren’t fit for painting. It’s desirable for one to make it to 60 at least, and necessary for one to make it to 50, if one begins when one is around 30.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">But one absolutely doesn’t have to be perfectly healthy; one may have all sorts of things wrong. The work doesn’t always suffer as a result — on the contrary, nervous fellows are more sensitive and more refined. But Theo, precisely because it has proved in my case that my health leaves something to be desired — I’ve decided to concentrate specifically on the loftier figure and to try to refine myself. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> It really struck me so unexpectedly — I did feel weak and feverish, but I still kept going. Only it began to worry me that teeth were breaking off one after another. And that I was starting to look worse and worse. Anyway, we’ll see about putting it right.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I think that getting the teeth attended to will help in itself because, as my mouth was usually painful, I just swallowed my food as quickly as possible.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">And perhaps it will also help my appearance, at least a little.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">As regards this month, I’ve paid 25 francs in advance for my room, 30 francs in advance for my food, and 50 francs to the dentist; also a visit to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_330">doctor</rs> and some drawing materials — which leaves <hi rend="italics">6 francs</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Now the important issue this month is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to be ill, which isn’t easy to resolve — and which could very well happen. But we’ll see — I still think I’ve got a certain toughness in common with the peasants, who also don’t eat anything very special and still go on living and working. So don’t worry too much about it. If you could send a little bit extra, very well — but if you can’t, I’ll wait calmly to see how it goes. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> What I don’t like is that I’m feverish, and I reason about it thus: although I may be weakened, I’ve still taken some care not to eat any unwholesome food. Over-exertion isn’t excessive either — because, despite everything, I keep my spirits up all the time — so that it’s because I’m weak that I over-exert myself. <hi rend="italics">It seems to me that it must sort itself out</hi>. You understand, though, that <hi rend="italics">if</hi> it were to get worse — and took a <hi rend="italics">virulent</hi> turn — one might have to contend with typhus or at least typhoid fever.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">And actually the <hi rend="italics">only</hi> reasons why I certainly don’t expect that are these — <hi rend="italics">1</hi> that I’ve had a great deal of fresh air, and <hi rend="italics">2</hi> that, as I said, even though I’ve evidently not fed myself well enough, as a precaution I’ve nonetheless made do with very simple food rather than the muck in the cheap restaurants — and 3 — that I have a degree of calm and serenity in the face of things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">So we must wait and see. Don’t you worry about it, because not even I do — I maintain that, supposing I do get a fever, I’ve lived and eaten too simply for it to become very virulent all that easily. After all, things don’t happen of their own accord, and there’s a reason for everything. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Write to me soon, though, because I really do need it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">As regards going to Nuenen too — I want to know what you’d think best.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">But I’m not needed there — because someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_632">Rijken</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> the gardener, for instance, can see to what needs to be packed or sent at least as well as I can.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">If there’s any point in it, though, I can be ready by March if need be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The opening words of the letter, to the effect that Van Gogh can see ‘light’ despite the problems <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref>, are a direct reference to a similar passage in <ref target="let557.xml#l-167">letter 557, ll. 167-169</ref>. Since he wrote this preceding letter ‘the day before yesterday’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>) and we have dated it on or about 2 February, we date the present letter on or about Thursday, 4 February 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plan to move to Paris (<ref target="let555.xml">letter 555</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plan to study with Cormon <ref target="let556.xml">(556)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh has problems with his teeth <ref target="let557.xml">(557)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>See for the move to this studio in Nuenen: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let500.xml">letters 500</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let501.xml">501</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘niets’ (nothing).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The physician <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_330">Hubertus Amadeus Cavenaille</rs>, who had his surgery at 2 rue de Hollande in Antwerp. His name is noted in one of Van Gogh’s sketchbooks. See Tralbaut 1948, pp. 69-70; Wilkie 1978, pp. 154-168; Van der Wolk 1987, p. 104. According to Cavenaille’s descendants, Van Gogh gave him two painted portraits, which are not known, in payment for his medical services. See Ken Wilkie, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Van Gogh file. The myth and the man</hi>. Rev. ed. London 2004, pp. 226-227 (with a portrait photograph of Cavenaille).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for these ‘drawing clubs’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let555.xml#n-1">letter 555, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Some thirty artists, among them several foreigners, worked at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>’s well-known studio. See Destremau 1997, and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let557.xml#n-1">letter 557, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Cf. Eccl. 9:10, ‘whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might.’</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This could mean either ‘hard’ or ‘expensive’ times.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Means: ‘beschadigd, gehavend’ (damaged, battered).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_632">Adriaan Rijken</rs>, about whom <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had written to Theo on 30 December 1884: ‘Rijken is still our workman and perfectly fit again. These people are flourishing and the children are doing so well too. I am so pleased’ (FR b2264). Rijken was present at the reading of the inventory after Mr van Gogh’s death; on the list of funeral expenses there is an entry of 1 guilder for ‘Rijken workman’ (FR b2918, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">RHC</hi>, De Brouwer 1984, p. 23, and exhib. cat. ’s-Hertogenbosch 1987, pp. 87, 89).</p>

<p rend="indent">His son Cornelis Rijken, then aged 14, evidently also worked for the Van Goghs. Cornelis’s son S.A. Rijken wrote about it in a letter of 4 February 1963: ‘At the house of my grandfather A. Rijken, who lived at the time in Beekstraat Nuenen behind the parsonage, there were a couple of looms at the time, drawn and painted by Vincent many times ... His son, my father C. Rijken, was the garden boy at that time and looked after Dr v Gogh’s garden, and also kept the studio clean. As I heard him tell many times, also that he several times pushed the barrow to Nuenen station to take paintings to the train etc.’ (Letter Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, Archives Vincent van Gogh Foundation).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    