<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Saturday, 6 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let559"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b490 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>559</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>450</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>561</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-02-06">on or about Saturday, 6 February 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0490 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0490 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000664_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0490 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0490 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000665_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Uw brief en ingesloten frs 25 heb ik ontvangen en ik bedank U wel voor beiden. Zeer verheugt het mij dat gij naar het plan van mijn naar Parijs komen ooren hebt. Ik geloof ik er door vorderen zal en tevens dat<c type="kk">/</c> ging ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> ik ligt in een gâchis zou raken, in een zelfde kring te veel blijven rondvaren<c type="kk">/</c> dezelfde fouten houden.– Verder<c type="kk">/</c> voor U<c type="kk">/</c> het t’huiskomen in een atelier geloof ik niet dat U kwaad zal doen. Overigens ik moet U ’t zelfde zeggen van mijzelf wat gij schrijft van U zelf – <hi rend="italics">ik zal U tegenvallen</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">En toch is het de manier zich te vereenigen<c type="kp">_</c>– En toch kan er veel beter elkaar verstaan uit volgen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> wat zal ik U zeggen over mijn gezondheid. ik blijf gelooven dat ik kans heb om een bepaald ziek zijn te ontwijken<c type="kk">/</c> toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal tijd noodig hebben om mij te redresseeren.– Ik heb na nog twee tanden bovendien te laten plombeeren nu mijn boven kaak<c type="kk">/</c> die ’t meest geabimeerd<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> was<c type="kk">/</c> weer in orde<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik moet er nog 10 francs op betalen en dan nog 40 francs om ook de onderste helft in orde te krijgen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Eenige jaren van die bewuste 10 jaar cellulair<c type="kk">/</c> die ik ’t voorkomen heb doorgemaakt te hebben<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-b"/> zullen hierdoor verdwijnen<c type="kp">_</c>– Omdat een slecht gebit, dat men tegenwoordig zoo zelden meer ziet waar<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> ’t zoo makkelijk is ’t te laten restaureeren, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>daar een slecht gebit iets ineengezakts aan een physionomie geeft<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Enfin – verder<c type="kk">/</c> ook met hetzelfde te gebruiken kan men beter verteeren wanneer men goed kaauwen kan natuurlijk<c type="kk">/</c> en zoo zal mijn maag eer kans hebben teregt te komen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Ik merk het echter terdeeg dat ik op zeer laag water ben geraakt – en zoo als gij het zelf schrijft<c type="kk">/</c> door het te verwaarloozen kon er van alles dat nog erger is uit voortkomen. We willen echter zien het in orde te krijgen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Ik heb eens een paar dagen niet gewerkt<c type="kk">/</c> een keer of wat s’avonds vroeg naar bed gegaan (anders was het door ’t teekenen op de club telkens 1 of 2 uur)<c type="kp">_</c> En ik voel dat het mij calmeert<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Nu heb ik een briefje van Moe gehad die schrijft ze met Maart gaan inpakken<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Verder<c type="kk">/</c> daar gij spreekt van dat ge huur hebt tot en met Junij – welnu misschien is het dan après tout ’t beste dat ik van maart te beginnen nog terug keer naar Nuenen<c type="kk">/</c> alleen – als ik er tegenwerking en standjes ondervind als vòòr mijn vertrek<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik mijn tijd er verliezen en dus<c type="kk">/</c> al was ’t voor die paar maanden maar<c type="kk">/</c> toch nog veranderen daar ik nog wat nieuws van buiten klaar wil hebben om mee naar Parijs te brengen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Die Sibert<c type="kk">/</c> de leeraar voor het antiek<c type="kk">/</c> die eerst tegen mij sprak zooals ik U schreef<c type="kk">/</c> heeft van daag een standje 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>bepaald <hi rend="italics">gezocht</hi> met mij<c type="kk">/</c> dat misschien ten doel had om mij weg te krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>– Wat niet door is gegaan in zoover dat ik zeide – Pourquoi cherchez vous dispute avec moi<c type="kk">/</c> je ne veux pas me disputer et en tout cas je n’y tiens aucunément à vous contredire<c type="kk">/</c> seulement vous me cherchez dispute exprès<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Hij was hier blijkbaar niet op verdacht en kon niet veel er tegen zeggen nu deze keer<c type="kk">/</c> maar – de volgende keer kan hij natuurlijk iets uitlokken.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">De kwestie die er achter zit is dat de lui op de klas over dingen in mijn werk onder elkaar praten en ik niet tegen Sibert maar wel buiten de klas tot zekere lui gezegd heb dat hun teekeningen glad verkeerd waren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Denk er eens over dat als ik naar Cormon ging en hetzij met den meester hetzij met de leerlingen vroeger of later moeite kreeg<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">ik mij dit niet</hi> <hi rend="italics">zou aantrekken</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– Desnoods<c type="kk">/</c> al had ik geen meester<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik alleen ook die cursus van antiek kunnen doormaken door in de Louvre te gaan teekenen of zoo<c type="kp">_</c>– En dus als het moest zou ik dat doen – ofschoon veel liever ik correctie had – zoolang het geen OPZETTELIJK <hi rend="italics">treiteren</hi> wordt<c type="kk">/</c> die correctie zonder dat men er andere aanleiding toe geeft dan een zekere eigenaardigheid in zijn manier van werken te hebben die anders is dan de anderen<c type="kp">_</c>– Als hij me weer begint zal ik hardop in de klas zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> je veux bien faire mecaniquement tout ce que vous me direz de faire parce que j’y tiens à vous rendre ce qui vous revient<c type="kk">/</c> à la rigueur<c type="kk">/</c> si vous y tenez<c type="kk">/</c> mais – 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>pour ce qui est de me mécaniser comme vous mécanisez les autres<c type="kk">/</c> cela n’a, je vous assure, pas la moindre prise sur moi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vous avez du reste commencé à me dire tout autre chose c’est à dire que vous m’avez dit: prenez vous y comme vous voudrez<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">De kwestie waarom ik antiek teeken – <hi rend="italics">ne pas prendre par le contour mais prendre</hi> <hi rend="italics">par les milieux</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/><hi rend="italics"> </hi>– ik heb ’t nog niet maar ik voel het meer en meer en – ik ga er zeker op door<c type="kk">/</c> het is te interessant<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Ik wou wel dat wij zamen eens eenige dagen in de Louvre waren en het er eens over hebben konden. Ik geloof dat het U interesseeren zou<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Ik heb U gestuurd van morgen <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi><c type="kk">/</c> vooral ook <hi rend="italics">om de voorrede</hi> die U zeker treffen zal<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">En – ik wou wel dat aan ’t eind van ons leven wij ook ergens zamen konden wandelen en – terugziende zeggen – wij hebben <hi rend="italics">dit</hi> gedaan – et <hi rend="italics">d’un</hi>; <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> – et <hi rend="italics">de deux</hi>; <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> – et <hi rend="italics">de trois</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En als we willen en durven – zal er dan iets te bepraten zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Wij kunnen twee dingen zoeken – iets goeds zelf te maken – het geen we van anderen mooi vinden verzamelen en er mee handelen<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>Maar <hi rend="italics">beiden</hi> moeten we wat <hi rend="italics">sterker leven</hi> en een stap om sterker te worden is mischien juist dat zich vereenigen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Laat ik nu echter nog over een teere kwestie mogen spreken – als ik U onaangename dingen heb gezegd juist ook over onze opvoeding en ons t’huis<c type="kk">/</c> is zulks geweest omdat voor het elkaar vinden en begrijpen in zaken en in zamenwerken wij op een terrein ons bevinden waar critiek zijn <hi rend="italics">moet</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Nu kan ik mij goed begrijpen dat men hartstogtelijk van iets of iemand houde waar men niets aan doen <hi rend="italics">kan</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">Goed – daar kom ik niet in maar wel in zoover het fataal scheiding tusschen ons kon maken waar vereeniging noodig is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.24" n="24">En onze opvoeding &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> – zullen niet blijken zoo goed te zijn dat wij er veel illusies over zullen houden – ziedaar – en wij waren misschien met een andere opvoeding gelukkiger geweest<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar als wij ons houden aan het positieve van te willen produceeren en <hi rend="italics">iets zijn</hi><c type="kk">/</c> dan kunnen wij zonder ons driftig te maken faits accomplis als zoodanig bepraten waar ’t on<c type="shy">-</c>vermijdelijk is en soms of de Goupils of de familie wel eens mogt raken of direct aangaan<c type="kp">_</c>– En overigens zijn die kwesties entre nous voor ’t verstaan der toestanden en niet uit rancune<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.25" n="25">Maar als wij iets ondernemen zal het voor beiden van ons geen onverschillige zaak zijn ons te versterken wat de gezondheid betreft omdat wij tijd van leven noodig hebben – een jaar of 25 of 30 van aanhoudend werken<c type="kp">_</c> Er is zoo veel interessants in den tijd van tegenwoordig als men denkt hoezeer het mogelijk is dat wij ’t begin van ’t eind van een maatschappij misschien nog wel zien zullen<c type="kp">_</c> En even als er in den herfst of in een zonsondergang een oneindige poezij ligt en er dan zoo zeer ziel en mysterieus streven in de natuur is<c type="kk">/</c> zoo ook nu. En wat de kunst betreft – decadence<c type="kk">/</c> als men wil<c type="kk">/</c> na de Delacroix<c type="kk">/</c> Corots<c type="kk">/</c> Millets<c type="kk">/</c> Duprés<c type="kk">/</c> Troyons<c type="kk">/</c> Bretons<c type="kk">/</c> Rousseaux<c type="kk">/</c> Daubignys – que soit – maar een decadence zóó vol van charme – dat waarlijk er nog enorm<c type="kk">/</c> enorm veel moois te wachten is en dagelijks gemaakt wordt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.26" n="26">Ik ben verbazend verlangend naar de Louvre<c type="kk">/</c> Luxembourg enz<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> waar alles mij zoo nieuw zal zijn.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.27" n="27">Jammer zal ik ’t mijn leven lang blijven vinden dat ik de cent chefs d’oeuvre<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> de expositie Delacroix<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en de expositie Meissonier<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> niet heb gezien<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar er is nog veel aan te doen.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.28" n="28">Het is waar dat ik<c type="kk">/</c> hier b.v. te gaauw vooruit willende<c type="kk">/</c> juist misschien minder vorderde<c type="kk">/</c> maar wat wilt gij<c type="kk">/</c> mijn gezondheid zit er ook achter en als ik die terug krijg zoo als ik hoop dan zal het minder tevergeefs zijn dat ik moeite doe.–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.29" n="29">Ik heb het immers wel dat als men er permissie voor vraagt<c type="kk">/</c> men antiek mag gaan teekenen in de Louvre<c type="kk">/</c> ook al is men niet op de Ecole des Beaux Arts<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.30" n="30">Het zou me niet verwonderen dat een maal het idee van zamenwonen er zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> gij het meer en meer zonderling zult gaan vinden dat wij zoo verbazend weinig zamen zijn geweest<c type="kk">/</c> als ge wilt – volle 10 jaar lang<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.31" n="31">Enfin laat dat nu aan een eind zijn en niet weer beginnen<c type="kk">/</c> hoop ik van harte<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.32" n="32">Hetgeen gij zegt over de woning is misschien wel wat duur<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> al moest het wat minder<c type="kk">/</c> ware mij net zoo lief<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.33" n="33">Ik ben nieuwsgierig hoe het mij zou gaan<c type="kk">/</c> die eenige maanden te Nuenen<c type="kp">_</c> Daar ik er eenige meubels heb<c type="kk">/</c> daar verder het er mooi is en ik de streek wat ken<c type="kk">/</c> kon ik er een pied à terre houden<c type="kk">/</c> desnoods in een herberg waar ik die meubels deponeerde<c type="kk">/</c> ware wel goed<c type="kk">/</c> daar zij anders weg zijn en – het kan nog zoo te pas komen<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.34" n="34">Er is soms ’t meest te doen door terug te komen op oude plekken<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.35" n="35">Ik moet deze eindigen daar ik nog naar de club ga<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.36" n="36">Blijf er over denken hoe wij ’t best handelen<c type="kp">_</c> Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.37" n="37">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.38" n="38">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve received your letter and 25 francs enclosed and I thank you very much for both. I’m really glad that you like my plan to come to Paris. I believe it will help me make progress and at the same time that, if I didn’t go, I might easily get into a mess, keep moving around in the same circle too much, persist in the same mistakes. Furthermore, as for you, I don’t think that coming home to a studio would do you any harm. For the rest, I have to tell you the same about me as you write about yourself — <hi rend="italics">I’ll disappoint you</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And even so, this is the way to combine forces. And even so, much greater understanding of each other can follow from it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Now what shall I tell you about my health? I still believe that I have a chance of avoiding being really ill; all the same, I’ll need time to get better. I also still have two more teeth to be filled, then my upper jaw, which was most affected, will be all right again. I still have to pay 10 francs for that, and then another 40 francs to get the bottom half right too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Some years of those 10 years that I appear to have spent in prison will disappear as a result. Because bad teeth, which one so seldom sees any more as it’s so easy to get them put right, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> since bad teeth give a physiognomy a sort of sunken look.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">And then — even eating the same things, one can naturally digest better when one can chew properly, and so my stomach will have a chance to recover.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I really do notice that I’ve been at a very low ebb, though — and as you wrote yourself, all sorts of things that are even worse could arise out of neglecting it. However, we’ll see that we get it put right.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I haven’t worked for a few days, gone to bed early a couple of nights (otherwise it was usually 1 or 2 o’clock because of drawing at the club). And I feel that it’s calming me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’ve had a note from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>, who writes that they’re going to start packing in March.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Further, since you say you’ll have to pay rent until the end of June — well then, perhaps it would be best after all if I were to return to Nuenen, starting in March, only — if I encountered opposition and scenes like I got before I left, I would be wasting my time there and so, even if it were only just for those few months, I’d make a change anyhow, since I want to have some new things from the country ready to bring to Paris with me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1351">Siberdt</rs>, the teacher of the antique, who spoke to me at first as I told you, definitely <hi rend="italics">tried </hi>to pick a quarrel 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> with me today, perhaps with a view to getting rid of me. Which didn’t work inasmuch as I said — Why are you trying to pick a quarrel with me? I have no wish to quarrel, and in any case I have absolutely no desire to contradict you, but you deliberately try to pick a quarrel with me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">He evidently hadn’t expected that and couldn’t say much to refute it this time, but — next time, of course, he’ll be able to start something.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The issue behind it is that the fellows in the class are talking about things in my work among themselves, and I’ve said, not to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1351">Siberdt</rs> but outside the class to some of the fellows, that their drawings were completely wrong.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Bear in mind that if I go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs> and run into trouble sooner or later either with the master or the pupils, <hi rend="italics">I wouldn’t let it worry me</hi>. If need be, even if I didn’t have a master, I could also go through the antique course by going to draw in the Louvre or somewhere. And so I’d do that if I had to — although I’d far rather have correction — as long as it doesn’t become DELIBERATE <hi rend="italics">provocation</hi>; that correction without one giving any cause other than a certain singularity in one’s manner of working which is different from the others. If he starts on me again, I’ll say out loud in the class, I’m happy to do mechanically everything that you tell me to do, because I’m determined to pay you back what is your due, if need be, if you insist on it, but — 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> as far as mechanizing me as you mechanize the others is concerned, that has not, I assure you, the slightest hold over me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Besides, you started by telling me something quite different, that’s to say, you told me: tackle it as you wish.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">The reason why I’m drawing plaster casts — <hi rend="italics">not to start from the outline, but to start from the centres</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/>— I haven’t got it yet, but I feel it more and more and — I’ll certainly carry on with it, it’s too interesting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I wish that we could spend a few days together in the Louvre and could just talk about it. I believe it would interest you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">This morning I sent you <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi>, mainly <hi rend="italics">for the preface</hi>, which will certainly strike you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">And — I wish that at the end of our lives we could also walk somewhere together and — looking back, say — we’ve done <hi rend="italics">this</hi> — and that’s <hi rend="italics">one</hi>; and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> — and that’s <hi rend="italics">two</hi>; and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> — and that’s <hi rend="italics">three</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And if we want to and dare to — will there be anything to talk about then?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">We can try two things — making something good ourselves — collecting things by other people that we think are good, and dealing in them. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> But we must <hi rend="italics">both</hi> <hi rend="italics">live</hi> rather more <hi rend="italics">robustly</hi>, and perhaps combining forces is a step towards becoming more robust.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">But now allow me to touch on a delicate matter — if I’ve said unpleasant things to you, specifically about our upbringing and our home, this has been because we’re in an area where being critical is <hi rend="italics">essential </hi>in order for us to get along with and understand each other and cooperate in business.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Now I can well understand that one can passionately love something or someone that one <hi rend="italics">can’t</hi> do anything about.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Very well — I won’t go into that except in so far as it might make a fatal separation between us where reconciliation is needed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And our upbringing &amp;c. — won’t prove to be so good that we’ll retain many illusions about it — there you are — and we might perhaps have been happier with a different upbringing. But if we stick to the positive idea of wanting to produce and <hi rend="italics">to be something</hi>, then we’ll be able, without getting angry, to discuss <hi rend="italics">faits accomplis</hi> as such when it’s unavoidable and might perhaps touch on or directly concern the Goupils or the family. And for the rest, these issues between us are for the understanding of the situation and not out of rancour. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">But if we undertake something it won’t be a matter of indifference to either of us to improve our health, because we need time alive — some 25 or 30 years of working constantly. There’s so much of interest in the present age when one thinks how very possible it is that we may well yet see the beginning of the end of a society. And just as there is infinite poetry in the autumn or in a sunset, and then there’s so much soul and mysterious endeavour in nature, so it is now. And as for art — decline, if you will, after the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs>s, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>s, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Dupré</rs>s, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1389">Troyon</rs>s, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Breton</rs>s, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1332">Rousseau</rs>x, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>s — very well — but a decline so full of charm — that there truly is still an immense, immense amount of good things to come, and they’re being made every day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I’m longing dreadfully for the Louvre, Luxembourg etc., where everything will be so new to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">For the rest of my life I’ll regret that I didn’t see the Cent chefs d’oeuvre,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> exhibition<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs> exhibition.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> But there will still be plenty of opportunities to catch up. It’s true, for instance, that wanting to progress too quickly here, I may actually have progressed less, but what would you? My health is also behind it, and if I regain that as I hope to do, then my taking pains will have been less in vain. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">After all, I believe that if one asks permission, one may draw plaster casts in the Louvre, even if one isn’t at L’Ecole des Beaux-Arts.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">It wouldn’t surprise me if, once the idea of living together takes hold, you’ll find it odder and odder that we’ve been together so surprisingly little, if you will — for fully 10 years.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Anyway, I most certainly hope that this will be the end of it, and that it won’t begin again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">What you say about the apartment is perhaps really rather expensive. I mean, I’d be just as happy if it weren’t quite as good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">I’m curious as to how those few months in Nuenen will be for me. Since I have some furniture there, since it’s beautiful there, too, and I know the district a little, it might be a good thing for me to keep a pied-à-terre there, if need be in an inn where I could leave that furniture, since otherwise it will be lost — and it could still come in very useful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">There’s sometimes the most to do by returning to old places. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">I must finish this now, since I’m going to the club.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Keep thinking about what we can best do. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Between <ref target="let558.xml">letter 558</ref> of about 4 February and <ref target="let563.xml">letter 563</ref> of Tuesday, 16 or Wednesday, 17 February Vincent wrote Theo a further four letters (<ref target="let559.xml">559</ref>-<ref target="let562.xml">562</ref>). It is not possible to date them precisely, but the sequence has been established. There are three points of reference for this: the requests for money, the sending of the novel <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi> and the progress of the plans to settle in Paris.</p>
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">In <ref target="let558.xml">558</ref> Vincent asks Theo if he could send something extra; in <ref target="let559.xml">559</ref> he thanks him for the 25 francs he has received. He is also pleased that Theo has evidently said that he can definitely come to Paris, and he sends Theo the novel <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi>. <ref target="let560.xml">Letter 560</ref> is a direct continuation of this letter: Vincent says he has to write ‘one more time’, discusses various possibilities for living in Paris, and explains why he wanted Theo to read <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi>. He then decides that he does not want to make a detour and stay in Nuenen on the way and urges Theo – in <ref target="let561.xml">letter 561</ref> – to let him go to Paris earlier, at once if needs be; this places <ref target="let561.xml">561</ref> after <ref target="let560.xml">560</ref>. In <ref target="let562.xml">letter 562</ref>, written on a Sunday, Van Gogh says ‘I write to you often these days and often the same’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>), and asks Theo if he can send something more ‘this month’, even if it is only five francs; he repeats this request in <ref target="let564.xml">letter 564</ref> of about 18 February. The Sunday in question must therefore have been the fourteenth. This order also tallies with the question as to whether Theo has meanwhile read the preface to <hi rend="italics">Chérie</hi>. The wording ‘that one month’ (<ref target="let562.xml#l-65">letter 562, l. 65</ref>) refers back to the month of March mentioned in <ref target="let561.xml">letter 561</ref> (<ref target="let561.xml#l-36">ll. 36-37</ref>).</p>
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">We have spaced the four letters that followed in quick succession at intervals of two and three days over the intervening 12 days, and allocated them the dates of about Saturday, 6, about Tuesday, 9, about Thursday, 11 and Sunday, 14 February 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plan to move to Paris <ref target="let555.xml">(555)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh has problems with his teeth <ref target="let557.xml">(557)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plan to study with Cormon <ref target="let556.xml">(556)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘beschadigd, gehavend’ (damaged, battered).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: Die ik uiterlijk lijk te hebben doorgemaakt’ (that I appear to have suffered).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Means: ‘aangezien’ (as, since).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For the impending move from Nuenen to Breda, which was to take place at the end of March.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Gigoux</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let494.xml#n-2">See letter 494, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>At the end of the preface to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_422">Chérie</ref></hi>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617">Edmond de Goncourt</rs> writes about a walk he took with his brother some months before <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_618">Jules</rs>’s death, during which Jules reflected on their achievements. Van Gogh quotes the closing words of the following three paragraphs:</p>

<p>‘All of a sudden my brother stopped dead and said to me:</p>

<p rend="indent">“It doesn’t matter, do you see, they can deny us all they like… one day it will have to be acknowledged that we created GERMINIE LACERTEUX… and that ‘Germinie Lacerteux’ is the original book that served as the model for everything that has been produced since us, under the name of realism, naturalism, etc. And that’s one!</p>

<p rend="indent">Now through writing, through talk, through purchases… who has imposed on the generation of mahogany chests of drawers the taste for eighteenth-century art and furniture?… Where is he who will dare to say it is not us? And that’s two! </p>

<p rend="indent">And what about that description of a Paris salon furnished with japonaiseries, published in our first novel, in our novel EN 18.., that appeared in 1851 … yes, in 1851 …– let them show me people with a taste for Japanese things in those days…– and our acquisitions during those years of bronzes and lacquerware from Mallinet and a little later from Mrs Desoye… and our discovery in 1860, at the Porte Chinoise, of the first Japanese album known in Paris… known at least to the world of men of letters and painters… and the pages devoted to Japanese things in MANETTE SALOMON, in IDÉES ET SENSATIONS… do they not make us the first propagators of that art… of that art, which, without doubt, is revolutionizing the perspective of western peoples? And that’s three!</p>

<p rend="indent">Now the search for truth in literature, the revival of eighteenth-century art, the triumph of Japonism: these are, do you know, – he added after a silence, and with an awakening of intelligent life in his eye, – these are the three great literary and artistic movements of the second half of the nineteenth century… and we will have led them, these three movements… us, poor unknown us. Well! when you have done that… it will be really difficult not to be someone in the future.”</p>

<p rend="indent">And it’s true, the dying man taking a walk along the avenue of the Bois de Boulogne could perhaps be right.’</p>

<p>(Tout à coup brusquement mon frère s’arrêta, et me dit:</p>

<p rend="indent">“Ça ne fait rien, vois-tu, on nous niera tant qu’on voudra... il faudra bien reconnaître un jour que nous avons fait GERMINIE LACERTEUX... et que ‘Germinie Lacerteux’ est le livre-type qui a servi de modèle à tout ce qui a été fabriqué depuis nous, sous le nom de réalisme, naturalisme, etc. Et d’un!</p>

<p rend="indent">Maintenant par les écrits, par la parole, par les achats... qu’est-ce qui a imposé à la génération aux commodes d’acajou, le goût de l’art et du mobilier du XVIIIe siècle?... Où est celui qui osera dire que ce n’est pas nous? Et de deux!</p>

<p rend="indent">Enfin cette description d’un salon parisien meublé de japonaiseries, publiée dans notre premier roman, dans notre roman d’EN 18.., paru en 1851 ... oui, en 1851 ... – qu’on me montre les japonisants de ce temps-là... – et nos acquisitions de bronzes et de laques de ces années chez Mallinet et un peu plus tard chez Mme Desoye... et la découverte en 1860, à la Porte Chinoise, du premier album japonais connu à Paris... connu au moins du monde des littérateurs et des peintres... et les pages consacrées aux choses du Japon dans MANETTE SALOMON, dans IDÉES ET SENSATIONS... ne font-ils pas de nous les premiers propagateurs de cet art... de cet art en train, sans qu’on s’en doute, de révolutionner l’optique des peuples occidentaux? Et de trois!</p>

<p rend="indent">Or la recherche du vrai en littérature, la résurrection de l’art du XVIIIe siècle, la victoire du japonisme: ce sont, sais-tu, – ajouta-t-il après un silence, et avec un réveil de la vie intelligente dans l’oeil, – ce sont les trois grands mouvements littéraires et artistiques de la seconde moitié du XIXe siècle... et nous les aurons menés, ces trois mouvements... nous, pauvres obscurs. Eh bien! quand on a fait cela... c’est vraiment difficile de n’être pas quelqu’un dans l’avenir.”</p>

<p rend="indent">Et, ma foi, le promeneur mourant de l’allée du Bois de Boulogne pourrait peut-être avoir raison.) See Goncourt 1884, pp. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xiv</hi>-<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xvi</hi>. Cf. for this preface also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let550.xml">letters 550</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let551.xml">551</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This was one of the annual ‘Expositions Internationales’ mounted by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_552">Georges Petit</rs> in 8 rue de Sèze since 1882. Vincent knew about the one in 1883 from what Theo had told him. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let358.xml#n-1">See letter 358, n. 1.</ref></p>

<p rend="indent">On 10 May 1884 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> wrote to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> about this ‘jewel of an exhibition’: ‘A small number of masterpieces by Bastien-Lepage, Cazin, Carolus-Duran, Stevens, Jan van Beers, Jean Béraud and a couple of Spanish painters have been brought together. I find it impossible to describe to you the joy I experienced when looking at those paintings’ (FR b1787).</p>

<p rend="indent">‘The exhibitors reflected the cosmopolitanism which had developed in the Paris art world ... It attracted a public of an equally international scope. Eventually scheduled regularly in May, it was anticipated and attended by fashionable society as well as those with a serious interest in the latest names and trends in art, and the newest output by painters with established reputations’, wrote Roger Terry Dunn, The Monet-Rodin exhibition at the Galerie Georges Petit in 1889. Diss. Northwestern University 1979, pp. 10-11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exposition Eugène Delacroix au profit de la souscription destinée à éléver à Paris un monument sa mémoire</hi> at the Ecole nationale des Beaux-Arts in Paris 1885. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let461.xml#n-2">See letter 461, n. 2.</ref> Theo went to the exhibition with<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282"> Andries Bonger</rs>, who wrote enthusiastically to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> on 4 April 1885: ‘He is the most sympathetic person I have met in Paris. He is a charming fellow to get along with. One cannot conceive of more entertaining company than his. The exhibition of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eug. Delacroix</rs>’s paintings is an inexhaustible subject of discussion. They are so good that we can never say enough about them. We are going there again tomorrow morning’ (FR b1812).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exposition Meissonier. 24 Mai- 24 Julliet 1884. Au profit de l’oeuvre de l’hospitalité de nuit</hi>. Paris, Galerie Georges Petit.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The fact that people who were not students were allowed into the Louvre to draw – as well as professional copyists, women were also admitted – emerges in Theodore Reff, ‘Copyists in the Louvre, 1850-1870’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Art Bulletin</hi> 46-4 (1964), pp. 552-559 and Paul Duro, ‘Copyists in the Louvre in the middle decades of the nineteenth century’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 130 (1988), no. 1431 (April), pp. 249-254. Duro observes: ‘From early in the century a series of regulations defined, clarified and bureaucratized the practice of copying’, but all the same the regulations were ‘surprisingly liberal’, with a distinction between ‘those who copied for instruction and those who copied for profit’ (p. 249).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    