<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Vincent van Gogh and Andries Bonger to Theo van Gogh. Paris, on or about Wednesday, 18 August 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let568"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b500 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>568</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>460</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>571</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-08-18">on or about Wednesday, 18 August 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0500" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0500" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000676_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Van morgen ontvingen wij<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Uw schrijven<c type="kp">_</c> En vinden dat het al heel mooi is dat ge de zaak hebt geentameerd – en het ijs gebroken in zoover ge er met de Hollandsche heeren over gesproken hebt &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">En mijn “elle sera à la vapeur” zie ik nog niet in dat onjuist is<c type="kk">/</c> daar ik zelf dat à la vapeur zijn in ’t verschiet zie en op staanden voet slechts in zoover dat onze energie à la vapeur moet wezen. In ’t verschiet zie ik ’t <hi rend="italics">wel</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– En wat op staanden voet aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> ge herinnert U nog dat ik U zeide: Vang desnoods deze keer bot<c type="kk">/</c> maar dan is er vast eens over gesproken – en dan moet er een tweeden togt naar Holland van Bonger en U zamen overheen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Voorloopig is er alle reden om met vader Pangloss te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> tout est pour le mieux dans le meilleur des mondes<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Maar nu, kerel<c type="kk">/</c> de oplossing van het vraagstuk S<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> die ge in Uw brief van heden geeft<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. “Zij er uit of ik er uit”<c type="kk">/</c> zou heel kort<c type="kk">/</c> bondig en afdoend wezen – als het uitvoerbaar was.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Doch gij zult op moeielijkheden stuiten die Bonger en ik dezer dagen onder de oogen hadden en waar wij ons uiterste best op doen om er licht in te krijgen. Die moeielijkheden zijn anders dan ge denkt maar het is nu ’t moment niet in details te treden; wij zullen U er alles van vertellen als ge terugkomt<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Dat gij niet bij S<c type="kp">_</c> en S<c type="kp">_</c> niet bij U hoort is dunkt me vast en zeker. en dat het dus uitgemaakt moet worden ook – maar hoe?– Het is goed dat gij U er op voor<c type="shy">-</c>bereid houdt dat de zaak misschien niet <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> afgemaakt worden op de door U voorgestelde wijze<c type="kk">/</c> daar door haar te brusqueeren ge haar lijnregt of tot zelfmoord zoudt kunnen brengen of haar gek maken<c type="kk">/</c> waarvan de terugwerking op uw zelf natuurlijk triest zou zijn en U voor altijd zou kunnen knakken<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Geen ongelukken dus s.v.p. Nu heb ik tegen Bonger ook gezegd wat ik tot U zeide<c type="kk">/</c> dat ge haar aan een ander moest zien over te doen<c type="kk">/</c> en tegen Bonger heb ik ten volle gezegd hoe ik het voelde – dat een arrangement à l’amiable dat vrij wel voor de hand ligt<c type="kk">/</c> is dat ge haar overdoet aan mij. Zooveel is zeker<c type="kk">/</c> indien zoowel gij als zijzelve er in berusten wildet dan ben ik bereid S<c type="kp">_</c> van U over te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> liefst echter <hi rend="italics">zonder</hi> haar te trouwen doch als ’t beter uitkomt dan <hi rend="italics">zelfs met</hi> een mariage de raison. Ik schrijf U dit kortaf opdat gij vóór Uw terugkomst nog tijd zoudt hebben er eens over te denken<c type="kp">_</c> Daar zij zoodoende het huishouden zou kunnen doen en daar zij zich zelf bedruipt door haar werk<c type="kk">/</c> ware ’t voor U eer eene bezuiniging dan andersom<c type="kp">_</c> Lucie<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> heeft haar congé<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb haar gezegd dat gij er niet mede zoudt doorgaan omdat het te duur uitkwam<c type="kk">/</c> maar haar aangehouden tot Uw terugkomst omdat gij dan kunt beslissen hoe ’t huishouden wezen zal<c type="kk">/</c> en ingeval die beslissing niet den eersten besten dag genomen kan worden is ’t welligt wenschelijk <hi rend="italics">tot er beslist is met S<c type="kp">_</c></hi> het huishouden op den zelfden voet te laten wat Lucie betreft.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Kondt gij zelf in dit arrangement treden dan zie ik als eerste gevolg voor U er in dat gij U geheel vrij man zoudt voelen en uw eigen engagement<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> à la vapeur zou gaan.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Goeden moed en bedaardheid<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Wat het werk betreft<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een pendant voor die bouquet die ge bij U hebt<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> verder een tak witte lelies – wit<c type="kk">/</c> rose<c type="kk">/</c> groen – tegen zwart<c type="kk">/</c> in den geest van een zwart japansch verlakt<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> met parelmoer ingelegd<c type="kk">/</c> die ge kent – dan een tak oranje tijgerlelies tegen blaauw fond<c type="kk">/</c> dan een bouquet daliahs<c type="kk">/</c> violet tegen geel fond<c type="kk">/</c> en Roode glaïeuls in een blaauwen vaas tegen licht geel.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Bonger is bezig te lezen au Bonheur des dames<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en ik heb gelezen Bel ami van Guy de Maupassant<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Weet ge dat en Bonger en S. hier slapen en het zijn curieuse dagen<c type="kk">/</c> soms zijn we erg<c type="kk">/</c> erg bang voor haar en soms zijn we almagtig vrolijk en opgewekt. Maar S<c type="kp">_</c> is geducht gederangeerd. en het is nog lang niet over.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Dat het echter beslist <hi rend="italics">af</hi> is tusschen U en haar zult ge weerkeerig pas voelen als ge elkaar terug ziet en ge hoeft dus niet te vreezen ge er weer aan vast raakt. Maar gij moet veel met haar praten en haar zien te bezorgen. Denk er over na in den tusschentijd van nu en dat ge weer terugkomt<c type="kk">/</c> aux grands maux les grands remèdes.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Bonger schrijft hier zeker bij<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij hij heden U van zijn kantoor uit schrijft.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Groeten thuis<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">De ruil tegen 2 aquarellen Isabey zou ik heel goed vinden<c type="kk">/</c> vooral indien het figuren van Isabey zijn<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Zie er de pendant die ik hier heb bij te ruilen en iets anders er bij te krijgen. Zeg eens<c type="kk">/</c> is het onmogelijk de <hi rend="italics">Otto Weber</hi> van Prinsenh<c type="kp">_</c> te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> die mooie herfst<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> ik zou daarvoor hun een <hi rend="italics">serie</hi> maken <hi rend="italics">van 4</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– We hebben meer aan schilderijen dan aan teekeningen. maar doe zoo als het uitkomt<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

    
<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18"><hi rend="italics">[Continued by Andries Bonger]</hi></p>


<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">    	De fond van V’s redeneering is ook mijne over<c type="shy">-</c>tuiging. De kwestie is S. de oogen te openen. 
    	Ze is hoegenaamd niet verliefd op je, maar 
    	’t is alsof je haar behekst hebt.– Ze is zedelijk zwaar 
    	ziek.– Het spreekt dat we haar, in dien toestand, 
    	niet aan haar lot hebben kunnen overlaten.– 
    	We zijn integendeel zoo hartelijk mogelijk voor 
    	haar geweest.– Zoo we ’t niet gedaan hadden zou 
    	ze waanzinnig geworden zijn.– Hetgeen me doet 
    	hoopen op haar genezing is hetgeen ze me 
    	gisteren avond zei: Que je suis bête de ne pouvoir 
    	me faire un raisonnement. Ze schijnt dus wel 
    	te gevoelen waaraan ’t hapert.– De groote 
    	moeielijkheid is haar koppigheid, waartegen we 
    <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
    	ons reeds verscheidene malen het hoofd gestoten 
    	hebben.– Met hardheid is niets aan te vangen.– Het is 
    	uiterlijk moeielijk voorshands een plan te maken, 
    	(dat van Vincent is onuitvoerbaar; dunkt me) maar 
    	ik hoop dat je hiervan doordrongen bent dat je 
    	haar verkeerd hebt aangepakt; de verhouding 
    	van het laatste jaar heeft tot niets geleid dan 
    	haar geheel van de wijs te helpen. Het zou misschien
    	nog veel beter geweest zijn geheel met elkaâr te 
    	leven: dan zou ze zelf wel ingezien hebben, dat 
    	je volstrekt niet bij elkaâr pasten.– Wanneer ze 
    	een maand lang met iemand anders leven kon, 
    	die haar zinnen wist te boeien, haar verzorgde (want 
    	ze heeft veel zorg noodig) en haar gezondheid weêr 
    	opfleurde, zou je vergeten zijn.– Haar toestand 
    	heeft veel van de overspanning van de meeste 
    	meisjes in Holland.– Het zal niet minder 
    	moeielijk zijn S. van de hare te overtuigen, dan 
    	rust te brengen in de gemoederen daarginds.–
    </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Ik vermoed dat je mijn zuster Jo en Annie 
    	niet getroffen zult hebben; beiden zijn, meen ik, 
    	uit de stad.–<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> We verlangen beiden te weten 
    	hoe de zaken te Amsterdam staan.–
</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Veel genoegen deed ’t me te hooren dat V. thans 
    	erkend wordt.– Wat een voldoening voor het vaste 
    	vertrouwen dat je in hem gehad hebt! Hij heeft 
    	een paar heele mooie dingen gemaakt; die op 
    	gelen fond doen heel goed. Het ensemble van de 
    	bloemenstukken is heel vroolijk en kleurrijk; maar 
    	sommige zijn plat, waar van ik hem maar niet 
    	overtuigen kan.– Hij antwoordt me aldoor: maar 
    	ik heb er dat en dat kleurenkontrast in willen brengen. 
    	Comme si je ne m’en fichais pas de ce qu’il a <hi rend="italics">voulu</hi> 
    	faire! Schrijf ons wanneer je terug komt. Tracht te komen 
    	met vernieuwde lichaamskrachten en een klaren geest en een 
    	vasten wil. Ze zijn alle drie noodig. De toestand is anders volstrekt 
    	niet hopeloos, maar wel zorgelijk. Spijker gaat maar heel langzaam 
    	vooruit.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Groet je familie van me en geloof me van harte 
</p>
    <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">    je vrind</p>
    
<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">    Bonger</p>

    
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">We<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> received your letter this morning. And think that it’s very good that you’ve already raised the matter — and broken the ice in so far as you’ve spoken to the Dutch gentlemen about it &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And I don’t yet see that my ‘it’ll go full steam ahead’ is wrong, since I myself can see that full steam ahead is in prospect and right now only in so far as our energy must be at full steam ahead. I <hi rend="italics">do</hi> see it in prospect. And as to right now, you still remember that I said to you: come away empty-handed this time if need be, but then at least it has been discussed – and then there will have to be a second trip to Holland by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> and you together.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">For the time being there’s every reason to say, with <hi rend="italics">père</hi> Pangloss, all is for the best in the best of possible worlds.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> But now, old chap, the solution to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S.</rs> question<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> that you give in your letter of today, that’s to say ‘Either she goes or I go’, would be very short, sweet and conclusive — if it were practicable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">But you’ll run up against difficulties that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> and I have been facing these last few days, and which we’re doing our utmost best to shed light on. These difficulties are different from what you think, but now isn’t the time to go into details: we’ll tell you all about it when you get back.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">That you don’t belong with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S.</rs> nor S. with you is absolutely certain, it seems to me. And that it has to be finished, too — but how? It’s a good thing for you to be prepared that the affair perhaps <hi rend="italics">cannot</hi> be ended in the way you suggest, because by rushing her you could simply either provoke her to suicide or send her mad, and the effect of that on you would be tragic, of course, and could shatter you for ever. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">So no accidents please. Now I’ve also told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> what I told you, that you’ll have to pass her on to someone else, and I told Bonger at length how I saw it – that an amicable arrangement which is virtually self-evident is that you pass her on to me. This much is certain, if both you and she were willing to accept it, then I’m prepared to take <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S.</rs> over from you, preferably, though, <hi rend="italics">without</hi> marrying her, but if it works out better then <hi rend="italics">even with</hi> a marriage of convenience. I’m writing this to you in a few words so that you’d still have time to think about it before your return. Since this way she could do the housekeeping, and since she can support herself by her work, it would be an economy for you rather than the other way round. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_492">Lucie</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> has been given notice; I told her that you wouldn’t go on with it because it worked out too expensive, but kept her on until your return because you can then decide how the housekeeping will be, and in the event that this decision can’t be taken straightaway it’s probably advisable to keep the housekeeping on the same footing as regards Lucie <hi rend="italics">until something is decided with S</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">If you could enter into this arrangement yourself, then I see as the first consequence for you that you would feel yourself an entirely free man and your own engagement<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> would go full steam ahead.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Courage and composure.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">As regards the work, I have a pendant for that bouquet that you have with you,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and also a branch of white lilies — white, pink, green — against black, in the spirit of black Japanese lacquer<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> inlaid with mother-of-pearl that you know — then a branch of orange tiger lilies on a blue ground, then a bouquet of dahlias, violet on a yellow ground, and red gladioli in a blue vase on light yellow.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> is reading Au bonheur des dames<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and I’ve read Bel-ami by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Do you know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S. </rs>are sleeping here, and these are strange days, sometimes we’re very, very afraid of her, and sometimes we’re almighty merry and cheerful. But S. is terribly deranged, and it’s not over by a long shot.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"> Both of you will only feel that it’s finally <hi rend="italics">finished</hi> between you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">her</rs> when you see each other again, and so you don’t have to fear that you’ll get caught again. But you’ll have to talk to her a lot and try to get her settled. Think about it in the meantime between now and when you come back; serious remedies for serious ills.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> will certainly add something to this, unless he writes to you today from his office.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Regards to everyone at home, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’d be very pleased with the exchange for 2 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1104">Isabey</rs> watercolours, particularly if they’re figures by Isabey.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> See if you can exchange the pendant I have here as well and get something else as well. Tell me, is it impossible to get the <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1423">Otto Weber</rs></hi> from Princenhage, that fine autumn?<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> For that I would make a <hi rend="italics">series of 4</hi> for them. Paintings are more use to us than drawings, but do what’s convenient.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><hi rend="italics">[Continued by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs>]</hi></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’m also convinced of the basis of V.’s reasoning. The issue is to open <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S</rs>.’s eyes. She’s not in love with you at all, but it’s as if you’ve bewitched her. Morally she is seriously sick. It is obvious that we can’t abandon her to her fate in that condition. On the contrary, we’ve been as cordial towards her as possible. If we hadn’t done that she would have gone mad. What makes me hope for her recovery is what she said to me yesterday evening: “How stupid of me that I can’t think straight.” So she does seem to realize where it has gone wrong. The great difficulty is her stubbornness, and we’ve 
    <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
    run up against that several times. Treating her harshly doesn’t work. It’s extremely difficult to come up with a plan in advance (Vincent’s is unworkable, in my opinion), but I hope that you realize from this that you’ve dealt with her the wrong way. The relationship of the past year has done nothing but make her lose her head. It would perhaps have been far better if you had lived together completely, then she would have seen for herself that you absolutely did not belong together. If she could live with someone else for a month who succeeded in fascinating her, who took care of her (for she needs a lot of care) and revived her health, you would be forgotten. Her condition is a lot like the nervous exhaustion of most girls in Holland. It will be no less difficult to convince S. of hers than to calm the emotions over there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I suspect that you won’t have seen my sister <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Annie</rs>; I think both of them are out of town.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> We both long to know how matters stand in Amsterdam.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I was very pleased to hear that V. is now getting recognition. What repayment for the steadfast faith that you’ve had in him! He has made a few very beautiful things; the ones on a yellow ground look very good. The ensemble of flower pieces is very gay and colourful; some, though, are flat, but I just can’t persuade him of that. He keeps replying: but I wanted to get this or that colour contrast into it. As if I gave a damn what he <hi rend="italics">wanted</hi> to do! Write to tell us when you’re coming back. Try to come with renewed vitality and a clear mind and a steadfast will. All three are necessary. The situation otherwise isn’t hopeless at all, but it is worrying. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_753">Spijker</rs> is only very slowly getting better.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> My regards to your family, and believe me wholeheartedly
</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">your friend</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo is in the Netherlands, but we do not know the precise dates of his trip. In any event the visit took place in August 1886, because he returned to Paris on 26 August (FR b1844). Theo usually had two weeks’ holiday, starting at the weekend. This would mean that he could not have set out any earlier than the weekend of 14 August. Since his letter from the Netherlands arrived in Paris ‘this morning’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>) and he was able to report on conversations he had had, at least a few days of his stay must already have elapsed. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Wednesday, 18 August 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent and Andries Bonger both wrote to Theo; Bonger read Vincent’s letter and referred to its contents in his own letter, written on the same sheet.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo was staying in the Netherlands. His letter was addressed to Vincent and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs>. At that time Andries was living at 80 rue d’Hauteville (FR b1030), but he was staying with Vincent at 54 rue Lepic, as we learn from a letter to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> (Paris, Friday 27 August 1886): ‘My invalids (Vincent van Gogh also fell ill during Theo’s absence) have hindered me from writing. Otherwise I should have thanked you much sooner for the warmth of the reception you gave Theo. He was in raptures over his stay with you (he got back Thursday morning). It also pleases me greatly that he is to your liking. The longer one gets to know him, the more one learns to appreciate his fine mind. He is always entertaining company. I slept at the apartment while he was away, because Vincent was alone. ... I now go to eat with Van Gogh every evening as a permanent thing. It does take up a lot of time, since he lives in Montmartre, and the evenings are now taken up altogether, but it’s more pleasant for us both. The three of us always have plenty to talk about’ (FR b1844). The flat on the third floor ‘had three reasonably large rooms, a tiny study and a little kitchen. ... Vincent slept in the study, and behind that was the studio, an ordinary room with one not particularly large window’, wrote <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> in her introduction to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xlvii</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo used his stay in the Netherlands to try to get support for his plans to set up his own art gallery with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs>. He talked to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs>, but his uncle saw no merit in the idea. We do not know who else is meant by the ‘Dutch gentlemen’, but it is reasonable to assume that he also spoke to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs>. On the basis of Vincent’s remark about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> and Uncle Vincent in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let659.xml">letter 659</ref> we can assume that Theo approached Uncle Cor too.</p>

<p rend="indent">A year later, on 26 July 1887, Theo was to write to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo Bonger</rs> about his uncle’s reaction: ‘I had several artists in mind whose work I admired and with whom I was sure I could do business. André shared my views and we arranged that I would approach my uncle, who had once promised to help me, to get the money we needed to carry out our plan and start a business together. … My uncle refused to help and fobbed me off, kindly at first, but later, when I persisted, quite firmly. André’s attempts to raise funds were no more successful. For a while I was bitterly disappointed, so much so that I fell ill.’ See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 63-64, letter 1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>These words are quoted from the ‘philosopher’ Pangloss in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_445">Candide</ref></hi> (1759), where they occur repeatedly. The novel tells the story of the journey of the young, open-minded Candide, who is driven out of the palace where he lives. He has learned from the household philosopher Pangloss that he lives in the best possible world: ‘Tout est pour le mieux dans le meilleur des mondes’. During his wanderings Candide encounters a great deal of misery (so that he begins to have doubts), but nonetheless in the end he calls for fortitude with the cry: ‘we must cultivate our own garden’ (il faut cultiver notre jardin).</p>

<p rend="indent">Later in the correspondence, Van Gogh quotes Pangloss’s maxim about the best of all possible worlds several times more. However he interprets it as a genuine exhortation to be optimistic; the irony with which Voltaire put these words into the quasi-philosopher’s mouth largely escapes him.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>At this time Theo had a relationship with a woman referred to only as ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_662">S</rs>’, about whom nothing further is known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_492">Lucie</rs> was evidently the domestic help in Theo’s apartment.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This remark appears to indicate that Theo had told his brother about his feelings for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo Bonger</rs>, whom he had met for the first time a year earlier, on 7 August 1885. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> was also aware of them, as emerges from Theo’s first letter to Jo; see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 63-64.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Theo had taken a flower still life by Vincent with him on his trip to show it (or sell it?) – possibly to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422 bio.xml#_423">uncles</rs> or to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs> – or to use as an exchange for two watercolours by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1104">Isabey</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-14">see n. 14</ref> below). The works in question cannot be identified.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Japanese lacquer, an artistically lacquered object.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The four works described here cannot be identified. Van Gogh painted new scenes on top of several still lifes, and that might be what happened with these. See cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_275">Au bonheur des dames</ref></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml#n-35">letter 333, n. 35,</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let464.xml#n-2">letter 464, n. 2</ref> ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_446">Bel-ami</ref></hi> (1885). The protagonist is George Duroy who, on his return from military service in Algeria, is in danger of descending into a life of poverty until a childhood friend helps find him a job on a newspaper. As well as amorous intrigues in mondaine circles this later results in a political career. Duroy’s nickname is ‘Bel-ami’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Saying. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> worked at the offices of the insurance brokers Geo Wehry in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The Van Gogh brothers had started to build up an art collection together. One way of acquiring works was to swap them for work by Vincent – and placing Vincent’s work elsewhere would also automatically increase the chances of his establishing a reputation. Evidently Theo tried to come by two watercolours by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1104">Eugène Isabey</rs> in this manner while he was in the Netherlands, but this transaction did not take place. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 161.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The sale catalogue of the paintings in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs>’s estate lists two works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1423">Otto Weber</rs>: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_645">Sous les noyers</rs></hi> (Under the walnut trees) (sold for 600 guilders to Van Wisselingh in The Hague; present whereabouts unknown) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_646">Sous les châtaigniers</rs></hi> (Under the chestnut trees) (sold for 395 guilders to M.A. van Walcheren in The Hague; present whereabouts unknown). This latter canvas features ‘a beautiful autumn sun’ (un beau soleil d’automne), so it is probably the work Vincent means. The picture is described as follows: ‘In a wooded Breton landscape three children are sitting at the foot of an old chestnut tree. In a beautiful autumn sunset, which penetrates in a thousand places and casts a bright light over the tree-trunks and the ground, three cows make their way to the cowshed.’ (Dans un paysage boisé en Bretagne trois enfants sont assis au pied d’un vieux châtaignier. Au coucher d’un beau soleil d’automne, qui pénètre en mille endroits et éclaire vivement les troncs des arbres et le sol, trois vaches prennent le chemin de l’étable.) See auct. cat. The Hague<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1889, pp. 54-55, cat. nos. 154-155 (Lugt<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1938-1987, no. 48116).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            
        
<p>In May 1886 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs> had become officially engaged to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Anne (Annie) Marie Louise van der Linden</rs>; he had already informed his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> of his intentions in October 1885 (FR b1825). Both Annie and his sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> lived in Amsterdam (Jo at her parent’s house). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 14, 21.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            
        
<p>Very probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_753">François Spijker</rs>, a colleague and friend of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Bonger</rs>’s in Paris. He is mentioned repeatedly in the correspondence between Andries and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, as well as in letters between Jo and Theo (FR b1824; b1832; b1843; b1029; b1846; b1034; b4285; b4286; b4290 and b4302). There is no Spijker listed in the Paris directories, and the ‘Archives de la Préfecture de Police’ contain no data on the registration of foreigners prior to 1900. Cf. exhib. cat. Paris 1988, p. 367.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    