<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Friday, 24 February 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let578"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b504 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>578</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>464</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>580</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-02-24">on or about Friday, 24 February 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0504" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0504" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000680_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci de ta bonne lettre ainsi que du billet de 50 francs<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je ne trouve pas jusqu’à présent la vie ici aussi avantageuse que j’eusse pu l’espérer<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> seulement j’ai trois études de faites<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> ce qu’à Paris de ces jours-ci probablement je n’aurais pas su faire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">J’étais content de ce que les nouvelles de la Hollande étaient assez satisfaisantes<c type="kp">_</c> Pour ce qui est de Reid je serais peu étonné de ce qu’– (à tort pourtant) – il prît de mauvaise part que je l’aie dévancé dans le midi.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Dire de notre part que nous n’aurions jamais eu avantage à le connaître serait relativement injuste puisque 1° il nous a fait cadeau d’un très-beau tableau (lequel tableau soit dit entre paranthèses on avait l’intention d’acquérir)<ptr target="#note-t-4"/><c type="kk">/</c> 2° Reid a fait monter les Monticelli de valeur et puisqu’on en possède 5 il en résulte pour nous que ces tableaux ont haussé en tant que valeur<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – 3 il a été de bonne et agréable compagnie dans les premiers mois<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Maintenant de notre côté on a voulu le faire participer à une affaire plus importante que celle des Monticelli et il a fait semblant de n’y pas comprendre grand-chôse.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Il me semble que pour avoir davantage encore le droit de rester maîtres de notre terrain en tant que quant aux impressionistes – pour qu’il n’y puisse avoir de doute concernant notre bonne foi à l’égard de Reid – on pourrait le laisser agir sans intervenir comme bon lui semblera pour les Monticelli de Marseille. Insistant sur ceci que les peintres décédés ne nous intéressent qu’indirectement au point de vue argent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Et si tu es d’accord en ceci<c type="kk">/</c> à la rigueur tu peux de ma part aussi lui dire que s’il a l’intention de venir à Marseille pour y acheter des Monticelli il n’a rien à craindre de notre part mais qu’on a le droit de lui demander ses intentions à cet égard vu qu’on l’a dévancé sur ce territoire<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Pour les impressionistes – il me semblerait juste que ce soit par ton intermediaire sinon par toi directement qu’ils soient introduits en Angleterre<c type="kp">_</c>– Et si Reid prenait les devants on aurait le droit de le considérer comme ayant agi envers nous de mauvaise foi<c type="kk">/</c> à plus forte raison depuis qu’on lui aurait<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> laissé libre pour les Monticelli de Marseille.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Tu rendrais sûrement service à notre ami Koning en le laissant rester<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> avec toi<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – sa visite chez Rivet doit lui avoir prouvé que ce n’est pas nous qui l’ayons mal conseillé<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">En cas que tu voudrais le prendre – et il me semble que ce serait un debrouillage pour lui<c type="kk">/</c> seulement il faudrait clairement s’expliquer avec le père<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> de façon que tu n’aies pas de responsabilités<c type="kk">/</c> indirectes mêmes.– </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Si tu vois Bernard dis lui alors que jusqu’à présent j’ai à payer plus cher qu’à Pont aven<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> mais qu’ici je crois qu’en restant<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> en garni avec les bourgeois il doit y avoir des économies à faire<c type="kk">/</c> ce que je cherche<c type="kk">/</c> et dès que j’aurai vérifié je lui écrirai ce qui me paraîtra la moyenne des dépenses.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Il me semble par moments que mon sang veuille bien plus ou 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>moins se remettre à circuler<c type="kk">/</c> cela n’ayant pas été le cas dans les derniers temps à Paris<c type="kk">/</c> je n’en pouvais véritablement plus<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Il faut que je prenne mes couleurs et mes toiles soit chez un épicier soit chez un libraire<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> qui n’ont pas tout ce qui serait désirable. Il faudra bien que j’aille à Marseille pour voir comment l’état de ces chôses serait par là<c type="kp">_</c> J’avais espérer trouver du beau bleu &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> et en somme je n’en désespère pas vu qu’à Marseille on doit pouvoir acheter les matières brutes de première main<c type="kp">_</c> Et je voudrais pouvoir faire des bleus comme Ziem – qui ne bougent pas tant que les autres<c type="kk">/</c> enfin nous verrons<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Ne t’embêtes pas et donne une poignée de main aux copains pour moi<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">les etudes que j’ai sont une vieille femme Arlesienne<c type="kk">/</c> un paysage avec d.l<c type="kp">_</c> neige<c type="kk">/</c> une vue d’un bout de trottoir avec la boutique d’un charcutier<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Les femmes sont bien belles ici<c type="kk">/</c> c’est pas une blague<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> – par contraire le musée d’Arles est atroce et une blague et digne d’etre à Tarascon<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> – il y a aussi un musee d’antiquités<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> vraies celles-là.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your kind letter and the 50-franc note.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">So far I’m not finding living here as profitable as I might have hoped,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but I’ve finished three studies,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> which I would probably not have been able to do in Paris these days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I was glad the news from Holland was fairly satisfactory. As far as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> goes, I wouldn’t be very surprised if — (wrongly, however) — he took it badly that I went to the south before him.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> For us to say we’d never have benefited from knowing him would be relatively unfair since, 1, he made us a gift of a very fine painting (which painting, let it be said by the way, we intended to acquire),<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 2, Reid made <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s go up in value, and since we own 5 of them the result for us is that these paintings have increased in value<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> — 3, he was good and pleasant company in the first months.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Now for our part we wanted him to take part in a bigger deal than the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> one, and he pretended not to understand very much about it.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It seems to me that in order to be even more clearly entitled to stay masters on our own terrain regarding the Impressionists — so that there can be no doubt about our good faith towards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> — we could leave him alone and let him do as he thinks fit regarding the Marseille <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s. Making the point that dead painters are only of indirect interest to us from the monetary point of view.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And if you agree with this, if need be you can tell him on my behalf too that if he intends to come to Marseille to buy Monticellis he has nothing to fear from us, but that we’re entitled to ask him his intentions in this regard, given that we came to this territory before he did. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">About the Impressionists — it would seem fair to me that they should be introduced into England through you, if not by you in person. And if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> made a move first, we’d be justified in thinking he had acted in bad faith towards us, all the more so since we’d have left him free regarding the Marseille <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">You would definitely be doing our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> a favour if you let him stay with you<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> — his visit to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Rivet</rs> must have proved to him that it wasn’t we who advised him badly.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">If you did feel like taking him in — and it seems to me that it would get him out of a mess, you’d just have to get things straight with his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_125">father</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> so that you wouldn’t have any responsibilities, even indirect ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">If you see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> tell him that so far I’m having to pay more than at Pont-Aven,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> but that I think if you live here in furnished rooms with middle-class people it must be possible to save money, which I’m trying to do, and as soon as I’ve found out I’ll write and tell him what seem to me the average expenses.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">At times it seems to me that my blood is more or 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> less ready to start circulating again, which wasn’t the case lately in Paris, I really couldn’t stand it any more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I have to buy my colours and canvases from either a grocer or a bookseller,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> who don’t have everything one might wish for. I’ll definitely have to go to Marseille to see what the state of these things is like there. I had hoped to find some beautiful blue &amp;c., and in fact I haven’t given up, seeing that in Marseille you should be able to buy raw materials first hand. And I’d like to be able to do blues like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1449">Ziem</rs> — which don’t change as much as the others, well, we’ll see.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Don’t worry, and give the pals a handshake for me.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The studies I have are an old woman of Arles, a landscape with snow, a view of a stretch of pavement with a butcher’s shop.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> The women really are beautiful here, it’s no joke<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> — on the other hand, the Arles museum is dreadful and a joke, and fit to be in Tarascon<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> — there’s also a museum of antiquities,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> they’re genuine.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo wrote to his sister Willemien about Vincent in a letter of 24 and 26 February (FR b914). <ref target="documentation.xml#2426February1888">See <hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, 24 and 26 February 1888</ref>. <hi rend="italics"> </hi>In the second part, written on the 26th, he quoted from the present letter from Vincent. This means that it must have been sent on 25 February at the latest. Since his letter of 21 February <ref target="let577.xml">(577)</ref> Vincent had been to the museum and made three studies. Since all this would probably have taken a few days, we are dating the letter on or about Friday, 24 February 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo quoted <ref target="#l-80">ll. 80-85</ref> in his letter to Willemien of 24-26 February (see <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>); it also emerges from this letter that <ref target="let579.xml">letter 579</ref> to Willemien was enclosed with the present one.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh started out paying 5 francs and later 4 francs a day for board and lodging. From 1 May onwards, when he had his studio in the Yellow House and consequently took up less space, he only paid 3 francs. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let587.xml">See letters 587</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let603.xml">603</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for these studies the postscript and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-13">n. 13.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In the spring of 1887, the Scottish art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Alexander Reid</rs>, a friend of Theo and Vincent in Paris, had set up as an ‘agent en chambre’ (a dealer working from home) at 6 place d’Anvers in Paris. Alongside his job at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs> he also dealt on his own account in work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs> and others, and, one of the few people to do so, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>. See Fowle 2000, p. 93.</p>

<p rend="indent">Fowle thought it likely that Reid had gone to Marseille himself as early as 1886 or 1887 to look for work by Monticelli, or in any event that he had contacts there (Fowle 1993, p. 36). In view of the Van Gogh brothers’ interest in this artist, Reid evidently saw Vincent’s departure for the south of France as a threat to his monopoly in this field.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs>’s gift was probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vase of flowers </hi>(Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_306">Ill. 306</rs>. Van Gogh mentions this several more times. See also Fowle 2000, p. 94.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
    
<p>Van Gogh is referring to the following five works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, which are mentioned in the correspondence: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_306">Vase of flowers</rs></hi> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-4">see n. 4</ref>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_308">Woman with a parasol</rs></hi> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-17">letter 686, n. 17</ref>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_307">Woman at the well </rs></hi>(<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-16">letter 686, n. 16</ref>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2302">Italian girl</rs> </hi>(<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let830.xml#n-7">letter 830, n. 7</ref>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_305">Arabs and horseman</rs></hi> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let594.xml#n-7">letter 594, n. 7</ref>). See also exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 206, n. 13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The Van Gogh brothers befriended <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> in February 1887. See Fowle 2010, p. 31, and cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-3">n. 3</ref> above.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>It transpires from the continuation of the letter that Vincent and Theo had plans to sell the work of the French modern artists in England in association with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs>; he, though, proved to have other ideas. To prevent Reid from muscling in on their territory, Vincent suggested leaving the trade in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s in Marseille to him. He pursues the matter in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let580.xml">letter 580</ref>. From <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml">letter 589</ref> it emerges that it had been agreed with Reid that the Van Gogh brothers would help him find paintings for his stock, but that they had since fallen out with him because of the way he treated artists: Vincent accused Reid of being concerned with nothing but making money.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘l’aurait’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habiter’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            
    
<p>The Dutch painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Arnold Koning</rs> was in Paris from September 1887 to the end of May 1888. After Vincent went to Arles, Koning stayed with Theo in the apartment in rue Lepic for a short time. See also the letter from Theo to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> van Gogh (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="documentation.xml#2426February1888"><hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, 24 and 26 February 1888</ref>).  Koning moved in with Theo soon after 14 March (FR b915); he returned to the Netherlands on 30 May 1888 (FR b1077).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Louis Rivet</rs> was Theo’s doctor in Paris; he had his practice at 6 rue de la Victoire. Koning evidently had health problems; we do not know what his ailments were.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_125">Arnold Hendrik Koning</rs>, a lawyer in Winschoten.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Pont-Aven, a small village in Brittany, was discovered by painters around 1865, and grew to become a well-known artists’ colony. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> had been to Pont-Aven in August 1886 and had met <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs> there. The latter had been staying there again since late January 1888, as he had told Van Gogh (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let581.xml">letter 581</ref>). The group of artists who worked there in Gauguin’s style is known as the School of Pont-Aven. See exhib. cat. Paris 2003. The cost of living in Brittany and the south of France had evidently been a subject of discussion between Bernard and Van Gogh.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habitant’<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">.</hi></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>We do not know which bookshops in Arles sold paint and canvas. Not long afterwards, Van Gogh says that he knows a grocer who sells artists’ supplies; this was probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_3">Jules Armand</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-8">See letter 583, n. 8.</ref> It may well also have been possible to buy artists’ materials in Bompard fils’ wallpaper (papiers peints) shop at 14 place de la République; it is clear from the local newspapers that work by local artists was regularly displayed in the shop window. On the basis of accounts given by Jeanne Calment, who said she met Van Gogh through her cousin, it has been assumed that Van Gogh bought his canvas in the fabric shop run by Jeanne’s aunt, the Widow Calment. However, there is no evidence of this. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>These three studies are respectively: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">An old woman of Arles</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2561">F 390 / JH 1357</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape with snow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2564">F 290 / JH 1360</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">View of a butcher’s shop</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2563">F 389 / JH 1359</rs>). There is another <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Landscape with snow</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2562">F 391 / JH 1358</rs>), but that must be the painting referred to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let582.xml">letter 582</ref>, where Van Gogh talks about a ‘whitened landscape’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The beauty of the women of Arles was legendary and a popular topic in nineteenth-century art, literature and theatre. See exhib. cat. Arles 1999 and Dorn 1990, p. 152. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> had also written about it in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi>, which Van Gogh knew well: ‘In Paris a young man sees a beautiful young girl with regular features. He falls in love. He marries, and is eager to get to know the place his wife comes from, the town of Arles ... He sees a hundred, a thousand young girls who are just as pretty. It is the beauty of a whole population, the beauty of Arles, that he has loved’ (Un jeune homme voit dans Paris une belle demoiselle de traits réguliers. Il est épris. Il épouse, puis est curieux de connaître le pays de sa femme, la ville d’Arles<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>... Il voit cent filles et mille aussi jolies. C’est la beauté d’un peuple entier, la beauté arlésienne qu’il a aimée). Michelet, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’amour</hi>, p. 313.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the Musée Réattu in Arles, in the former Grand-Prieuré. Baedecker describes it as ‘a small collection of paintings, many of them copies, so called after its founder, a painter from Arles’ (une petite collection de tableaux, dont beaucoup de copies, ainsi nommée de son fondateur, un peintre arlésien). Baedeker 1889-2, p. 213. Van Gogh’s sarcastic reference to Tarascon leads us to suppose that he had meanwhile become familiar with the picture of it that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Alphonse Daudet</rs> sketched in his satirical novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_459">Aventures prodigieuses de Tartarin de Tarascon</ref></hi> (1872). It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let609.xml">letter 609</ref> that Van Gogh knew this book, and he must also have read the sequel, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref></hi> (1885), at about this time (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">see letter 583, n. 9</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p> The Musée Lapidaire was housed in a former church opposite Saint-Trophime at place de la République. The museum was ‘especially rich in ancient and Christian sarcophagi, made of marble and with bas-reliefs, that came from the Alyscamps’ (surtout très riche en sarcophages antiques et chrétiens, en marbre et à bas-reliefs, provenant des Aliscamps). Baedeker 1889-2, p. 212.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    