<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Emile Bernard. Arles, Sunday, 18 March 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let587"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>New York</settlement>
                                        <institution>Thaw Collection</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>587</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>B2</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>590</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-03-18">Sunday, 18 March 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Emile Bernard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Bernard,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">ayant promis de t’écrire<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> je veux commencer par te dire que le pays me parait aussi beau que le Japon pour la limpidité de l’atmosphère et les effets de couleur gaie<c type="kp">_</c> Les eaux<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> font des taches d’un bel éméraude et d’un riche bleu dans les paysages ainsi que nous le voyons dans les crepons.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Des couchers de soleil orangé pâle faisant paraître bleu les terrains – des soleils jaunes splendides<c type="kp">_</c> Cependant je n’ai encore guère vu le pays dans sa splendeur habituelle d’été<c type="kp">_</c> Le costume des femmes est joli et le dimanche surtout on voit sur le boulevard des arrangements de couleur très-naïfs et bien trouvés.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Et cela aussi sans doute s’égayera encore en été<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je regrette que la vie ici n’est pas à si bon marché que je l’avais espéré et je n’ai pas trouvé moyen jusqu’à présent de m’en tirer à aussi bon compte qu’on pourrait le faire à Pont Aven<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai commencé par payer 5 fr<c type="kp">_</c> et maintenant je suis à 4 francs par jour. Il faudrait savoir le patois d’ici et savoir manger de la bouillabaisse et de l’aïoli<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> alors on trouverait surement une pension bourgeoise peu coûteuse. Puis si on était à plusieurs on obtiendrait, je suis porté à le croire, des conditions plus avantageuses.– Il y aurait peut-être un réel avantage pour bien des artistes amoureux de soleil et de couleur d’émigrer dans le midi. Si les Japonais ne sont pas en progrès dans leur pays il est indubitable que leur art se continue en France. En tête de cette lettre je t’envoie un petit croquis d’une étude qui me préoccupe pour en faire quelque chôse – des matelots qui remontent avec leurs amoureuses vers la ville qui profile l’étrange silhouette de son pont levis sur un énorme soleil jaune<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">J’ai une autre étude du même pont levis avec un groupe de laveuses.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Serai content d’un mot de toi pour savoir ce que tu fais et où tu iras<c type="kp">_</c>– Poignée de main bien cordiale à toi-même et aux amis<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">bien à toi</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Bernard,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Having promised to write to you,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I want to begin by telling you that this part of the world seems to me as beautiful as Japan for the clearness of the atmosphere and the gay colour effects. The stretches of water<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> make patches of a beautiful emerald and a rich blue in the landscapes, as we see it in the Japanese prints.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Pale orange sunsets making the fields look blue — glorious yellow suns. However, so far I’ve hardly seen this part of the world in its usual summer splendour. The women’s costume is pretty, and especially on the boulevard on Sunday you see some very naive and well-chosen arrangements of colour.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And that, too, will doubtless get even livelier in summer. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I regret that living here isn’t as cheap as I’d hoped, and until now I haven’t found a way of getting by as easily as one could do in Pont-Aven. I started out paying 5 francs and now I’m on 4 francs a day. One would need to know the local patois, and know how to eat bouillabaisse and aïoli,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> then one would surely find an inexpensive family boarding-house. Then if there were several of us, I’m inclined to believe we’d get more favourable terms. Perhaps there’d be a real advantage in emigrating to the south for many artists in love with sunshine and colour. The Japanese may not be making progress in their country, but there’s no doubt that their art is being carried on in France. At the top of this letter I’m sending you a little croquis of a study that’s preoccupying me as to how to make something of it — sailors coming back with their sweethearts towards the town, which projects the strange silhouette of its drawbridge against a huge yellow sun.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I have another study of the same drawbridge with a group of washerwomen.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Shall be happy to have a line from you to know what you’re doing and where you’re going to go. A very warm handshake to you and the friends.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent sent this letter off with one to Theo dating from Wednesday, 21 or Thursday, 22 March (<ref target="let588.xml">letter 588</ref>). It emerges from <ref target="let585.xml">letter 585</ref> of about 16 March that Van Gogh planned to write the present letter the following Sunday, the day of the week that he often set aside for his correspondence. Since there is no reason to believe that he departed from that plan, and lacking any other clues, we have dated the letter Sunday, 18 March 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had got Theo to pass on this message; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml">see letter 578</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Arles is on the river Rhône. There are also several canals in and outside the town, including the Arles-Bouc Canal, which is shown in the letter sketch. It is also depicted in the paintings of the Langlois bridge mentioned later in the letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Although strictly speaking a ‘crépon’ is a woodcut printed on crepe paper or crepe fabric, Van Gogh uses the term for Japanese prints in general, which he also calls ‘Japonaiseries’. He and Theo had built up a collection in Paris, and later he repeatedly urged his brother to acquire new ones. See for their collection of Japanese prints: cat. Amsterdam 1991. In July 1888 Van Gogh wrote to Theo telling him that he had introduced <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_328">Anquetin</rs> to Japanese graphic art (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let642.xml">letter 642</ref>). It was a major influence on the new style that Anquetin and Bernard developed, Cloisonnism. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let575.xml#n-7">letter 575, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For the women of Arles, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-14">see letter 578, n. 14.</ref> They wore the traditional costume of the region. See exhib. cat. Arles 1999, and Dorn 1990, p. 152.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Bouillabaisse is a regional fish soup served with garlic-flavoured mayonaise (aïoli).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The fragment <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Walking couple</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2572">F 544 / JH 1369</rs>) is all that has survived of this study, which is reproduced in its entirety in the letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Langlois bridge with walking couple</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_154">F - / JH 1370</rs>). In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml">letter 589</ref> Van Gogh said that he had ruined the study.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Langlois bridge with washerwomen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2571">F 397 / JH 1368</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    