<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Arles, on or about Friday, 30 March 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let590"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b703 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>590</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W3</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>593</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-03-30">on or about Friday, 30 March 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0703" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0703" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000955_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Lieve Zuster,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">om uw brief niet onbeant<c type="shy">-</c>woord te laten schrijf ik U dadelijk na ontvangst van uw schrijven en dat van Moe en u beider goede wenschen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ge moet weten dat ik U regt graag meer zou schrijven als ’t niet ware dat nog al veel dingen er toe bijdragen om me niet meester van mijn tijd te laten en ge moet U niet voorstellen ik doe waar ik precies lust in heb of laat datgene wat ik liever niet deed<c type="kp">_</c>– Het werk heeft me nu te pakken<c type="kk">/</c> ’k denk wel voor altijd en al is zulks niet ongelukkig<c type="kk">/</c> het geluk stel ik me toch heel anders voor<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Om te beginnen heeft het me hier verbazend veel genoegen gedaan dat tusschen Theo en de Hr. Tersteeg de relaties begonnen zijn om het werk van de schilders van hier die men impressionisten noemt ook in Holland bekend te maken<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Verder ik zelf heb geen spijt naar hier te zijn gegaan daar ik de natuur hier magtig mooi vind<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Tegen ’t volgend jaar – wanneer de wereldtentoonstelling zal plaats hebben<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – moet ik een massa dingen maken omdat mijn vrienden zeker ook niet in gebreke zullen blijven dan veel interessants voorhanden te hebben<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Niet dat ik of iemand van de schilders met wie ik meer speciaal omgang heb exposeeren zullen met de anderen doch er zal alsdan denkelijk een vrije tentoonstelling naast de officieele worden gehouden<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Nu heb ik hier b.v<c type="kp">_</c> op dit moment 6 schilderijen onder handen van bloeiende vruchtboomen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> En dat wat ik heden ’thuis heb gebragt zou U welligt bevallen – het is een omgewerkt vak grond in een boomgaard<c type="kk">/</c> een rieten schutting en twee perzik boomen in volle bloei<c type="kk">/</c> rose tegen een tintelend blaauwe lucht met witte wolken en in zonneschijn<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ge zult ’t mogelijk zien daar ’k maar besloten heb dit voor Jet Mauve te bestemmen<c type="kp">_</c> ik heb er op geschreven</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Souvenir de Mauve</hi></p> 
<p xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9"><hi rend="italics">Vincent &amp; Theo</hi><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Ik weet nu zeer wel dat ik zoodanig onderwerp ook elders had kunnen vinden doch als ik naga dat veel schilders ’t zelfde zullen maken reken ik het geenszins onverschillig te werken in een natuur die<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon al mee ’t zelfde nog als bij ons als onderwerp en gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> ongetwijfeld veel rijker en kleuriger is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Verder zijn de menschen hier ook schilderachtig<c type="kk">/</c> en gelijkt bij ons een bedelaar veeleer op een spook<c type="kk">/</c> hier wordt hij een karikatuur<c type="kp">_</c>– Daar zooals ge ’t merken zult bij ’t lezen van Zola en Guy de Maupassant men absoluut wil – in de kunst – iets zeer rijks en iets zeer vroolijks – ook al hebben die zelfden Zola en Maupassant de meest navrante dingen gezegd die ooit gezegd zijn misschien – zoo is de zelfde beweging ook in de schilderkunst aan het beginnen regel te worden<c type="kp">_</c>– Bij voorbeeld kan ik me voorstellen dat een schilder van heden iets make als ’t geen men vindt beschreven in ’t boek van Pierre Loti<c type="kk">/</c> le mariage de Loti<c type="kk">/</c> waar de natuur van Otaheite wordt beschreven<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Een boek dat ik U erg kan recommandeeren<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Ge begrijpt dat de natuur van ’t zuiden niet precies kan worden geschilderd met ’t palet van b.v. Mauve die in ’t noorden hoort en meester is en blijft in ’t grijs<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar het palet van tegenwoordig is absoluut kleurig – hemelsblaauw<c type="kk">/</c> rose<c type="kk">/</c> oranje<c type="kk">/</c> vermilloen<c type="kk">/</c> hoog geel<c type="kk">/</c> helder groen<c type="kk">/</c> helder wijnrood<c type="kk">/</c> violet<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Maar <hi rend="italics">alle</hi> kleuren opvoerende komt men op nieuw tot kalmte en harmonie. En geschiedt er iets dergelijks als met de Wagner muziek die met een groot orchest uitgevoerd daarom niet minder intiem is<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Alleen men kiest bij voorkeur zonnige en kleurige effekten en niets belet me soms te denken dat later er veel schilders in de tropische landen zullen gaan werken<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge kunt u wel een begrip maken van de verandering in de schilderijen als ge b.v. denkt aan de kleurige japansche voorstellingen die men overal ziet<c type="kk">/</c> landschappen en figuren. Theo en ik hebben honderden van die Japansche prenten<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">ge ziet ik schrijf U enkel over ’t werk van daag en ik moet eindigen en weet niet of ik hier nog verder bij zal kunnen schrijven. Het beste U zelf en Moe toegewenscht en dank voor Uwe brieven.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Mijnerzijds moet ik U zelf ook met Uw verjaardag gelukwenschen<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – daar ik U graag iets van mijn werk wou geven dat U bevallen mogt zal ik voor U apart houden een kleine studie van een boek en een bloem<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> – in grooter formaat met een heele massa boeken met rose<c type="kk">/</c> geele<c type="kk">/</c> groene omslagen en vuurroode – was mijn sch<hi rend="super">ij </hi><hi rend="italics">romans Parisiens</hi> ’t zelfde onderwerp<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Theo zal U die meebrengen<c type="kp">_</c>– ik heb ook een studie voor Jet Mauve<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">So as not to let your letter go unanswered I’m writing immediately upon receipt of your letter and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>’s and the good wishes from you both.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You should know that I’d be very happy to write to you more often were it not that quite a lot of things contribute to my not being master of my time, and you mustn’t imagine that I do exactly what I want or leave what I’d rather not do. The work has me in its grip now, I think for all time, and although this isn’t unhappy, I nonetheless imagine happiness as something very different.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">To begin with, it gave me an enormous amount of pleasure here that relations have begun between Theo and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> in order to make the work of the painters from here whom they call Impressionists known in Holland too.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">For myself I have no regrets about having come here, since I find nature here almighty beautiful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">By next year — when the World Exhibition will be held<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — I have to make a mass of things, because my friends will certainly also not fail to have a great many interesting things on hand.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Not that I or any of the painters with whom I’m more especially friendly will exhibit with the others, but an open exhibition will probably be staged alongside the official one at that time.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Now here, for instance, at this moment, I have 6 paintings of blossoming fruit trees.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> And the one I brought home today would possibly appeal to you — it’s a dug-over patch of ground in an orchard, a wicker fence and two peach trees in full bloom, pink against a sparkling blue sky with white clouds and in sunshine.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> You may well see it, since I’ve decided to send this one to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321">Jet Mauve</rs>. I’ve written on it</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Souvenir de Mauve</hi></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"><hi rend="italics">Vincent &amp; Theo</hi><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now I know very well that I could also have found such a subject elsewhere, but when I think that many painters will do the same I reckon it by no means immaterial to work in nature which, although it’s the same as at home in subject and fact, is undoubtedly much richer and more colourful.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Furthermore, the people here are picturesque too, and whereas at home a beggar looks much like a spectre, here he becomes a caricature. Since, as you’ll see when you read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>, people definitely want — in art — something very rich and something very cheerful — even though that same Zola and Maupassant have said the most heart-rending things that have perhaps ever been said — the same movement is also beginning to become the rule in painting. For example I can imagine that a painter of today might make something like one finds described in the book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Pierre Loti</rs>, Le mariage de Loti, where nature in Otaheite is described.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> A book that I can really recommend to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">You understand that the countryside of the south can’t exactly be painted with the palette of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, say, who belongs in the north and is and always will be the master of grey. But today’s palette is definitely colourful — sky blue, pink, orange, vermilion, brilliant yellow, bright green, bright wine red, violet. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"> But by intensifying <hi rend="italics">all the</hi> colours one again achieves calm and harmony. And something happens like with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_814">Wagner</rs> music which, performed by a large orchestra, is no less intimate for that.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Only people prefer sunny and colourful effects, and nothing stops me from thinking sometimes that later on many painters will go and work in tropical countries. You can get an idea of the change in painting if you think, say, of the colourful Japanese pictures that one sees everywhere, landscapes and figures. Theo and I have hundreds of these Japanese prints.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">You see I’m writing to you only about the work today, and I must close, and don’t know whether I’ll be able to write any more to add to it. Best wishes to you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>, and thanks for your letters.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">For my part I must also wish you a happy birthday<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> — since I’d like to give you something of my work that you’ll like I’ll set aside a little study of a book and a flower<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> for you — in a large format with a whole mass of books with pink, yellow, green covers and fiery red — my painting <hi rend="italics">Parisian novels</hi> was the same subject.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Theo will bring this for you — I also have a study for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321">Jet Mauve</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh thanks his sister for her letter with ‘good wishes’ from her and from their mother <ref target="#l-3">(ll. 3-4)</ref>; these relate to his birthday, which was on 30 March. Since he replied ‘immediately upon receipt’ <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref>, we have dated the present letter on or about Friday, 30 March 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote to Vincent on the occasion of his thirty-fifth birthday on 30 March.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo had sent a consignment of modern paintings to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml#n-4">see letter 589, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The World Exhibition was staged in Paris from 5 May to 5 November 1889. Van Gogh, like his artist friends, wanted to take advantage of the enormous influx of visitors and show work during this period.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>During the 1889 World Exhibition, the Groupe impressionniste et synthétiste, of which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs> was the leading light, mounted an exhibition in Café Volpini in the Champs-de-Mars (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let779.xml#n-13">see letter 779, n. 13</ref>). We do not know whether the exhibition was already being planned at this time; according to Welsh-Ovcharov specific preparations did not start until early May 1889, but this does not necessarily mean that such an exhibition was not already being discussed. Cf. exhib. cat. Toronto 1981, pp. 41-42. The fifth exhibition of the Indépendants was also held in 1889, as a counterpart to the traditional Salon.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Besides the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pink peach trees</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘Souvenir de Mauve’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2577">F 394/ JH 1379</rs>) described later in this letter, these six studies in any event included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with apricot trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2581">F 556 / JH 1383</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with apricot trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2585">F 553 / JH 1387</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml#n-6">see letter 589, n. 6.</ref> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peach tree in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2592">F 557 / JH 1397</rs>) may also have been among these first studies of orchards. Van Gogh must have painted <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard bordered by cypresses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2586">F 554 / JH 1388</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peach tree in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2593">F 399 / JH 1398</rs>) later, as preliminary studies for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2587">F 513 / JH 1389</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2591">F 551 / JH 1396</rs>, and the other extant orchards are not mentioned in the correspondence until later. Among the studies he refers to here there were probably works that he subsequently destroyed (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let606.xml">see letter 606</ref>); in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let591.xml">letter 591</ref> to Theo he refers to ‘4 or 5’ studies plus F 394.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The work that Van Gogh earmarked for Mauve’s widow was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pink peach trees</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘Souvenir de Mauve’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2577">F 394/ JH 1379</rs>); he sent it to Theo in May 1888 with his first batch of paintings. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml">See letters 583</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let608.xml">608</ref>. It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let719.xml">letter 719</ref> that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_321">Jet Mauve</rs> did receive the painting.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh added the sentence ‘You may ... Theo’ later, after he had written the postscript. The words ‘&amp; Theo’ cannot now be seen on the painting. Vincent probably removed them at Theo’s insistence, because it was done before the canvas was completely dry. See cat. Otterlo 2003, pp. 212-213.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_464">Le mariage de Loti</ref></hi> (1880) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Pierre Loti</rs> contains idealized descriptions of nature in Tahiti and people’s way of life. The naval officer Harry Grant spends several years on the island, where he is called Loti (‘rose’). He falls in love with a young girl, Rarahu, and this makes him think that he is getting to know the true Tahiti. Otaheite is the original name for the island, however it does not occur anywhere in the book.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_814">Richard Wagner</rs> composed large-scale, ambitious operas for big orchestras. Van Gogh had been to performances of Wagner in Paris. Theo wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> about it: ‘And before Vincent left I went to a couple of Wagner concerts with him and we both enjoyed them very much’ (FR b915, 14 March 1888).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>See for the brothers’ collection of Japanese prints: cat. Amsterdam 1991. Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let587.xml#n-3">letter 587, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> turned 26 on 16 March.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sprig of almond blossom in a glass with a book</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2566">F 393 / JH 1362</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> did indeed have the work in her possession. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 20 (n. 33).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Piles of French novels and roses in a glass</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘Romans parisiens’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2556">F 359 / JH 1332</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh wrote this passage before he inserted <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-44">ll. 44-49</ref>; this explains the duplication of the reference to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pink peach trees</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘Souvenir de Mauve’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2577">F 394/ JH 1379</rs>); cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-5">nn. 5</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-6">6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    