<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To John Peter Russell. Arles, Thursday, 19 April 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let598"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>New York</settlement>
                                        <institution/>
                                        
                                        <idno>78.2514 T18.</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>598</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>477a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>600</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-04-19">Thursday, 19 April 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">John Peter Russell</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1r/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1r/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1r/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1v/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1v/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/598_1v/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="en" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Russell,</p>

<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I ought to have answered your letter ever so long ago<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but working pretty hard every day<c type="kk">/</c> at night I feel so often to weary to write. As it rains to day I avail myself of the opportunity. Last Sunday I have met Macknight and a Danish painter and I intend to go to see him at Fonvieille next monday.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I feel sure I shall prefer him as an artist to what he is as an art critic<c type="kk">/</c> his vieuws as such being so narrow that they make me smile.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I heartily hope for you that you will be able to leave Paris for good soon<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and no doubt leaving Paris will do you <hi rend="italics">a world of good</hi> in all respects. As for me I remain enraptured with the scenery here<c type="kk">/</c> am working at a series of blooming orchards.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And unvoluntarily thought often of you because you did the same in Sicily.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I wished you would one day or another<c type="kk">/</c> when I shall send over some work to Paris<c type="kk">/</c> exchange a Sicilian study with me – in case you should have one to spare<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You know I thought and think such a deal of those of yours<c type="kp">_</c> I don’t gainsay that your portraits are more serious and higher art but I think it meritory in you and a rare quality that together with a perfection as appeared to me the Fabian and M<hi rend="super">c</hi> Knight portraits<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> you are at the same time able to give a Scherzo<c type="kk">/</c> the adagio con expressione<c type="kk">/</c> the gay note in one word<c type="kk">/</c> together with more manly conceptions of a higher order. And I so heartily hope that you will continue to give us simultanément both the grave and elaborate works and those aforesaid scherzos.– Then let them say if they like that you are <hi rend="italics">not always</hi> serious or that you <hi rend="italics">have</hi> done work <hi rend="italics">of a lighter sort</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– So much the worse for the critics &amp; the better for you<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I have heard nothing of our friend M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Reid. I felt rather anxious on his account because I feel sure that he was on a false track. My brother has received a letter of him but pretty unsatisfactory.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I was very much taken in by him during the first 6 weeks or 2 months<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> but after that period he was in pecuniary difficulties and in the same acted in a way that made on me the impression that he had lost his wits.</p>
    
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Which I still think was the case and consequently he’s not responsable even if his doings then were pretty unfair. He is very nervous – as we all are – and can’t help being so<c type="kp">_</c>– He is prompted to act in his crisis of nerves to make money – – – whilst painters would make pictures.....</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">So much to say that I consider <hi rend="italics">the dealer</hi> <hi>stronger</hi> in him than THE ARTIST though there be a battle in his conscience concerning this – of the which battle I do not yet know the result<c type="kp">_</c> So much – pour votre gouverne – as I had the pleasure of introducing him to you<c type="kk">/</c> feel bound to warn you with the same sympathy however for him because I found him artistic in pleading the Monticelli cause<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> In the which I took and take my part<c type="kp">_</c> Witnessing the very scenery which inspired Monticelli I maintain this artists rights to public though too late appreciation<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
    
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Surely Monticelli gives us not<c type="kk">/</c> neither pretends to give us<c type="kk">/</c> local colour or even local truth. But gives us something passionate and eternal – the rich coulour and rich sun of the glorious South in a true colourists way parralel with Delacroix’ conception of the South<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Viz<c type="kp">_</c> that the South be represented now by contraste simultané of colours<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> and their derivations and harmonies<c type="kk">/</c> and not by forms or lines in themselves as the ancient artists did formerly<c type="kk">/</c> by pure <hi rend="italics">form </hi>greeks &amp; Michel Ange<c type="kk">/</c> or by pure line or delineation Rafael<c type="kk">/</c> Mantegna<c type="kk">/</c> Venetian <hi rend="italics">primitifs</hi><c type="kp">_</c> (Botticelli<c type="kk">/</c> Cimabue<c type="kk">/</c> Giotto<c type="kk">/</c> Bellini.) Contrariwise the thing undertaken by P. Veronese &amp; Titian – Colour<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> The thing undertaken by Velasquez and Goya to be continued and – more fully or rather more universally done by the more universal knowledge we have &amp; possess of the colours of the prism and their proprieties<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Hoping to write to you again and to hear of you pretty soon<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Yours very truly,</p>

<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I ought to have answered your letter ever so long ago<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but working pretty hard every day, at night I feel so often too weary to write. As it rains to day I avail myself of the opportunity. Last Sunday I have met <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> and a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1233">Danish painter</rs> and I intend to go and see him at Fontvieille next Monday.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I feel sure I’ll prefer him as an artist to what he is as an art critic, his views as such being so narrow that they make me smile.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"> I heartily hope for you that you will be able to leave Paris for good soon<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and no doubt leaving Paris will do you <hi rend="italics">a world of good</hi> in all respects. As for me I remain enraptured with the scenery here, am working at a series of blooming orchards.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And unvoluntarily thought often of you because you did the same in Sicily.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I wished you would one day or another, when I shall send over some work to Paris, exchange a Sicilian study with me – in case you should have one to spare.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4"> You know I thought and think such a deal of those of yours. I don’t gainsay that your portraits are more serious and higher art but I think it meritory in you and a rare quality that together with a perfection as appeared to me the Fabian and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> portraits,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> you are at the same time able to give a Scherzo, the adagio con espressione, the gay note in one word, together with more manly conceptions of a higher order. And I so heartily hope that you will continue to give us simultanément both the grave and elaborate works and those aforesaid scherzos. Then let them say if they like that you are <hi rend="italics">not always</hi> serious or that you <hi rend="italics">have</hi> done work <hi rend="italics">of a lighter sort</hi>. So much the worse for the critics and the better for you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I have heard nothing of our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Mr Reid</rs>. I felt rather anxious on his account because I feel sure that he was on a false track. My brother has received a letter of him but pretty unsatisfactory.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"> I was very much taken in by<ptr target="#note-t-a"/>  him during the first 6 weeks or 2 months<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> but after that period he was in pecuniary difficulties and in the same acted in a way that made on me the impression that he had lost his wits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"> Which I still think was the case and consequently he’s not responsable even if his doings then were pretty unfair. He is very nervous – as we all are – and can’t help being so. He is prompted to act in his crisis of nerves to make money – – – whilst painters would make pictures.....</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"> So much to say that I consider <hi rend="italics">the dealer</hi> <hi>stronger</hi> in him than THE ARTIST though there be a battle in his conscience concerning this – of the which battle I do not yet know the result. So much – for your information<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> – as I had the pleasure of introducing him to you, feel bound to warn you with the same sympathy however for him because I found him artistic in pleading the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> cause.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> In the which I took and take my part. Witnessing the very scenery which inspired Monticelli I maintain this artists rights to public though too late appreciation. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"> Surely <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> gives us not, neither pretends to give us, local colour or even local truth. But gives us something passionate and eternal – the rich coulour and rich sun of the glorious south in a true colourists way parralel with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>’ conception of the south.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Viz. that the south be represented now by contraste simultané of colours<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> and their derivations and harmonies, and not by forms or lines in themselves as the ancient artists did formerly, by pure <hi rend="italics">form </hi>greeks and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs>, or by pure line or delineation <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1283">Raphael</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1194">Mantegna</rs>, Venetian <hi rend="italics">primitifs</hi>. (<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_886">Botticelli</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_946">Cimabue</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_860">Bellini</rs>.) Contrariwise the thing undertaken by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1418">P. Veronese</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1393">Titian</rs> – Colour.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> The thing undertaken by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1402">Velázquez</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs> to be continued and – more fully or rather more universally done by the more universal knowledge we have and possess of the colours of the prism and their proprieties.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"> Hoping to write to you again and to hear of you pretty soon,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Yours very truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh remarks that he met Macknight and Mourier-Petersen ‘last Sunday’ <ref target="#l-6">(l. 6)</ref>; that must have been Sunday, 15 April because on 19 April 1888 Macknight mentioned this meeting in a letter to Eugène Boch (<ref target="#n-2">see n. 2</ref>). Since Van Gogh also writes that it is raining <ref target="#l-5">(l. 5)</ref> – something he likewise mentioned in his letter to Bernard (<ref target="let599.xml">see letter 599</ref>) – and the weather reports record heavy rain on 19 April 1888 (<hi rend="italics">Météo-France</hi>), we have dated the letter that day.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written in English.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The proposed  exchange with Russell <ref target="let589.xml">(589)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Disagreement with Reid <ref target="let578.xml">(578)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had received a letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> about a month before; he sent it on to Theo with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml">letter 589</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In 1888 the American artist <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Dodge Macknight</rs>, who Van Gogh had met through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> in Paris, spent some time in Fontvieille, a village 9 km to the north of Arles. On 19 April 1888 Macknight wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Eugène Boch</rs> and told him that he had seen Van Gogh in Arles. See exhib. cat. Pontoise 1994, pp. 80, 96 (n. 18). The Danish painter is <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1233">Christian Mourier-Petersen</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> must have mentioned his impending departure in his letter; in the spring of 1888 he moved with his family to the Breton island Belle-Île. See Galbally 1977, p. 45.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for this series: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let597.xml">letter 597</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In the late autumn of 1886 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> left Paris and set off on a six-month trip around Italy, during which he also went to Sicily. One of the studies of trees in blossom he made there is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_676">Almond trees and ruins on Sicily</rs></hi>, c. 1887 (sale Christie, Manson &amp; Woods, Australia, 6-7 June 1989, p. 71, no. 184).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>See for the hoped-for exchange: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml#n-5">letter 589, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">John Peter Russell</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fabian</hi>, c. 1887 (Cambridge, Mass., Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1309">Ill. 1309</rs>; and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Dodge Macknight</hi> (private collection). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1308">Ill. 1308</rs>. Nothing is known about Fabian, the subject of the first work, except that he, like Russell and Van Gogh, had studied in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>’s studio in Paris, and that he and Van Gogh may have exchanged work (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let569.xml#n-13">see letter 569, n. 13</ref>). It seems unlikely that he was the Spanish artist <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_374">Fabian de Castro</rs>, as was suggested earlier. See cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            
    
<p>This letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> to Theo, which was also mentioned in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml">letter 589</ref>, is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            
<p>Read ‘taken with’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
    
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> had lived with the Van Gogh brothers in Paris for some time. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-6">See letter 578, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
<p>Van Gogh wrote in French ‘pour votre gouverne’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-3">letter 578, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>After his trip to Morocco in 1832 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> painted predominantly ‘southern’ – African, Greek and Turkish – subjects, in which he applied his colour theories.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>See for the concept ‘simultaneous contrast’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let536.xml#n-28">letter 536, n. 28.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The artists that Van Gogh counted among the Venetian School belonged – with the exception of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_860">Giovanni Bellini</rs> – to the Florentine School, which is known for its emphasis on line; the Venetian School, to which Bellini, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1393">Titian</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1418">Veronese</rs> are considered to belong, is known for its colourful qualities.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh probably meant ‘properties’ (cf. the French ‘propriété’); the English ‘proprieties’ seems inappropriate here.</p>
    
<p rend="indent">Van Gogh admired <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1402">Velázquez</rs> for his use of grey half-tones. He had read about his use of colour in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Charles Blanc</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_403">Les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let450.xml#n-15">see letter 450, n.15</ref>.
        ; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let450.xml">see letter 450</ref>. Velázquez’s work, with sketchy handling of the paint and strong chiaroscuro, was a major source of inspiration for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    