<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Friday, 20 April 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let600"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b518 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>600</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>478</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>602</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-04-20">on or about Friday, 20 April 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0518 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0518 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000698_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0518 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000696_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000696_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0518 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000696_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000696_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000696_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci de ta lettre d’aujourd’hui et du billet de 100 fr. qu’elle contenait. Pour ce qui est de la lettre précédente contenant 50 fr<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> je l’ai également reçue et je te l’ai aussi écrit le jour avant ou deux jours avant que je n’aie envoyé les deux dessins<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ces dessins sont faits avec un roseau taillé comme serait une plume d’oie. Je compte en faire une série comme cela. et j’espère faire mieux que les deux premiers<c type="kp">_</c> C’est un procedé que j’ai déjà cherché en Hollande dans le temps, mais là je n’avais pas d’aussi bons roseaux qu’ici<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Ai reçu une lettre de Koning de laquelle veuille le remercier – très volontiers je veux lui échanger les deux dessins contre une étude de lui que tu choisiras &amp; garderas dans la collection.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Je lui écrirai pour lui expliquer le procedé et lui enverrai des roseaux taillés pour qu’il puisse en faire aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Maintenant c’était une impor<c type="shy">-</c>tante nouvelle que celle de ton voyage à Bruxelles.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Tu seras à même de juger comment marche l’ancienne marchandise à haut prix là-bas<c type="kp">_</c> Mais quelle affaire. Car il est probable en effet que ces messieurs préparent quelque coup.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Te rappelles tu que nous en avons encore causé avant mon départ<c type="kk">/</c> que en vue de l’exposition universelle<c type="kk">/</c> Bouguereau<c type="kk">/</c> Lefevre<c type="kk">/</c> Benjamin C<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> toute la clique irait chez Boussod se plaindre et insister sur ce qu’ils y tiennent que la maison B. (la première du monde) demeure pure et fidèle aux principes de l’art vraiment le plus civilisé et le plus aimable<c type="kk">/</c> soit leurs tableaux à eux.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Quoi qu’il en soit cela donne rudement à penser. Et la situation serait grave si tu te brouilles avec ces messieurs<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Je ne te cache pas que ce sera un rude choc pour toi<c type="kk">/</c> non pas immédiatement<c type="kk">/</c> mais 6 mois disons après à cause du changement de vie que cela te causerait.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Quand on sort de prison après y avoir longtemps sejourné<c type="kk">/</c> il y a des moments où l’on regrette la prison même<c type="kk">/</c> parce que l’on se trouve desorienté dans la liberté<c type="kk">/</c> ainsi probablement nommée puisque la tâche quotidienne éreintante pour gagner sa vie ne laisse guère de liberté. Mais tu sais tout cela<c type="kp">_</c>– Certainement tu regretteras des choses involontairement même en en gagnant d’autres.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">J’ai maintenant 10 vergers sans compter trois petites etudes et une grande d’un cérisier que j’ai ereintée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Quand est ce que tu serais de retour<c type="kk">/</c> comment faire pour l’envoi en définitive? Car il me faut maintenant changer de motifs<c type="kk">/</c> les vergers ayant pour la plupart perdu leurs fleurs<c type="kp">_</c> Donc ces vergers avec le pont de l’Anglais<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> forment une premiere serie.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Si tu prefèrès que cela sèche encore ici<c type="kk">/</c> cela n’est pas mauvais peutêtre. Ils sont maintenant sur une terrasse couverte pour y sécher.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Dites donc <hi rend="italics">Daumier</hi> est exposé aux Beaux arts &amp; Gavarni n’est ce pas<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Bravo pour le Daumier<c type="kk">/</c> pas pour les Beaux arts<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Voici croquis d’un verger que j’avais plus spécialement destiné pour toi à l’occasion du 1° Mai<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> C’est absolument clair et absolument fait d’un coup<c type="kk">/</c> une furie d’empatements à peine teinté de jaune et de lilas dans la touffe blanche première<c type="kp">_</c> Tu seras alors probablement en Hollande et là-bas tu verras peutêtre ce jour-là les mêmes arbres en fleur<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Quel dommage de Cor<c type="kk">/</c> pourvu que cela ne soit pas quelque chose de grâve<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Cela me fait grand plaisir que tu aies pris des leçons de manger au jeune Koning<c type="kk">/</c> il est très malin là-dedans et c’est amusant de manger avec cette jeune verdure d’artiste<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>Je suis bien content que tu aies son étude de négresse<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Enfin mais cela te fera du bien de déjeûner. Ici j’ai fait d’ailleurs la meme chôse en mangeant 2 oeufs le matin<c type="kp">_</c> L’estomac chez moi est très faible mais j’espère y arriver à le retablir<c type="kk">/</c> il faudra du temps &amp; de la patience. En tout cas je me porte déjà beaucoup mieux <hi rend="italics">en réalité</hi> qu’à Paris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Il parait d’ailleurs qu’ici on n’a pas precisement besoin d’une grande quantité de nourriture et je voulais bien à cette occasion encore te dire que je doute de plus en plus de la véracité de la légende Monticelli absorbeur de quantites énormes d’absinthe<c type="kp">_</c> Considérant son oeuvre<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> il me parait pas possible qu’un homme enervé par la boisson aie fait cela.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Peutêtre cette Limousine<c type="kk">/</c> la dame la Roquette<c type="kk">/</c> y a mis de sa médisance après tout pour que cette légende se soit enracinée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Enfin je t’écris à la hâte<c type="kk">/</c> de cette façon tu auras ma lettre avant ton depart si c’est ce Dimanche-ci que tu comptes partir.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Tout en sentant que ce voyage ne t’enchantera pas fort si ce sont des tableaux Delort<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> &amp; C° qui formeront surtout la collection destinée aux vertueux Belges<c type="kk">/</c> n’empêche que je te souhaite bon sang et bon voyage et bon courage surtout.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">J’ai vu la nature morte de Bernard en train<c type="kk">/</c> je la trouvais superbe<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Poignée de main à toi et à Koning.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for today’s letter and for the 100-franc note it contained. About the previous letter containing 50 francs, I received it as well, and I also wrote telling you that the day before or two days before I sent the two drawings.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> These drawings are done with a reed cut the same way as you’d cut a goose quill. I plan to do a series like that. And I hope to do better than the first two. It’s a process I already tried in Holland in the past, but I didn’t have as good reeds there as here.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Have had a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> for which please thank him — I’ll be very glad to exchange the two drawings with him for a study of his that you will choose and keep in the collection.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’ll write to him to explain the process to him, and will send him some cut reeds so that he can make some too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Now that was an important piece of news about your trip to Brussels.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> You’ll be in a position to judge how the old and highly priced merchandise is doing over there. But what a business. Because it’s indeed likely that those gentlemen are up to something.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Do you remember, we had a chat about it before I left, that with the World Exhibition coming, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_890">Bouguereau</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1158">Lefebvre</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_733">Benjamin C.</rs>, the whole clique would go to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_303">Boussod</rs> to grumble and to insist on their determination that the house of B. (the world’s leader) remain pure and faithful to the principles of the art that is truly the most civilized and the most agreeable, namely their own paintings.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Be that as it may, it certainly gives you a hell of a lot to think about. And the situation would be serious if you were to fall out with those gentlemen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I won’t hide from you that it would be a rude shock for you, not immediately, but let’s say 6 months later, because of the change it would bring about in your life. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">When a man comes out of prison after having spent a long time there, there are times when he even misses prison, because he feels disoriented once he’s at liberty, probably so called because the exhausting daily task of earning one’s living leaves one hardly any liberty. But you know all that. You’ll certainly regret some things without choosing to, even while you gain others.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I have 10 orchards now, not counting three small studies and a large one of a cherry tree that I worked to death.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">When will you be back, and what to do about the definitive consignment? Because now I have to change subjects, the orchards having mostly lost their blossom. So these orchards with the Langlois bridge <ptr target="#note-t-8"/> form a first series. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">If you prefer them to continue to dry here, that’s not bad perhaps. At the moment they’re on a covered terrace to dry.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Tell me, isn’t <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> </hi>on show at the Beaux-Arts, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs>?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Bravo as far as Daumier’s concerned, not the Beaux-Arts.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Croquis here of an orchard that I had especially intended for you to mark the first of May.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> It’s entirely bright and done entirely in one go, a riot of impastos barely tinged with yellow and lilac in the first white clump. You’ll probably be in Holland then, and over there you’ll perhaps see the same trees in blossom on that day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">What a pity about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>, let’s hope it’s nothing serious.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m very pleased to hear you’ve taken lessons in eating from young <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>, he’s very clever at that, and it’s entertaining to eat with that young sprig of an artist. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> I’m very glad you have his study of a negro woman.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Well, anyway, it will do you good to eat breakfast. I’ve done the same thing here by the way, eating 2 eggs in the morning. My stomach’s very weak but I hope I can get it back to normal, it’ll take time and patience. In any case I’m <hi rend="italics">in fact</hi> already much better than in Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Anyway, it seems you don’t exactly need a vast amount of food here, and on this occasion I also really wanted to tell you that I’m increasingly doubtful about the truth of the legend of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s absorbing huge quantities of absinthe. When I think of his work it doesn’t seem possible to me that a man who’s jittery from drink could have done it. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Perhaps that woman from the Limousin, the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343">Roquette</rs> lady, has after all put in a bit of her spiteful gossip to plant this legend.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Well then, I’m writing to you in haste, that way you’ll have my letter before you leave if it’s this coming Sunday you plan to go.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">While I feel this visit won’t delight you so much if it’s mainly paintings from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_980">Delort</rs> &amp; Co.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> that make up the collection intended for the virtuous Belgians, it doesn’t stop me saying that I wish you good health and bon voyage, and above all, good luck.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s still life when he was working on it, and I thought it superb.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Handshake to you and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter follows <ref target="let599.xml">letter 599</ref>, which was written on Thursday, 19 April. In that one Van Gogh has nine orchards on the go; in the present letter he mentions ten. Both letters include a sketch after <hi rend="italics">Orchard and house with orange roof</hi> and a reference to the failed study of a cherry tree. Vincent also says he hopes that Theo will receive this letter before he leaves on Sunday <ref target="#l-144">(ll. 144-145)</ref>, so he must have posted the letter by Saturday at the latest. We have therefore dated it on or about Friday, 20 April 1888.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">This means that Theo must have sent the 100 francs for which Vincent thanks him earlier than usual. This is explained by the fact that he was under the impression that Vincent had not received the instalment of 50 francs he had sent around 15 April (<ref target="let601.xml">see letter 601</ref>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Koning’s stay with Theo <ref target="let578.xml">(578)</ref> </p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This letter from Vincent has not survived; he addressed it wrongly and it was returned to him (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let601.xml">see letter 601</ref>).</p>

<p rend="indent">The drawings he sent must have been quite large given that in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let601.xml">letter 601</ref> Van Gogh writes that he is working on a ‘series of pen drawings of which you’ve had the first two, but in a smaller format’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-40">(ll. 40-42)</ref>. They must therefore be <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with Arles in the background</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2575">F 1516 / JH 1376</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The white orchard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2583">F 1414 / JH 1385</rs>). Both measure approx. 39.5 x 54 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh first mentioned working with a reed pen in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let168.xml">letter 168</ref> of late June 1881; according to Pickvance traces of it can be determined in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marsh with water lilies</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2335">F 845 / JH 7</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marsh </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2336">F 846 / JH 8</rs>). Van Heugten, though, believes that Van Gogh is referring here to his drawings in Nuenen, ‘however it is difficult to say exactly when he used a reed, a quill or a metal nib’. See exhib. cat. New York 1984, p. 54 and cat. Amsterdam 1997, p. 22 (quotation). Vellekoop thinks Etten is more likely and mentions in this regard <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The daughter of Jacob Meyer (after Holbein) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2339">F 833 / JH 13</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marsh with water lilies</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2335">F 845 / JH 7</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Garden with arbour </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_677">F 902 / JH 9</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 2007, p. 3, n. 17.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> did not get the two drawings that were sent (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-2">n. 2</ref>). <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The white orchard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2583">F 1414 / JH 1385</rs>) is still in the Van Gogh Museum collection. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with Arles in the background </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2575">F 1516 / JH 1376</rs>) also remained in Theo’s possession; it was sold by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> in 1924 (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 197; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-13">n. 13</ref> below, and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let614.xml#n-3">letter 614, n. 3</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Later in the letter it says that Theo was planning to go to Brussels ‘this coming Sunday’; this would have been 22 April. He cannot have returned to Paris before 12 May at the earliest, since Vincent had still not had any word from him on that date (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let609.xml">letter 609</ref>) and thanked him in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let610.xml">letter 610</ref> of about 14 May for writing so soon after he got back. It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml">letter 602</ref> that Theo combined his business trip to Brussels with a visit to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> in Breda.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo’s employers at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>. In this and the subsequent letters Van Gogh hints at a possible breach between Theo and his employers. Vincent was evidently afraid that Theo’s position was in danger because of his preference for modern art. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_890">Bouguereau</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1158">Lefebvre</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_733">Benjamin-Constant</rs> sold their work successfully through Goupil for a long time; in the 1870s people even referred to ‘The school of Goupil’. Bouguereau’s contract with Goupil was terminated as part of the reorganization of the business in 1884-1887, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs> tried to build up a new stock with new names. See Richard Thomson in exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 70-71, 76. Bouguereau and co.’s ‘grumble’ to Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie is possibly related to this.</p>

<p rend="indent">These artists were in any event very well represented at the Paris World Exhibition of 1889: Benjamin-Constant had ten works there, Lefebvre had nine, Bouguereau had fourteen. See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-3, pp. 2 (cat. nos. 59-68), 4 (cat. nos. 157-166), 18 (cat. nos. 885-893), 45 (cat. nos. 91-94).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>These ten orchards are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The pink peach tree </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2588">F 404 / JH 1391</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The pink orchard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2578">F 555 / JH 1380</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The white orchard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2576">F 403 / JH 1378</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Small pear tree in blossom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2590">F 405 / JH 1394</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with apricot trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2585">F 553 / JH 1387</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with apricot trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2581">F 556 / JH 1383</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard bordered by cypresses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2587">F 513 / JH 1389</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with peach trees in blossom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2591">F 551 / JH 1396</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2579">F 552 / JH 1381</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with pear trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2594">F 406 / JH 1399</rs>). Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let597.xml">letter 597</ref>.</p>

<p rend="indent"> The three small studies are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard bordered by cypresses</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2586">F 554 / JH 1388</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peach tree in blossom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2592">F 557 / JH 1397</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peach tree in blossom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2593">F 399 / JH 1398</rs>). They measure 32 x 40 cm, 48.5 x 38 cm and 41 x 33 cm respectively.</p>

<p rend="indent">The ‘large one of a cherry tree that I worked to death’ has not survived; Van Gogh described the work in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let599.xml">letter 599</ref> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The Pont de Langlois, pictured by Van Gogh in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Langlois bridge with washerwomen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2571">F 397 / JH 1368</rs>) and the repetition <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Langlois bridge with washerwomen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2589">F 571 / JH 1392</rs>). Since Van Gogh had intended the first work for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>, he must have the repetition for Theo in mind here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>See for this terrace: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let599.xml#n-7">letter 599, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1043">Gavarni</rs> was on show in the exhibition of caricatures in the Ecole des Beaux-Arts in Paris from 17 April. See exhib. cat. Paris 1888, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Revue Indépendante</hi>, no. 19 (May 1888), vol. 7, p. 382.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Theo turned 31 on 1 May. The painting meant for him was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with pear trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2594">F 406 / JH 1399</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
      
<p>Apparently <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>, who was employed  in an engineering works in Lincoln, was ill or had some other problem. On 18 March his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> had told Theo that she had received good reports about her youngest son (FR b2417). Vincent himself had little contact with him: Cor wrote to Theo from Lincoln on 16 October 1888: ‘How’s Vincent getting on? I never hear anything from him now, except something about he’s going to Algiers or is there ... Don’t think that even though I don’t write often I’ve forgotten you, because in fact you’re my only brother’ (FR b3706).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Three paintings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Arnold Koning</rs> from Theo’s collection are candidates; all three are titled <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a Gypsy woman</hi> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1016">Ill. 1016</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2189">Ill. 2189</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2190">2190</rs>. See for the works that Koning (possibly) gave Theo: exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 157, 160, 206 (n. 16).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>After this Van Gogh crossed out: ‘si multiple et si constant’ (so varied and so constant).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>By ‘<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343">La Roquette</rs>’ Van Gogh meant the wife of the art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_342">François Joseph Delarebeyrette</rs>, who carried on the trade in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s with her son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_344">Gabriel</rs> after her husband’s death in 1886. Van Gogh refers to the son as ‘Gabriel de la Roquette’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let625.xml">see letter 625</ref>). This must have been a nickname since the woman’s full name was Evelina Delarebeyrette-Lassarre and her son is always referred to in official documents as Gabriel Delarebeyrette.</p>

<p rend="indent">In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml">letter 686</ref> Vincent talks about ‘Madame de Larebey la Roquette’, so we know that he did know her real name; Theo also calls her ‘La Roquette’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let830.xml">see letter 830</ref>). They may have called her this because she was so touchy and liable to fly off the handle – a ‘roquette’ is a rocket – the fact that it sounds something like ‘Delarebeyrette’ may also have been a factor. The Delarebeyrettes came from the department of Creuse in the Limousin, a region in central France (Archives de Paris).</p>

<p rend="indent">Although <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s legendary consumption of alcohol sounds somewhat exaggerated, he must nonetheless have been a heavy drinker. He used to do the rounds of the bars in Marseille to sell his paintings, and from 1880 onwards he only ever received buyers in his local, Café Plauchut. See Alauzen and Ripert 1969, p. 153.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The popular genre and history painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_980">Charles Edouard Delort</rs>, a pupil of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1044">Gérôme</rs>, made his debut at the 1864 Salon and painted chiefly anecdotal, eighteenth-century costume pieces and Oriental scenes. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is most probably referring here to one of the still lifes he saw at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s before he left Paris: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life: the blue coffee-pot</hi>, 1888 (Bremen, Kunsthalle) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life: earthenware pot and apples </hi>(Paris, Musée d’Orsay). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2179">Ill. 2179</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_567">Ill. 567</rs>. He was full of praise for these still lifes in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let655.xml">letter 655</ref> to Bernard. It is not possible to tell which of the two he means here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    