<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Friday, 4 May 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let603"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b521 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>603</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>481</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>605</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-05-04">Friday, 4 May 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0521 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0521 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000700_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0521 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0521 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000701_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">hier j’ai été chez des marchands de meubles pour voir si je pourrais louer un lit &amp;c. Malheureusement on ne louait <hi rend="italics">pas</hi> et même on refusait de vendre à condition de payer tant par mois<c type="kp">_</c>– Ceci est assez embarassant. J’y ai pensé maintenant que peut-être – dans le cas où Koning partirait après avoir vu le Salon comme je crois que d’abord c’était son intention, tu pourrais après son départ m’envoyer le lit qu’il occupe maintenant.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Il faut considérer que si je couche à l’atelier cela fait pourtant une différence au bout d’un an de ± 300 fr. que sans cela on paye dans l’hôtel<c type="kp">_</c> Je sais bien qu’il est pas possible de dire d’avance: je resterai ici autant de temps<c type="kk">/</c> toutefois j’ai tant de raisons pour croire un long sejour ici probable.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">J’ai été hier à Fontvieille chez M<hi rend="super">c</hi> Knight – il avait un pastel bien – un arbre rose – deux aquarelles commencées<c type="kk">/</c> et je le trouvais en train de faire une tête de vieille femme au fusain. Il est dans la periode où les nouvelles theories de couleur le tourmentent et tout en lui empêchant de faire selon le vieux système<c type="kk">/</c> il n’est pas assez le maître de sa palette nouvelle pour pouvoir réussir de cette façon.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Il paraissait très gêné de me les montrer<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai dû y aller expres ainsi et lui dire que je voulais voir <hi rend="italics">absolument</hi> son travail<c type="kk">/</c> maintenant il n’est pas impossible qu’il vienne rester<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> avec moi quelque temps ici<c type="kp">_</c>– Alors nous y gagnerions<c type="kk">/</c> je crois<c type="kk">/</c> des deux côtés.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Très souvent je pense à <hi rend="italics">Renoir</hi> ici et son dessin pur et net<c type="kp">_</c> C’est bien comme ça que sont les objets ou personnages ici dans la clarté<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Nous avons énormement du vent et du mistral ici<c type="kk">/</c> actuellement 3 jours sur quatre<c type="kk">/</c> toujours avec du soleil pourtant mais il est alors difficile de travailler dehors.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Je crois qu’il y aurait quelque chose à faire ici pour le portrait<c type="kp">_</c>– Si les gens sont d’une ignorance crasse en tant que quant à la peinture<c type="kk">/</c> en géneral ils sont <hi rend="italics">bien plus artistes </hi>que dans le nord pour leur propre figure et leur propre vie<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai vu ici des figures certes aussi belles que des Goya et des Velasquez<c type="kp">_</c> Elles savent vous ficher une note rose dans un costume noir<c type="kk">/</c> ou bien confectionner un habillement blanc jaune rose ou encore vert et rose ou encore <hi rend="italics">bleu</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italics">jaune</hi> où il n’y a rien à changer au point de vue artistique. Seurat trouverait ici des figures d’hommes très pittoresques malgré leurs costumes modernes.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Maintenant j’ose dire que ces gens d’ici mordraient au portrait<c type="kp">_</c> Mais moi<c type="kk">/</c> avant d’oser risquer de me lancer là-dedans<c type="kk">/</c> veux d’abord avoir mon organisme nerveux tranquilisé et puis je veux être établi d’une façon qu’on puisse recevoir les gens à l’atelier. Et si je dois te dire le gros mot<c type="kk">/</c> de mon calcul pour me porter bien et être acclimatisé pour de bon ici 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>il me faudra un an et pour m’établir il faudra bien mille francs<c type="kp">_</c> Si dans la premiere année – la courante – je dépenserais 100 francs pour vivre &amp; 100 francs pour cet établissement par mois<c type="kk">/</c> tu vois qu’il ne resterait pas un sou dans ce budget pour peindre<c type="kp">_</c> Mais au bout de cette annee j’aurais gagné et mon établissement un peu bien et ma santé<c type="kk">/</c> je suis porté à le croire.– Et mon occupation en attendant serait surtout de dessiner tous les jours avec en plus deux ou trois tableaux par mois<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Dans – l’établissement – je compte alors aussi un renouvellement complet de linge &amp; de vêtements et de chaussures<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Et je serais un autre homme au bout de l’année<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’aurais un chez moi et j’aurais mon calme pour la santé<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>Et alors je puis espérer de ne pas tomber essoufflé avant le temps ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Monticelli etait plus vigoureux que moi je pense au physique et si j’en avais la force je vivrais au jour le jour comme lui<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Mais si lui-même a été paralysé et cela sans être si buveur que ça<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – moi à plus forte raison ne pourrais résister<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">J’étais surement sur le droit chemin d’attrapper une paralysie quand j’ai quitté Paris. Ça m’a joliment pris après! Quand j’ai cessé de boire<c type="kk">/</c> quand j’ai cessé de tant fumer<c type="kk">/</c> quand j’ai recommencé à réfléchir au lieu de chercher à ne pas penser – mon dieu quelles mélancolies et quel abattement<c type="kp">_</c>– Le travail dans cette magnifique nature m’a soutenu au moral mais encore là<c type="kk">/</c> au bout de certains efforts les forces me manquaient.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Eh bien voila pourquoi lorsque je t’écrivais l’autre jour je disais que si tu quittais les Goupil tu te sentirais mieux au moral probable mais que la guérison serait très douloureuse.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> tandis que la maladie même<c type="kk">/</c> on ne la sent pas<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Mon pauvre ami<c type="kk">/</c> notre nevrose &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> vient bien aussi de notre facon de vivre un peu trop artistique – mais elle est aussi un héritage fatal puisque dans la civilisation on va en s’affaiblissant de génération en génération.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Prends notre soeur Wil<c type="kk">/</c> elle n’a ni bu ni fait la noce<c type="kk">/</c> et nous connaissons un portrait d’elle pourtant où elle a le regard d’une folle<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Cela prouve-t-il assez que si nous voulons envisager en face le vrai état de notre tempérament il faut nous ranger dans le nombre de ceux qui souffrent d’une nevrose qui vient déjà de loin.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je crois Gruby<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> dans le vrai pour ces cas-là<c type="kk">/</c> bien manger<c type="kk">/</c> bien vivre<c type="kk">/</c> voir peu de femmes<c type="kk">/</c> en un mot vivre d’avance absolument comme si on avait déjà une maladie cérébrale et une maladie de la moelle sans compter la névrose<c type="kk">/</c> qui elle existe réellement.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Certes c’est là prendre le taureau par les cornes<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui n’est pas une mauvaise politique<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Et de Gas – fait comme ça et réussit<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Tout de même ne sens tu pas comme moi que c’est rudement dur<c type="kp">_</c> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Et est ce que en somme cela ne fait pas énormément du bien d’écouter les sages conseils de Rivet<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> et de Pangloss<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> ces excellents optimistes de vraie et joviale race Gauloise qui vous laissent votre amour propre<c type="kp">_</c> Pourtant si nous voulons vivre et travailler<c type="kk">/</c> il faut être très prudent et nous soigner<c type="kp">_</c>– De l’eau froide<c type="kk">/</c> de l’air<c type="kk">/</c> nourriture simple et bonne<c type="kk">/</c> être bien vêtu<c type="kk">/</c> etre bien couché et ne pas avoir des embêtements. Et pas se laisser aller aux femmes et à la vraie vie dans la mesure qu’on serait porté à désirer<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22"><hi rend="italics">Je n’y tiens pas</hi> de coucher à l’atelier mais <hi>si</hi> j’allais y coucher alors ce serait dans le cas où je verrais possibilité de m’établir un peu définitivement et pour une longue période<c type="kp">_</c> N’ayant maintenant aucunément besoin de place dans l’hotêl vu que j’ai l’atelier ailleurs<c type="kk">/</c> je mettrai les gens bon gré mal gré à 3 francs par jour.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Et conséquemment il n’y a rien qui presse. Mais si cela t’est égal envoie moi tout de même 100 fr<c type="kp">_</c> la prochaine fois vu que je voudrais aussi me faire faire des caleçons de même que j’ai fait faire des chemises et des chaussures, et que je dois donner faire nettoyer et reparer presque tous les vêtements. Alors ils seront encore très bons. Cela c’est d’urgence pour le cas que j’aurais à aller à Marseille ou à voir des gens ici. Pour toutes ces précautions qu’on prend maintenant on est plus sûr de pouvoir résister à la longue et régulariser le travail.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Il y a une dizaine de toiles pour lesquels je cherche une caisse et que j’expédierai de ces jours ci<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Je te serre bien la main ainsi qu’à Koning. J’ai reçu une carte postale de Koning pour dire qu’il avait reçu une lettre pour reprendre les tableaux aux Indépendants.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Mais il n’avait naturellement qu’à les reprendre<c type="kk">/</c> qu’y puis je moi. </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p> 
<p xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">(il va sans dire que s’il y avait chez toi des toiles qui prendraient trop de place tu pourrais les envoyer ici petite vitesse et je les garderais à l’atelier ici. Si tel n’est pas encore le cas cela le sera plus tard<c type="kk">/</c> aussi je garde ici bien des etudes qui me semblent pas assez bonnes pour t’être envoyees<c type="kp">_</c>)</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Yesterday I went to visit some furniture dealers to see if I could rent a bed, &amp;c. Unfortunately they do<hi rend="italics"> not </hi>rent, and even refused to sell on terms of paying so much per month. This is rather awkward. Now I’ve thought that perhaps — if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> were to leave after seeing the Salon, as I believe was his original intention, after he left you could send me the bed he’s occupying now.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">We have to consider that if I sleep at the studio, that makes a difference after all of around 300 francs at the end of a year, which is otherwise spent at the hotel. I’m quite aware that it’s not possible to say in advance: I’ll stay here for such or such a length of time; however, I have many reasons to believe that a long stay here is likely. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Yesterday I was at Fontvieille, at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs>’s — he had a good pastel — a pink tree — two watercolours under way, and I found him working on a head of an old woman in charcoal. He’s at the stage when the new colour theories are tormenting him, and while they prevent him from doing things according to the old system, he hasn’t sufficiently mastered his new palette to be able to succeed this way.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> He seemed very embarrassed to show them to me, so I had to go there specially and tell him I <hi rend="italics">very much </hi>wanted to see his work, and now it’s not impossible that he may come to stay with me here for a while. Then we would benefit, I think, on both sides.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I very often think of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1293">Renoir</rs></hi> here and his pure, clean drawing. That’s just the way objects or figures are here, in the clear light.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">We have a tremendous amount of wind and mistral here, 3 days out of four at the moment, always with sunshine, though, but then it’s difficult to work out of doors. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I think something could be done here in the way of portraits. People may be crassly ignorant as far as painting goes, but in general they’re <hi rend="italics">much more artistic </hi>than in the north in their own appearance and their own lives. I’ve seen figures here as lovely as those of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1402">Velázquez</rs>. They know how to stick a touch of pink on a black suit, or make a white, yellow, pink or green and pink, or <hi rend="italics">blue and yellow</hi> outfit, in which nothing needs to be changed from the artistic point of view. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1353">Seurat</rs> would find some very picturesque figures of men here, despite their modern suits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Now I dare say these people here would jump at portraits. But, before daring to take the risk of throwing myself into that, I want my nervous system to calm down first, and then I want to be settled in such a way that we can receive people at the studio. And if I have to mention the big subject, by my calculations to be in good health and be acclimatized here once and for all 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I’ll need a year, and to establish myself I’ll need a good thousand francs. If in the first year — the current one — I spent 100 francs to live and 100 francs for this establishment per month, you can see there wouldn’t be a sou left in this budget for painting. But by the end of this year I’m inclined to believe I’d have gained both my quite decent establishment and my health. And my occupation while waiting would above all be to spend every day drawing, with two or three paintings a month in addition.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">In — the establishment — I thus also count a complete renewal of all my linen and clothes and shoes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And I would be a different man by the end of the year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’d have a home and I’d have my peace of mind about my health. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> And so I can hope not to collapse out of breath before my time, here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> was physically more vigorous than I am, I think, and if I had the strength I would live like him, one day at a time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">But if he became paralyzed, and without being that much of a drinker<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — all the more reason why I couldn’t withstand it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I was certainly well on the way to catching a paralysis when I left Paris. It caught up with me afterwards, right enough! When I stopped drinking, when I stopped smoking so much, when I started reflecting on things again instead of trying not to think — my God, what melancholias and what dejection. Working in this magnificent nature kept up my morale, but there too, after a certain amount of effort I didn’t have the strength. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Ah well, that’s why when I was writing to you the other day I said that if you left the Goupils you would probably feel better in terms of morale but the recovery would be very painful.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> While the sickness itself, you don’t feel it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">My poor friend, our neurosis &amp;c. surely also comes from our rather too artistic way of life — but it’s also a fatal inheritance, since in civilization we go on becoming weaker from generation to generation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Take our sister <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs>, she has neither drunk nor led a wild life, and yet we know a photograph of her in which she has the look of a madwoman.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Isn’t that proof enough that if we want to look the true state of our temperament in the face we have to range ourselves among those who suffer from a neurosis that goes back a good long way. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_446">Gruby</rs>’s<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> in the right in these cases: eat well, live well, see few women, in a word live in anticipation just as though one already had a brain disease and a disease of the marrow, not to mention neurosis, which really does exist.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Certainly that’s taking the bull by the horns, which isn’t a bad policy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_981">Degas</rs> — does that and is successful.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> All the same, don’t you feel, as I do, it’s awfully hard?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">And in short doesn’t it do us a tremendous amount of good to listen to the wise advice of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Rivet</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and Pangloss,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> those splendid optimists of the true and jovial Gallic race who leave you your self-esteem? Yet, if we want to live and work, we must be very careful and look after ourselves. Cold water, air, good simple food, wear the right clothes, sleep in a good bed and don’t have worries. And not letting yourself go with the women and real life to the extent you might like to. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"><hi rend="italics">I’m not set on </hi>sleeping at the studio but <hi>if</hi> I went to sleep there, it would be if I could see the possibility of establishing myself more or less for good and for a long period of time. Having no need at all now of space at the hotel, since I have the studio elsewhere, I’ll tell the people it’s 3 francs a day, take it or leave it.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> And consequently there’s nothing pressing. But if it’s all the same to you, send me 100 francs anyway next time, as I’d also like to have some drawers made, the way I had shirts and shoes made, and as I have to have almost all my clothes cleaned and mended. Then they’ll still be perfectly good. This is urgent, in case I’d have to go to Marseille or see people here. With all these precautions we’re taking now we can be more certain of being able to hold out in the long term and of putting our work in order.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">There are about ten canvases, for which I’m looking for a crate and which I’ll send you in the next few days.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I shake your hand firmly, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>’s too. I had a postcard from Koning to say he’d received a letter to collect the paintings from the Independents.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> But of course he just had to collect them, what can I do about it?</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">(It goes without saying that if at your home there were canvases that were taking up too much space you could send them here by goods train and I’d keep them in the studio here. If that isn’t yet the case it will be later, so I keep quite a few studies here that don’t seem good enough to me to be sent to you.)</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In the previous letter <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref>, which dates from 1 May, Van Gogh says he wants to go and look for furniture for his house ‘today or tomorrow morning’. In the present letter he wrote that he had been to see furniture dealers ‘yesterday’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). Since Jo van Gogh-Bonger gave the date as 4 May in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, and she may have had a postmark to go on, we have dated the letter Friday, 4 May 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The possibility that Theo will leave Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie <ref target="let600.xml">(600)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The plan to exhibit work by modern artists in Marseille <ref target="let580.xml">(580)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Koning’s stay with Theo <ref target="let578.xml">(578)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Entry for the 1888 Indépendants exhibition <ref target="let582.xml">(582)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>, who was lodging with Theo in Paris, went back to the Netherlands on 30 May. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let616.xml#n-4">See letter 616, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>These works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> cannot be identified. With the exception of a number of pastels dating from the 1880s and early 1890s, he painted virtually nothing but watercolours. His palette is characterized by unusual combinations of contrasting colours and reveals the influence of the Impressionists and Post-Impressionists. See exhib. cat. New York 1998, p. 198.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habiter’. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In the last years of his life <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> suffered a series of strokes that left him partially paralyzed. See Alauzen and Ripert 1969, pp. 159, 163, 165. See for Monticelli’s drinking: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-14">letter 600, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written about this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml">letter 600</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In the estate there are various photographs of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> at about 20 years old; Van Gogh may have had one of these portraits in mind. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2183">Ill. 2183</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3113">Ill. 3113</rs>. It is difficult to say how old she is in these photographs, but judging by Van Gogh’s remark the second is the most likely. Later Willemien actually did go mad; she died in an asylum in 1941.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_446">David Gruby</rs>, who lived at 66 rue Saint-Lazare in Paris, was a well-known homeopathic doctor whom Theo and Vincent consulted. They knew him through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs>, who had been a patient of his since March 1882 (FR b1697). Gruby was known as a ‘psychological doctor’, who believed that health revolved around equilibrium and regarded illness as the consequence of a disturbance of the balance. See L. le Leu,<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Le Dr Gruby. Notes et souvenirs</hi>. Paris 1908.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_981">Edgar Degas</rs> was a bachelor and on several occasions Van Gogh expressed his respect for the fact that Degas had adapted his lifestyle to serve his art. Cf. Kendall 1999, pp. 38-39.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>See for the doctor <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Louis Rivet:</rs> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-9">letter 578, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The philosopher Pangloss is a character in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_445">Candide</rs></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let568.xml#n-3">see letter 568, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was staying in Hotel-Restaurant Carrel: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let577.xml#n-4">see letter 577, n. 4.</ref> The hotel <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_42 bio.xml#_43">owner</rs> had complained that Van Gogh’s paintings took up too much room (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let601.xml">letter 601</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>See for this proposed consignment: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml#n-11">letter 602, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>This question is clarified to some extent in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let605.xml">letter 605</ref>, where we learn that the organizers of the Indépendants exhibition had announced that the paintings that had been submitted had to be collected on 5 and 6 May (the exhibition closed on 3 May); <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>, however, had misunderstood, and thought that it was 5 and 6 April. See for the exhibited works: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let582.xml#n-9">letter 582, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    