<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Monday, 25 June 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let631"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b545 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>631</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>504</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>640</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-06-25">on or about Monday, 25 June 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0545 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0545 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000730_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0545 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0545 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000731_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Si nous prenons une pièce entière de toile ordinaire voici alors le prix net que je viens d’apprendre par hasard:<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3"><hi rend="italics">Toile ordinaire jaune à grain</hi> <hi rend="italics">N</hi><hi rend="super"><hi rend="italics">o</hi></hi><hi rend="italics"> 0</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Largeur deux mètres</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Piece entière 10 mètres de long</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Prix 40 francs</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">la remise est certainement de 25%; probablement prix de fabrique – de première main – 33 1/3%<c type="kp">_</c></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> 

<p xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Voici donc une occasion pour vérifier les prix de Tasset. Laissant de côté ou non les 5 mètres que j’avais demandées<c type="kk">/</c> le mieux serait de prendre une piece entière<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ayant récemment acheté des toiles dont je garderai les chassis l’avantage est sérieux<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Pour faire une toile de 30 – ne comptant pas le chassis que j’ai – la toile me coûte pas 1.50 (au prix susmentionné) et actuellement avec le chassis 4 fr. Comptez 1 fr<c type="kp">_</c> pour le chassis – qui coute moins; sur chaque toile de 30 cela fait une difference de 1.50 et plus. ce plus va pour le port qui sera de 5 francs.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Vois un peu – si tu peux – ce que dit Tasset lorsque tu lui demanderas prix de la pièce<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> mais ce que je te dis pour le prix de la piece est ainsi et tu pourras comparer.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Te rappelles tu dans les petits dessins un pont de bois avec lavoir – une vue de ville dans le fond.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> je viens de peindre ce motif-là en grand format.–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Je dois te prévenir que tout le monde va trouver que je travaille trop vite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">N’en crois rien<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">N’est ce pas l’emotion<c type="kk">/</c> la sincérité du sentiment de la nature qui nous mène et – si ces émotions sont quelquefois si fortes qu’on travaille – sans sentir qu’on travaille – lorsque quelquefois les touches viennent avec une suite et des rapports entre eux comme les mots dans un discours ou dans une lettre –</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">il faut alors se souvenir que cela n’a pas toujours été ainsi et que dans l’avenir il y aura aussi bien des jours lourds sans inspiration<c type="kp">_</c> Donc il faut battre le fer pendant qu’il est chaud et mettre les barres forgées de côté.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Je n’ai pas encore la moitié des 50 toiles présentables en public et il me les faut toutes dans cette année.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je sais d’avance que l’on les critiquera d’<hi rend="italics">hâtives</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Je sais aussi que j’espère bien garder mon raisonnement de cet hiver lorsque nous avons causé d’une association d’artistes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Non pas que je garde grande envie ou espoir pour la réaliser mais cela étant un raisonnement sérieux<c type="kk">/</c> reste à garder son sérieux et garder le droit d’y revenir<c type="kk">/</c> sur cette question<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Si Gauguin ne viendrait pas travailler avec moi alors je n’ai d’autre ressource pour contre<c type="shy">-</c>balancer mes dépenses que mon travail.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Cette perspective ne m’effraye que médiocrement<c type="kp">_</c> Si la santé ne me trahit pas j’abbatrai mes toiles et dans le nombre il y en aura qui pourront aller.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Je suis presque reconcilié avec le verger qui n’était pas sur chassis et son pendant au pointillé<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Dans le nombre ils pourront aller<c type="kp">_</c> Seulement je travaille avec <hi rend="italics">moins de mal</hi> en pleine chaleur qu’alors au printemps.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Bientôt je t’enverrai quelques toiles roulées et les autres à fur &amp; à mesure que cela soit possible de les rouler.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Je voudrais bien doubler la commande pour les <hi rend="italics">blancs</hi> <hi rend="italics">de zinc</hi>. Ce blanc de zinc est un peu cause que ça sèche si lentement mais il a d’autres avantages dans les melanges.–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Est ce que cela ne faisait pas plaisir chez Guillaumin cet hiver – d’y trouver le palier et l’escalier même<c type="kk">/</c> sans compter l’atelier – tout plein de toiles. Tu comprends dès lors que j’ai une certaine ambition non pour le <hi rend="italics">nombre</hi> de toiles mais pour que l’ensemble de ces toiles tout de même représente un vrai labeur de ta part autant que de ma part.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Les blés cela a été une occasion de travailler comme les vergers en fleurs.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Et je n’ai que juste le temps pour me préparer pour la nouvelle campagne<c type="kk">/</c> celle des vignes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Et entre les deux je voudrais encore faire des marines.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Les vergers representaient le rose et le blanc<c type="kk">/</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">les bles le jaune<c type="kk">/</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">les marines le bleu<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Peutêtre que maintenant je vais un peu chercher des verts<c type="kp">_</c> Or l’automne – cela donne toute la gamme de la lyre<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-b"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">Je suis bien curieux de savoir ce que fera Gauguin – le principal c’est de ne pas le décourager – je pense toujours que tout son plan n’était qu’une toquade<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Sais tu ce que je voudrais encore te repéter à toi – ceci – que mes désirs personnels sont subordonnés à l’interet de plusieurs et qu’il me semble toujours qu’un autre pourrait profiter de l’argent que je dépense seul<c type="kp">_</c> Soit Vignon<c type="kk">/</c> soit Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> soit Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> soit un autre.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">Et que pour ces combinaisons<c type="kk">/</c> même si elles entraineraient mon déplacement<c type="kk">/</c> je suis prêt<c type="kp">_</c> Deux personnes qui s’entendent ne dépensent – et même trois – pas beaucoup plus qu’un.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Pas non plus en couleur.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Alors – sans compter le surplus de travaux accomplis – il y aurait pour toi la satisfaction d’en nourrir deux ou trois au lieu d’un.–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.39" n="39">Ceci pour plus tot ou plus tard<c type="kp">_</c> Et pourvu que moi je sois aussi fort que les autres<c type="kp">_</c> saches bien ceci que difficilement on pourrait être trompé vu que s’ils font des difficultés pour travailler je les connais aussi ces difficultés.– et je saurais ce qui en était peut-être.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.40" n="40">Or on aurait parfaitement le droit – et même possiblement le devoir – de pousser au travail<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.41" n="41">Et voilà ce qu’il faut faire.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.42" n="42">Si je suis seul ma foi je n’y peux rien – j’ai alors moins le besoin de compagnie que celui d’un travail effréné et voilà pourquoi hardiment je commande toile et couleurs. Alors seulement je ressens la vie lorsque je pousse raide le travail<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.43" n="43">Et en compagnie j’en sentirais un peu moins le besoin ou plutôt je travaillerais à des choses plus compliquées.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.44" n="44">Mais isolé je ne compte que sur mon exaltation dans de certains moments et je me laisse 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>aller à des extravagances alors<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.45" n="45">Ainsi les toiles que j’ai achetees ici il n’y a vraiment pas longtemps sont à peu près toutes couvertes<c type="kp">_</c> Lorsque je t’enverrai des toiles roulées tu pourras peut-être ôter des chassis pas mal de chôses sans conséquence.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.46" n="46">De façon à pouvoir à la fin de l’année disons en montrer 50 à Pissarro et aux autres<c type="kp">_</c>– Et le reste cela c’est des études qui seront un fonds de renseignements et étant bien séchées on peut les garder en portefeuille ou dans une armoire sans que cela prenne beaucoup de place.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.47" n="47">Poignée de main à toi et aux copains si tu en vois<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.48" n="48">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.49" n="49">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">If we take a whole piece of ordinary canvas, this is the net price, which I’ve just found out by chance:<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><hi rend="italics">Ordinary rough yellow canvas, no. 0</hi><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Width two metres</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Whole piece 10 metres long</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Price 40 francs</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The discount is definitely 25%; probably the price from the factory — at first hand — 33 1/3%.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">So here’s an opportunity to check <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_784">Tasset</rs>’s prices. Leaving aside, or not, the 5 metres that I’d requested, the best thing would be to take a whole piece.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Having recently bought some canvases from which I’ll keep the stretching frames, it’s a big saving.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">To do a no. 30 canvas — not counting the stretching frame, which I have — the canvas doesn’t cost me 1.50 (at the price quoted above) and at present, with the stretching frame, 4 francs. Count 1 franc for the stretching frame — which costs less; on every no. 30 canvas that makes a difference of 1.50, and more. This extra goes for carriage, which will be 5 francs. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">See — if you can — what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs> says when you ask him the price by the piece, but what I’m telling you about the price by the piece is just so, and you’ll be able to compare.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Do you remember among the small drawings a wooden bridge with a washing-place — a view of a town in the background?<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’ve just painted that subject in large format.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I must warn you that everyone will find that I work too quickly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Don’t you believe a word of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Isn’t it the emotion, the sincerity of our feeling for nature, that leads us and — if these emotions are sometimes so strong that we work — without feeling that we’re working — when sometimes the brushstrokes come in a sequence and in relation one to another like the words in a speech or a letter — 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> then we have to remember that it hasn’t always been like that, and that in the future there will also be quite a few heavy days without inspiration. So we have to strike while the iron’s hot and lay aside the bars we forge.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t yet have half of the 50 canvases fit to be presented in public, and I need all of them by the end of this year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I know in advance that they’ll be criticized as <hi rend="italics">hasty</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I also know that I very much hope to stick to my argument of the past winter, when we talked about an association of artists.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Not that I still have a great desire or hope to bring it about, but as it was a serious argument, we have to retain our seriousness and retain the right to come back to it, to this question.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> weren’t to come to work with me, then I have no other resources to balance my expenses but my work. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">This prospect only mildly frightens me. If my health doesn’t let me down I’ll do a whole heap of my canvases and out of that lot there’ll be some that will do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">I’m almost reconciled with the orchard, which wasn’t on a stretching frame, and its pendant with the stippling.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Out of the whole lot, they’ll do. But I’m working with <hi rend="italics">less trouble </hi>in the full heat than back in the spring.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Soon I’ll send you some rolled canvases, and the rest as and when it’s possible to roll them up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I’d very much like to double the order for the <hi rend="italics">zinc whites</hi>. This zinc white is part of the reason why everything dries so slowly, but it has other advantages in the mixtures. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Wasn’t it pleasant at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>’s last winter — finding the landing and even the stairs, not to mention the studio — chock-full of canvases? You understand since then that I have a certain ambition, not about the <hi rend="italics">number </hi>of canvases, but that these canvases as a whole should, after all, represent a real labour on your part as well as mine.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The wheatfields — that has been an opportunity to work, like the orchards in blossom.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">And I only just have time to prepare myself for the new campaign, the one on the vineyards.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And between the two I’d like to do some more seascapes.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">The orchards represented pink and white, the wheatfields yellow, the seascapes blue.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Perhaps now I’ll have a try at doing greens. Now autumn — that gives you the whole range of tones. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">I’m quite curious to know what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> will do — the main thing is not to discourage him — I still think his whole plan was just a whim.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Do you know what I’d like to tell you once again — this — that my personal desires are subordinate to the interests of a number of people, and that it always seems to me that another person could benefit from the money I spend by myself. Either <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1415">Vignon</rs>, or Gauguin, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, or someone else.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">And that for these arrangements, even if they’d involve my moving, I’m prepared. Two people who get along don’t spend — and even three — much more than one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">No more on colours, either.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">So — without counting the surplus of finished works — there would be the satisfaction for you of providing for two or three people instead of one. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">This for sooner or later. And as long as I’m as strong as the others. You can be sure of this, that it would be hard for us to be deceived, seeing that if they make difficulties about working, I know those difficulties too. And I’d perhaps know what it was all about.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Now, we’d have a perfect right — and perhaps even a duty — to urge them to work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">And that’s what we have to do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">If I’m alone, my word, I can’t do anything about that — then I have less need for company than for frantic work, and that’s why I’m boldly ordering canvas and paints. And so I only feel life when I’m working at full stretch.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">And in company I’d feel a bit less need to do that, or rather, I’d work on more complicated things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">But in isolation I can count only on my excitement at certain moments, and then I let myself 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/> run to extravagances.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">And so the canvases I bought here really not so long ago are almost all covered. When I send you the rolled up canvases you could perhaps take quite a few unimportant things off their stretching frames.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">So as to be able, at the end of the year, let’s say, to show 50 of them to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> and the others. And the rest, it’s studies, which will be a source of information, and being thoroughly dried, we can keep them in a portfolio or in a cupboard without their taking up a lot of space.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Handshake to you, and to the pals if you see any of them.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.45" n="45">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.46" n="46">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter must date from after <ref target="let630.xml">letter 630</ref> of 23 June in which Van Gogh is still complaining about the rain, and before <ref target="let634.xml">letter 634</ref> of about 28 June in which he writes that he worked on the sower yesterday and today. This sower – an important subject to him – is not mentioned in the present letter. The remark ‘The wheatfields – that has been an opportunity to work’ <ref target="#l-116">(l. 116)</ref>, and the fact that he told Bernard on 27 June (<ref target="let633.xml#l-65">letter 633, l. 65</ref>) ‘I have seven studies of wheatfields’ also place the letter in the last week of June. This is borne out by his statement that he bought his canvases ‘really not so long ago’ <ref target="#l-186">(l. 186)</ref> – and that was shortly before 15 June (<ref target="let625.xml">see letter 625</ref>) – and his request to Theo to double the order for zinc white <ref target="#l-100">(l. 100)</ref> – this refers to <ref target="let629.xml">letter 629</ref> of 21 June, in which Vincent asked for new paint from Tasset. For all these reasons we, like Merlhès, have dated the letter on or about Monday, 25 June 1888.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The letter has given rise to various datings. Pickvance put the date at about 16 June, but given that Van Gogh bought new canvas between 12 and 15 June and he says in the present letter that he has painted on all he has, this seems highly unlikely. Hulsker and <hi rend="italics">De brieven </hi>1990 dated it about 7 July, but it is clear from the letter that it has not yet been decided that Gauguin will go to Arles (see <ref target="#l-79">ll. 79</ref> ff. and <ref target="#l-132">ll. 132</ref> ff.), whereas this was known on 1 July (<ref target="let635.xml">letter 635</ref>). Dorn, finally, dated the <ref target="let027.xml">letter 27</ref> June (see Hulsker 1993-1, p. 32; Dorn 1998, p. 25).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plans for a society of artists <ref target="let584.xml">(584)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let639.xml">letter 639</ref> Van Gogh said that he knew what the price of ‘ordinary canvas’ was through the catalogue of the Parisian paint merchant <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_302">Bourgeois</rs>. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let625.xml">letter 625</ref> he had suggested ordering this type of canvas from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs>. He had enclosed a new order for Tasset with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let629.xml">letter 629</ref>; it no doubt included the five metres of canvas he mentions later in this letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>‘Toile jaune’ (literally ‘yellow canvas’) is coarse canvas that has not been bleached.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘à la pièce’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Canal with bridge and washerwomen</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2596">F 1473 / JH 1405</rs>). Theo had received the drawing in May; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml#n-1">see letter 602, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Canal with washerwomen </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2659">F 427 / JH 1490</rs>), which measures 74 x 61 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The paintings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard bordered by cypresses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2587">F 513 / JH 1389</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard with peach trees in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2591">F 551 / JH 1396</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Conflation of two expressions: ‘toute la gamme’ (the whole gamut from first to last) and ‘toute la lyre’ (the whole caboodle).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>See for Van Gogh’s paintings of orchards in blossom in March-April 1888: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-7;">letter 600, n. 7;</ref> for his paintings of wheatfields: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let629.xml#n-3">letter 629, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let623.xml#n-4">See letter 623, n. 4,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s plan.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    