<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Emile Bernard. Arles, Wednesday, 27 June 1888. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let633"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>New York</settlement>
                                        <institution>Thaw Collection</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>633</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>B9</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>636</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-06-27">Wednesday, 27 June 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Emile Bernard</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 2 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 2 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Bernard –</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">je ne sais ce que j’ai fourré dans ma lettre d’hier à la place du feuillet ci-inclus<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> ayant rapport à ton dernier sonnet. Le cas est que je suis si éreinté par le travail que le soir – quoique cela me repose d’écrire – je suis comme une machine détraquée<c type="kk">/</c> tellement la journée en plein soleil m’a fatigué d’un autre côté. et c’est pourquoi j’ai fourré dans la lettre un autre feuillet à la place de celui-ci.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">En relisant le feuillet d’hier – ma foi je te l’envoie tel quel<c type="kk">/</c> pour moi en le relisant il me semble lisible et donc je te l’envoie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Aujourd’hui encore journée raide de travail.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Si tu voyais mes toiles qu’en dirais-tu – tu n’y trouverais pas le coup de brosse presque timide et consciencieux de Cezanne<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Mais puisqu’actuellement je peins la même campagne de la Crau &amp; Camargue – quoiqu’à un endroit un peu divergent – toutefois il pourrait y demeurer certains rapports de couleur<c type="kp">_</c>– Qu’en sais-je – involontairement j’ai de temps en temps pensé à Cezanne<c type="kk">/</c> justement lorsque je me suis rendu compte de sa touche si malhabile dans certaines etudes – passe moi le mot malhabile – vu qu’il a exécuté les dites études probablement lorsque le mistral soufflait<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Ayant affaire à la même difficulté la moitié du temps<c type="kk">/</c> je m’explique la raison pourquoi la touche de Cezanne est tantôt très sûre et tantôt parait maladroite<c type="kp">_</c> C’est son chevalet qui branle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">J’ai quelquefois travaillé excessivement vite<c type="kk">/</c> est ce un defaut? je n’y peux rien<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ainsi une toile de 30 – le soir d’eté<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – je l’ai peinte dans une seule seance<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Y revenir est pas possible – la détruire – pourquoi<c type="kk">/</c> puisque je suis sorti dehors en plein mistral exprès pour faire cela<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">N’est-ce pas plutôt l’intensité de la pensée que le calme de la touche que nous recherchons – et dans la circonstance donnée de travail primesautier sur place et sur nature<c type="kk">/</c> la touche calme et bien reglée est-elle toujours possible? Ma foi – il me semble – pas plus que l’escrime à l’assaut.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">J’ai envoyé ton dessin du bordel<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> à mon frère et j’ai sollicité de te faire un achat<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Si mon frère <hi rend="italics">peut</hi><c type="kk">/</c> il le fera<c type="kk">/</c> car il sait bien que je dois avoir le désir de te faire vendre quelque chôse<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Si tu voulais je destinerais à un échange avec toi la tête de zouave que j’ai peinte<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Seulement je n’en parlerai qu’en cas que je puisse en même temps te faire vendre quelque chôse<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ce serait en réponse de ton essai de bordel<c type="kp">_</c>– Si <hi rend="italics">à nous deux</hi> nous exécutions un bordel je suis sûr que comme caractère nous y employerions l’étude du zouave<c type="kp">_</c>– Ah si plusieurs peintres étaient d’accord pour collaborer à de grandes chôses<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">L’art de l’avenir pourrait nous montrer des exemples de cela<c type="kp">_</c>– Les tableaux <hi rend="italics">nécessaires</hi> maintenant<c type="kk">/</c> c’est qu’il faudrait être à plusieurs pour en supporter les difficultés matérielles. Enfin – hélas – nous n’en sommes pas là – l’art de la peinture ne va pas aussi vite que la littérature<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je t’écris cette fois ci ainsi qu’hier bien à la hâte<c type="kk">/</c> bien éreinté. et à ce moment aussi je ne suis pas capable de dessiner<c type="kk">/</c> la matinée dans les champs m’a complètement fatiguée dans cette capacité là.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">C’est que çà fatigue<c type="kk">/</c> ce soleil d’ici<c type="kp">_</c>– Je suis de même entièrement incapable de juger mon propre travail<c type="kp">_</c> Je ne puis pas voir si les études soient bonnes ou mauvaises<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai <hi rend="italics">sept études</hi> <hi rend="italics">des blés</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> malheureusement toutes bien contre mon gré rien que des paysages<c type="kp">_</c>– Des paysages jaunes vieil or – faits vite vite vite et pressé comme le moissonneur qui se tait sous le soleil ardent<c type="kk">/</c> se concentrant pour en abattre<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Je me dis que tu dois peut-être – être surpris de voir combien peu moi j’aime la bible laquelle pourtant j’ai souvent cherché à etudier un peu – il n’y a que ce noyau<c type="kk">/</c> le christ – qui au point de vue de l’art me semble superieur – dans tous les cas <hi rend="italics">autre chôse</hi> – que l’antiquité Grecque<c type="kk">/</c> Indienne<c type="kk">/</c> Egyptienne<c type="kk">/</c> Persane<c type="kk">/</c> lesquelles ont été si loin. Or je le repète – ce Christ est plus artiste que les artistes – il travaille en esprit et chair vivants<c type="kk">/</c> il fait des hommes au lieu de statues alors..... je me sens bien être boeuf – etant peintre.... et j’admire le taureau<c type="kk">/</c> l’aigle<c type="kk">/</c> l’homme<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> avec une vénération – qui – m’empêchera d’être un ambitieux<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Poignée de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">j’ajoute pour ces sonnets<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> explication de ce que j’entends par – le dessin n’en est pas bien sûr de soi:</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Tu fais la morale à la fin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">tu dis à la société qu’elle est infâme parceque la putain nous fait penser à la viande<c type="kk">/</c> à la halle<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Très bien cela<c type="kk">/</c> la putain est comme la viande chez le charcutier<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Moi, abruti, je comprends<c type="kk">/</c> je sens cela<c type="kk">/</c> je retrouve une sensation de ma vie à moi<c type="kk">/</c> je dis: c’est bien parlé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">car le rythme sonore des mots colorés m’évoque la réalité brutale du bouge avec une grande intensité<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Mais les reproches adressées à la fin à “la societe”, <hi rend="italics">pour moi abruti</hi><c type="kk">/</c> mot creux comme “le bon dieu”<c type="kk">/</c> ne me font plus d’effet<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Ca n’y est pas<c type="kk">/</c> dis-je<c type="kk">/</c> et je retombe dans mon abrutissement<c type="kk">/</c> j’oublie la poésie forte assez d’abord<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> pour dissiper mon hébétude<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Est ce vrai ou non.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33"><hi rend="italics">Constater des faits</hi> comme tu commences à le faire c’est donner des coups de bistouri de chirurgien qui explique une anatomie.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">j’écoute recueilli et interessé<c type="kk">/</c> je regarde mais si après le chirurgien anatomiste va me faire de la morale comme ça<c type="kk">/</c> je trouve que cette derniere tirade n’a pas la même valeur que la démonstration anatomique<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">étudier<c type="kk">/</c> analyser la société<c type="kk">/</c> cela dit toujours plus que moraliser<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">Rien ne me semblerait plus curieux que de dire par exemple pourtant: “voilà cette viande de la halle<c type="kk">/</c> remarquez combien tout de même<c type="kk">/</c> malgré tout<c type="kk">/</c> elle reste électrisable momentanément par le stimulus d’un amour plus raffiné &amp; inattendu.”</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Ainsi que la chenille repue qui ne mange plus<c type="kk">/</c> qui rampe sur un mur au lieu de ramper sur une feuille de choux<c type="kk">/</c> cette femelle repue ne peut plus aimer quand bien même qu’elle s’y met – elle cherche<c type="kk">/</c> cherche<c type="kk">/</c> cherche<c type="kk">/</c> sait-elle elle-<c type="shy">-</c>même quoi? Elle est conscientieuse<c type="kk">/</c> vivante<c type="kk">/</c> sensible<c type="kk">/</c> galvanisée<c type="kk">/</c> rajeunie momentanément<c type="kk">/</c> mais impuissante<c type="kp">_</c> Elle aime encore pourtant – donc sa vie y est – <hi rend="italics">pas à tortiller</hi> – malgré qu’elle soit finie et mourante en tant que bête terrestre<c type="kp">_</c> le papillon<c type="kk">/</c> où éclot-il le papillon<c type="kk">/</c> de cette chenille repue – le hanneton de ce blanc ver.–––</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Voilà d’ailleurs où j’en suis en tant qu’études de vieilles putains –––––– je voudrais bien aussi aproximativement savoir de quoi moi-même je suis peutêtre la larve. </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> —</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I don’t know what I stuck into my letter of yesterday instead of the enclosed sheet<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> on the subject of your last sonnet. The fact is that I’m so worn out by work that in the evening — although writing is restful for me — I’m like a broken-down machine, so much has the day in the full sun tired me otherwise. And that’s why I stuck another sheet into your letter instead of this one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">On re-reading yesterday’s sheet — well, I’m sending you it as it is; on re-reading it, it seems legible to me and so I’m sending you it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Another hard day’s work today.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">If you saw my canvases, what would you say about them — you wouldn’t find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_932">Cézanne</rs>’s almost diffident and conscientious brushstroke there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But since at present I’m painting the same countryside of La Crau and the Camargue — although in a slightly different place – nevertheless, certain colour relationships could remain. What do I know about it — from time to time I couldn’t help thinking of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_932">Cézanne</rs>, particularly when I realized that his touch is so clumsy in certain studies – disregard the word clumsy — seeing that he probably executed those studies when the mistral was blowing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Having to deal with the same difficulty half the time, I can explain why <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_932">Cézanne</rs>’s touch is sometimes so sure and sometimes seems awkward. It’s his easel that’s wobbling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I’ve sometimes worked excessively fast; is that a fault? I can’t help it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">For example I’ve painted a no. 30 canvas — the summer evening<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — at a single sitting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It’s not possible to rework it; to destroy it — why, because I deliberately went outside to make it, out in the mistral.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Isn’t it rather intensity of thought than calmness of touch that we’re looking for — and in the given circumstances of impulsive work on the spot and from life, is a calm and controlled touch always possible? Well — it seems to me — no more than fencing moves during an attack. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’ve sent your drawing of the brothel<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> to my brother, and I’ve asked him to buy something of yours. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">If my brother <hi rend="italics">can</hi>, he’ll do it, because he knows very well that I must want to have you sell something.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">If you wished, I would earmark for an exchange with you the head of a Zouave that I’ve painted.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">But I won’t speak about it unless I can have you sell something at the same time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">That would be in response to your attempt at a brothel. If <hi rend="italics">we</hi> executed a brothel <hi rend="italics">together</hi>, I’m sure we’d use the study of the Zouave as a character type in it. Ah, if several painters agreed to collaborate on great things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">The art of the future might be able to show us examples of that. The thing is, for the paintings that are <hi rend="italics">needed</hi> now there would have to be several of us in order to cope with the material difficulties. Well — alas — we’re not at that point — the art of painting doesn’t move as fast as literature.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Like yesterday, I’m writing to you this time in great haste, really worn out. And at this moment, too, I’m not capable of drawing; the morning in the fields has tired me out completely in that capacity. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">The thing is, it’s tiring, the sun down here. I’m also utterly incapable of judging my own work. I can’t see whether the studies are good or bad. I have <hi rend="italics">seven studies of wheatfields</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> unfortunately all of them nothing but landscapes, much against my will. Old gold yellow landscapes — done quick quick quick and in a hurry, like the reaper who is silent under the blazing sun, concentrating on getting the job done.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I tell myself that you may perhaps — be surprised to see how little I love the Bible myself, which I’ve nevertheless often tried to study a little — there is only this kernel, Christ — who, from the point of view of art, seems superior to me — at any rate <hi rend="italics">something other </hi>— than Greek, Indian, Egyptian, Persian antiquity, which went so far. Now I say it again — this Christ is more of an artist than the artists — he works in living spirit and flesh, he makes men instead of statues, so….. as a painter I feel good being an ox …. and I admire the bull, the eagle, the man,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> with a veneration — which — will prevent my being a man of ambition.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"> Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I add about these sonnets<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> explanation of what I understand by — their design isn’t really sure of itself:</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">You moralize at the end.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">You tell society that it’s squalid because the whore makes us think of meat, of the market.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Very good, that, the whore is like meat at the butcher’s. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">For myself — numbed — I understand, I feel that, I recognize a sensation from my own life, I say: that’s well said.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Because the sonorous rhythm of the colourful words suggests to me the brutal reality of the dive with great intensity.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">But the reproofs addressed at the end to ‘society’, a word as hollow as ‘the good Lord’ <hi rend="italics">to me, numbed as I am</hi>, no longer have any effect on me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">It isn’t there, I say, and I sink into my numbness again; I forget the poem, at first strong enough to dispel my lethargy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Is that true or not?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34"><hi rend="italics">To report the facts</hi>,<hi rend="italics"> </hi>as you do at the beginning, is to wield the lancet like a surgeon explaining anatomy. 
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">I listen, meditative and interested; I watch, but if, later, the surgeon-anatomist is going to moralize at me like that, I find that that last tirade doesn’t have the same value as the anatomy demonstration.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">To study, to analyze society, that always says more than moralizing. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Nothing would seem more curious to me, however, than to say, for example: ‘see that meat from the market, notice how, all the same, despite everything, it can still be electrified for a moment by the stimulus of a love more refined and unexpected.’</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Like the sated caterpillar that no longer eats, that crawls on a wall instead of crawling on a cabbage leaf, this sated female can no longer love, either, even though she goes about it — she seeks, seeks, seeks, does she herself know what for? She’s conscientious, alive, responsive, galvanized, rejuvenated for a moment, but powerless. Yet she still loves — her life’s there, then — <hi rend="italics">make no bones about it</hi> — despite the fact that she’s finished and dying as an earthly creature. The butterfly, where does the butterfly emerge, from that sated caterpillar — the cockchafer from that white grub?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">Here, by the way, is where I am in terms of studies of old whores ———— I’d also very much like to know roughly what I’m the larva of myself, perhaps.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says that he is tired <hi rend="italics">again</hi> after working out in the sun <ref target="#l-60">(l. 60)</ref>, which means that there must have been at least two days of good weather after the rainy period, which ended on 25 June (<hi rend="italics">Météo France</hi>). Since he would immediately have seized the chance to work outdoors again, we have dated this letter Wednesday, 27 June 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The postscript was originally meant to accompany <ref target="let632.xml">letter 632</ref>, but Van Gogh forgot to enclose it.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The second sheet of this letter was written a day earlier – Van Gogh says he forgot to enclose it with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let632.xml">letter 632</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield with setting sun</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2647">F 465 / JH 1473</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let630.xml#n-4">See letter 630, n. 4,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2322"> Brothel scene</rs></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Zouave </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2655">F 423 / JH 1486</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> never got this painting.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
      
<p>These seven studies are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2647">F 465 / JH 1473</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2649">F 411 / JH 1476</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arles seen from the wheatfields </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2650">F 545 / JH 1477</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield with sheaves</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2651">F 561 / JH 1480</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield with sheaves</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2652">F 558 / JH 1481</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheat stacks </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2623">F 425 / JH 1442</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2646">F 422 / JH 1470</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let629.xml#n-3">See letter 629, nn. 3</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let629.xml#n-4">4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In his Vollard edition of the letters, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> felt that he had to correct Van Gogh about the animals symbolizing the evangelists: ‘He ought to have said <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">lion </hi>instead of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">bull</hi>, the ox having already been mentioned for Saint Luke, patron of painters, to whom Vincent dedicates himself’ (‘Il eut fallu dire le <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">lion</hi> au lieu du <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">taureau</hi>, le boeuf étant déjà cité pour Saint Luc, patron des peintres, auquel Vincent se voue.’). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Lettres à Bernard</hi> 1911, p. 117. The crux of the passage, however, is not so much iconographical accuracy or completeness as Van Gogh’s view that one must accept one’s humble place in the face of the very great. See also exhib. cat. Chicago 2001, p. 122.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to his earlier remarks about Christ as an artist (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let632.xml">letter 632</ref>) and about creativity as against sexual activity (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml">letter 628</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>These were the poems on the back of the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2322">Brothel scene</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let630.xml#n-6">see letter 630, n. 6.</ref> Although Van Gogh calls them ‘sonnets’, strictly speaking they are not.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘suffisamment forte en premier lieu’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    