<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 July 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let638"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b547 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>638</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>506</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>642</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-07-09">Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 July 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0547 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0547 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000734_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0547 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000735_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000735_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0547 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000735_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000735_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000735_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">je rentre d’une journée à Mont majour et mon ami le sous lieutenant<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> m’a tenu compagnie. Nous avons alors à nous deux exploré le vieux jardin et y avons volé d’excellentes figues<c type="kp">_</c> Si c’eût été plus grand cela eut fait penser au Paradou de Zola<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> de grands roseaux<c type="kk">/</c> de la vigne<c type="kk">/</c> du lierre<c type="kk">/</c> des figuiers<c type="kk">/</c> des oliviers<c type="kk">/</c> des grenadiers aux fleurs grasses du plus vif orangé<c type="kk">/</c> des cyprès centenaires<c type="kk">/</c> des frênes et des saules<c type="kk">/</c> des chênes de roche. des escaliers démolis à demi<c type="kk">/</c> des fenêtres ogivales en ruines<c type="kk">/</c> des blocs de blanc rochers couverts de lichen et des pans de murs écroulés épars cà et là dans la verdure, j’en ai encore rapporté un grand dessin. non pas du jardin cependant. Cela me fait 3 dessins<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> lorsque j’en aurai demi douzaine<c type="kk">/</c> les enverrai.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Hier j’ai été à Fontvieilles pour faire une visite à Bock et à Mac Knight<c type="kk">/</c> seulement ces messieurs étaient partis pour 8 jours pour un petit voyage en Suisse.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je crois que la chaleur me fait toujours du bien malgré les moustiques et les mouches.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Les cigales – non pas celles de chez nous mais des comme ceci</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
  
<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">on les voit sur les albums japonais<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Puis des <hi rend="italics">Cantharides</hi> dorées et vertes en essaim sur les oliviers<c type="kp">_</c> Ces cigales (je crois que leur nom est <hi rend="italics">cicada</hi>) chantent au moins aussi fort qu’une grenouille<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">J’ai encore pensé que si tu veux te rappeler que j’ai fait le portrait du père Tanguy (qu’il a encore)<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> de la mère Tanguy (qu’ils ont vendu)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> de leur ami (il est vrai que ce dernier portrait m’a été payé 20 francs par lui)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> que j’ai acheté sans rabais pour 250 francs de couleur chez Tanguy sur lesquelles naturellement il a gagné<c type="kk">/</c> qu’enfin je n’ai pas moins été son ami que lui n’ait été le mien<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai les plus graves raisons pour douter de son droit de me réclamer de l’argent<c type="kk">/</c> lequel se trouve vraiment réglé par l’étude qu’il tient encore de moi<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> à plus forte raison puisqu’il y a condition bien expresse qu’il se payerait sur la vente d’un tableau. Xantippe<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> la mère Tanguy et d’autres dames ont par un caprice étrange de la nature le cerveau en silex ou pierre à fusil. Certes ces dames sont bien davantage nuisibles dans la société civilisée dans laquelle elles circulent que les citoyens mordus par des chiens enragés qui habitent l’institut Pasteur.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Aussi le pere Tanguy aurait mille fois raison de tuer sa dame.... mais il ne le fait pas plus que Socrate.....</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Et pour ce motif le père Tanguy a plutot des rapports – en tant que la résignation et la longue patience – avec les antiques chrétiens martyrs et esclaves qu’avec les modernes maquereaux de Paris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">N’empêche qu’il n’y existe aucune raison pour lui payer 80 francs mais il y existe des raisons pour ne jamais se facher avec lui<c type="kk">/</c> même si lui se fâcherait lorsque<c type="kk">/</c> comme de juste dans ce cas<c type="kk">/</c> on le fout à la porte ou au moins l’envoie carrément promener.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">J’écris à Russell en même temps – nous savons probablement n’est ce pas que les anglais<c type="kk">/</c> les yankees &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> ont ceci en commun avec les hollandais que leur charité – – .................... est très chrétienne<c type="kp">_</c>– Or nous autres n’étant pas de très-bons chrétiens........... Voilà ce que je ne peux m’empêcher de penser en écrivant encore une fois<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Ce Bock a un peu la tête d’un gentilhomme flamand du temps des compromis des nobles du temps du Taciturne et de Marnix<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Cela ne m’étonnerait pas du tout qu’il fusse bon.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">J’ai écrit à Russell que pour notre échange je lui enverrais mon envoi roulé directement chez lui si je savais qu’il fut à Paris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">De cette façon il doit bien en tout cas me répondre de ces jours ci.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Maintenant il me faudrait <hi rend="italics">bientôt</hi> encore de la toile et de la couleur. Seulement je n’ai pas encore l’adresse de cette toile à 40 francs les 20 mètres<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je crois bien faire en travaillant surtout les dessins dans ce moment et de faire de façon d’avoir de la couleur et de la toile en réserve pour le moment où Gauguin viendra.– Je voudrais bien que avec la couleur on eut aussi peu à se gêner qu’avec la plume et le papier.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Parce que j’ai peur de gacher de la couleur je rate souvent une etude peinte<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">avec le papier</hi> – si ce n’est pas une lettre que j’ecris mais un dessin que je fais – ça ne rate guère<c type="kk">/</c> autant de feuilles Whatman<c type="kk">/</c> autant de dessins<c type="kp">_</c> Je crois que si j’étais riche je depenserais moins que maintenant<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Enfin – le père Martin dirait – alors il faut se faire riche – et il a bien raison ainsi que pour le chef d’oeuvre.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Te rappelles tu dans Guy de Maupassant le monsieur chasseur de lapins et autre gibier qui avait si fort chassé pendant 10 ans et s’etait tellement éreinté à courir après le gibier qu’au moment où il voulait se marier il ne bandait plus<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui lui causait les plus grandes inquiétudes et consternations.–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Sans être dans le cas de ce monsieur en tant que quant à devoir ou vouloir me marier<c type="kk">/</c> quant au physique je commence à lui ressembler. Selon l’excellent maitre Ziem<c type="kk">/</c> l’homme devient ambitieux du moment qu’il ne bande plus.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> <hi rend="italics">Or</hi> si cela m’est plus ou moins égal de bander ou pas je proteste lorsque cela doit fatalement me mèner à l’ambition<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Il n’y a que le plus grand philosophe de son temps et de son pays et par conséquent de tous les pays et de tous les temps – l’excellent maître Pangloss<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> – qui pourrait – s’il était là – me renseigner et me tranquilliser l’âme.–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Voilà – la lettre pour Russell est sous enveloppe – et j’ai écrit comme je pensais<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Je lui ai demandé s’il avait des nouvelles de Reid et je te fais la même question<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">J’ai dit à Russell qu’il avait pleine liberté de prendre ce qu’il voudrait aussi dans le premier envoi. Et que j’attendais seulement réponse catégorique pour savoir si chez lui ou chez toi il voulait choisir. que dans le premier cas, s’il voulait les voir chez lui – tu lui enverrais aussi quelques vergers. et que tu ferais reprendre le tout<c type="kk">/</c> son choix fait. Donc il ne peut rien dire à cela. S’il ne prend pas de Gauguin c’est qu’il ne peut pas<c type="kp">_</c>– S’il peut le faire je serais porté à espérer qu’il le fera.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">je lui ai dit que si j’osais insister sur un achat ce n’était <hi rend="italics">pas</hi> que sans lui la chôse ne se ferait pas mais que Gauguin ayant été malade et étant donné la complication de ce qu’il avait été au lit et devait payer son medecin<c type="kk">/</c> la chôse était un peu lourde pour nous et que nous etions d’autant plus porté à trouver amateur pour un tableau. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Je pense beaucoup à Gauguin et aurais beaucoup d’idées pour des tableaux et pour le travail en général. J’ai actuellement une femme de ménage qui pour 1 franc me balaye et lave la maison 2 fois par semaine<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> je fonde de grandes esperances sur elle pour pouvoir y compter qu’elle nous fera les lits si nous nous decidons à coucher chez nous. D’autre part il y a une combinaison possible avec le bonhomme où je loge actuellement. Enfin on cherchera à travailler à ce que ce soit en somme une économie au lieu d’une dépense<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Comment va ta santé maintenant? Vois tu encore Gruby<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Ce que tu disais de cette conversation à la Nouvelle Athènes<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> est intéressant. Tu connais bien le petit portrait de Desboutin qu’a Portier<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> C’est certes un etrange phénomène que tous les artistes<c type="kk">/</c> poetes<c type="kk">/</c> musiciens<c type="kk">/</c> peintres soient materiellement des malheureux – les heureux aussi – ce que dernierement tu disais de Guy de Maupassant le prouve une fois de plus<c type="kp">_</c>– Cela remue la question éternelle: <hi rend="italics">la vie</hi> est elle toute entière visible pour nous ou bien n’en connaissons nous avant la mort qu’un hemisphère<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Les peintres – pour ne parler que d’eux – etant morts et enterrés<c type="kk">/</c> parlent à une génération suivante ou à plusieurs générations suivantes par leurs oeuvres<c type="kp">_</c> Est ce là tout ou y a-t-il même encore plus. Dans la vie du peintre peutêtre la mort n’est pas ce qu’il y aurait de plus difficile<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Moi je déclare ne pas en savoir quoi que ce soit<c type="kp">_</c>– Mais toujours la vue des étoiles me fait rêver <hi rend="italics">aussi simplement</hi> que me donnent à rêver les points noirs représentant sur la carte géographique villes &amp; villages.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Pourquoi<c type="kk">/</c> me dis je<c type="kk">/</c> les points lumineux du firmament nous seraient elles moins accessibles que les points noirs sur la carte de France.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Si nous prenons le train pour nous rendre à Tarascon ou à Rouen nous prenons la mort pour aller dans une étoile<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Ce qui est certainement vrai dans ce raison<c type="shy">-</c>nement c’est que étant <hi rend="italics">en vie</hi> nous ne pouvons <hi rend="italics">pas</hi> nous rendre dans une étoile. pas plus qu’etant morts nous puissions prendre le train. Enfin il ne me semble pas impossible que le cholera<c type="kk">/</c> la gravelle<c type="kk">/</c> la phtisie<c type="kk">/</c> le cancer<c type="kk">/</c> soient des moyens de locomotion céleste comme les bateaux à vapeur<c type="kk">/</c> les omnibus et le chemin de fer en soient de terrestres.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Mourir tranquillement de vieillesse serait y aller à pied.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">Pour le moment je vais me coucher car il est tard et je te souhaite bonne nuit et bonne chance<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Poignee de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve just come back from a day at Montmajour, and my friend the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">second lieutenant</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> kept me company. So the two of us explored the old garden and we stole some excellent figs there. If it had been bigger it would have made you think of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s Paradou,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> tall reeds, grape vines, ivy, fig trees, olive trees, pomegranate trees with fat flowers of the brightest orange, hundred-year-old cypresses, ash trees and willows, rock oaks. Half-demolished staircases, ruined Gothic windows, clumps of white rock covered in lichen, and pieces of collapsed wall scattered here and there in the undergrowth; I brought back another large drawing of it. Not of the garden, though. That makes 3 drawings;<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> when I have half dozen, will send them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Yesterday I went to Fontvieille to pay a visit to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs>, but those gentlemen had left for a week for a short trip to Switzerland.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I think the heat is still doing me good, in spite of the mosquitoes and flies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The cicadas — not those at home but like this,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">you see them in Japanese albums.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> And golden and green <hi rend="italics">Cantharides </hi>swarming on the olive trees. These cicadas (I think their name is <hi rend="italics">cicada</hi>) sing at least as loudly as a frog.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I had the further thought that if you care to recall that I painted portraits of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy</rs> (which he still has),<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_773"><hi rend="italics">mère</hi> Tanguy</rs> (which they sold),<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> of their friend (it’s true that I was paid 20 francs by him for the latter portrait),<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> that I bought 250 francs worth of colours from Tanguy without a discount, on which he of course made a profit, that after all, I was no less his friend than he was mine, I have the most serious of reasons to doubt his right to demand money from me, which is actually settled with the study of mine that he still has,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> all the more so since there’s the clearly expressed condition that he would be paid with the sale of a painting. Xanthippe,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_773"><hi rend="italics">mère</hi> Tanguy</rs> and some other ladies have, by some strange freak of nature, brains of flintstone or gunflint. Certainly these ladies are much more harmful in the civilized society in which they move than the citizens bitten by rabid dogs who live at the Institut <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_564">Pasteur</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> So <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy</rs> would be right a thousand times over if he killed his lady.... but he doesn’t do it, any more than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs>.....</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And for that reason <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy</rs> is more closely connected — in terms of resignation and long patience — with the early Christian martyrs and slaves than with present-day Paris pimps.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Which doesn’t mean there’s any reason to pay him 80 francs, but there are reasons for never losing your temper with him, even if he might lose his temper when, rightly so in this case, you kick him out, or at least send him packing in no uncertain terms. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I’m writing to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> at the same time — we probably know, don’t we, that the English, the Yankees &amp;c. have this in common with the Dutch, that their charity — — .................... is very Christian. Now, the rest of us not being very good Christians........... That’s what I can’t stop myself thinking as I write once again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">That <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> looks a bit like a Flemish gentleman from the time of the compromise of the nobles in the time of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_822">Silent</rs> one and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_504">Marnix</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> I wouldn’t be at all surprised if he was good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’ve written to Russell that for our exchange I’d send him my consignment rolled up, straight to his home, if I knew he was in Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">This way he should in any case reply to me in the next few days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">And now I’ll need more canvas and paint <hi rend="italics">soon. </hi>Only I don’t yet have the address for that canvas at 40 francs for 20 metres.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I believe that at this moment I’m doing the right thing by working chiefly on drawings, and seeing to it that I have colours and canvas in reserve for the time when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> comes. I very much wish we could rein ourselves in as little with paint as with pen and paper.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Because I’m afraid of wasting paint, I often spoil a painted study.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><hi rend="italics">With paper </hi>— if it’s not a letter I’m writing but a drawing I’m doing — it hardly ever goes wrong: so many sheets of Whatman, so many drawings. I think if I were rich I’d spend less than now.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ah well — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_503"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Martin</rs> would say — then we’ll have to make sure we get rich — and he’s quite right, just as he is about the masterpiece.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Do you remember in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs> the gentleman who hunted rabbits and other game and who had hunted so hard for 10 years and was so worn out with running after game that at the point when he wanted to get married he couldn’t get a hard-on, which caused him the greatest anxieties and consternation.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Without being in this gentleman’s position as far as having or wishing to get married, in the physical sense I’m beginning to resemble him. According to the excellent master <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1449">Ziem</rs>, a man becomes ambitious the moment he can’t get a hard-on.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> <hi rend="italics">Now, </hi>while it’s more or less the same to me whether or not I can get a hard-on, I protest when it must inevitably lead me to ambition.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">There is no one but the greatest philosopher of his time and of his country, and therefore of all countries and all times — the excellent master Pangloss<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> — who could — if here were there — give me advice and calm my soul.
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">There we are — the letter for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> is in its envelope — and I’ve written as I thought.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I asked him if he had news of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs>, and I put the same question to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> that he was perfectly at liberty to take what he might want, and from the first consignment too. And that I was only waiting for a categorical answer to know whether he wanted to choose at his home or yours. That in the first case, if he wanted to see them at his home — you’d send him some orchards too. And that you’d have all of them brought back, once he’d made his choice. So he can’t say anything to that. If he doesn’t buy a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> it’s because he can’t. If he can do it, I’d be inclined to hope he will do it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I told him that if I was bold enough to insist on a purchase, it <hi rend="italics">wasn’t </hi>that without him the thing wouldn’t come about, but that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> having been ill, and given the complication that he’d been in bed and had to pay his doctor, the business was rather hard for us and we were all the more eager to find a collector for a painting. </p><pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27"> I think about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> a lot, and would have plenty of ideas for paintings and for work in general. At the moment I have a charwoman, who sweeps and scrubs the house twice a week for 1 franc;<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> I place great hopes in her, to be able to count on her making the beds if we decide to sleep at home. On the other hand, there’s a possible arrangement with the chap where I’m lodging at the moment. Anyway, we’ll try to ensure that in the end it’ll be a saving instead of an expense.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">How’s your health now? Are you still seeing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_446">Gruby</rs>?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">What you were saying about that conversation at the Nouvelle Athènes<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> is interesting. You’re familiar with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_973">Desboutin</rs>’s little portrait that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> has.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> It’s certainly a strange phenomenon that all artists, poets, musicians, painters are unfortunate in the material sense — even the happy ones — what you were saying recently about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs> proves it once again. That rakes up the eternal question: is <hi rend="italics">life </hi>visible to us in its entirety, or before we die do we know of only one hemisphere?
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Painters — to speak only of them — being dead and buried, speak to a following generation or to several following generations through their works. Is that all, or is there more, even? In the life of the painter, death may perhaps not be the most difficult thing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">For myself, I declare I don’t know anything about it. But the sight of the stars always makes me dream <hi rend="italics">in as simple a way </hi>as the black spots on the map, representing towns and villages, make me dream.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Why, I say to myself, should the spots of light in the firmament be less accessible to us than the black spots on the map of France.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Just as we take the train to go to Tarascon or Rouen, we take death to go to a star.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> What’s certainly true in this argument is that while <hi rend="italics">alive, </hi>we <hi rend="italics">cannot </hi>go to a star, any more than once dead we’d be able to take the train. So it seems to me not impossible that cholera, the stone, consumption, cancer are celestial means of locomotion, just as steamboats, omnibuses and the railway are terrestrial ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">To die peacefully of old age would be to go there on foot.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">For the moment I’m going to go to bed because it’s late, and I wish you good-night and good luck.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let637.xml">letter 637</ref> of Sunday, 8 or Monday, 9 July, Van Gogh says that he is going to see Boch in Fontvieille ‘this afternoon’. Since he writes in the present letter that he was there ‘yesterday’, we may safely assume that it was written a day later. We have therefore dated it Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 July 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The proposed exchange with Russell <ref target="let589.xml">(589)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">First consignment of paintings from Arles <ref target="let606.xml">(606)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Request to Russell to buy a painting from Gauguin <ref target="let582.xml">(582)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s illness <ref target="let581.xml">(581)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="ogt_6">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is staying at Café de la Gare <ref target="let606.xml">(606)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="ogt_7">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s health problems <ref target="let611.xml">(611)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Paul Eugène Milliet</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>On the similarities between Van Gogh’s description and that of the garden in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_253">La faute de l’abbé Mouret</ref></hi>: Sund 1992, p. 175; see for the reference to ‘Le Paradou’: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let344.xml#n-1">letter 344, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The drawing of the ruin was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Hill with the ruins of Montmajour</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Abbey </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2666">F 1446 / JH 1504</rs>). Van Gogh had previously drawn <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The rock of Montmajour with pine trees</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2665">F 1447 / JH 1503</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Trees, Montmajour </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2324">F - / JH add. 3</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml">see letter 637</ref>. The three drawings were all the same large size (approx. 49 x 60 cm).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>In Pierre Loti’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi>, which Van Gogh was reading at the time (see letters <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml">637</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let639.xml">639</ref>), there are similar illustrations of cicadas. See Loti 1888, pp. 107, 286 and 312. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> owned two portraits: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Père Tanguy</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2547">F 263 / JH 1202</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Père Tanguy</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2560">F 363 / JH 1351</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This portrait of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_773">Mrs Tanguy</rs> is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Portrait of a man </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2546">F 288 / JH 1200</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml#n-2">See letter 637, n. 2,</ref> for the study that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> had: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Seine with moored boats</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_720">F 300 / JH 1275</rs>) or <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Bank of the Seine with a boat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_721">F 353 / JH 1271</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For Xantippe, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let595.xml#n-8">see letter 595, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_564">Louis Pasteur</rs> had discovered a rabies vaccine in 1885. The institute named after him opened in Paris in 1888. There was a ward for treating patients infected with rabies. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The time of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_822">William the Silent</rs> (William <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">i</hi> of Orange) and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_504">Philips van Marnix</rs>, Lord of Sint Aldegonde, William’s right-hand man. The <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">League of Nobles</hi> is a reference to the petition (the ‘compromis’) that was presented to the governor-general, Margaret of Parma, in 1566.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let639.xml">letter 639</ref> that this was the paint supplier <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_302">Bourgeois</rs> in Paris. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let366.xml#n-9">See letter 366, n. 9,</ref> for Bourgeois.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh also quoted this remark by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_503">Père Martin</rs> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let634.xml">letter 634</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>In the story ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_489">La rouille</ref>’ the fanatical huntsman Gontran de Coutelier meets Berthe Vilers. They go hunting together (among other things for partridge, known for their sexual energy) and he falls in love with her. He goes to Paris to reflect on his proposed alliance, but returns changed and aged. Later he confesses to a friend that his prolonged period of celibacy has left him impotent. See Maupassant 1974, pp. 1458 ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>What Van Gogh writes here is confirmed by a letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1449">Ziem</rs> to Arsène Houssaye of 26 September 1885: ‘Just imagine that right here I am producing some of my finest pictures: the autumnal fruits of the waking hours, the worries and the scourgings which clot the sperm to solidify brain matter. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Matter</hi> is pretty. Your Zanzibar Ziem.’ (Figurez-vous que je fais ici même, mes plus beaux tableaux: le fruit automnal des veilles, des préoccupations, des macérations qui figent le sperme pour solidifier la matière cérébrale. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Matière</hi> est jolie. Votre Zanzibar Ziem.) Taken from Pierre Miquel, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Félix Ziem 1821-1911</hi>. 2 vols. Maurs-la-Jolie 1978, vol. 1, p. 161.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>The philosopher Pangloss is a character in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_445">Candide</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let568.xml#n-3">see letter 568, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The cleaning woman was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1926">Thérèse Balmoissière</rs>. See Murphy 2016, p. 94. Van Gogh paid her 20 francs a month (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let736.xml">see letter 736</ref>). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let747.xml#n-1">letter 747, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Café in the place Pigalle in Paris, where the group of artists and writers around <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_981">Degas</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_973">Desboutin</rs> met regularly. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>In view of the context, Van Gogh must have meant a portrait of an artist. It is not possible to work out from this passage whether <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_973">Desboutin</rs> was the subject of the portrait, the painter, or both, and it is therefore not possible to identify the work. Van Gogh’s use of the word ‘unfortunate’ must allude to Desboutin who was ‘a ruined man having squandered his considerable inheritance collecting paintings and enjoying a bohemian life ... Misery and sadness surrounded him’. See exhib. cat. Cleveland 1980, p. 286.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s remark about stars and the hereafter has been linked to the story ‘Les étoiles’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_538">Lettres de mon moulin</ref></hi> and to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_408"> La joie de vivre</ref></hi> (see Sund 1992, p. 187).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    