<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Sunday, 29 July 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let650"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b555 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>650</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>514</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>652</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-07-29">Sunday, 29 July 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0555 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0555 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000746_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0555 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0555 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000747_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">bien merci de ta bonne lettre. Si tu te rappelles<c type="kk">/</c> la mienne finissait par: nous nous faisons vieux<c type="kk">/</c> voila ce qui <hi rend="italics">est</hi> et le reste est <hi rend="italics">imagination</hi> et n’existe point.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Or je disais cela plutôt encore pour moi que pour toi<c type="kp">_</c> Et je le disais sentant l’absolue necessité pour moi d’agir selon<c type="kk">/</c> de travailler peut-être pas davantage mais avec conception plus grave.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Maintenant tu parles du vide que tu sens parfois<c type="kk">/</c> cela c’est juste la même chose que j’ai moi aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Considérant si tu veux le temps où nous vivons comme une renaissance vraie et grande de l’art<c type="kk">/</c> la tradition vermoulue et officielle qui est encore debout mais qui est impuissante et faineante au fond<c type="kk">/</c> les nouveaux peintres seuls<c type="kk">/</c> pauvres<c type="kk">/</c> traités comme des fous et par suite de ce traitement le devenant reellement au moins en tant que quant à leur vie sociale.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Alors saches que toi tu fais absolument la même besogne que ces peintres primitifs puisque tu leur fournis de l’argent et que tu leur vends leurs toiles<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui leur permet d’en produire d’autres.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Si un peintre se ruine le caractère en travaillant dur à la peinture qui le rend stérile pour bien des choses<c type="kk">/</c> pour la vie de famille &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Si conséquemment il peint non seulement avec de la couleur mais avec de l’abnégation et du renoncement à soi et le coeur brisé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Ton travail à toi non seulement ne t’est pas payé non plus mais te coute exactement comme à un peintre cet effacement de la personalité<c type="kk">/</c> moitié volontaire moitie fortuit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Ceci pour dire que si tu fais de la peinture <hi rend="italics">indirectement</hi><c type="kk">/</c> tu es plus productif que par exemple moi. Plus que tu deviens totalement marchand<c type="kk">/</c> plus tu deviens artiste<c type="kp">_</c> De meme que j’espère bien etre dans le meme cas… plus que je deviens dissipé<c type="kk">/</c> malade<c type="kk">/</c> crûche cassée<c type="kk">/</c> plus moi aussi je deviens artiste créateur dans cette grande renaissance de l’art de laquelle nous parlons.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ces chôses certes sont ainsi mais cet art éternellement existant et cette renaissance – ce rejeton vert sorti des racines du vieux tronc coupé – ce sont des chôses si spirituelles qu’une certaine melancolie nous demeure 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>en y songeant qu’à moins de frais on aurait pu faire de la vie au lieu de faire de l’art<c type="kp">_</c> Tu devrais bien<c type="kk">/</c> si tu peux<c type="kk">/</c> me faire sentir que l’art est vivant<c type="kk">/</c> toi qui aimes peut etre l’art plus que moi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Je me dis que cela tient non pas à l’art mais à moi<c type="kk">/</c> que le seul moyen de me retrouver d’aplomb et sérein est de <hi rend="italics">faire mieux</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Et nous revoilà à la fin de ma dernière lettre – je me fais vieux mais ce n’est que de l’imagination si je croirais que l’art est une vieillerie. Maintenant si tu sais ce que c’est qu’une “<hi rend="italics">mousmé</hi>” (tu le sauras lorsque tu auras lu madame Chrysantème de Loti)<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> je viens d’en peindre une.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Cela m’a coûté toute ma semaine<c type="kk">/</c> je n’ai rien pu faire d’autre chôse ayant encore été pas trop bien portant. Voilà ce qui m’embête<c type="kk">/</c> si j’eusse été bien portant j’aurais sabré entre temps encore des paysages. mais pour mener bien ma mousmé je devais réserver ma puissance cérébrale. Une mousmé est une fille Japonaise – provencale dans ce cas – de 12 à 14 ans. Cela fait 2 figures<c type="kk">/</c> le zouave<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> et elle<c type="kk">/</c> que j’ai.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">menage ta santé<c type="kk">/</c> prends des bains<c type="kk">/</c> surtout <hi rend="italics">si Gruby t’en commande</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Car tu verras dans 4 ans<c type="kk">/</c> lesquels j’ai de plus que toi<c type="kk">/</c> combien la santé relative est necessaire pour pouvoir travailler. Or nous qui travaillons de la tête<c type="kk">/</c> notre seule et unique ressource pour ne pas etre trop vite fini c’est la rallonge factice d’une hygiène moderne rigoureusement suivie<c type="kk">/</c> pour autant que nous puissions la supporter. Car moi pour un ne fais pas tout ce que je devrais faire. Et un peu de bonne humeur vaut mieux que le reste des remèdes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">J’ai une lettre de Russell. Il dit qu’il m’aurait ecrit avant si ce n’était que son démenagement à Belle Ile l’avait absorbé<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Il est là maintenant et dit que cela lui fera plaisir si tôt ou tard j’y vienne passer quelque temps. C’est toujours encore qu’il veut refaire mon portrait.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Il dit même “Je serais allé chez Boussod pour voir le Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> négresses causant<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> si ce n’etait pas pour la même raison que j’en aie été empeché”<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">En somme il ne refuse pas d’en acheter un mais donne à entendre qu’il ne voudrait pas moindre qualité que le nôtre.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Tu vois que cela vaut en tout cas mieux que rien du tout.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">J’ecrirai cela à Gauguin et lui demanderai croquis de tableaux. nous ne devons pas presser cette affaire et renoncer à R. pour le moment mais considerer la chôse comme une affaire en train qui se fera<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ainsi de même pour Guillaumin je voudrais qu’il prenne une figure de G.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Il dit qu’il a reçu de <hi rend="italics">Rodin</hi> un bien beau buste de sa femme<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> et qu’il a déjeuné à cette occasion avec Claude Monet et qu’il a vu alors les 10 tableaux d’Antibes<c type="kp">_</c>– Je lui envoie l’article de Geffroy.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Il critique les Monet très bien<c type="kk">/</c> d’abord en les aimant beaucoup<c type="kk">/</c> la difficulté attaqué<c type="kk">/</c> l’enveloppe d’air coloré<c type="kk">/</c> la couleur. Maintenant après<c type="kk">/</c> dit-il<c type="kk">/</c> ce qu’il y a à y redire c’est que tout manque partout de construction<c type="kk">/</c> par exemple un arbre chez lui aura beaucoup trop de feuillage pour la grosseur du tronc et ainsi toujours et partout au point de vue de la realité des chôses<c type="kk">/</c> au point de vue d’un tas de <hi rend="italics">lois</hi> de la nature<c type="kk">/</c> il est assez desespérant.– Il finit par dire que cette qualité d’attaquer la difficulté est ce que tous devraient avoir.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">J’ai reçu de Bernard 10 croquis<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> comme son bordel<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> il y en a 3 qui sont à la Redon<c type="kk">/</c> enthousiasme qu’il a pour cela que moi je ne partage pas trop.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Mais il y a une femme qui se laves bien rembrandtesque ou à la Goya<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> et un paysage avec figures tres étrange<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Il me défend expressément de te les envoyer<c type="kk">/</c> seulement tu les recevra par même poste<c type="kp">_</c> Je pense que Russell prendra encore quelque chôse à Bernard. Maintenant j’ai vu du travail de ce <hi rend="italics">Bock</hi><c type="kk">/</c> c’est rigoureusement impressioniste mais pas fort<c type="kk">/</c> dans ce moment où cette technique nouvelle le préoccupe encore trop pour pouvoir être soi.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Il se fortifiera et dégagera sa personalité je pense. Mais Mc Knight fait des aquarelles de la force des <hi rend="italics">Destree</hi><c type="kk">/</c> tu sais cet ignoble Hollandais qu’autrefois nous avons connu.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Cependant il avait lavé de petites natures mortes<c type="kk">/</c> pot jaune sur avant plan violet<c type="kk">/</c> pot rouge sur du vert<c type="kk">/</c> pot orangé sur du bleu<c type="kk">/</c> mieux mais c’est bien pauvre.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Le village où ils restent est du <hi rend="italics">vrai Millet</hi><c type="kk">/</c> des petits paysans<c type="kk">/</c> rien que cela<c type="kk">/</c> absolument <hi rend="italics">agreste</hi> et intime. Ce caractère leur échappe complètement. Je crois que Mac Knight a civilisé et converti au christianisme civilisé son bougre de logeur<c type="kp">_</c> Du moins cette canaille et sa digne épouse<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’on y vient<c type="kk">/</c> vous serrent la main – c’est dans un café naturellement<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> – lorsqu’on 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>y demande une consommation ils ont des manières de refuser l’argent “oh je ne pourrais pas prendre de l’argent à un arti<hi rend="italics">ss</hi>e” (avec deux ss)<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin c’est abominable par leur propre faute et ce Bock doit joliment s’abrutir avec Mc Knight<c type="kp">_</c> Je pense que Mc Knight a de l’argent mais pas beaucoup.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Ainsi ils empestent le village<c type="kk">/</c> sans cela j’y irais souvent pour y travailler. Ce qu’il faudrait faire là c’est pas causer avec les gens civilisés<c type="kk">/</c> or eux connaissent le chef de gare et une vingtaine d’emmerdeurs et de là vient en grande partie qu’ils ne foutent rien<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai déjà dit cela à Mouriés qui dans le temps croyait que Mac Knight était très-intelligent avec “l’homme des champs”.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Naturellement ces simples et naïfs habitants des champs se moquent d’eux et les méprisent. Au contraire si on y fait sa besogne sans s’occuper des fainéants du village à faux col<c type="kk">/</c> alors on peut entrer chez les paysans en leur faisant gagner quelques sous. Et alors ce sacré Fontvieille serait un trésor pour eux mais les indigènes sont – des petits paysans de Zola<c type="kk">/</c> êtres innocents et doux comme nous savons.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> Il est probable que Mc Knight fera sous peu des petits paysages avec moutons pour bonbonnières<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Non seulement mes tableaux mais surtout moi-<c type="shy">-</c>même dans ces derniers temps j’etais devenu hagard comme Hugues van der Goes dans le tableau d’Emile Wauters à peu près<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Seulement m’étant fait soigneusement raser toute ma barbe je crois que je tiens autant de l’abbé très calme dans le même tableau que du peintre fou y représenté si intelligemment<c type="kp">_</c> Et je ne suis pas mécontent d’être un peu entre les deux car <hi rend="italics">il faut vivre</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">surtout parce qu’il n’y a pas à tortiller qu’un jour ou un autre il peut y avoir une crise si tu changeais en tant que ta position chez les Boussod. Raison de plus de garder les relations avec les artistes de mon côté autant que du tien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">D’ailleurs je crois avoir dit la verité pourtant<c type="kp">_</c> Si je réussissais à faire rentrer en valeurs l’argent dépensé je ne ferais que mon devoir. Et puis ce que je peux faire de <hi rend="italics">pratique</hi> c’est le portrait. Pour ce qui est de boire de trop... si c’est mauvais je n’en sais rien.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Voila pourtant Bismarck qui en tous les cas est fort pratique et fort intelligent<c type="kp">_</c>– Son petit medecin lui a dit qu’il buvait trop et <hi rend="italics">qu’il s’etait surmené toute</hi> <hi rend="italics">sa vie de l’estomac à la cervelle</hi>. B. brusquement cesse de boire. Depuis il a perdu et traine<c type="kp">_</c> Il doit en dedans joliment se moquer de son medecin qu’heureusement pour lui il n’a pas consulté trop tôt.–<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Enfin<c type="kk">/</c> bonne poignee de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Sache le bien que avec Gauguin nous ne devons rien changer à l’idee de lui venir en aide si la proposition est acceptable telle quelle mais <hi rend="italics">nous n’avons pas besoin</hi> de lui<c type="kp">_</c> Ainsi pour travailler seul ne crois pas que cela me gène et ne presse pas l’affaire pour moi<c type="kk">/</c> sois en <hi>bien assuré</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">le portrait de jeune fille est sur fond blanc teinté fortement de vert véronèse<c type="kk">/</c> le corsage est rayé rouge sang et violet. La jupe est bleu de roi à gros pointillés orangé jaune<c type="kp">_</c> Les chairs mates sont gris jaune<c type="kk">/</c> les cheveux violacés<c type="kk">/</c> les sourcils noirs et les cils<c type="kk">/</c> les yeux orangé et bleu de prusse<c type="kk">/</c> une branche de laurier rose entre les doigts car les 2 mains sont dedans.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many thanks for your kind letter. If you recall, mine ended with: we’re getting old, that’s what <hi rend="italics">is </hi>and the rest is <hi rend="italics">imagination</hi> and doesn’t exist.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Now, I said that even more for myself, than for you. And I said it feeling the absolute necessity for me to act accordingly, to work, not more, perhaps, but with a more serious conception.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Now you talk about the emptiness you sometimes feel; that’s just the same thing that I have, too. Considering, if you will, the times in which we live as a true and great revival of art, the moth-eaten and official tradition, which is still on its feet, but which is at bottom powerless and bone-idle, the new painters, alone, poor, treated like madmen and as a result of this treatment becoming so in fact, at least as far as their social life is concerned. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then remember that you do exactly the same work as these primitive painters, since you provide them with money and you sell their canvases for them, which enables them to produce others. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">If a painter ruins his character by working hard at painting, which makes him sterile for many things, for family life, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">If as a consequence he paints not only with paint but with self-denial and self-abnegation and a broken heart.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Not only are you not paid for your own work either, but it costs you exactly the same as this effacement of personality, half deliberate, half accidental, costs a painter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">This is to say that if you do painting <hi rend="italics">indirectly</hi>, you’re more productive than me, for example. The more completely you become a dealer, the more you become an artist. Just as I very much hope to be in the same case... The more I become dissipated, ill, a broken pitcher, the more I too become a creative artist in that great revival of art of which we’re speaking.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">These things are indeed so, but this eternally existing art and this revival — this green shoot growing from the roots of the old felled trunk — these are things so spiritual that a kind of melancholy remains with us 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> when we reflect that at less expense we could have made life instead of making art. You really ought, if you can, to make me feel that art is alive, you who perhaps love art more than I do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I say to myself that that doesn’t have to do with art, but with me, that the only way for me to regain self-confidence and tranquillity is by <hi rend="italics">doing better</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And here we are again at the end of my last letter — I’m getting old, but it’s only imagination if I were to believe that art is an old, stale thing. Now, if you know what a ‘<hi rend="italics">mousmé</hi>’ is (you’ll know when you’ve read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs>’s Madame Chrysanthème),<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve just painted one.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> It took me my whole week, I wasn’t able to do anything else, having been not too well again. That’s what annoys me, if I’d been well I’d have knocked off some more landscapes in between times. But in order to finish off my mousmé I had to save my mental powers. A mousmé is a Japanese girl — Provençale in this case — aged between 12 and 14. That makes 2 figures, the Zouave,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and her, that I have. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Look after your health, take baths, especially <hi rend="italics">if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_446">Gruby</rs> recommends that you do</hi>. Because you’ll see in 4 years, the years by which I’m older than you, how far relative health is necessary in order to be able to work. Now we who work with our heads, our only and unique means of avoiding being finished too soon is the artificial prolongation of modern hygiene, rigorously followed, as far as we can endure it. Because I for one don’t do everything that I should do. And a little good cheer is better than any other remedy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I have a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>. He says that he would have written to me before had it not been that his move to Belle-Île had absorbed him.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> He’s there now, and says that he’d be pleased if sooner or later I came to spend some time there. He still wants to do my portrait again.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> He even says, ‘I would have gone to Boussod’s to see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, negresses talking,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> had it not been that I was prevented from doing so for the same reason’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">In short, he’s not refusing to buy one, but is making it understood that he wouldn’t want poorer quality than ours.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> You see that this is in any case better than nothing at all. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ll write this to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and will ask him for croquis of paintings. We shouldn’t push this business and give up on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">R.</rs> for the time being, but consider the thing as an ongoing piece of business that will come off.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">And the same for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>, I’d like him to buy a figure by G.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">He says he’s received a very fine bust of his wife from <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1319">Rodin</rs></hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and that on that occasion he lunched with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs> and that he saw the 10 paintings of Antibes then. I’m sending him <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_616">Geffroy</rs>’s article.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> He makes a very good critique of the Monets, first of all liking them very much: the difficulty attacked, the envelope of coloured air, the colour. Now after that he says, what must be repeated is that it all lacks construction everywhere, for example, with him a tree will have far too much foliage for the size of the trunk, and so always and everywhere, from the point of view of the reality of things, from the point of view of a whole number of <hi rend="italics">laws</hi> of nature, he’s pretty well hopeless. He ends by saying that this quality of attacking difficulties is what everyone should have.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I’ve received from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> 10 croquis<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> like his brothel;<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> there are 3 of them that are in the style of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1303">Redon</rs>; the enthusiasm that he has for that I don’t much share myself.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">But there’s a woman washing herself, very <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>esque, or in the style of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1055">Goya</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and a very strange landscape with figures.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">He expressly forbids me to send them to you, but you’ll receive them by the same post. I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> will buy something else from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>. Now I’ve seen work by this <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs></hi>; it’s rigorously Impressionist but not powerful, at this moment when this new technique is still preoccupying him too much to allow him to be himself.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> He’ll become stronger and will bring out his individuality, I think. But <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> does watercolours of the power of those by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_987">Destrée</rs></hi>, you know, that vile Dutchman we knew back in the old days.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> However, he’d washed some small still lifes, yellow jug on purple foreground, red jug on green, orange jug on blue: better, but it’s pretty poor.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> The village where they’re staying is <hi rend="italics">pure <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs></hi>, small peasants, nothing but that, totally <hi rend="italics">rustic</hi> and intimate. That character completely escapes them. I believe that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> has civilized and converted to civilized Christianity his lout of a landlord. At least, when you go there that scoundrel and his worthy spouse shake your hand — it’s in a café, of course<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> — when you 
  <pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> ask for a drink they have ways of refusing the money, ‘Oh, I couldn’t take money from an arti<hi rend="italics">ss</hi>’ (with two s’s). Anyhow, it’s their own fault that it’s appalling, and this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> must be getting pretty dull-witted with Macknight. I think Macknight has money, but not much.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> So they contaminate the village; if it weren’t for that, I’d go there often to work there. What one ought to do there is not talk to civilized people; but they know the stationmaster and a score of bloody nuisances, and that’s largely why they don’t do a damned thing. I’ve already said that to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1233">Mourier</rs>, who once used to believe that Macknight got on highly intelligently with the ‘man of the fields’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Naturally, these simple and naive people of the fields make fun of them, and despise them. On the contrary, if you do your work there without worrying about the village idlers with their stiff collars, then you can go into the homes of the peasants, enabling them to earn a few sous. And then that bloody Fontvieille would be a treasure to them, but the natives are — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s small peasants, innocent and gentle beings, as we know.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> It’s likely that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> will shortly do little landscapes with sheep, for boxes of sweets. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Not just my paintings, but I myself most of all, I had recently become wild-eyed, a bit like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1468">Hugo van der Goes</rs> in the painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1424">Emile Wauters</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">But having had all my beard carefully shaved off, I believe that I have as much of the very placid abbot in the same painting as of the mad painter so intelligently depicted in it. And I’m not unhappy to be somewhere between the two, because <hi rend="italics">you have to live</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Especially as there’s no getting away from the fact that one day or another there could be a crisis if you changed as far as your position with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussods</rs> was concerned. One more reason for maintaining relations with artists on my part as well as on yours.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Besides, I believe I’ve told the truth, all the same. If I succeeded in bringing back in prices the money spent, I would be doing no more than my duty. And the <hi rend="italics">practical </hi>thing I can do is the portrait. As far as drinking too much goes... I don’t know if it’s bad.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> But just look at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_292">Bismarck</rs>, who in any case is very practical and very intelligent. His little doctor told him he was drinking too much and <hi rend="italics">that he’d overtaxed himself all his life, from his stomach to his brain.</hi> B. stopped drinking there and then. Since then he’s lost ground and is dragging along. He must really be laughing inside at his doctor, whom fortunately for him he didn’t consult too soon.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Anyway, good handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Remember that with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> we should in no way change the idea of coming to his aid if the proposal is acceptable as it stands, but <hi rend="italics">we don’t need </hi>him. So, as far as working alone goes, don’t believe that it bothers me, and don’t press the matter for me, be <hi>fully assured</hi> of that.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">The portrait of a young girl is on a white background strongly tinted with Veronese green, the bodice is striped blood-red and purple. The skirt is royal blue with large orange-yellow stippling. The matt areas of flesh are yellow grey, the hair purplish, the eyebrows black, and the eyelashes, the eyes orange and Prussian blue; a sprig of oleander between the fingers, because the 2 hands are included.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 Jo van Gogh-Bonger gave the date as ‘29 Juillet’ – she may have had a postmark to go on. This date is borne out by Van Gogh’s remark that it took him all week to make <hi rend="italics">Mousmé</hi> (‘my whole week’, <ref target="#l-67">l. 67</ref>); this is a form of words that looks back over the week. He does not thank Theo for his allowance in this letter, which also helps to confirm the date since the money did not arrive until Monday (<ref target="let652.xml">see letter 652</ref>). For these reasons we have dated the letter Sunday, 29 July 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s health problems <ref target="let611.xml">(611)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Request to Russell to buy a painting from Gauguin <ref target="let582.xml">(582)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s Monet exhibition <ref target="let625.xml">(625)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>A reference to what Van Gogh says in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-88">ll. 88-91</ref> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let645.xml">letter 645</ref>. However, that was not the end of the letter – although it was of the sheet, which was not full. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs> writes in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi>: ‘<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mousmé</hi> is a word meaning a young girl or a very young woman. It is one of the prettiest words in the Japanese language; it seems to reflect both <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">moue </hi>(meaning a young girl’s funny and pretty pout) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">frimousse</hi> (meaning a young girl’s pert and sweet little face). I will use it often, not knowing any word in French that comes close to expressing the meaning’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mousmé</hi> est un mot qui signifie jeune fille ou très jeune femme. C’est un des plus jolis de la langue nipponne; il semble qu’il y ait, dans ce mot, de la <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">moue</hi> (de la petite moue gentille et drôle comme elles en font) et surtout de la <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">frimousse</hi> (de la frimousse chiffonnée comme est la leur). Je l’emploierai souvent, n’en connaissant aucun en français qui le vaille) (see Loti 1990, pp. 90-91, chapter 11).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mousmé </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2671">F 431 / JH 1519</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh painted two portraits of the Zouave: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Zouave</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2655">F 423 / JH 1486</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Seated Zouave </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2657">F 424 / JH 1488</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let647.xml">647</ref>. For Russell’s move, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let623.xml#n-16">see letter 623, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs> had painted <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vincent van Gogh</hi> in Paris in 1886 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1310">Ill. 1310</rs>. It may have been exchanged for Van Gogh’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Shoes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_655">F 332 / JH 1234</rs>). See exhib. cat. Sydney 2001, pp. 51, 130 (n. 23).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_108">Negresses talking or Conversation (Tropics)</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let627.xml#n-6">letter 627, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_107">Among the mangoes</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let612.xml#n-1">letter 612, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must mean that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>, who had previously bought work from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml">see letter 602</ref>), should buy a figure painting by him. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let623.xml#n-17">See letter 623, n. 17,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1319">Rodin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2184">Bust of Mrs Russell</rs></hi>. This must be the preliminary study in wax; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let647.xml#n-4">see letter 647, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_616">Gustave Geffroy</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_542">Dix tableaux de Claude Monet</ref>’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Justice</hi> 9 (17 June 1888), no. 3077, pp. 1-2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>For these sketches by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let649.xml#n-1">see letter 649, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brothel scene</hi>, 1888 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2322">Ill. 2322</rs>, which Vincent had sent on to Theo with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let630.xml">letter 630</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh probably counted <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2195">Lubricity</rs></hi>, which he did not think very successful, among these drawings ‘in the style of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1303">Redon</rs>’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let651.xml">see letter 651</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2202">A woman washing herself</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let649.xml#n-5">letter 649, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>See for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2196">Lane in Brittany with figures</rs></hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let649.xml#n-2">letter 649, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> made Impressionist paintings from 1885 until the end of 1888. During this period he often stayed in Moret-sur-Loing, where <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1349">Sisley</rs> was also working. See exhib. cat. Saarbrücken 1971, pp. 47, 55. There are some known landscapes by Boch from his time in Fontvieille: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_740">Flower garden in Fontvieille</rs></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_741">Houses in Fontvieille</rs> </hi>(both private collection). See exhib. cat. La Louvière 1958. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_747">Olive trees</rs></hi>, c. 1888-1889, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_748">Fruit trees in blossom</rs></hi>,<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1885-1890 (both private collection) were probably also painted during his stay in Provence. See exhib. cat. Pontoise 1994, pp. 81 (ill.), 101.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had once described this artist, who was in fact Belgian, as ‘the incarnation of mealy-mouthed pedantry’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let175.xml">letters 175</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let176.xml">176</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>These works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> have not been identified. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let603.xml#n-2">letter 603, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> were staying at Café de l’Alcazar on the Cours in Fontvieille. The café was run by Jean Peyrol and his wife Emilie Peyrol-Girard (Mairie de Fontvieille; Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts, letters from Macknight to Boch 1888-1889).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Little is known about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1189">Macknight</rs>’s financial circumstances. From 1878 he had worked for some years for the Taber Art Compagny in New Bedford, Massachusetts, which made reproductions. A friend paid for Macknight’s trip to Europe in 1883. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Awash in Color: Homer, Sargent, and the Great American Watercolor</hi>. Sue Welsh Reed and Carol Troyen. Exhib. cat. Boston (Museum of Fine Arts). Boston 1993, p. 138.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Probably an ironic reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_478">La terre</ref> </hi>(1887). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let657.xml#n-18">letter 657, n. 18.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let011.xml#n-8">See letter 11, n. 8,</ref>
  <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1424">Emile Wauters</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_447">The painter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1468">Hugo van der Goes</rs> in the red cloister</rs></hi>, a portrait of the mentally ill fifteenth-century artist.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Theo must have responded to Vincent’s remark that when life becomes too much for him, he drinks more to distract himself (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let645.xml#l-147">letter 645, ll. 147-148</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>In 1883 the physician Ernst Schweninger advised <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_292">Bismarck</rs>, whose health was poor from 1881 onwards, to eat and drink significantly less. Contrary to what Van Gogh asserts, Bismarck did benefit from the regimen. See Ernst Engelberg,<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Bismarck. Das Reich in der Mitte Europas</hi>. Berlin 1990 pp. 360-364, 593-595.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh’s source has not been identified. In any event he did not get his information from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_616">Geffroy</rs>’s article (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let630.xml#n-1">see letter 630, n. 1</ref>), although there is a reference in it to Bismarck’s heavy drinking: ‘They wanted to make him drink to get him talking. He drank, like the dreadful drinker that he is, swallowing a bottle of anything, in one go, without its even touching his lips’ (On a voulu le faire boire pour le faire parler. Il a bu, comme le terrible buveur qu’il est, avalant une bouteille de n’importe quoi, d’un coup, à la régalade, sans toucher les lèvres) (p. 25).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    