<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Sunday, 19 or Monday, 20 August 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let664"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b564 V/1962 (sheet 1) and b563 b V/1962 (sheet 2)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>664</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>523</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>668</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-08-19">Sunday, 19 or Monday, 20 August 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0564" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0564" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000760_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0563 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000759_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000759_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0563 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000759_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000759_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">bien merci de ta bonne lettre et du billet de 100 fr. qui y etait inclus<c type="kp">_</c> Et tu es bien bon de nous promettre à Gauguin et moi de nous mettre à même d’exécuter le projet d’une combinaison.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Je viens de recevoir une lettre de Bernard qui depuis quelques jours a rejoint Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> Laval et encore un autre à Pont aven<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Dans cette lettre qui d’ailleurs est très bonne il n’est cependant pas dit une syllabe de ce que Gauguin aurait l’intention de me rejoindre et pas davantage une autre syllabe de ce qu’on me demandait là-bas<c type="kp">_</c> Toutefois la lettre était tres amicale<c type="kp">_</c> De Gauguin lui-même pas un mot depuis à peu près un mois.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Moi je crois que Gauguin préfère se débrouiller avec les amis du nord et s’il vend par bonheur un ou plusieurs tableaux pourrait avoir d’autres vues que celles de me rejoindre<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">N’ai je pas<c type="kk">/</c> moi qui ai moins que lui le désir de la bataille Parisienne<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>le droit de faire à ma tête<c type="kp">_</c> Voici:</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Le jour où tu pourras<c type="kk">/</c> voudrais tu non pas me donner mais me prêter pour un an 300 francs d’un seul coup.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">alors si je mets<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> que tu m’envoies à présent 250 francs par mois<c type="kk">/</c> tu ne m’en enverrais plus que 200 après<c type="kk">/</c> jusqu’à que les 300 depensés d’un coup fussent payés<c type="kp">_</c> J’acheterais alors deux bons lits complets à 100 francs chacun et pour 100 francs d’autres meubles. Cela me mettrait en état de coucher chez moi et de pouvoir y loger Gauguin ou un autre également<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Cela me ferait un avantage de 300 francs par an car c’est toujours 1 franc par nuit que je paye au logeur<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Je me sentirais un chez moi plus fixe et réellement c’est une condition pour pouvoir travailler.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Cela n’augmenterait pas mes dépenses sur l’annee mais cela me donnerait des meubles et la possibilité d’arriver à joindre les deux bouts<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Alors<c type="kk">/</c> que Gauguin vienne ou pas c’est son affaire et du moment que nous soyons prêts à le recevoir<c type="kk">/</c> que son lit<c type="kk">/</c> son logement est là<c type="kk">/</c> c’est que nous tenons notre promesse.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’insiste sur ceci<c type="kk">/</c> le plan reste aussi vrai et aussi solide que Gauguin vienne ou non<c type="kk">/</c> pourvu que notre but ne bouge pas en tant que visant de nous délivrer<c type="kk">/</c> moi et un autre copain<c type="kk">/</c> de ce cancer qui ronge à notre travail<c type="kk">/</c> la nécessité de vivre dans des hotelleries ruineuses. Sans aucun profit pour nous.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Ce qui est pure folie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Etre insouciant<c type="kk">/</c> espérer qu’un jour ou un autre delivré<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> de la deche: pure illusion. Je me compterai bien heureux moi de travailler pour une pension juste suffisante et ma tranquilité dans mon atelier toute ma vie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Eh bien<c type="kk">/</c> si je repète encore une fois que cela m’est on ne peut plus egal de me fixer à Pont aven ou à Arles –</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je me propose d’être inflexible sur ce point de fonder un atelier fixe et de coucher là et pas à l’hôtellerie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Si tu es bon assez de nous mettre<c type="kk">/</c> Gauguin et moi<c type="kk">/</c> à même de nous installer ainsi –</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">je dis seulement ceci que si nous ne profitons pas de cette occasion pour nous delivrer des logeurs nous jetons à l’eau tout ton argent et notre possibilité de résister au siège de la dèche.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Là-dessus mon parti est bien pris et je ne veux pas céder sur ce point-là<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Dans les conditions présentes<c type="kk">/</c> tout en dépensant je n’ai pas ce qui est le juste necessaire et je ne me sens plus les forces de continuer longtemps comme cela<c type="kp">_</c>– Gauguin peut-il trouver la même occasion à Pont Aven<c type="kk">/</c> c’est bon<c type="kk">/</c> mais moi je te dis le prix d’ici où cette dépense accomplie<c type="kk">/</c> bien du gros travail sera fait. Le soleil d’ici c’est tout de même beaucoup. Comme cela est je me ruine et je m’éreinte. Maintenant c’est dit<c type="kk">/</c> je ne viens pas à Pont aven si c’est que je doive y loger à l’hotellerie avec ces anglais et ces gens de l’ecole des beaux arts avec qui on discute tous les soirs<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Tempête dans une cuvette<c type="kp">_</c> Poignee de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Vis à vis de Gauguin enfin<c type="kk">/</c> tout en l’appréciant je crois qu’il faudra agir en mère de famille et calculer les dépenses réelles<c type="kp">_</c> Si on l’écoutait on espérerait quelque chôse de bien vague pour l’avenir et on resterait à l’hôtellerie et on vivrait comme dans un enfer sans issue.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">J’aime mieux me cloitrer comme des moines<c type="kk">/</c> libre à nous d’aller egalement comme les moines au bordel ou chez le marchand de vin si le coeur nous en dit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">mais notre travail demande un chez soi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Gauguin me laisse en somme parfaitement dans le vague pour Pont aven<c type="kk">/</c> il accepte par son silence à mes lettres ma proposition de venir à lui au besoin mais il ne m’ecrit rien sur les moyens de trouver là un atelier à soi ou le prix que couteraient les meubles. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>Et cela n’est pas sans me paraitre étrange<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Non pas que cela me dérange car je sais ce que je veux et ce que je ne veux pas<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Et je suis donc bien décidé de ne pas aller à Pont aven à moins que là aussi nous trouvions une maison dans les bas prix (15 fr<c type="kp">_</c> par mois est le prix de la mienne) et que nous nous y installions de façon à pouvoir y coucher<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">J’écris à la soeur ce soir si j’en trouve le temps<c type="kp">_</c> En pensee je l’embrasse bien<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Poignee de main.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">as tu reçu les dessins des jardins<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> et les deux dessins de figure<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Je crois que le tableau de la tête de vieux paysan<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> est aussi étrange de couleur que le semeur<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> mais le semeur est un échec et la tete de paysan y est davantage<c type="kp">_</c>– Ah celle là je l’enverrai toute seule aussitot sèche et j’y mettrai une dedicace pour toi.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many thanks for your kind letter and for the 100-franc note that was included with it. And you’re very kind to promise <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and me to put us in a position to carry out the partnership project.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’ve just received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, who joined Gauguin, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs> and someone else at Pont-Aven several days ago.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> In this letter, which is very kind by the way, there isn’t, however, a syllable about whether Gauguin intends joining me, nor another syllable, moreover, asking me to go there. All the same, the letter was very friendly. From Gauguin himself, not a word for almost a month.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I personally believe that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> prefers to manage with his friends in the north, and if by good luck he sells a painting, or several, he could have ideas other than those of joining me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Do I, who have less desire than he does for the battle of Paris, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> not have the right to do as I please? Look here:</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The day when you could, would you — not give me, but lend me 300 francs for a year, all at one go?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Then if I reckon that at present you’re sending me 250 francs a month, you wouldn’t send me more than 200 after that, until the 300 paid out all at once had been paid off. Then I’d buy two good beds, complete, at 100 francs each, and other furniture for 100 francs. That would put me in a position to sleep at home, and to be able to put up <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> or another person there as well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">That would give me a saving of 300 francs a year, because it’s still 1 franc a night that I’m paying to the lodging-house keeper.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I’d have the sense of a more permanent home, and really it’s a condition for being able to work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">That wouldn’t increase my outgoings over the year, but it would give me furniture and the possibility of managing to make ends meet. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So, if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> comes or not, it’s his business, and from the moment we’re ready to receive him, and his bed, his lodging, is there, it means we’re keeping our promise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I insist on this: the plan remains as true and as firm whether <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> comes or not, as long as our goal doesn’t change, in the sense of aiming to free us, me and another pal, from this cancer that gnaws at our work, the need to live in ruinous guest-houses. Without any benefit to us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Which is sheer madness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">To be carefree, to hope that one of these days I’ll be freed from pennilessness: pure illusion. I’ll count myself well content to work for an allowance that’s just enough and my peace and quiet in my studio for the rest of my life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Well, if I repeat once more that I couldn’t be more indifferent as to whether I settled in Pont-Aven or in Arles — 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I mean to be inflexible on this point of setting up a permanent studio and to sleep there and not at the guest-house.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">If you’re kind enough to put us, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and me, in a position to set ourselves up like that —</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I only say this, that if we don’t take advantage of this opportunity to free ourselves from lodging-house keepers, we’re throwing into the water all your money and our possibility of withstanding the siege of pennilessness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">On that my mind is well and truly made up, and I don’t wish to give in on that point.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Under the present circumstances, even while spending, I don’t have what’s barely essential, and I no longer feel in myself the strength to go on very long like that. If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> can find the same opportunity at Pont-Aven, that’s fine, but I tell you the costs here, for which, once this expenditure has been made, plenty of hard work will have been done. The sun down here means a good deal, all the same. As things are, I’m ruining myself and I’m wearing myself out. Now that’s said, I’m not going to Pont-Aven if it means I have to stay at the guest-house there, with those Englishmen and those people from L’Ecole des Beaux-Arts, with whom one debates every evening.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> A storm in a wash-basin. Handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Lastly, vis-à-vis <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, however much we appreciate him, I believe we’ll have to behave like the mother of a family, and calculate the actual expenses. If we listened to him, we’d have hopes of something pretty vague for the future, and we’d stay at the guest-house and we’d live as if in a hell with no way out.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I prefer to cloister myself like the monks, free to go to the brothel, just like the monks, or to the wine shop if our heart tells us to.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">But our work requires a home.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">All in all, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> leaves me absolutely in the dark about Pont-Aven; by his silence toward my letters he accepts my offer to go to him if need be, but he writes me nothing about ways of finding a studio of our own there, or the price that furniture would cost. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> And that does seem strange to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Not that it bothers me, because I know what I want and what I don’t want.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And I’m therefore quite resolved not to go to Pont-Aven, unless there too we were to find a house at the low end of prices (15 francs a month is the price of mine), and unless we were to set ourselves up in it so as to be able to sleep there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I’ll write to our sister this evening if I find the time. I kiss her affectionately in thought.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Have you received the drawings of the gardens<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and the two figure drawings?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I believe that the painting of the head of the old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_372">peasant</rs><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> is as strange in colour as the sower,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but the sower’s a failure and the head of a peasant, that’s more like it. Ah well, I’ll send that one on its own as soon as it’s dry, and I’ll put a dedication to you on it.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">As a rule we would date the letter on or about Sunday, 19 August, given the receipt of the allowance of 100 francs. It emerges from <ref target="let663.xml">letter 663</ref>, however, that the money had not arrived by Saturday; so we have dated the letter Sunday, 19 or Monday, 20 August 1888. This is consistent with Van Gogh’s comment that it has been almost a month since he heard from Gauguin <ref target="#l-15">(ll. 15-16)</ref>: that was <ref target="let646.xml">letter 646</ref> of about 22 July.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The second sheet of this letter was previously placed with <ref target="let659.xml">letter 659</ref> of about 12 August, but since Van Gogh wrote on it: ‘I’ll write to our sister this evening if I find the time. I kiss her affectionately in thought’ <ref target="#l-136">(ll. 136-138)</ref> and Willemien did not go to Paris until 15 August (FR b2421), this sheet cannot have belonged there. We have put it with the present letter because we believe that the addition is a continuation of the issue of the financial advantages of sharing the house in Arles with Gauguin. (Hulsker, Pickvance and Dorn also suggested this move. See Hulsker, Van Gogh Museum, Documentation, memo; exhib. cat. New York 1984, p. 260 and Dorn 1990, p. 494).</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is staying at the Café de la Gare <ref target="let606.xml">(606)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Willemien’s visit to Paris (<ref target="let660.xml">660</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo’s promise to make it financially possible for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> to come was perhaps connected to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent</rs>’s legacy. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let659.xml#n-12">See letter 659, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let655.xml">letter 655</ref> of about 5 August Van Gogh had answered <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s question as to whether <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> was still in Pont-Aven in the affirmative. However, Bernard had already decided to go to Pont-Aven before he received it, as we learn from a letter he wrote to his sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_930">Madeleine</rs> on 29 July. His plan was to arrive on 8 or 10 August, and Gauguin wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1357">Schuffenecker</rs> on 14 August 1888: ‘Young Bernard is here and has brought some interesting things back from St-Briac’ (Le petit Bernard est ici et a rapporté de St-Briac des choses intéressantes) (see Harscoët-Maire 1997, p. 180 and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Correspondance Gauguin </hi>1984, p. 210). After Gauguin left for Arles, Bernard went back to Paris at the beginning of November (see exhib. cat. Mannheim 1990, p. 98). </p>
      
<p rend="indent">The ‘someone else’ in the company was either <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1237">Henry Moret</rs>, whose studio acted as a meeting place for the group surrounding Gauguin, or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_936">Ernest Ponthier de Chamaillard</rs>, whom Van Gogh referred to in later letters as ‘the other one’ and ‘the other young one’. In 1906 Chamaillard said in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mercure de France</hi>: ‘In 1888, when Gauguin was in Pont-Aven with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs>, Moret and me, he told us of the arrival of a very young painter called Bernard, whose early work he liked and from whom he hoped to see some good art’ (En 1888, alors que Gauguin se trouvait à Pont-Aven avec Laval, Moret et moi, il nous annonça l’arrivée d’un tout jeune peintre nommé Bernard, dont il appréciait les débuts, et de qui il espérait un bel effort d’art.) Quoted from Wildenstein 2001, p. 612. See also <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Henry Moret, aquarelles et peintures 1856-1913</hi>. C. Puget and C. Sauvage. Exhib. cat. Pont-Aven (Musée de Pont-Aven), 1988. Pont-Aven 1988, ‘Biographie’ (not paginated).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘mettons’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘je serai délivré’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This remark about debates with Englishmen and academic artists must have been prompted by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s letter. In Pont-Aven there was something of a hierarchy among the three hotels where artists stayed: the Americans and British stayed at the Hôtel des Voyageurs, the French and a few less well-off foreigners at the Hôtel du Lion d’Or, and the penniless painters at the Auberge Gloanec. See exhib. cat. Paris 2003, p. 24. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had written to Van Gogh about his relations with the academic artists in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let646.xml">letter 646</ref>; he wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1357">Schuffenecker</rs> on 14 August 1888: ‘All the Americans here are violently against Impressionism. I was obliged to threaten to hit them, and now we have peace’ (Ici tous les Américains sont furieux contre l’impressionisme. J’ai été obligé de menacer de cogner et maintenant nous avons la paix). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Correspondance Gauguin </hi>1984, p. 210.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Garden with flowers </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2685">F 1456 / JH 1537</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Garden of a bathhouse </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2687">F 1457 / JH 1539</rs>), and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Garden with flowers </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2669">F 1455 / JH 1512</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let657.xml#n-3">See letter 657, nn. 3</ref><ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let657.xml#n-5">-5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Patience Escalier</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘The peasant’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2695">F 1460 / JH 1549</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Joseph Roulin</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2693">F 1459 / JH 1547</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let663.xml#n-2">See letter 663, nn. 2</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let663.xml#n-3">3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Patience Escalier</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘The peasant’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2694">F 443 / JH 1548</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2646">F 422 / JH 1470</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>There are no signs that Van Gogh ever put a dedication on the painting.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    