<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Arles, on or about Sunday, 26 August 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let670"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b708 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>670</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W8</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>674</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-08-26">on or about Sunday, 26 August 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0708" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0708" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000962_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">si tu me laisses t’écrire en français vraiment cela me simplifie ma lettre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Tu me fais bien davantage plaisir à être émotionné par la sculpture que par la peinture – à plus forte raison puisque Theo m’assure que tu vois juste pour les tableaux aussi<c type="kp">_</c>– Naturellement cela ne saurait encore être un goût fixé qui n’hésistera jamais mais l’intuition<c type="kk">/</c> l’instinct est déjà beaucoup et justement ce que tout le monde n’a pas toujours<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Mais je suis tout de même très curieux de savoir l’effet que te fera le Luxembourg.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Est ce vrai<c type="kk">/</c> ce que dans les moments de bonne humeur je pense<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui est vivant dans l’art et éternellement vivant c’est d’abord le peintre et puis le tableau<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Enfin<c type="kk">/</c> qu’est ce que cela fait – seulement si l’on <hi rend="italics">voit travailler</hi> les gens c’est tout de même une chose qu’on ne trouve pas sous verre dans les musées<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Pauvre miss Harriet de Guy de Maupassant<c type="kk">/</c> elle était dans le juste peutêtre<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Mais le peintre avait il tort d’aller avec la servante de ferme<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Peutêtre pas<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Il y a toujours une fatalité bien embêtante dans la vie<c type="kp">_</c> Et bien des peintres meurent ou deviennent fous de désespoir ou paralysés dans leur production parce que personne ne les aime personellement<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">As tu déjà lu les poésies americaines de <hi rend="italics">Whitman</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Theo doit les avoir et je t’engage bien à les lire parceque c’est réellement beau d’abord et puis des anglais en parlent beaucoup actuellement.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Il voit dans l’avenir et même dans le présent un monde de santé<c type="kk">/</c> d’amour charnel large et franc – d’amitié – de travail<c type="kk">/</c> avec le grand firmament étoilé<c type="kk">/</c> quelquechôse qu’en somme on ne sait appeler que Dieu et l’éternité remis en place au-dessus de ce monde<c type="kp">_</c> Cela fait sourire d’abord tellement c’est <hi rend="italics">candide</hi><c type="kk">/</c> et puis cela fait réfléchir pour la même raison. La prière de Christophe Colomb est fort belle.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Qu’est ce que tu dis du bouquet de fleurs de Monticelli qui est chez Theo<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> et de la femme espagnole de Prevost<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Voilà deux vrais tableaux du midi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Je pense moi ici énormément à Monticelli. C’était un homme fort – un peu toqué et même beaucoup – rêvant soleil et amour et gaité mais toujours embêté par la pauvreté<c type="kk">/</c> un goût extrêmement raffiné de coloriste<c type="kk">/</c> un homme de race rare continuant les meilleures traditions anciennes<c type="kp">_</c>– Il meurt à Marseille assez tristement et probablement en passant par un véritable Ghetsémane<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Eh bien moi je suis sûr que je le continue ici comme si j’etais son fils ou son frère<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Nous parlions tout à l’heure de fatalité qui nous parait triste<c type="kp">_</c> Mais n’en existe-t-il pas une autre de fatalité charmante. Et qu’est ce que cela nous fait qu’il y ait ou non une résurrection lorsque nous voyons immédiatement surgir un homme vivant à la place d’un homme mort. Reprenant la même cause<c type="kk">/</c> continuant le même travail<c type="kk">/</c> vivant de la même vie<c type="kk">/</c> mourant de la même mort<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Lorsque l’ami Gauguin sera ici et que nous irons à Marseille<c type="kk">/</c> je me suis bien proposé de me promener là sur la Cannebière<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> absolument vêtu comme lui<c type="kk">/</c> comme j’ai vu son portrait<c type="kk">/</c> avec un immense chapeau jaune<c type="kk">/</c> un veston de velours noir<c type="kk">/</c> un pantalon blanc<c type="kk">/</c> des gants jaunes et une canne de roseau et avec un grand air méridional<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Et je trouverai des marseillais qui l’auront connu vivant et si tu as lu dans Tartarin ce que c’est que <hi rend="italics">fên de brût</hi>.......<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> On en fera du bruit à cette occasion<c type="kp">_</c> Monticelli est un peintre qui a fait le midi en plein jaune<c type="kk">/</c> en plein orangé<c type="kk">/</c> en plein souffre. La plupart des peintres parcequ’ils ne sont pas <hi rend="italics">coloristes</hi> proprement dits n’y voient pas ces couleurs et prétendent fou le peintre qui voit avec d’autres yeux que les leurs. (tu verras au Luxembourg des Monthenard qui ne sont pas jaunes.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> et que j’aime tout de même beaucoup. Mais il est probable que Monthenard trouverait absolument méprisable ce que moi je fais<c type="kp">_</c> ) Tout cela est naturellement prévu<c type="kp">_</c> Aussi moi j’ai déjà prêt exprès un tableau en plein jaune de tournesols (14 fleurs) dans un vase jaune et sur un fond jaune<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> (c’en est encore un autre que le précédent avec 12 fleurs sur fond bleu vert)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Et je compte un jour exposer celui là à Marseille<c type="kp">_</c>– Et tu verras qu’il y aura un marseillais ou un autre qui se souviendra de ce que Monticelli a dit et fait dans le temps. Est ce que Theo t’a montré déjà de la barbotine<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> c’est bien beau. amuse toi bien, en pensée je t’embrasse<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">If you’ll let me write to you in French, that will really make my letter easier for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">You please me much more by being moved by sculpture than by painting — all the more so since Theo assures me that you also have a good eye for paintings. Naturally, that couldn’t yet be a settled taste, which will never waver, but intuition, instinct, is already a great deal, and precisely what everyone doesn’t always have.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">But all the same, I’m very curious to know what effect the Luxembourg will have on you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Is it true, as I think in moments when I’m in a good mood, that what is alive in art, and eternally alive, is first the painter and then the painting?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Well, what difference does that make — but if one <hi rend="italics">sees</hi> people <hi rend="italics">working</hi> it’s still something one doesn’t find under glass in museums.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Poor Miss Harriet in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>, she was right, perhaps.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But was the painter wrong to go with the farm-girl?<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Perhaps not.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">In life there’s always a fate that’s very annoying. And many painters die or go mad from despair, or become paralyzed in their production because nobody loves them personally.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Have you read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_840">Whitman</rs>’s American poems yet? Theo should have them, and I really urge you to read them, first because they’re really beautiful, and also, English people are talking about them a lot at the moment.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> He sees in the future, and even in the present, a world of health, of generous, frank carnal love — of friendship — of work, with the great starry firmament, something, in short, that one could only call God and eternity, put back in place above this world. They make you smile at first, they’re so <hi rend="italics">candid</hi>, and then they make you think, for the same reason. The prayer of Christopher Columbus is very beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What do you say about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s bouquet of flowers that’s at Theo’s,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1275">Prévost</rs>’s Spanish woman?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> There are two real paintings of the south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I myself think about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> a great deal down here. He was a strong man — a little, even very, cracked — dreaming of sunshine and love and gaiety, but always frustrated by poverty, a colourist’s extremely refined taste, a man of rare breeding, carrying on the best ancient traditions. He died in Marseille, rather sadly and probably after going through a real Gethsemane.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Ah well, I myself am sure that I’ll carry him on here as if I were his son or his brother.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">We were talking just now about a fate that seemed sad to us. But isn’t there another, delightful fate? And what is it to us if there is or isn’t a resurrection, when we see a living man rise up immediately in a dead man’s place? Taking up the same cause, carrying on the same work, living the same life, dying the same death.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">When friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s here, and we go to Marseille, I firmly intend to walk there on the Canebière,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> dressed exactly like him, as I’ve seen his portrait, with an enormous yellow hat, a black velvet jacket, white trousers, yellow gloves and a reed cane and with a great southern air.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">And I’ll find Marseillais who knew him when he was alive, and if you’ve read in Tartarin what <hi rend="italics">fên de brût</hi> is.......<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> We’ll make quite a noise on that occasion. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> is a painter who did the south all in yellow, all in orange, all in sulphur. Most painters, because they’re not <hi rend="italics">colourists,</hi> properly speaking, don’t see these colours there, and declare that a painter who sees with other eyes than theirs is mad. (In the Luxembourg you’ll see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1241">Montenard</rs>s that aren’t yellow,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and I like them very much all the same. But it’s likely that Montenard would find what I do totally contemptible.) All that is to be expected, of course. So I’ve already prepared especially a painting all in yellow of sunflowers (14 flowers) in a yellow vase and against a yellow background<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> (it’s yet another one, in addition to the previous one with 12 flowers against a blue-green background).<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> And I expect one day to exhibit that one in Marseille. And you’ll see that there’ll be some Marseillais or other who will remember what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> once said and did. Has Theo shown you the barbotine yet?<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> It’s really fine. Enjoy yourself, I kiss you in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This letter to Willemien, who was staying with Theo in Paris, was probably enclosed with <ref target="let669.xml">letter 669</ref>, so we have dated it on or about Sunday, 26 August 1888. See also the notes to <ref target="let665.xml">letter 665</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Probably enclosed with <ref target="let669.xml">letter 669</ref>.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Willemien’s visit to Paris <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_500">Miss Harriet</ref></hi> (1884) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs> is a collection of twelve stories and novellas; the opening story – ‘Miss Harriet’ – is a tragic love story. When he is twenty-five, the painter Leon Chenal gets to know the English spinster Harriet, a fanatical propagandist for Protestantism. The two meet often, but when Harriet becomes deeply unhappy on seeing a painting of a pair of lovers, Leon decides to leave. The evening before his departure he has a fling with the maid Céleste, and Harriet, who witnesses this, takes a drastic decision – she throws herself down a well.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The American poet <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_840">Walt Whitman</rs>’s reputation had been established in England since the 1870s; in France his work did not really start to be appreciated until the 1880s and 1890s. Whitman’s poems were published in a French translation in the magazines <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Vogue </hi>and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Revue Indépendante </hi>in 1886 and 1887. </p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> took Vincent’s advice. As early as October 1888 she wrote to Theo: ‘Your Whitman’s doing the rounds, too. I thought it was so wonderfully good that for the moment it has spoiled my taste for lighter poetry altogether, or rather taken it away. Those verses are so solid and broad, nothing can compare, a healthy, powerful, hard-working love of life shines through them, refreshing. I have enjoyed them’ (FR b2275).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_840">Walt Whitman</rs>’s ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_501">Prayer of Columbus</ref>’ was included in his anthology <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Leaves of grass</hi> (1881). It is a poetic rendition of a prayer that Columbus addresses to God, in which the explorer puts his religious feelings and existential doubts into words. Since Van Gogh quotes the French title of the poem, it is possible that he read Whitman’s poetry in the French translation.</p>

<p rend="indent">For a possible connection between Whitman’s poetry and Van Gogh’s work see Hope B. Werness, ‘Whitman and Van Gogh: starry nights and other similarities’, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 2-4 (1985), pp. 35-41.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-4">See letter 578, n. 4,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_306">Vase of flowers</rs></hi>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let658.xml#n-9">See letter 658, n. 9,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1275">Prévost</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2216">Lady with a dog</rs></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s last years <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let603.xml#n-3">see letter 603, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>‘La Canebière’ is Marseille’s main boulevard, which leads to the old docks.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1728">Jules Monge</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Adolphe Monticelli</hi>, 1883 (Paris, Musée d’Orsay), or the similar drawing on the cover of the weekly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Provence Artistique et Pittoresque</hi> 1 (21 August 1881), no. 12. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2235">Ill. 2235</rs>. In the accompanying article A. Meyer described <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> as follows: ‘I can still see him striding up and down the Avenues, dressed in a baggy black velvet jacket, over immaculate white trousers, dazzling long cuffs showing above his yellow gloves, dispensing good humour all along this fashionable walk of the time.’ (Je le vois encore arpentant les Allées; vêtu d’un grand sac en velours noir, sur un pantalon d’un blanc immaculé, avec de longues manchettes éclatantes qui tranchaient sur ses gants jaunes, étalant sa belle humeur sur cette promenade alors à la mode.) Since Monticelli wears a flat black cap in the portrait, the ‘enormous yellow hat’ must be Van Gogh’s own embellishment, probably because he had one himself; in his previous letter (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let669.xml">669</ref>) he wrote that he had bought a hat and a black velvet jacket.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let599.xml#n-6">See letter 599, n. 6,</ref> for the expression ‘fen de brut’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Alphonse Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Tartarin de Tarascon</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is probably referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1241">Frédéric Montenard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The warship La Corrèze leaving Toulon Roads</hi>, which was placed in the Musée National du Luxembourg in 1887 (Brignoles, Musée du pays Brignolais, géré par le Musée d’Orsay). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1178">Ill. 1178</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let668.xml#n-2">See letter 668, n. 2,</ref> for the number of flowers.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>). See Dorn 1999, pp. 49; Van Tilborgh and Hendriks 2001, p. 22, for the number of flowers.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>For ‘barbotine’ (slip or liquid clay) and the association with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let663.xml#n-7">see letter 663, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    