<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Saturday, 1 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let672"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b572 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>672</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>530</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>676</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-01">Saturday, 1 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0572" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0572" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000769_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo, </p>
<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">un mot à la hâte pour te remercier énormement du prompt envoi de ta lettre.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Justement mon bonhomme était déjà venu ce matin à la première heure pour son loyer<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> il a naturellement fallu me prononcer aujourd’hui si oui ou non je garderais la maison (car je l’ai louée jusqu’à la S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Michel et il faut d’avance renouveler ou se dédire)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> J’ai dit à mon bonhomme que je reprenais pour 3 mois seulement ou au mois encore plutôt encore.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> Ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> supposant que l’ami Gauguin arriverait<c type="kk">/</c> nous n’aurions pas dans le cas que cela ne lui plairait pas<c type="kk">/</c> un bien long bail devant nous.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Bien trop souvent je me décourage à fond en songeant à ce que dira Gauguin du pays à la longue. L’isolement est bien serieux ici et toujours en payant il faut se tailler des degrés dans la glace pour aller de la journée de travail au meme lendemain.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> La difficulté pour les modèles existe<c type="kk">/</c> seulement la patience et surtout d’avoir continuellement quelques sous naturellement y peut quelque chôse<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Mais cette difficulté est réelle<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je sens que même encore à l’heure qu’il est je pourrais être un tout autre peintre si j’etais capable de forcer la question des modèles<c type="kp">_</c> Mais je sens aussi la possibilité de m’abrutir et de voir passer l’heure de la puissance de production artistique comme dans le cours de la vie on perd ses couilles. Cela c’est la fatalité et naturellement ici comme là c’est l’aplomb et le battre le fer pendant qu’il est chaud qui est d’urgence.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Aussi je me morfonds tres souvent. Mais Gauguin et tant d’autres se trouvent exactement dans la même position et nous devons surtout chercher le remède en dedans de nous<c type="kk">/</c> dans la bonne volonté et la patience<c type="kp">_</c> En nous contentant de n’être que des médiocretés. Peut être ainsi faisant préparons nous une nouvelle voie.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Je suis bien curieux de recevoir ta prochaine lettre rendant compte plus amplement de ta visite chez Bing<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Cela ne m’étonne pas que tu dises qu’après le départ de la soeur tu sentiras un vide. Il faut surtout chercher à le combler. Et qu’est ce qui s’y opposerait que Gauguin viendrait rester avec<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> toi<c type="kp">_</c> Il pourrait ainsi se satisfaire au sujet de Paris tout en travaillant<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Seulement dans ce cas ce ne serait que comme de juste qu’également il te rembourse en tableaux ce que tu ferais pour lui. Moi cela m’est une douleur continuelle de faire relativement si peu avec l’argent que je dépense<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Ma vie est agitée et inquiète mais enfin en changeant<c type="kk">/</c> en bougeant de place beaucoup<c type="kk">/</c> peutêtre ne ferais je qu’empirer les chôses<c type="kp">_</c> Cela me fait énormement du tort que je ne parle pas le patois provençal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Je pense toujours très sérieusement à me servir de couleurs plus grossieres qui n’en seraient pas moins solides pour être moins broyées<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Maintenant je m’arrête souvent devant un projet de tableau à cause de la couleur que cela nous coûte. Or cela est tout de même un peu dommage pour cette bonne raison que nous avons peutetre la puissance de travailler aujourd’hui<c type="kk">/</c> seulement ignorons si elle se maintiendra demain.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Tout de même plutôt que de perdre des forces physiques j’en reprends et surtout l’estomac est plus fort. Je t’envoie aujourd’hui 3 volumes de Balzac<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> cela est bien un peu vieux etc<c type="kp">_</c> mais du Daumier et du de Lemud n’est pas plus laid pour apartenir à une epoque qui n’existe plus. Je lis dans ce moment enfin l’immortel de Daudet que je trouve <hi rend="italics">très beau</hi> mais bien peu consolant<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Je crois que je serai obligé de lire un livre sur la chasse à l’éléphant ou un livre absolument menteur d’aventures catégoriquement impossibles de par exemple Gustave Aimard<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> pour faire passer le navrement que l’immortel va me laisser. Justement parce que c’est si beau et si vrai en tant que faisant sentir le neant du monde civilisé. Je dois dire que je préfère comme force vraie son Tartarin<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> pourtant. Bien des chôses à la soeur et encore une fois merci de ta lettre.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">t<c type="kp">_</c> à toi</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">A line in haste to thank you very, very much indeed for the prompt dispatch of your letter.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> In fact, my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_755">chap</rs> had already come first thing this morning for his rent.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Of course, I had to make my decision known today whether or not I’d keep the house on (because I rented it until Michaelmas, and you have to renew or withdraw beforehand).<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I told my chap that I’d take it on again for 3 months only, or preferably by the month. That way, supposing that our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> arrived, we wouldn’t have a very long lease ahead of us should he not like it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Far too often I become thoroughly discouraged, thinking about what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> will say about this part of the country in the long run. Isolation here is quite considerable, and while paying, you have to hack each step out of the ice in order just to get from one day’s work to the same the next day.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> The difficulty about models is there, but patience, and especially always having a few sous, can help there, of course. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> But this difficulty is real.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I feel that even at the present time I could be an entirely different painter if I was able to settle the question of models. But I also feel the possibility of getting dull-witted and of seeing the time of potency in artistic production disappearing, just as in the course of life our balls start to let us down. That’s inevitable, and of course, here as there it’s self-confidence and striking while the iron’s hot that’s pressing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And so I very often feel despondent. But <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and so many others are in exactly the same position, and we must above all look for the remedy within ourselves, in good will and patience. By being content to be no more than mediocrities. Acting like that, perhaps we’ll open up a new path. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’m very curious to receive your next letter, reporting more fully on your visit to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_290">Bing</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> It doesn’t surprise me that you say that after our sister’s departure you’ll feel an empty gap. You must above all try to fill it. And what could there be against <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s coming to live with you? That way he could satisfy himself on the subject of Paris while working at the same time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But in that case it would only be fair that he should also reimburse you in paintings for what you would do for him. For me, it’s a constant sorrow to do so comparatively little with the money I spend.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">My life is restless and anxious, but then, moving house and moving around a lot, perhaps I would only make things worse. It makes enormous trouble for me that I don’t speak the Provençal patois. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’m still thinking very seriously about using coarser colours, which would be no less solid for being less finely ground.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">At present I often stop myself when planning a painting, because of the paint it costs us. Now, that’s rather a pity, all the same, for this good reason, that perhaps we have the power to work today, but we don’t know if it’ll still be there tomorrow.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">All the same, rather than losing physical strength, I’m regaining it, and my stomach, especially, is stronger. I’m sending you 3 volumes of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> today;<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> it’s really a bit old, etc., but the work of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1167">De Lemud</rs> is no uglier for belonging to a period that doesn’t exist any more. At the moment, I’m at last reading <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s L’immortel, which I find <hi rend="italics">very beautiful</hi> but hardly consoling.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I believe that I’ll have to read a book about elephant hunting, or a totally mendacious book of categorically impossible adventures, by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_510">Gustave Aimard</rs><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> for example, in order to get over the heartbreak that L’immortel will leave in me. Particularly because it’s so beautiful and so true, in making one feel the emptiness of the civilized world. I must say that for real power I prefer his Tartarin<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> though. Warm regards to our sister, and once again, thank you for your letter.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter must have been written on 1 September. We know this because the landlord came to collect the rent that day and Van Gogh had to let him know whether or not he wanted to go on renting the Yellow House <ref target="#l-6">(l. 6)</ref>. It emerges from <ref target="let654.xml">letter 654</ref> that the landlord usually came for his money on the first of the month. Jo van Gogh-Bonger also gave it this date in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 and she may have had a postmark to go on. Accordingly, we date it Saturday, 1 September 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Willemien’s visit to Paris <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo had complied with Vincent’s request in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let671.xml">letter 671</ref> to send his allowance early.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The rent was undoubtedly collected by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_755">Bernard Soulè</rs>, the owner’s agent. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml#n-19">See letter 602, n. 19.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let654.xml#n-2">See letter 654, n. 2,</ref> for the lease expiry date.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>To be understood as: ‘nog veel liever’ (much rather).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must have got the saying ‘you have to hack each step out of the ice’ from chapter 10 of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref> </hi>(see Daudet 1986-1994, vol. 3, p. 640).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo’s visit to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_290">Siegfried Bing</rs>’s art gallery would have been to do with the ‘stock’ of prints Vincent had there. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml#n-5">See letter 637, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habiter chez’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Vincent had previously debated the use of more coarsely ground paint; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let668.xml">see letter 668</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The three volumes of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs> that Van Gogh sent probably included the novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_488">César Birotteau</ref></hi> (1837), which he had promised to send Theo; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let636.xml#n-8">see letter 636, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Alphonse Daudet</rs><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_504">L’immortel – Moeurs parisiennes</ref></hi>, which had appeared in book form two months earlier, satirizes the academic world with its untalented people. The book is indeed not very comforting: Astier-Réhu, the central character, commits suicide.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_510">Gustave Aimard</rs>, who travelled widely, wrote more than a hundred novels of adventure and travel that were very popular in their day, including <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_505">Les trappeurs de l’Arkansas</ref></hi> (1858) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_506">La loi de lynch</ref></hi> (1859). Van Gogh may have come up with the name by way of Tartarin, the self-styled lion hunter in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s eponymous novels, who is a great fan of Aimard’s tales. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_459">Tartarin de Tarascon</ref> </hi>and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref></hi> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">see letter 583, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    