<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Pont-Aven, on or about Saturday, 8 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let675"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b846 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>675</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>GAC 31</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>682</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-08">on or about Saturday, 8 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Pont-Aven</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0846" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001132_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001132_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0846" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001132_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001132_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Vincent</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Je reçois votre lettre au moment où j’allais vous écrire.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Excusez si j’écris si peu souvent et si court. Je m’ennuie terriblement et je souffre de l’estomac; nous avons de la pluie constamment. Je travaille et je ne fais rien<c type="kk">/</c> en ce sens que je dessine de la main<c type="kk">/</c> de la tête et de coeur en vue de ce que je veux faire plus tard. Oui vous avez raison de vouloir de la peinture avec une coloration suggestive d’idées poetiques et en ce sens je suis d’accord avec vous avec une différence. Je ne connais pas d’<hi rend="italics">idées poétiques</hi><c type="kk">/</c> c’est probablement un sens qui me manque. Je trouve TOUT poetique et c’est dans les coins de mon coeur qui sont parfois mysterieux que j’entrevois la poesie. Les formes et les couleurs conduites en harmonies produisent d’elles mêmes une poesie. Sans me laisser surprendre par le motif je ressens devant le tableau d’un autre une sensation qui m’amène à un état poetique selon que les forces intellectuelles du peintre s’en dégagent.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Inutile d’ergoter là-dessus; nous en causerons longuement. À ce propos je suis bien chagrin d’être retenu à Pont Aven; chaque jour la dette augmente et rend mon voyage de plus en plus improbable. C’est un long calvaire à parcourir que la vie d’artiste! et c’est peut-être ce qui nous fait vivre. La passion vivifie et nous mourons lorsqu’elle n’a plus d’aliment. Quittons 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>ces sentiers remplis de buissons épineux<c type="kk">/</c> ils ont pourtant leur poésie sauvage.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’étudie le petit Bernard<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> que je connais moins que vous; je crois que vous lui ferez du bien et il en a besoin. Il a naturellement souffert et il débute dans la vie rempli de fiel<c type="kk">/</c> entrainé à voir le mauvais côté de l’homme. J’espère qu’avec son intelligence et son amour de l’art il s’apercevra un jour que la bonté est une force contre les autres et une consolation pour nos malheurs propres. Il vous aime et vous estime, vous pouvez donc avoir une bonne influence sur lui<c type="kp">_</c>– Nous avons besoin d’être très unis de coeur et d’intelligence si nous voulons que l’avenir nous mette à notre vraie place.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Est-ce que votre frère est en voyage<c type="kk">/</c> je n’ai plus de ses nouvelles<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">cordialement à vous</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Paul Gauguin</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Vincent</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter the very moment I was about to write to you.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Excuse me if I write so infrequently and so briefly. I’m terribly bored and I’m suffering from stomach trouble; we have rain constantly. I work and I do nothing, in the sense that I draw with hand, head and heart, with a view to what I wish to do later. Yes, you’re right to wish for painting with a coloration suggesting poetic ideas, and in that sense I’m in agreement with you, with one difference. I don’t know any <hi rend="italics">poetic ideas</hi>, it’s probably a sense that I lack. I find EVERYTHING poetic, and it’s in the corners of my heart which are sometimes mysterious that I catch a glimpse of poetry. Forms and colours brought into harmonies create a form of poetry in themselves. Without allowing myself to be surprised by the subject, when looking at a painting by someone else, I feel a sensation that leads me into a poetic state depending on whether the painter’s intellectual powers emanate from it.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> There’s no point quibbling about it; we’ll talk about it at length. In that respect, I’m very despondent at being detained at Pont-Aven; my debt is increasing every day, and making my journey more and more unlikely. The artist’s life is one long Calvary to go through! And that’s perhaps what makes us live. Passion enlivens us, and we die when it has nothing more to feed on. Let’s leave 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> these paths full of thorny bushes, but they have their wild poetry all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’m studying young <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> whom I don’t know as well as you do; I believe you’ll do him good, and he needs it. He has suffered, of course, and he’s starting out in life full of bile, ready to see man’s bad side. I hope that with his intelligence and his love of art he’ll see one day that goodness is a force against others, and a consolation for our own ills. He likes you and respects you, so you can have a good influence on him. We need to be very united in heart and in intellect if we wish the future to put us in our true place.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Is your brother travelling? I have no more news from him.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Cordially yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter is a reply to a letter from Van Gogh written in the week prior to Saturday, 8 September (<ref target="let676.xml">see letter 676</ref>). Vincent sent the present letter on to Theo on or about 11 September <ref target="let679.xml">(679)</ref>. On the assumption that he did this soon after he received it, we have dated the letter on or about Saturday, 8 September. The <hi rend="italics">Météo-France </hi>data do not provide any further points of reference. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This letter is written on paper with the printed letterhead (crossed out) of the canvas manufacturer Dillies &amp; Cie. Gauguin had worked as a sales representative for this company in 1884-1885, when he spent some months with his family in Copenhagen. See Wildenstein<hi rend="italics"> </hi>2001, p. 592. The present letter was probably sent together with an (unknown) letter from Bernard; cf. the wording at the beginning of <ref target="let679.xml">letter 679</ref>. Van Gogh sent Gauguin’s letter on to Theo (<ref target="let679.xml">see letter 679</ref>).</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s illness <ref target="let581.xml">(581)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> must be replying here to the letter Van Gogh said he had written in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let676.xml">letter 676</ref> of 8 September.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See Van Uitert 1983, pp. 13-16, for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s symbolist art theory of emotion, based on Swedenborg and Balzac</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Emile Bernard</rs> had been in Pont-Aven for a month, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let664.xml">see letter 664</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    