<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Arles, Sunday, 9 and about Friday, 14 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let678"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b707 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>678</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W7</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>681</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-09">Sunday, 9 and about Friday, 14 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0707 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0707 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000960_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0707 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000961_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000961_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0707 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000961_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000961_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">ta lettre m’a fait bien plaisir et aujourd’hui j’ai le loisir de te répondre tranquillement<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ainsi ta visite à Paris a bien réussie<c type="kk">/</c> je voudrais bien que l’année prochaine tu viennes ici également. Dans ce moment je suis en train de meubler l’atelier de façon à pouvoir toujours loger quelqu’un. Car il y a 2 petites pieces en haut qui donnent sur un jardin public tres joli et où le matin on peut apercevoir le soleil levant<c type="kp">_</c> Une de ces pieces je l’arrangerai pour loger un ami et l’autre sera pour moi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Là je veux rien que des chaises de pailles et une table et un lit en bois blanc<c type="kp">_</c> Les murs blanchis à la chaux<c type="kk">/</c> le carreau rouge. Mais j’y veux un grand luxe de portraits et d’etudes peintes de figures que je compte faire à fur et à mesure. J’en ai un pour commencer<c type="kk">/</c> le portrait d’un jeune impressioniste Belge<c type="kk">/</c> je l’ai peint un peu en poète<c type="kk">/</c> la tête fine &amp; nerveuse se détachant sur un fond de ciel de nuit d’un outremer profond avec les scintillements des étoiles.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Maintenant l’autre chambre je la voudrais presque élégante avec un lit en noyer à couverture bleue.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Et tout le reste<c type="kk">/</c> la table à toilette et la commode également en noyer mat<c type="kp">_</c> Dans cette toute petite pièce je veux, à la japonaise, fourrer au moins 6 très grandes toiles<c type="kk">/</c> surtout les énormes bouquets de tournesols.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Tu sais que les Japonais cherchent instinctivement des contrastes et mangent des piments sucrés<c type="kk">/</c> des bonbons salés et des glaces frites et des fritures glacées<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Alors aussi dans une grande chambre il faudrait probablement selon le même système ne mettre que de forts petits tableaux mais dans une toute petite piece on en mettra beaucoup de grands.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">J’espère que le jour viendra où je pourrai te montrer ce beau pays d’ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Je viens de terminer une toile qui représente un interieur de café la nuit éclairé par des lampes<c type="kp">_</c> Quelques pauvres rodeurs de nuit dorment dans un coin<c type="kp">_</c> La salle est peinte en rouge et là-dedans sous le gaz le billard vert qui projette une immense ombre sur le plancher. Dans cette toile il y a 6 ou 7 rouges differents<c type="kk">/</c> depuis le rouge sang jusqu’au rose tendre<c type="kk">/</c> faisant opposition à autant de verts pâles ou foncés<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">J’en ai aujourd’hui envoye un dessin à Theo qui est comme un crepon Japonais.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Theo m’a écrit qu’il t’a donné des japonaiseries<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> C’est certes le moyen le plus pratique pour arriver à comprendre la direction qu’actuellement a prise la peinture. colorée et claire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Pour moi ici je n’ai pas besoin de Japonaiseries car je me dis toujours <hi rend="italics">qu’ici je suis</hi> <hi rend="italics">au Japon</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Que conséquemment je n’ai qu’à ouvrir les yeux et à peindre droit devant moi ce qui me fait de l’effet.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">As tu vu chez nous un tout petit masque de femme japonaise souriante et grasse? il est bien surprenant d’expression ce petit masque-là<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Y aurais tu pensé d’emporter pour toi un tableau de moi<c type="kp">_</c> je l’espère et je suis assez intrigué pour savoir lequel tu aurais choisi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> J’avais moi pensé que tu aurais pris les cabanes blanches sous le ciel bleu dans de la verdure que j’ai faites à S<hi rend="super">tes</hi> Maries au bord de la Mediterranée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">je devrais déjà être retourné à S<hi rend="super">tes</hi> Maries maintenant qu’il y a du monde sur la plage. mais enfin<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai tellement à faire ici meme.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Je veux maintenant absolument peindre un ciel étoilé. Souvent il me semble que la nuit est encore plus richement coloré que le jour<c type="kk">/</c> colorée des violets<c type="kk">/</c> des bleus et des verts les plus intenses.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Lorsque tu y feras attention tu verras que de certaines étoiles sont citronnées<c type="kk">/</c> d’autres ont des feux roses<c type="kk">/</c> verts, bleus myosotys<c type="kp">_</c> Et sans insister davantage il est évident que pour peindre un ciel étoilé il ne suffise point du tout de mettre des points blancs sur du noir bleu.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ma maison ici est peinte en dehors en jaune beurre frais à volets verts cru et elle est en plein soleil sur la place où il y a un jardin vert de platanes<c type="kk">/</c> de lauriers roses<c type="kk">/</c> d’accacias<c type="kp">_</c> En dedans elle est toute blanchie à la chaux et le sol est en briques rouges. Et le ciel bleu intense dessus<c type="kp">_</c> Là-dedans je peux vivre et respirer moi et réflechir et peindre<c type="kp">_</c> Et il me semble que j’irais plus loin dans le Sud plutôt que de remonter vers le nord puisque j’ai trop grand besoin de la forte chaleur pour que mon sang circule normalement<c type="kp">_</c> Ici je me porte bien mieux qu’à Paris<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Or je n’en doute guère que pour toi aussi tu aimerais enormement le midi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">C’est le soleil qui ne nous a jamais assez pénétré<c type="kk">/</c> nous autres du nord.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Il y a déjà plusieurs jours que j’ai commencé cette lettre jusqu’ici et je reprends maintenant.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">j’ai été interrompu justement par le travail que m’a donné de ces jours ci un nouveau tableau réprésentant l’extérieur d’un café le soir<c type="kp">_</c> Sur la terrasse il y a de petites figurines de buveurs. Une immense lanterne jaune éclaire la terrasse, la devanture<c type="kk">/</c> le trottoir<c type="kk">/</c> et projette meme une lumiere sur les pavés de la rue<c type="kk">/</c> qui prend une teinte de violet rose<c type="kp">_</c> Les pignons des maisons d’une rue qui file sous le ciel bleu constellé d’etoiles sont bleus foncés ou violets avec un arbre vert.– Voila un tableau de nuit sans noir. rien qu’avec du beau bleu et du violet et du vert<c type="kk">/</c> et dans cet entourage la place illuminée se colore de souffre pâle<c type="kk">/</c> de citron vert.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Cela m’amuse enormement de peindre la nuit sur place<c type="kp">_</c> Autrefois on dessinait et peignait le tableau le jour d’après le dessin. Mais moi je m’en trouve bien de peindre la chôse immediatement. Il est bien vrai que dans l’obscurité je peux prendre un bleu pour un vert<c type="kk">/</c> un lilas bleu pour un lilas rose puisqu’on ne distingue pas bien la qualité du ton<c type="kp">_</c> Mais c’est le seul moyen de sortir de la nuit noire conventionelle avec une pauvre lumière blafarde et blanchâtre alors que pourtant une simple bougie déjà nous donne les jaunes<c type="kk">/</c> les orangés les plus riches.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> J’ai aussi fait un nouveau portrait de moi-même comme étude où j’ai l’air d’un japonais.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Tu ne m’as jamais dit si tu avais lu Bel ami de Guy de Maupassant et ce que tu penses maintenant en general de son talent. Je dis cela parceque le commencement de Bel ami est justement la description d’une nuit étoilée à Paris avec les cafés illuminés du Boulevard<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> et c’est à peu près ce même sujet que je viens de peindre maintenant.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Parlant de Guy de Maupassant<c type="kk">/</c> je trouve bien beau ce qu’il fait et je te recommande bien de lire tout ce qu’il a fait<c type="kp">_</c>– Zola – Maupassan<c type="kk">/</c> de Goncourt<c type="kk">/</c> il faut les avoir lu aussi complètement que possible pour voir un peu clair dans le roman moderne<c type="kp">_</c> As tu lu du Balzac<c type="kk">/</c> je le relis encore ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Ma chère soeur je crois que actuellement il faut peindre les aspects riches et magnifiques de la nature<c type="kk">/</c> nous avons besoin de gaité et de bonheur<c type="kk">/</c> d’esperance et d’amour.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Plus je me fais laid<c type="kk">/</c> vieux<c type="kk">/</c> mechant<c type="kk">/</c> malade<c type="kk">/</c> pauvre<c type="kk">/</c> plus je veux me venger en faisant de la couleur brillante<c type="kk">/</c> bien arrangée<c type="kk">/</c> resplendissante.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Les byjoutiers sont vieux et laids aussi avant de savoir bien arranger les pierres précieuses. Et arranger les couleurs dans un tableau pour les faire vibrer et valoir par leur opposition cela c’est quelque chôse comme d’aranger les bijoux ou – d’inventer des costumes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Tu vas voir qu’en regardant habituellement maintenant les japonaiseries tu aimeras encore davantage à faire des bouquets<c type="kk">/</c> à travailler dans les fleurs. Je dois finir cette lettre si je veux la faire partir aujourd’hui. Je serai tres content d’avoir le portrait de la mère dont tu parles<c type="kk">/</c> n’oublie donc pas de me l’envoyer<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Dis lui bien des chôses de ma part à la mère<c type="kk">/</c> je pense souvent à vous deux et j’en suis bien content de ce que maintenant tu connais un peu mieux notre vie. Je crains bien que Theo se trouvera trop seul. mais de ces jours ci il aura un peintre impressioniste Belge<c type="kk">/</c> celui dont je te parle plus haut<c type="kk">/</c> qui viendra passer un temps à Paris. Puis il y aura beaucoup d’autres peintres qui vont bientot rentrer à Paris avec leurs études faites pendant la belle saison<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Je t’embrasse bien et la mère<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Your letter gave me great pleasure, and today I have the leisure to reply to you in peace and quiet.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> So your visit to Paris was a great success. I would really like it if you were to come here too next year. At the moment I’m furnishing the studio in such a way as always to be able to put someone up. Because there are 2 small rooms upstairs, which look out on a very pretty public garden, and where you can see the sunrise in the morning. I’ll arrange one of these rooms for putting up a friend, and the other one will be for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I want nothing there but straw-bottomed chairs and a table and a deal bed. The walls whitewashed, the tiles red. But in it I want a great wealth of portraits and painted studies of figures, which I plan to do as I go along. I have one to start with, the portrait of a young <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Belgian</rs> Impressionist; I’ve painted him as something of a poet, his refined and nervous head standing out against a deep ultramarine background of the night sky, with the twinkling of the stars.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Now the other room, I would like it almost elegant, with a walnut bed with a blue blanket. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And all the rest, the dressing-table and the chest of drawers too, in matt walnut. I want to stuff at least 6 very large canvases into this tiny little room, the way the Japanese do, especially the huge bouquets of sunflowers.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> You know that the Japanese instinctively look for contrasts, and eat sweetened peppers, salty sweets, and fried ices and frozen fried dishes.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> So, too, following the same system you should probably only put very small paintings in a large room, but in a very small room you’ll put a lot of big ones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I hope the day will come when I’ll be able to show you this beautiful part of the world.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’ve just finished a canvas of a café interior at night, lit by lamps. Some poor night-prowlers are sleeping in a corner. The room is painted red, and inside, in the gaslight, the green billiard table, which casts an immense shadow over the floor. In this canvas there are 6 or 7 different reds, from blood-red to delicate pink, contrasting with the same number of pale or dark greens.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Today I sent Theo a drawing of it, which is like a Japanese print.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Theo wrote telling me that he has given you some Japanese prints.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> It’s certainly the most practical way of getting to understand the direction that painting has taken at present. Colourful and bright.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">For myself, I don’t need Japanese prints here, because I’m always saying to myself <hi rend="italics">that I’m in Japan here.</hi> That as a result I only have to open my eyes and paint right in front of me what makes an impression on me.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Have you seen a tiny little mask of a fat, smiling Japanese woman at our place? The expression on that little mask is really surprising.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Did you think of taking one of my paintings with you for yourself? I hope so, and I’m quite intrigued to know which you would have chosen.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I myself thought you would have taken the white huts under the blue sky among the greenery, which I did at Saintes-Maries, on the Mediterranean.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I should have gone back to Saintes-Maries already, now that there are people on the beach. But anyway, I have so much to do right here. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I definitely want to paint a starry sky now. It often seems to me that the night is even more richly coloured than the day, coloured in the most intense violets, blues and greens.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">If you look carefully you’ll see that some stars are lemony, others have a pink, green, forget-me-not blue glow. And without labouring the point, it’s clear that to paint a starry sky it’s not nearly enough to put white spots on blue-black.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">My house here is painted outside in the yellow of fresh butter, with garish green shutters, and it’s in the full sun on the square, where there’s a green garden of plane trees, oleanders, acacias. And inside, it’s all whitewashed, and the floor’s of red bricks. And the intense blue sky above. Inside, I can live and breathe, and think and paint. And it seems to me that I should go further into the south rather than going back up north, because I have too great a need of the strong heat so that my blood circulates normally. I’m in really much better health here than in Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now I have scarcely a doubt that for you, too, you would like the south enormously.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">It’s the sun, that has never sufficiently penetrated us northerners.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I started this letter several days ago, up to here, and I’m picking it up again now. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I was interrupted precisely by the work that a new painting of the outside of a café in the evening has been giving me these past few days. On the terrace, there are little figures of people drinking. A huge yellow lantern lights the terrace, the façade, the pavement, and even projects light over the cobblestones of the street, which takes on a violet-pink tinge. The gables of the houses on a street that leads away under the blue sky studded with stars are dark blue or violet, with a green tree. Now there’s a painting of night without black. With nothing but beautiful blue, violet and green, and in these surroundings the lighted square is coloured pale sulphur, lemon green.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I enormously enjoy painting on the spot at night. In the past they used to draw, and paint the picture from the drawing in the daytime. But I find that it suits me to paint the thing straightaway. It’s quite true that I may take a blue for a green in the dark, a blue lilac for a pink lilac, since you can’t make out the nature of the tone clearly. But it’s the only way of getting away from the conventional black night with a poor, pallid and whitish light, while in fact a mere candle by itself gives us the richest yellows and oranges.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> I’ve also done a new portrait of myself, as a study, in which I look like a Japanese.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> You never told me if you had read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>’s Bel-ami, and what you now think of his talent in general. I say this because the beginning of Bel-ami is precisely the description of a starry night in Paris, with the lighted cafés of the boulevard,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and it’s something like the same subject that I’ve painted just now. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Speaking of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Guy de Maupassant</rs>, I find what he does really beautiful, and I really recommend that you read everything that he’s done. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> — Maupassant, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>, one has to have read them as thoroughly as possible in order to get a reasonably clear idea of the modern novel. Have you read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>? I’m reading him again here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>, I believe that at present we must paint nature’s rich and magnificent aspects; we need good cheer and happiness, hope and love.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">The uglier, older, meaner, iller, poorer I get, the more I wish to take my revenge by doing brilliant colour, well arranged, resplendent. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Jewellers are old and ugly too, before they know how to arrange precious stones well. And arranging colours in a painting to make them shimmer and stand out through their contrasts, that’s something like arranging jewels or — designing costumes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">You’ll see now that by regularly looking at Japanese prints you’ll enjoy making bouquets even more, working among flowers. I must finish this letter if I want it to go off today. I’ll be very happy to have the photograph of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> that you mention, so don’t forget to send it to me.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Give my warm regards to our mother; I often think of you both, and I’m really pleased that now you know our life a little better. I really fear that Theo will find himself too lonely. But one of these days there’ll be a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Belgian</rs> Impressionist painter, the one I mentioned above, who’ll come to spend some time in Paris. And there’ll be many other painters who’ll soon come back to Paris with their studies done during the summer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I kiss you affectionately, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> too.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent tells Willemien that he sent Theo the drawing of the night café ‘today’ <ref target="#l-48">(l. 48)</ref>; he wrote the same thing in <ref target="let677.xml">letter 677</ref>, so that the first part of the present letter – written the same day – must be dated Sunday, 9 September 1888. In <ref target="#l-97*">ll. 97*-99</ref>, however, he says that he had put the letter aside for ‘several days’ and that he was now carrying on with it. In the light of the description of two paintings he did in the week of 10 to 15 September (<ref target="let681.xml">see letter 681</ref> of 16 September) it is possible to place the second part of the letter at the end of that week. Hulsker and Pickvance dated the second sheet 16 September; Dorn about Friday, 14 September. He argues that the present letter predates 681, because Van Gogh does not mention <hi rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>) here, whereas in <ref target="let681.xml">letter 681</ref> he refers to it as ‘the first painting this week’ <ref target="let681.xml#l-46">(l. 46)</ref>. On the grounds that he would have told Willemien if he had already made a start on this work, we dated the second part on or about Friday, 14 September 1888 (see exhib. cat. New York 1984, p. 263; Dorn 1990, pp. 505-506; Hulsker 1993-1, p. 32).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Willemien’s visit to Paris <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Boch’s visit to Theo <ref target="let673.xml">(673)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent had received this letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> on Sunday, 2 September; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let673.xml">see letter 673</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Eugène Boch (‘The poet’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2710">F 462 / JH 1574</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh had intended <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>), no. 30 canvases, for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s room. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let677.xml">See letters 677</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let743.xml">743</ref>. Later he added the four pictures of the ‘poet’s garden’. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let695.xml#n-13">See letters 695, n. 13</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let709.xml#n-6">709, nn. 6</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let709.xml#n-7">7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>An allusion to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let657.xml#n-17">see letter 657, n. 17.</ref> Vincent had already recommended Loti’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_464">Le mariage de Loti </ref></hi>to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let590.xml">letter 590</ref>), and she was also familiar with his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_502">Pêcheur d’Islande</ref> </hi>(FR b2275).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Vincent had sent Theo the drawing of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3005">F 1463 / JH 1576</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let677.xml">see letter 677</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>On 19 October 1888 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> wrote to Theo and told him that she got great pleasure from the Japanese prints. There must have been a considerable number, since she said that she had given fifteen or so to a friend (FR b2275).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Although Van Gogh says here that he doesn’t need any Japanese prints, he had asked Theo that same day to send him prints to hang in his studio (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let677.xml">see letter 677</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
      
<p>The mask that Vincent and Theo had in Paris is no longer in the estate. It was probably of the primitive Shinto goddess Okame or Otafuku, whose full name is Ame no Uzume no Mikoto (the goddess of mirth). Her plump, rosy cheeked, laughing maiden’s face and well fed look symbolize prosperity. With thanks to Tsukasa Kōdera. The mask, from the Kyogen theatre, was popular in Japan and probably sold in large quantities. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2305">Ill. 2305</rs>. Cf. Louis Gonse, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Art japonais</hi>. Paris 1883, pl. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xi</hi>, no. 6 (between pp. 82-83).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Assuming <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> actually did take a painting, two works from the Arles period qualify: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sprig of almond blossom in a glass with a book </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2566">F 393 / JH 1362</rs>), which Van Gogh said in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let590.xml">letter 590</ref> he had intended for her, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard bordered by cypresses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2586">F 554 / JH 1388</rs>). We know that Willemien had both these paintings. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 20 (n. 33). She might equally, of course, have chosen a Paris work: according to De la Faille <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">A public garden with people strolling </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_768">F 225 / JH 1110</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Edge of a wheatfield with poppies </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_769">F 310a / JH 1273</rs>) once belonged to Willemien.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cottages in Saintes-Maries</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2643">F 419 / JH 1465</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Café terrace at night</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2714">F 467 / JH 1580</rs>). The pavement café is the Grand Café du Forum in the place du Forum in Arles. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>His nocturnal painting in Arles prompted a report in the local press: ‘Mr Vincent, an Impressionist painter, works, we are told, in the evening, by the light of the gaslamps, in one of our squares’ (M. Vincent, peintre impressionniste travaille, nous assure-t-on, le soir, à la lueur des becs de gaz, sur l’une de nos places.) See ‘Chronique artistique et musicale’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Homme de Bronze</hi>, 30 September 1888. See also Dorn 1990, pp. 85, 266 (n. 178).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2715">F 476/ JH 1581</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Maupassant</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_446">Bel-ami</ref></hi> <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let568.xml#n-11">see letter 568, n. 11.</ref> Van Gogh is referring to the description of the boulevards of Paris on a summer evening at the beginning of the book. There is no mention of a starry sky, but Maupassant does describe the brightly-lit café’s Duroy, the central character, walks past: ‘The big cafés, full of people, overflowed out on to the pavements, displaying their clientele of drinkers in the harsh, bright lights of their illuminated facades’. (Les grands cafés, pleins de monde, débordaient sur le trottoir, étalant leur public de buveurs sous la lumière éclatante et crue de leur devanture illuminée.) He also pictures the ‘sandy paths, lit by electric light’ (allées bien sablées, éclairées à la lumière électrique) and the ‘floodlit façade’ (façade illuminée) of the cabaret Les Folies-Bergère. See Maupassant 1987, pp. 199, 205-206. Cf. also Sund 1992, pp. 193-194.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> – who was now 69 – had given <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> the photograph to take to Paris (FR b2421). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2244">Ill. 2244</rs>. Vincent received it soon after this (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let685.xml">see letter 685</ref>). He painted the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Van Gogh’s mother </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2729">F 477 / JH 1600</rs>) from it in October 1888 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let699.xml#n-13">see letter 699, n. 13</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    