<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Tuesday, 18 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let683"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b583 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>683</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>539</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>687</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-18">Tuesday, 18 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0583 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0583 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000786_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0583 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0583 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000787_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">ce matin de bonne heure je t’ai dejà écrit<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> puis je suis allé continuer un tableau de jardin ensoleillé<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Puis je l’ai rentré – et suis ressorti avec une toile blanche et celle là aussi est faite<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Et maintenant j’ai encore envie de t’ecrire encore une fois.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Parceque jamais j’ai eu une telle chance<c type="kk">/</c> ici la nature est <hi rend="italics">extraordinairement</hi> belle. Tout et partout<c type="kp">_</c> La coupole du ciel est d’un bleu admirable<c type="kk">/</c> le soleil a un rayonnement de souffre pâle et c’est doux et charmant comme la combinaison des bleus celestes et des jaunes dans les Van der Meer de Delft. Je ne peux pas peindre aussi beau que cela mais cela m’absorbe tant<c type="kk">/</c> que je me laisse aller sans penser à aucune règle<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Cela me fait 3 tableaux des jardins en face de ma maison.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Puis les deux cafés<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Puis les tournesols<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Puis le portrait de Bock et le mien<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Puis le soleil rouge sur l’usine<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> et les déchargeurs de sable.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> le vieux moulin<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Laissant les autres etudes de côté tu vois qu’il y a de la besogne de faite.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Mais ma couleur<c type="kk">/</c> ma toile<c type="kk">/</c> ma bourse est epuisée aujourd’hui completement<c type="kp">_</c> Le dernier tableau<c type="kk">/</c> fait avec les derniers tubes sur le dernière toile<c type="kk">/</c> est un jardin naturellement vert<c type="kk">/</c> est peint sans vert proprement dit<c type="kk">/</c> rien qu’avec du bleu de prusse et du jaune de chrome<c type="kp">_</c> Je commence à me sentir tout autre chôse que ce que j’étais en venant ici<c type="kk">/</c> je ne doute plus<c type="kk">/</c> je n’hesite plus pour attaquer une chôse et cela pourrait bien encore croitre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Mais quelle nature<c type="kp">_</c>– C’est un jardin public où je suis<c type="kk">/</c> tout près de la rue des bonnes petites femmes<c type="kk">/</c> et Mouries par exemple n’y entrait guere lorsque pourtant presque journellement nous nous promenions dans ces jardins mais de l’autre côté (il y en a 3)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Mais tu comprends que juste cela donne un je ne sais quoi de Boccace à l’endroit.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Ce côté-là du jardin est d’ailleurs pour la meme raison de chastete ou de morale<c type="kk">/</c> degarni d’arbustes en fleur tel que le laurier rose. C’est des platanes communs<c type="kk">/</c> des sapins en buissons raides<c type="kk">/</c> un arbre pleureur et de l’herbe verte. Mais c’est d’une intimité<c type="kp">_</c> Il y a des jardins de Monet comme cela.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Tant que tu puisses supporter le poids de toute la couleur<c type="kk">/</c> de toile<c type="kk">/</c> d’argent que je suis forcé de dépenser<c type="kk">/</c> envoie moi toujours<c type="kp">_</c> Car ce que je prepare sera mieux que le dernier envoi et je crois que nous y gagnerons au lieu de perdre<c type="kp">_</c> Si j’arrive toutefois à faire un tout qui se tienne<c type="kp">_</c> Ce que je cherche.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Mais est il absolument impossible que Thomas me prête deux ou trois cents francs sur mes études? Cela m’en ferait gagner plus que mille car je ne saurais te le dire assez<c type="kk">/</c> je suis ravi ravi ravi de ce que je vois.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Et cela vous donne des <hi rend="italics">aspirations d’automne</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> un enthousiasme qui fait que le temps passe sans qu’on le sente<c type="kp">_</c>– Gare au lendemain de fete<c type="kk">/</c> aux mistrals d’hiver<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Aujourd’hui tout en travaillant j’ai beaucoup pensé à Bernard<c type="kp">_</c>– Sa lettre est empreinte de vénération pour le talent de Gauguin – il dit qu’il le trouve un si grand artiste qu’il en a presque peur et qu’il trouve mauvais tout ce que lui<c type="kk">/</c> Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> fait en comparaison de Gauguin. Et tu sais que cet hiver Bernard cherchait encore querelle à Gauguin<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Enfin quoi qu’il en soit et quoi qu’il arrive<c type="kk">/</c> il est tres consolant que ces artistes-là sont nos amis et j’ose le croire le resteront n’importe comment tournent les affaires.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’ai tant de bonheur avec la maison – avec le travail – que j’ose encore croire que les bonheurs ne resteront pas seuls mais que tu les partageras de ton côté en ayant de la veine aussi. J’ai lu il y a quelque temps un article sur le Dante<c type="kk">/</c> Petrarque<c type="kk">/</c> Boccace<c type="kk">/</c> Giotto<c type="kk">/</c> Botticelli<c type="kk">/</c> mon dieu comme cela m’a fait de l’impression en lisant les lettres de ces gens-là<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Or Petrarque etait ici tout près à Avignon<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> et je vois les mêmes cyprès et lauriers roses<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">J’ai cherché à mettre quelque chose de cela dans un des jardins peint en pleine pate jaune citron et vert citron.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Giotto m’a touché le plus – <hi rend="italics">toujours souffrant</hi> et toujours plein de bonté et d’ardeur comme s’il vivait deja dans un monde autre que celui ci<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Giotto est extraordinaire d’ailleurs et je le sens mieux que les poetes<c type="kk">/</c> le Dante<c type="kk">/</c> Petrarque<c type="kk">/</c> Boccace<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Il me semble toujours que la poesie est plus <hi rend="italics">terrible</hi> que la peinture quoique la peinture soit plus sâle et enfin plus emmerdante<c type="kp">_</c> Et le peintre en somme ne dit rien<c type="kk">/</c> il se tait et je préfère encore cela.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Mon cher Theo lorsque tu auras vu les cyprès<c type="kk">/</c> les laurier roses<c type="kk">/</c> le soleil d’ici – et ce jour-là viendra<c type="kk">/</c> sois tranquille. Encore plus souvent tu penseras aux beaux Puvis de Chavannes<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Doux pays</hi><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> et tant d’autres<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">A travers le côté Tartarin<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> et le côté Daumier du pays si drole où les bonnes gens ont l’accent que tu sais<c type="kk">/</c> il y a tant de Grec déjà et il y a la Venus d’Arles<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> comme celle de Lesbos<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> et on sent encore cette jeunesse-là malgré tout.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Je n’en doute pas le moins du monde qu’un jour toi aussi tu connaitras le midi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Tu iras peut etre voir Claude Monet quant il est à Antibes<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> ou enfin tu trouveras une occasion.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Quand il fait du mistral c’est pourtant juste le contraire d’un <hi rend="italics">doux</hi> pays ici car le mistral est d’un agaçant<c type="kp">_</c>– Mais quelle revanche<c type="kk">/</c> quelle revanche lorsqu’il y a un jour sans vent. Quelle intensité des couleurs<c type="kk">/</c> quel air pur<c type="kk">/</c> quelle vibration sereine.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Demain je vais dessiner jusqu’à ce qu’arrive la couleur<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Mais j’y suis arrivé maintenant de parti pris de ne plus dessiner un tableau au fusain<c type="kp">_</c> Cela ne sert à rien<c type="kk">/</c> il faut attaquer le dessin avec la couleur meme pour bien dessiner<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Ah – l’exposition à la revue independante<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> – bon – mais une fois pour toutes – nous sommes trop fumeurs pour mettre le cigare dans la bouche du mauvais côté.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Nous serons obligés de chercher à vendre pour pouvoir refaire mieux les memes choses vendues<c type="kk">/</c> cela c’est parceque nous sommes dans un mauvais metier – mais cherchons autre chose que la joie de rue qui est douleur de maison.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Cet après midi j’ai eu un public choisi..... de 4 ou 5 maquereaux et une douzaine de gamins qui trouvaient surtout interessant de voir la couleur sortir des tubes<c type="kp">_</c> Eh bien ce public-là – c’est la gloire ou plutôt j’ai la ferme intention de me moquer de l’ambition et de la gloire comme de ces gamins-là et de ces voyous des bords du Rhône et de la Rue du Bout d’Arles.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">J’ai été aujourd’hui chez Milliet<c type="kk">/</c> il va venir demain ayant prolongé son sejour de 4 jours<c type="kp">_</c> Je voudrais que Bernard aille faire son service en Afrique car là il ferait de belles choses et je ne sais encore que lui dire. Il a dit qu’il me ferait l’échange de son portrait pour une étude de moi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Mais il a dit qu’il <hi rend="italics">n’ose pas</hi> faire Gauguin comme je le lui avais demandé parcequ’il se sent trop timide devant Gauguin.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> Bernard est au fond un tel temperament!! il est quelquefois fou et méchant mais certes ce n’est pas moi qui aie le droit de lui reprocher cela parceque je connais trop moi-meme la même névrose et je sais que lui ne me reprocherait pas non plus.– S’il allait en Afrique chez Milliet<c type="kk">/</c> Milliet le prendrait certes en amitié<c type="kp">_</c> Car Milliet est tres fidèle comme ami et fait si facilement l’amour qu’il méprise l’amour presque.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Que fait Seurat<c type="kp">_</c>– Je n’oserais pas lui montrer les etudes deja envoyées mais celles des tournesols et des cabarets et des jardins je voudrais qu’il les voie – je réflechis souvent à son systeme et toutefois je ne le suivrai pas du tout mais lui est coloriste original et c’est la meme chose pour Signac mais à un autre degré<c type="kk">/</c> les pointilleurs ont trouvé du neuf et je les aime tout de même bien. Mais moi – je le dis franchement – je reviens plutôt à ce que je cherchais avant de venir à Paris et je ne sais si quelqu’un avant moi aie parlé de couleur suggestive<c type="kp">_</c> Mais Delacroix et Monticelli tout en n’en ayant pas parlé l’ont faite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Mais moi je suis encore comme j’etais à Nunen lorsque j’ai fait un vain effort pour apprendre la musique – alors déjà – tellement je sentais les rapports qu’il y a entre notre couleur et la musique de Wagner.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> Maintenant il est vrai<c type="kk">/</c> je vois dans l’impressionisme la résurrection de <hi rend="italics">Eugène Delacroix</hi> mais les interpretations étant et divergeantes et un peu irreconciliables ce ne sera pas encore l’impressionisme qui formulera la doctrine<c type="kp">_</c> C’est pour cela que je reste moi dans les impressionistes parceque cela ne dit rien et n’engage à rien. et je n’ai pas<c type="kk">/</c> là-<c type="shy">-</c>dedans en copain<c type="kk">/</c> à me formuler.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Mon dieu il faut faire la bête dans la vie<c type="kk">/</c> je demande moi du temps pour etudier et toi<c type="kk">/</c> est ce que tu demandes autre chôse que cela. Mais je sens que toi tu dois comme moi aimer à avoir la tranquilité nécessaire pour etudier sans parti pris.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Et je crains tant de te l’ôter par mes demandes d’argent.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Pourtant je calcule tant et aujourd’hui encore je trouvais que pour les dix mètres de toile j’avais calculé juste toutes les couleurs sauf une seule<c type="kk">/</c> la fondamentale du jaune<c type="kp">_</c> Si toutes mes couleurs finissent en même temps n’est ce pas là une preuve que je sens en somnambule les proportions relatives<c type="kp">_</c> C’est comme pour le dessin<c type="kk">/</c> je ne mesure presque pas et en cela je suis bien categoriquement opposé à Cormon qui dit que s’il ne mesurait pas il dessinerait comme un cochon.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Je pense que tu as tout de même bien fait d’acheter tant de chassis car il faut en avoir un certain nombre pour pouvoir bien secher les toiles ce qui est leur conservation et moi-même j’en ai un tas ici aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Mais il ne faut pas te gêner pour en ôter des chassis pour que le tout ne prenne pas trop de place.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Je paye moi ici les chassis de 30<c type="kk">/</c> 25<c type="kk">/</c> 20<c type="kk">/</c> à raison de fr<c type="kp">_</c> 1<c type="kp">_</c>50 et les 15<c type="kk">/</c> 12<c type="kk">/</c> 10<c type="kk">/</c> à 1 franc. Si je les fais faire par le menuisier<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-30"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">La menuiserie etant fort chère ici<c type="kk">/</c> Tanguy en les comptant à ce prix-là doit pouvoir les livrer aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Je cherche un cadre pour la toile de 30 carrée en noyer léger à 5 francs et je pense que je l’aurai<c type="kp">_</c> Le cadre en chêne lourd pour la toile de 10<c type="kk">/</c> portrait<c type="kk">/</c> me coûte 5 francs aussi.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">J’ai encore dû commander 5 chassis de 30 pour la nouvelle toile<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> qui sont déjà faites et que je dois prendre. cela te prouvera que je ne peux pas être sans quelque argent à cette epoque de travail. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Il y a une consolation que nous sommes dans les matieres premieres toujours et ne speculons pas mais ne cherchons qu’à produire.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> Et alors nous ne pouvons mal tourner.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">J’espère que cela sera comme cela et si je suis dans la necessité fatale d’user et ma couleur et ma toile et mon portemonaie saches bien que ce n’est pas encore par là que nous puissions perir<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Meme si de ton côté si tu uses ton portemonnaie et ce qu’il y a dedans c’est certes mauvais mais dis moi tranquillement: il n’y en a plus<c type="kk">/</c> alors il y en aura encore par ce que j’aurai fait avec<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Mais – me diras tu comme de juste – en attendant? En attendant – je ferai du dessin car c’est plus commode de ne faire que dessiner que de peindre<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.39" n="39">Je te serre bien la main. Quelles journees que celles ci<c type="kk">/</c> non pas par les evenements<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> mais je sens tellement que toi comme moi nous ne sommes pas de la decadence ni des finis encore et ne le serons pas dans la suite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.40" n="40">Mais tu sais je ne contredis pas aux critiques qui diront que mes tableaux ne sont pas – finis.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> Je te serre la main  et à bientot<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.41" n="41">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.42" n="42">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.43" n="43">J’ai moi aussi lu Cesarine de Richepin – j’aime bien ce que dit la femme dite toquée<c type="kk">/</c> la vie tout entière c’est des equations bien faites.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I already wrote to you early this morning,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> then I went to continue working on a painting of a sunny garden.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Then I brought it back — and went out again with a blank canvas and that’s done, too.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And now I feel like writing to you again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Because I’ve never had such good fortune; nature here is <hi rend="italics">extraordinarily </hi>beautiful. Everything and everywhere. The dome of the sky is a wonderful blue, the sun has a pale sulphur radiance, and it’s soft and charming, like the combination of celestial blues and yellows in paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1421">Vermeer of Delft</rs>. I can’t paint as beautifully as that, but it absorbs me so much that I let myself go without thinking about any rule.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">That gives me 3 paintings of the gardens facing the house.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Then the two cafés.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Then the sunflowers.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Then <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs>’s portrait, and mine.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Then the red sun over the factory<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and the men unloading sand.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> The old mill.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Leaving the other studies aside, you can see that some hard work has been done. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">But my colours, my canvas, my wallet are completely exhausted today. The last painting, done with the last tubes on the last canvas, is a naturally green garden, is painted without green as such, with nothing but Prussian blue and chrome yellow. I’m beginning to feel quite different from what I was when I came here, I have no more doubts, I no longer hesitate to tackle something, and that could increase still further.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But what scenery! It’s a public garden where I am, just near the street of the good little ladies, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1233">Mourier</rs>, for example, never went there, whereas we used to walk in these gardens almost every day, but on the other side (there are 3 of them).<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> But you’ll understand that it’s precisely that which gives a <hi rend="italics">je ne sais quoi</hi> of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs> to the place.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> That side of the garden is also, for the same reason of chastity or morality, empty of flowering shrubs such as the oleander. It’s ordinary plane trees, pines in tall clumps, a weeping tree and green grass. But it has such intimacy! There are gardens like that by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Monet</rs>. 
      <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">As long as you can bear the burden of all the colours, canvas, money that I’m forced to spend, keep on sending me them. Because what I’m preparing will be better than the last consignment, and believe that we’ll gain rather than lose by it. If, that is, I manage to do an ensemble that will hold together. Which I’m trying to do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">But is it absolutely impossible for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_216">Thomas</rs> to lend me two or three hundred francs on my studies? That would mean that I would earn over a thousand from them, because I couldn’t tell you enough, I’m thrilled, thrilled, thrilled with what I see.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And that gives you <hi rend="italics">yearnings for autumn</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> a zest that means that time passes without your feeling it. Beware the morning after, beware the winter mistrals.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Today, while actually working, I thought a lot about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>. His letter is full of veneration for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s talent — he says that he finds him so great an artist that it almost frightens him, and he finds everything that he, Bernard, does, bad in comparison with Gauguin. And you know that last winter Bernard was still trying to pick a quarrel with Gauguin.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Ah well, whatever the case, and whatever happens, it’s very consoling that those artists are our friends, and I dare to believe will remain so, no matter how things turn out.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I have such luck with the house — with work — that I even dare believe that blessings won’t come singly, but that you’ll share them for your part, and have good luck too. Some time ago I read an article on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_569">Dante</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_886">Botticelli</rs>; my God, what an impression that made on me, reading those people’s letters!<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> Now Petrarch was just near here, in Avignon,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> and I see the same cypresses and oleanders.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’ve tried to put something of that into one of the gardens, painted with thick impasto, lemon yellow and lemon green.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> touched me the most — <hi rend="italics">always suffering </hi>and always full of kindness and ardour as if he were already living in a world other than this.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> is extraordinary, anyway, and I feel him more than the poets: <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_569">Dante</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">It always seems to me that poetry is more <hi rend="italics">terrible</hi> than painting, although painting is dirtier and more damned annoying, in fact. And after all, the painter says nothing; he keeps quiet, and I like that even better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">My dear Theo, when you’ve seen the cypresses, the oleanders, the sun down here — and that day will come, don’t worry — you’ll think even more often of beautiful works by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>: <hi rend="italics">Pleasant land</hi><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and so many others.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Throughout the Tartarin side<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs> side of this funny part of the world, where the good folk have the accent that you know, there’s already so much that’s Greek, and there’s the Venus of Arles,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> like the one of Lesbos,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> and you can still feel that youthfulness, despite everything.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I don’t doubt in the very least that one day you too will know the south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">You’ll perhaps go to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs> when he’s in Antibes,<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> or you’ll find some opportunity, anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">When the mistral’s blowing, though, it’s the very opposite of a <hi rend="italics">pleasant </hi>land here, because the mistral’s really aggravating. But what a compensation, what a compensation, when there’s a day with no wind. What intensity of colours, what pure air, what serene vibrancy. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> Tomorrow I’m going to draw until the colours arrive.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> But now I’ve reached the point where I’ve made up my mind not to draw a painting in charcoal any more. There’s no point; you have to tackle the drawing with the colour itself in order to draw well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Ah — the exhibition at the Revue Indépendante<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> — fine — but once and for all — we’re far too much smokers to put the cigar in our mouth the wrong way round.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">We’ll be obliged to try to sell, in order to be able to do again, better, the same things sold; that’s because we’re in a lousy trade — but let’s look for something other than the joy of the town, which means grief at home.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">This afternoon I had a select audience..... of 4 or 5 pimps and a dozen kids who found it particularly interesting to watch the colours come out of the tubes. Ah, well, that sort of audience — that’s fame, or rather, I have the firm intention of thumbing my nose at ambition and fame, like these kids and these ruffians from the banks of the Rhône and rue du Bout d’Arles. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I was at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs>’s today; he’s going to come tomorrow, having extended his stay by 4 days. I’d like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> to go to do his military service in Africa, because he’d do fine things there, and I still don’t know what to say to him. He said he’d exchange his portrait for one of my studies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">But he said that he <hi rend="italics">daren’t </hi>do <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, as I’d asked him, because he feels too shy with Gauguin.<ptr target="#note-t-28"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> is actually so temperamental!! He’s sometimes crazy and mean, but I’m certainly not the one who has the right to blame him for that, because I know the same neurosis too much myself, and I know that he wouldn’t blame me either. If he went to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> in Africa, Milliet would certainly make friends with him. Because Milliet’s very loyal as a friend, and makes love so easily that he almost has contempt for love. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">What’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1353">Seurat</rs> doing? I wouldn’t dare show him the studies I’ve already sent, but the ones of the sunflowers and the bars and the gardens, those I’d like him to see — I often think about his system, and yet I won’t follow it at all, but he’s an original colourist, and it’s the same thing for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs>, but to a different degree; the pointillists have found something new, and I like them very much all the same. But I — I say so frankly — I’m returning more to what I was looking for before coming to Paris, and I don’t know if anyone before me has talked about suggestive colour. But <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, while not talking about it, did it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">But I’m again the way I was in Nuenen, when I made a vain attempt to learn music — even then — so strongly did I feel the connections there are between our colour and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_814">Wagner</rs>’s music.<ptr target="#note-t-29"/> Now it’s true, I see in Impressionism the resurrection of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs>, </hi>but the interpretations being both divergent and somewhat irreconcilable, it won’t be Impressionism that will formulate the doctrine. It’s for that reason that I remain among the Impressionists, because that says nothing and commits you to nothing. And being there as a pal, I don’t have to state my position.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">My God, you have to play the fool in life; I ask for the time to study, and you, do you ask for anything other than that? But I feel that you must, like me, long to have the peace and quiet needed in order to study with an open mind. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And I’m so afraid of taking it away from you with my requests for money.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">However, I do so many calculations, and actually today I found that for the ten metres of canvas I had calculated the colours correctly, except for one, the fundamental one of yellow. If all my colours run out at the same time, isn’t that proof that I can sense the relative proportions like a sleep-walker? It’s the way it is with drawing, I hardly measure, and in that I’m quite categorically opposed to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>, who says that if he didn’t measure he would draw like a pig.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I think you did quite well, all the same, to buy so many stretching frames, because you have to have a certain number to be able to dry the canvases thoroughly, which preserves them, and I also have a whole lot of them here myself. But you mustn’t hesitate to take them off the stretching frames, so that everything doesn’t take up too much space.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Here I pay 1.50 francs for no. 30, 25, 20 stretching frames, and 1 franc for no. 15, 12, 10. If I have them made by the carpenter.<ptr target="#note-t-30"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">As carpentry is very expensive here, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> could also supply them if he reckoned them at that price. I’m looking for a frame in light walnut, at 5 francs, for the square no. 30 canvas, and I think I’ll get it. A frame in heavy oak for the no. 10 canvas, portrait, also costs me 5 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-31"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I’ve also had to order 5 no. 30 stretching frames for the new canvas,<ptr target="#note-t-32"/> which are already made and which I have to collect. That will prove to you that I can’t be without some money at this period of work. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">There’s a consolation in that we’re always among raw materials, and aren’t speculating but only trying to produce.<ptr target="#note-t-33"/> And then we can’t go wrong.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">I hope it’ll be like that, and if I’m in the inevitable necessity of using up my colours and my canvas and<hi rend="italics"> </hi>my wallet, you can be sure that that’s not yet the way that we’re to perish.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Even if for your part you use up your purse and what’s in it, true, it’s bad, but say to me calmly: there’s nothing left, then there’ll be more, because of what I’ll have done with it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">But — you’ll say to me, rightly — in the meantime? In the meantime — I’ll draw, because it’s more convenient to do nothing but draw than to paint.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">I shake your hand firmly. What days these are, not because of events, but I feel so strongly that we’re not decadents, you and I, and not finished yet, and won’t be, in time to come.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">But you know that I don’t contradict the critics who will say that my paintings aren’t — finished.<ptr target="#note-t-34"/> I shake your hand, and more soon. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">I’ve read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_727">Richepin</rs>’s Césarine too — I love what the so-called crazy woman says, all of life is well-constructed equations.<ptr target="#note-t-35"/> </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written the same day as the previous one to Theo (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>), so we have dated it Tuesday, 18 September 1888. See further the notes to <ref target="let682.xml">letter 682</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Second consignment of paintings from Arles <ref target="let660.xml">(660)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Attempts to sell work through Thomas <ref target="let639.xml">(639)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Bernard’s military service <ref target="let575.xml">(575)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Exchange of portraits with Bernard and Gauguin <ref target="let680.xml">(680)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Milliet’s stay in Africa <ref target="let628.xml">(628)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="ogt_6">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Framing paintings for the decoration <ref target="let673.xml">(673)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let682.xml">letter 682</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Path in the public garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2716">F 470 / JH 1582</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let682.xml">see letter 682</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Path in the public garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2737">F 471 / JH 1613</rs>). Van Gogh describes this painting later in the letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>As well as the two works referred to above, Van Gogh had a third painting of the park: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let681.xml">See letter 681</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Café terrace at night </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2714">F 467 / JH 1580</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2701">F 453 / JH 1559</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2702">F 459 / JH 1560</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Eugène Boch (‘The poet’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2710">F 462 / JH 1574</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2715">F 476/ JH 1581</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This painting of a factory and a red sun is not known; cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let680.xml#n-10">letter 680, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Quay with sand barges</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2700">F 449 / JH 1558</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old mill </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2712">F 550 / JH 1577</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Rue du Bout d’Arles ran from the Roubine du Roi Canal to rue des Récollets; the ‘maisons de tolérance’ (brothels) were in these two streets.  Van Gogh meant the public garden to the south-east of place Lamartine. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let604.xml#n-2">See letter 604, n. 2,</ref> for the other parks. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
      
<p>An allusion to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs>’s sensual nature, which Van Gogh had read about in the article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_561">Boccace d’après ses oeuvres et les témoignages contemporains</ref>’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1804">Cochin</rs> discussed later in the letter (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-15">see n. 15</ref> below). Cochin said, among other things, that the young Boccaccio lived a dissipated life in Naples (p. 377).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>An allusion to the chapter entitled ‘Les aspirations de l’automne’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let014.xml#n-19">see letter 14, n. 19.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Nothing is known about a quarrel between <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> in the winter of 1887-1888. The two artists had not got on well at their first meeting in Pont-Aven in 1886. Bernard wrote about this in 1895: ‘The welcome Mr Gauguin gave me was extremely frosty, and that year there was nothing but the strangest antipathy between us.’ (L’accueil que me fit M. Gauguin fut un des plus glacés, et cette année-là il ne se manifesta entre nous que la plus étrange antipathie.) See Bernard 1994, vol. 2, p. 71.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>This is the article by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1804">Henry Cochin</rs> mentioned above, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_561">Boccace d’après ses oeuvres et les témoignages contemporains</ref>’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> 58 (15 July 1888), 3rd series, vol. 88, pp. 373-413 (see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let665.xml#n-12">letter 665, n. 12</ref>). It discusses <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs>’s friendship with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Francesco Petrarch</rs> at length. The author quotes from their letters several times. </p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_569">Dante</rs> is also referred to often in the article; <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> is mentioned twice and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_886">Botticelli</rs> only once (and then very much in passing). Aside from Botticelli – whom Van Gogh added later – his summing up accords with that on the last page of the article: ‘Dante, Petrarch, Boccaccio, Giotto, all the men were dead who had, after ten centuries, revived classical Latin glory’ (Dante, Petrarque, Boccace, Giotto, tous les hommes étaient morts, qui avaient, après dix siècles, revivifié l’antique gloire latine) (p. 413). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs> spent much of his youth in Avignon, the residence of the popes. After studying in Montpellier and Bologna he returned there and remained for some considerable time. Avignon was important above all as the place where the poet met his muse Laura, on 6 April 1327 in the Church of St Claire.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh based his remark about the sickly <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1804">Cochin</rs>’s article (‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_561">Boccace d’après ses oeuvres et les témoignages contemporains</ref>’; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-15">see n. 15</ref> above); he also referred to the passage in question in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let665.xml">letter 665</ref>. It reads in full: ‘Giotto, ugly and sickly but radiating natural genius, was painting scenes from the Divine Comedy at the Château de l’Oeuf. The king, full of respect and admiration, spent his days with the painter, delighting in the brazen charm of his Florentine speech and putting up with the most caustic witticisms from him. He heaped honours on him and wanted to keep him in Naples and make him “the first man of his kingdom”.’ (Giotto, laid et chétif, mais rayonnant de génie naturel, peignait au château de l’OEuf des scènes de la <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Divine Comédie</hi>. Et le roi, plein de respect et d’admiration, passait ses journées auprès du peintre, prenant plaisir à la grâce hardie de son language florentin, souffrant de lui les saillies les plus mordantes, le comblant d’honneurs, voulant le retenir à Naples et en faire “le premier homme de son royaume”.) (p. 378).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Pierre Puvis de Chavannes</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pleasant land</hi>, c. 1882 (New Haven, Yale University Art Gallery, Mary Gertrude Abbey Fund) had been on show at the Puvis de Chavannes retrospective at Durand-Ruel’s in Paris from 20 November-20 December 1887 (cat. no. 83). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_314">Ill. 314</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            
      
<p>The character of Tartarin in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s eponymous novels, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_459">Tartarin de Tarascon</ref> </hi>, which are set in the south of France. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">See letter 583, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>The marble statue ‘Venus of Arles’ is a Roman copy of an Aphrodite by Praxiteles from the end of the first century BC (Paris, Musée du Louvre). Cf. Baedeker 1889-2, p. 211. It was excavated in the Théâtre Antique in Arles in 1651 and given to Louis <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xiv</hi> for his palace at Versailles in 1684. The sculptor François Girardon restored the statue, adding arms and placing an apple in the goddess’s hand. The version Van Gogh saw in Arles is an early nineteenth-century plaster copy of the statue as restored by Girardon. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2246">Ill. 2246</rs> (Musée de l’Arles antique, Documentation).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was probably mistaken in the place name and meant the Venus de Milo (Melos) in the Louvre, from the first century BC, attributed to Alexandros of Antioch. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2248">Ill. 2248</rs>. Van Gogh might conceivably also be referring to the only other statue of Venus on display in the museum in Arles at the time: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a Goddess (Venus?)</hi>. (Musée de l’Arles antique, Documentation).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Monet</rs> had painted landscapes in Antibes in the spring of 1888 and Theo had exhibited some of them; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let625.xml#n-5">see letter 625, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>This would be the paint he had ordered in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let677.xml">letter 677</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>Theo had suggested that Vincent might exhibit at <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La Revue Indépendante</hi>: <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let677.xml#n-16">see letter 677, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let673.xml#n-6">See letter 673, n. 6,</ref> for this reference to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_504">L’immortel</ref></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>This proverb occurs in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_402">Numa Roumestan</ref></hi>. The novel, which Van Gogh had read in 1884 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let439.xml#n-4">see letter 439, n. 4</ref>), ends with a lengthy passage about the Provencal saying ‘Gau de carriero, doulou d’ostau’ (‘Joie de rue, douleur de maison’), which is also the last sentence of the book.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="28" xml:id="note-t-28">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had received a letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> the previous day; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let682.xml">see letter 682</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="29" xml:id="note-t-29">
                            
      
<p>In 1912, in the magazine <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Amsterdammer</hi>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Anton Kerssemakers</rs> recalled: ‘He was always comparing painting with music, and so as to get a better understanding of the gradation of tones, he started to take piano lessons with an old music teacher, who was also an organist, in E[indhoven]. This didn’t last long, though, because during the lessons Van Gogh kept comparing the notes of the piano with Prussian blue and dark green or dark ochre to bright cadmium, and so the poor man thought he must be dealing with a madman and became so afraid of him that he stopped the lessons.’ Quoted in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Verzamelde brieven </hi>1973, vol. 3, p. 95. The music teacher was Hein van der Zande (1820-1903), according to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_82">Dimmen Gestel</rs> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het Eindhovensch Dagblad</hi>, 10 October 1930. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_546">Charles Blanc</rs> had written in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_403">Les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi>: ‘Colour can be learned like music’ (Le coloris s’apprend comme la musique). See Blanc 1876, p. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="30" xml:id="note-t-30">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’indicateur marseillais </hi>1888 lists 23 carpenters (menuisiers); we do not know who Van Gogh got to make his stretching frames.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="31" xml:id="note-t-31">
                            

<p>By ‘the square no. 30 canvas’ and ‘the no. 10 canvas, portrait’ Van Gogh is referring in general to the canvas sizes for which he was seeking frames, although he did already have specific works in mind: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>), which he sent to Theo in a walnut frame in May 1889 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let777.xml">see letter 777</ref>), and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Eugène Boch (‘The poet’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2710">F 462 / JH 1574</rs>), which he planned to hang in his bedroom (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let693.xml">see letter 693</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="32" xml:id="note-t-32">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had ordered 5 metres of canvas in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let680.xml">letter 680</ref>; in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref> he confirmed that he had received it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="33" xml:id="note-t-33">
                            

<p>Cf. for this view the following passage in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_445">Candide</ref></hi>: ‘Let’s work without thinking, said Martin, it is the only way to make life bearable’ (Travaillons sans raisonner, dit Martin; c’est le seul moyen de rendre la vie supportable). Voltaire, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Romans et Contes</hi>. Ed. Frédéric Deloffre and Jacques van den Heuvel. Paris 1979, chapter 30, p. 233.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘not because anything special is going on’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="34" xml:id="note-t-34">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring here to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_673">Gustave Kahn</rs>’s criticism of his paintings; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let594.xml#n-15">see letter 594, n. 15.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="35" xml:id="note-t-35">
                            

<p>In <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_727">Jean Richepin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_511">Césarine</ref></hi> (1888), the title character, who is labelled as mad by those around her because of her promiscuous lifestyle, says: ‘Everything in life is resolved, on the whole, even the most extraordinary actions, by a series of careful equations’ (Tout se résout, en somme, dans la vie, même les actes les plus extraordinaires, par des équations bien faites) (see 4th ed. Paris 1888, p. 258).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    