<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Friday, 21 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let685"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b584 a V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>685</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>540</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>689</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-21">Friday, 21 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0584 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0584 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000788_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci beaucoup de ta lettre et du billet de 100 fr. qu’elle contenait<c type="kp">_</c> Egalement Milliet est venu ce matin m’apportant le paquet de Japonaiseries et autres.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> J’aime beaucoup là-dedans le café concert en deux feuilles avec une rangée de musiciennes violettes contre le mur eclairé jaune<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> je ne connaissais pas cette feuille-là<c type="kk">/</c> d’ailleurs il y en a plusieurs autres qui m’etaient inconnues<c type="kk">/</c> il y en a une – une tete de femme – qui doit être de bonne école<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">A présent j’ai aussi acheté une table à toilette et tout le necessaire et ma petite chambre à moi est au complet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Dans l’autre – celle de Gauguin ou autre logé – il faudra encore une table de toilette et une commode et en bas il me faudra un grand poele et une armoire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Tout cela n’est guère pressé et par conséquent je vois déjà la fin pour avoir de quoi être pour bien longtemps à l’abri.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Tu ne saurais croire combien cela me tranquilise<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai tellement l’amour de faire – une maison d’artiste<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – mais une de <hi rend="italics">pratique</hi> et non pas l’atelier ordinaire plein de bibelots<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">J’y songe aussi à planter deux lauriers roses devant la porte dans des tonneaux<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Enfin<c type="kk">/</c> il est probable que pour cet atelier nous depensons plusieurs fois moins de centaines de francs que par exemple Russell des mille.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Et justement même si j’avais le choix entre les deux<c type="kk">/</c> pour moi je prefererais la methode à quelques centaines de francs pourvu que chaque meuble soit carré et large<c type="kp">_</c> Et pourtant la chambre où je logerai ceux qui passent par ici sera comme un boudoir et quand cela sera fini tu verras que cela ne sera pas une creation du hasard mais un travail voulu ainsi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Le texte du Japon de Bing est un peu sec et laisse plutôt à désirer – il dit<c type="kk">/</c> il y a un grand art typique<c type="kk">/</c> mais s’il en donne quelques bribes il ne donne pas très bien à sentir le caractère de cet art.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> As tu lu madame chrysantème<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> déjà. La grande tranquilité que me procure la maison est surtout ceci que dès maintenant je me sens travailler en prenant des precautions d’avenir<c type="kk">/</c> après moi un autre peintre trouvera 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>une affaire en train. Il me faudra du temps mais j’ai l’idée fixe de faire pour la maison une décoration qui vaudra l’argent que j’ai dépensé dans les années dans lesquelles je n’ai pas produit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Le portrait de la mère m’a fait un très grand plaisir parceque l’on voit qu’elle se porte bien et que cela a une expression encore bien vivante.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Seulement je ne l’aime pas du tout comme ressemblance reelle<c type="kk">/</c> je viens de peindre mon portrait à moi qui ai la même coloration cendrée<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> et à moins qu’on ne nous fasse avec de la couleur on ne donnera de nous qu’une idee peu parlante. Justement comme je m’etais donné un mal terrible pour trouver la combinaison des tons cendrés et rose gris<c type="kk">/</c> je ne peux pas gouter la ressemblance en noir<c type="kp">_</c> Est ce que Germinie Lacerteux serait Germinie Lacerteux sans la couleur.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Evidemment non. Que je voudrais avoir peint des portraits dans notre famille<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’ai pour la deuxieme fois gratté une etude d’un Christ avec l’ange dans le jardin des oliviers<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Parceque ici je vois les oliviers vrais.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Mais je ne peux ou plutot je ne veux pas non plus le peindre sans modèles<c type="kp">_</c> Mais j’ai cela en tête avec de la couleur – la nuit etoilée<c type="kk">/</c> la figure du Christ bleue<c type="kk">/</c> les bleus les plus puissants<c type="kk">/</c> et l’ange jaune citron rompu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Et tous les violets depuis un pourpre rouge sang jusqu’à la cendre dans le paysage.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">J’ai été prendre cinq chassis de 30 donc j’ai encore des intentions<c type="kp">_</c>– Les tableaux qui restent ici je les fais encadrer en chêne et en noyer. Il me faudra du temps mais tu verras cela plus tard. J’espère que tu me donneras des détails de ta visite chez Maurin.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> J’aime énormement le dessin des deux femmes dans le wagon.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Si cela durait un temps avant que quelqu’un vienne ici avec moi cela ne me ferait pourtant pas changer d’idée que cette mesure ci est ce qu’il était urgent à faire et que dans la suite cela sera utile. L’art dans lequel nous travaillons<c type="kk">/</c> nous sentons que cela a un long avenir encore et il faut donc être etabli comme ceux qui sont calmes et non pas vivre comme les décadents. Ici j’aurai de plus en plus une existence de peintre japonais vivant bien dans la nature en petit bourgeois<c type="kp">_</c> Alors tu sens bien que cela est moins lugubre que les decadents. Si j’arrive à vivre assez vieux je serai quelquechôse comme le père Tanguy. Enfin notre avenir personel<c type="kk">/</c> en somme nous n’en savons rien mais nous sentons pourtant que l’impressionisme durera. à bientot et bien bien merci de toutes tes bontés. Je crois que je mettrai les japonaiseries en bas dans l’atelier.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Poignée de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many thanks for your letter and for the 100-franc note it contained. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> came this morning too, bringing me the parcel of Japanese prints and others.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Among them I love the café-concert on two sheets, with a line of purple female musicians against the yellow-lit wall;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I didn’t know that sheet, what’s more there are several others that were unknown to me; there’s one — a head of a woman — that must have a good pedigree.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">At present I’ve also bought a dressing-table with all the necessaries, and my own little bedroom is furnished.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">In the other one — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s or another lodger’s — we’ll still need a dressing-table and a chest of drawers, and downstairs I’ll need a large stove and a cupboard.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">None of that’s at all urgent, and as a result I can already see the goal, to have the means of having a roof over my head for a good long time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">You wouldn’t believe how much that calms me; I have such a passion to make — an artist’s house<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — but a <hi rend="italics">practical </hi>one and not the usual studio full of curios. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I’m also thinking of planting two oleanders outside the door, in tubs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Anyway, on this studio we’re probably spending several hundred francs less than <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>, for example, who spends thousands.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> And actually, even if I had the choice between the two, for my part I’d prefer the few-hundred-francs method, as long as each piece of furniture was four-square and substantial. But still, the room in which I’ll put up those who pass through here will be like a boudoir, and when it’s finished you’ll see that it’s not a haphazard creation, but a job done that way deliberately.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_290">Bing</rs>’s text on Japan is a bit dry and leaves something to be desired — he says, there’s a great, typical art, but while he gives a few scraps of it; he doesn’t do a very good job of making you feel the character of this art.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Have you read Madame Chrysanthème<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> yet? The great peace of mind that the house brings me is above all this, that from now on I feel that I’m working by providing for the future; after me another painter will find 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> an enterprise under way. I’ll need time, but my mind is set on making a decoration for the house that will be worth the money I spent in the years during which I didn’t produce.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">The portrait of our mother gave me great pleasure because you can see that she’s well and that she still has a very lively expression.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Only I don’t like it at all as a real likeness; I’ve just painted my own portrait, and I have the same ashy coloration,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and unless they do us in colour they’ll give an idea of us that’s not very lifelike. Precisely because I’d gone to terrible trouble to find the combination of ashy tones and grey pink, I cannot enjoy the likeness in black. Would Germinie Lacerteux be Germinie Lacerteux without colour?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Obviously not. How I’d like to have painted portraits in our family!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">For the second time I’ve scraped off a study of a Christ with the angel in the Garden of Olives.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Because here I see real olive trees. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">But I can’t, or rather, I don’t wish, to paint it without models. But I have it in my mind with colour — the starry night, the figure of Christ blue, the strongest blues, and the angel broken lemon yellow.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And all the purples from a blood-red purple to ash in the landscape.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I’ve been to get five no. 30 stretching frames, so I have even more intentions. I’m having the paintings that stay here framed in oak and in walnut. I’ll need time, but you’ll see it later. I hope you’ll give me details of your visit to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1207">Maurin</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I like the drawing of the two women in the cart enormously.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">If it took some time before anybody came here with me, it still wouldn’t make me change my mind that it was urgent to take this step, and that in time it will be useful. We feel that the art in which we’re working has a long future yet to come, and so we have to be established like those who are tranquil, and not live like the decadents. Here I’ll have more and more the existence of a Japanese painter, living close to nature like a petit bourgeois. So you can easily tell that it’s less gloomy than the decadents. If I manage to live to quite an old age I’ll be something like <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>. Ah well, as for our personal future, in fact we know nothing about it, but we nevertheless feel that Impressionism will last. More soon, and many, many thanks for all your kindnesses. I think I’ll put the Japanese prints downstairs in the studio.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">We learn from the last page of <ref target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref> that Theo’s letter containing 100 francs, for which Vincent thanks him in the present letter, had arrived on ‘Friday’ <ref target="#l-215">(l. 215)</ref>. This must have been Friday, 21 September 1888, since Vincent again refers to the Maurin illustration Theo had sent, which he had thanked him for around 18 September (<ref target="let682.xml">letter 682</ref>). We have assumed that Vincent would have written back the same day – he was after all very grateful to Theo for his generosity (‘many, many thanks for all your kindnesses’), <ref target="#l-103">(l. 103)</ref> – and have therefore placed this letter on that date.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">A paint order on a separate sheet was printed at the end of the letter in <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990; we have put it with <ref target="let674.xml">letter 674</ref>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref> </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Framing paintings for the decoration <ref target="let673.xml">(673)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let682.xml#n-13">See letter 682, n. 13</ref>, for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> and the Japanese prints.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Matsumotorō theatre in the Tokyo pleasure district (Tōkyō Matsumotorō</hi>) by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1407">Utagawa Kunisada <hi>ii</hi></rs>, 1870. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2250">Ill. 2250</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2285">Ill. 2285</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2286">Ill. 2286</rs>. The print survived as a triptych in the family estate. See cat. Amsterdam 1991, pp. 228-231, cat. no. 318. The package of Japanese prints probably also included <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_770">Geishas in a landscape</rs> </hi>by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1836">Sato Torakiyo</rs>, c. 1870-1880, since this woodcut is pictured in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait with bandaged ear </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2764">F 527 / JH 1657</rs>) which Van Gogh painted in January 1889. See also Douglas Cooper, ‘Two Japanese prints from Vincent van Gogh’s collection’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Burlington Magazine</hi> 99 (June 1957), no. 651, p. 204.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>It is not possible to identify the print Van Gogh means here; there are several heads of women in the family collection.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let681.xml#n-6">letter 681, n. 6,</ref> for the term ‘artist’s house’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let623.xml#n-16">See letter 623, n. 16,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>’s house.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml#n-10">See letter 637, n. 10,</ref> for the magazine <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Japon Artistique</hi>. The leading article of the first issue (May 1888) was ‘Programme’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_290">Siegfried Bing</rs> (pp. 1-10).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml#n-20">See letter 628, n. 20,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let678.xml#n-16">See letter 678, n. 16,</ref> for this photograph of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2715">F 476 / JH 1581</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let574.xml#n-5">See letter 574, n. 5,</ref> for the novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_449">Germinie Lacerteux</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Jules and Edmond de Goncourt</rs>. By ‘Germinie Lacerteux’s colour’ Van Gogh means Germinie’s ‘pale look’, which he talks about in a later letter. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let804.xml#n-12">See letter 804, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written about his first attempt to paint a Christ in the Garden of Olives in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let637.xml">letter 637</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Theo must have visited <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1207">Charles Maurin</rs> in his studio at 18 rue de Chabrol – this address is given in the catalogue of the Indépendants’ fourth exhibition (1888). On 17 September, Maurin wrote to Félix Vallotton about this visit from Theo: ‘Boussod et Valadon called on me today – he wants to exhibit my work, I told him that it’s unsaleable, they’re not fancy goods, but all the same, he insists.’ (Venu aujourd’hui chez moi Boussod et Valadon – il veut m’exposer, je lui dis que ça n’est pas vendable, pas article de Paris; mais quoique, et il insiste.) See G. Guisan, D. Jakubec, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Félix Vallotton: documents pour une biographie et pour l’histoire d’une oeuvre</hi>. Lausanne and Paris 1973-1975. Vol. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">i</hi>: Lettres 1884-1889, p. 44.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let682.xml#n-1">See letter 682, n. 1,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1207">Maurin</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2245">Before the accident</rs></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    