<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Saturday, 29 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let691"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b587 a V/1962 (sheet 1); private collection (sheet 2), wherabouts unknown (sheet 3)</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>691</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>543</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>695</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-09-29">on or about Saturday, 29 September 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0587 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0587 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000795_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="private collection" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="private collection" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="whereabouts unknown" xml:id="surf-pb-3r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3r-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci beaucoup de ta lettre et du billet de 50 francs qu’elle contenait. C’est pas couleur de rose que les douleurs dans la jambe t’aient reprises – mon dieu – il faudrait que ce fusse possible que tu vecusses dans le midi aussi car je pense toujours qu’il nous faut à nous autres et du soleil et du beau temps et de l’air bleu comme remède le plus solide. Le temps ici reste beau et si c’était toujours comme cela ce serait mieux que le paradis des peintres<c type="kk">/</c> ce serait du Japon en plein. Que je pense à toi et à Gauguin et à Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> à tout moment et partout. Tellement c’est beau et tellement je voudrais y voir tout le monde.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Ci inclus petit croquis d’une toile de 30 carrée – enfin le ciel étoilé peint la nuit même<c type="kk">/</c> sous un bec de gaz. Le ciel est bleu vert<c type="kk">/</c> l’eau est bleu de roi<c type="kk">/</c> les terrains sont mauves<c type="kp">_</c> La ville est bleue et violette. le gaz est jaune et ses reflets sont or roux et descendent jusqu’au bronze vert. Sur le champ bleu vert du ciel la Grande Ourse a un scintillement vert et rose dont la paleur discrète contraste avec l’or brutal du gaz.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Deux figurines colorées d’amoureux à l’avant plan.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Pareillement croquis d’une toile de 30 carrée représentant la maison et son entourage sous un soleil de souffre<c type="kk">/</c> sous un ciel de cobalt pur. Le motif est d’un dur! mais justement je veux le vaincre. Car c’est terrible ces maison jaunes dans le soleil et puis l’incomparable fraicheur du bleu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Tout le terrain est jaune aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Je t’en enverrai encore un meilleur dessin que ce croquis de tête<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> la maison à gauche est rose à volets verts<c type="kk">/</c> celle qui est ombragée par un arbre<c type="kk">/</c> c’est là le restaurant où je vais diner tous les jours<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Mon ami le facteur reste au fond de la rue à gauche entre les deux ponts du chemin de fer.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Le café de nuit que j’ai peint n’est pas dans le tableau<c type="kk">/</c> il est à gauche du restaurant<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Milliet trouve cela horrible mais je n’ai pas besoin de te dire que lorsqu’il dit ne pas pouvoir comprendre qu’on s’amuse à faire une boutique d’épicier<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> aussi banale et des maisons aussi raides et droites sans grace aucune<c type="kk">/</c> moi je songe que Zola a fait un certain boulevard dans le commencement de l’assommoir<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> et Flaubert un coin du quai de la Villette en pleine canicule dans le commencement de Bouvard et Pecuchet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> qui ne sont pas piqués des vers. Et cela me fait du bien de faire du <hi rend="italics">dur.</hi> Cela n’empêche que j’ai un besoin terrible de<c type="kk">/</c> dirai je le mot – de religion – alors je vais la nuit dehors pour peindre les étoiles et je rêve toujours un tableau comme cela avec un groupe de figures vivantes des copains.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Maintenant j’ai une lettre de Gauguin qui parait bien triste et dit que dès qu’il a fait une vente certes il viendra mais ne se prononce toujours pas si en cas qu’il aurait son voyage payé tout simplement il consentirait à se debrouiller là-bas. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Il dit que les gens où il loge sont et ont été parfaits pour lui et que les quitter comme cela serait une mauvaise action<c type="kp">_</c> Mais que je lui retourne un poignard dans le coeur si je croirais qu’il ne viendrait pas tout de suite s’il pouvait. Que d’ailleurs si tu pouvais vendre ses toiles à bas prix il serait lui content. Je t’enverrai sa lettre avec la réponse<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Certes sa venue augmenterait de 100 pour cent l’importance de cette entreprise de faire de la peinture dans le midi<c type="kp">_</c> Et une fois ici je ne le vois pas encore repartir car je crois qu’il y prendrait racine<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Et je me dis toujours que ce que tu fais en privé<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> serait enfin alors avec sa collaboration une chose plus serieuse que mon travail seul<c type="kk">/</c> sans augmentation des dépenses tu aurais plus de satisfaction.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Plus tard si peut être un jour tu serais à ton compte avec les tableaux impressionistes on n’aurait qu’à continuer et à agrandir ce qui existe actuellement. Enfin Gauguin en parle que Laval a trouvé quelqu’un qui lui donnera 150 francs par mois au moins pour un an<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> et que Laval aussi en fevrier viendrait peutêtre<c type="kp">_</c> Et moi ayant ecrit à Bernard que je croyais que dans le midi il ne pourrait vivre à moins de 3.50 ou 4 francs par jour rien que pour logement &amp; nourriture<c type="kk">/</c> il dit que lui croit que pour 200 francs par mois il y aurait nourriture et logement pour tous les 3<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui n’est pas impossible d’ailleurs en logeant &amp; mangeant à l’atelier.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Ce père benedictin doit avoir été bien interessant. Que serait selon lui la religion de l’avenir<c type="kp">_</c> Probable qu’il dirait toujours la même du passé<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Victor Hugo dit</hi><c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">Dieu est un phare à éclipse</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> et alors certes maintenant nous passons par cet éclipse<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Je voudrais seulement qu’on trouvat à nous prouver quelque chose de tranquillisant et qui nous consolat de façon que nous cessions de nous sentir coupables ou malheureux et que tels quels nous 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>pourrions marcher sans nous égarer dans la solitude ou le néant et sans avoir à chaque pas à craindre ou à calculer nerveusement le mal que nous pourrions sans le vouloir occasionner aux autres.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Ce drole de Giotto duquel sa biographie disait qu’il etait toujours souffrant et toujours plein d’ardeur et d’idees<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Voilà je voudrais pouvoir arriver à cette assurance-là qui rend heureux<c type="kk">/</c> gai et vivant en toute occasion. Cela peut bien mieux se faire dans la campagne ou une petite ville que dans cette fournaise Parisienne<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Je ne serais pas surpris si tu aimerais la nuit etoilée et les champs labourés<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> – cela est plus calme que d’autres toiles. Si le travail marchait toujours comme cela j’aurais moins d’inquietudes pour l’argent car les gens y viendraient plus facilement si la technique continuait à être plus harmonieuse. Mais ce sacré mistral est bien gênant pour faire des touches qui se tiennent et s’enlacent bien avec sentiment comme une musique jouee avec emotion.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Avec ce temps tranquille je me laisse aller et j’ai moins à lutter contre des impossibilités<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">L’envoi de Tanguy est arrivé et je t’en remercie beaucoup beaucoup car j’espère ainsi pouvoir faire quelquechôse pendant l’automne pour l’exposition prochaine. Ce qui est le plus pressé maintenant c’est 5 ou même 10 mètres de toile.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Je t’écris encore et t’enverrai lettre Gauguin avec la réponse. Très interessant ce que tu dis de Maurin<c type="kk">/</c> à 40 francs ses dessins certes ne sont pas chers.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> De plus en plus je crois qu’il faut croire que le vrai et le juste commerce de tableaux est de se laisser aller à son goût<c type="kk">/</c> son éducation devant les maitres<c type="kk">/</c> sa foi enfin. Il <hi rend="italics">n’est pas plus facile</hi><c type="kk">/</c> je suis convaincu<c type="kk">/</c> de faire un bon tableau que de trouver un diamant ou une perle<c type="kk">/</c> cela demande de la peine et on y risque sa vie comme marchand ou comme artiste. Alors une fois qu’on a des bonnes pierres il ne faut pas non plus douter de soi et hardiment tenir la chôse à un certain prix.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">En attendant pourtant.... Mais pourtant cette idée-là m’encourage à travailler alors que pourtant naturellement j’en souffre de devoir depenser de l’argent. Mais en pleine souffrance cette idee de la perle m’est venue et à toi je ne serais pas etonné qu’elle te fasse du bien aussi dans les heures de decouragement. Il n’y a pas plus de bons tableaux que des diamants<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Et faire le commerce des bonnes pierres cela n’a absolument rien de malhonnête. On peut croire en soi<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> lorsqu’on voit que la chôse qu’on vend est bonne. Maintenant si pourtant les gens aiment le strass cela leur est loisible et puisqu’ils le demandent<c type="kk">/</c> bon<c type="kk">/</c> on peut en avoir en magasin<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Mais cela ne suffit pas pour se sentir soi – avec les bons tableaux pourtant on peut se sentir soi et etre ferme car c’est pure erreur qu’il y en ait tant qu’on veut. Peutetre je m’exprime mal mais j’y ai beaucoup pensé de ces jours ci et le calme m’est venu pour l’affaire Gauguin<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Tous ces Gauguin sont de bonnes pierres et soyons les marchands des Gauguin hardiment.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Milliet te dit bien le bonjour<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai son portrait maintenant avec le kepi rouge sur fond emeraude et dans ce fond les armes de son regiment<c type="kk">/</c> le croissant et une étoile à 5 pointes<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/> 

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">bonne poignée de main et à bientôt et bien merci et j’espère que les douleurs ne dureront pas<c type="kp">_</c> As tu revu un médecin<c type="kp">_</c> Soigne toi car la douleur physique est si agaçante<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you very much for your letter and for the 50-franc note it contained. It’s not a rosy prospect that the pains in your leg have come back — my God — it should have to be possible for you to live in the south as well, because I always think that what we need is sunshine and fine weather and blue air as the most dependable remedy. The weather’s still fine here, and if it was always like that it would be better than the painters’ paradise, it would be Japan altogether. How I think of you and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, everywhere and at all times! It’s so beautiful, and I’d so much like to see everyone over here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Included herewith little croquis of a square no. 30 canvas — the starry sky at last, actually painted at night, under a gas-lamp. The sky is green-blue, the water is royal blue, the areas of land are mauve. The town is blue and violet. The gaslight is yellow, and its reflections are red gold and go right down to green bronze. Against the green-blue field of the sky the Great Bear has a green and pink sparkle whose discreet paleness contrasts with the harsh gold of the gaslight.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Two small coloured figures of lovers in the foreground.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Likewise croquis of a square no. 30 canvas showing the house and its surroundings under a sulphur sun, under a pure cobalt sky. That’s a really difficult subject! But I want to conquer it for that very reason. Because it’s tremendous, these yellow houses in the sunlight and then the incomparable freshness of the blue.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">All the ground’s yellow, too. I’ll send you another, better drawing of it than this croquis from memory;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> the house to the left is pink, with green shutters; the one that’s shaded by a tree, that’s the restaurant where I go to eat supper every day.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> My friend the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">postman</rs> lives at the bottom of the street on the left, between the two railway bridges.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">The night café that I painted isn’t in the painting; it’s to the left of the restaurant.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> finds it horrible, but I don’t need to tell you that when he says he can’t understand that someone can enjoy doing such an ordinary grocer’s shop,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and such stiff, square houses with no charm at all, I reflect that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> did a certain boulevard at the beginning of L’assommoir<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_596">Flaubert</rs> a corner of quai de la Villette in the summer heat, at the beginning of Bouvard et Pécuchet,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> that aren’t half bad. And it does me good to do what’s <hi rend="italics">difficult</hi>. That doesn’t stop me having a tremendous need for, shall I say the word — for religion — so I go outside at night to paint the stars, and I always dream a painting like that, with a group of lively figures of the pals.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Now I have a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, who seems very sad and says he’ll definitely come once he’s made a sale, but still doesn’t commit himself as to whether, if he had his fare paid, he would simply agree to untangle himself over there. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> He says that the people where he’s staying are and have been faultless towards him, and that to leave them like that would be a bad deed. But that I turn a dagger in his heart if I were to believe that he wouldn’t come straightaway if he could. And furthermore, that if you could sell his canvases cheaply, he for one would be happy. I’ll send you his letter with the reply.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Certainly, his arrival would increase the importance of this venture of painting in the south by 100 per cent. And once here, I don’t see him leaving soon, because I believe he would put down roots.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And I always say to myself that with his collaboration, what you do in private<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> would eventually be a more considerable thing than my work on my own; you would have more satisfaction without an increase in expenses.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Later, if some day you were perhaps established on your own account with Impressionist paintings, we’d only have to continue and to expand what exists at present. Lastly, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> says that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs> has found someone who’ll give him 150 francs a month, for a year at least,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and that Laval will perhaps also come in February. And I having written to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> that I believed that he couldn’t live on less than 3.50 or 4 francs a day in the south, for board and lodging alone, he says that he believes that for 200 francs a month there would be board and lodging for all 3, which isn’t impossible, by the way, living and eating at the studio.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">This Benedictine priest must have been very interesting. What, in his opinion, is the religion of the future likely to be? He’ll probably say, still the same as the past. <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs> says, God is a lighthouse whose beam flashes on and off</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and so now, of course, we’re passing through that darkness.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">My only wish is that they could manage to prove something that would be calming to us, that would console us so that we’d cease to feel guilty or unhappy, and that just as we 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> are we could proceed without getting lost in loneliness or nothingness, and without having at each step to fear or nervously calculate the harm which, without wishing to, we might cause others.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">That odd fellow, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, whose biography said that he was always unwell, and always full of ardour and ideas.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Well, I’d like to be able to attain that self-confidence that makes a person happy, cheerful and lively at all times. That can happen much more easily in the country or a small town than in that Parisian furnace.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I wouldn’t be surprised if you liked the starry night and the ploughed fields<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> — they’re calmer than some other canvases. If the work always went like that I’d have fewer worries about money, because people would come to it more easily if the technique continued to be more harmonious. But this bloody mistral is a real nuisance for doing brushstrokes that hold together and intertwine well, with feeling, like a piece of music played with emotion.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">With this quiet weather, I let myself go and I have less need to struggle against impossibilities.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s consignment has arrived and I thank you for it very, very much, because this way I hope to be able to do something during the autumn for the next exhibition. What’s most urgent now is 5 or even 10 metres of canvas.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I’ll write to you again and will send you <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s letter with the reply. Very interesting what you say about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1207">Maurin</rs>; at 40 francs his drawings are certainly not dear.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> More and more I believe that we must believe that true and fair dealing in paintings is to follow one’s taste, one’s education looking at the masters, one’s faith, in a word. It <hi rend="italics">is no easier</hi>, I’m convinced, to make a good painting than to find a diamond or a pearl; it requires effort, and you stake your life as a dealer or an artist on it. So once you have good stones, it’s important not to lack faith in yourself either, but boldly keep things at a certain price.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">While waiting, however.... But all the same, that thought gives me courage to work, while, however, I naturally suffer from the fact of having to spend money. But this thought of the pearl came to me right in the midst of my suffering, and I wouldn’t be surprised if it did you good, too, in your moments of discouragement. There are no more good paintings than there are diamonds.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">And there’s absolutely nothing dishonest about dealing in good stones. One can believe in oneself when the thing one’s selling is good. Now if, though, people like paste, they’re at liberty to do so, and since they ask for it, well, one may keep it in stock.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">But that isn’t enough to feel one is oneself – with good paintings, though, one can feel one is oneself and be firm, because it’s a pure error to think that there are as many as one wishes. Perhaps I express myself badly, but I’ve thought about it a lot lately, and calm has come to me about the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> business. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">All these <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>s are good stones, and let’s boldly be the dealers in Gauguins.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> greets you warmly, I have his portrait now, with the red képi against an emerald background, and in this background the emblem of his regiment, the crescent and a 5-pointed star.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Good handshake and more soon, and thank you very much, and I hope your pains won’t last. Have you seen a doctor again? Look after yourself, because physical pain is so annoying.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">
<pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In
<ref target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref> Vincent asked Theo if he could have his next allowance on Friday again. Assuming that his brother acceded to this request and that Vincent – as usual – thanked him for the money soon after receiving it (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>), we have dated this letter on or about Saturday, 29 September 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">We have placed the sheet that was previously regarded as the second sheet of this letter with
<ref target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref>. The original conclusion of the present letter is a sheet with the letter sketch
<hi rend="italics">The Yellow House (‘The street’) </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_189">F 1453 / JH 1590</rs>), letter text on the verso, and a signature. The letter sketch is the ‘croquis’ of ‘the house and its surroundings’
<ref target="#l-26">(l. 26)</ref>. The confusion about the placement of this sheet must have arisen because the original second sheet became separated from the rest of the letter in the family estate and ended up in private hands. Cf. exhib. cat. New York 1984, p. 260.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles
<ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh’s ambition to exhibit work at the 1889 World Exhibition
<ref target="let590.xml">(590)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The enclosed sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Starry night over the Rhône </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_190">F 1515 / JH 1593</rs>), dimensions unknown, is after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2723">F 474 / JH 1592</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Yellow House (‘The street’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_189">F 1453 / JH 1590</rs>) is after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2721">F 464 / JH 1589</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let700.xml">See letter 700</ref> for the drawing Van Gogh sent to Theo later.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This was Restaurant Vénissac in place Lamartine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Since <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> lived in rue de la Montagne des Cordes (on the right after the two bridges), Van Gogh must be referring to Roulin’s place of work: the station’s mail room was in the cul-de-sac Impasse Lamartine, on the left beside the Yellow House in the sketch. Cf. the map in exhib. cat. Chicago 2001, p. 109.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This was the Café de la Gare, where Van Gogh had painted <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let676.xml">See letter 676</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Next door to Van Gogh’s house, in the left-hand side of the premises at 2 place Lamartine, was the grocer’s shop run by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_52 bio.xml#_329">François Damase and Marguerite Crévoulin</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>The description in chapter 1 of boulevard de la Chapelle and boulevard de Rochechouart in Paris, where the hôtel de la Villette was located in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_255">L’assommoir</ref></hi>. See Zola 1960-1967, vol. 2, pp. 376ff, 1547.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The opening sentences of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_596">Flaubert</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_498">Bouvard et Pécuchet</ref></hi> read: ‘Since the temperature was 33 degrees, boulevard Bourdon was completely deserted. Lower down, the inky water of the Saint-Martin canal, closed between its two locks, lay spread out in a straight line’ (Comme il faisait une chaleur de 33 degrés, le boulevard Bourdon se trouvait absolument désert. Plus bas, le canal Saint-Martin, fermé par les deux écluses, étalait en ligne droite son eau couleur d’encre). See Gustave Flaubert, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Oeuvres. L’éducation sentimentale. Trois contes. Bouvard et Pécuchet</hi>. Ed. A. Thibaudet and R. Dumesnil. Paris 1952, p. 713.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh’s reference to the quai de la Villette (so that he locates the action considerably further to the north) was probably prompted by the fact that Flaubert also mentions the Saint Martin Canal. This canal is 6.6 km long and links the bassin de la Villette with the Seine, close to the scene of the action described by Flaubert. See Baedeker 1889-1, pp. 62, 190. Cf. Noll 1994, pp. 171-172.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let688.xml">688</ref>; Van Gogh’s reply to it is not known. In the surviving fragment of an unsent draft letter to Gauguin, Van Gogh responded to Gauguin’s suggestion to reduce the prices of his work. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="RM16.xml">See RM16</ref> and Jansen <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al</hi>. 2000.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Alongside his job at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>, where he dealt in the work of established artists, Theo also supported modern artists by buying their work for his own collection and offering them accommodation (as he did <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>, among others). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1999.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let688.xml#n-7">See letter 688, n. 7,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs>’s financial backer.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> about the cost of living in Arles in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let684.xml">letter 684</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let300.xml#n-10">See letter 300, n. 10,</ref> for the saying ‘God is like a lighthouse whose beam flashes on and off’ (Dieu est comme un phare à éclipse), taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>’s <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_312"><hi rend="italics">La sorcière</hi></ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let683.xml#n-18">See letter 683, n. 18,</ref> for the description of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> as sickly, but a genius. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ploughed fields (‘The furrows’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2719">F 574 / JH 1586</rs>), which Van Gogh had sketched in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>This consignment from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> must have contained the coarsely ground paint that Van Gogh had asked for in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref>. It emerges from that letter that he also wanted Theo to order the 5 or 10 metres of canvas from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Theo must have written about his visit to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1207">Maurin</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let685.xml">see letter 685</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Van Gogh made the same comparison between making paintings and mining diamonds in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let651.xml">letters 651</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let696.xml">696</ref> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Read:</hi> ‘en soi-même’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>This is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Paul Eugène Milliet</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘The lover’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2720">F 473 / JH 1588</rs>). Van Gogh drew a crescent moon and a star beside the text.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    