<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Eugène Boch. Arles, Tuesday, 2 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let693"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b598 a-c V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>693</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>553b</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>696</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-02">Tuesday, 2 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Eugène Boch</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000814_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000815_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000815_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598b V/1962" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000815_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000815_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598c V/1962" xml:id="surf-pb-3r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000816_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3r-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000816_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0598c V/1962" xml:id="surf-pb-3v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000816_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3v-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000816_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher ami Bock,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci bien de votre lettre qui m’a fait bien plaisir<c type="kp">_</c> Je vous en félicite de ne pas avoir hésité cette fois-ci – et d’avoir attaqué le Borinage.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Voilà un champ où vous pourrez travailler votre vie durant tant le paysage extraordinaire que la figure.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Les scloneuses<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> en loques de fosse sont surtout superbes<c type="kp">_</c> Si vous allez jamais au Petit Wasmes voulez vous vous informer si Jean Baptiste Denis (cultivateur) et Joseph Quinet (charbonnier)<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> y vivent encore et leur dire de ma part que je n’ai jamais oublié le Borinage et que j’aurais toujours encore envie de le revoir. Maintenant j’ai à vous raconter du neuf c.à.d. que j’ai enfin meublé la maison et que j’ai de suite meublé une chambre à coucher pour Gauguin aussi ou pour quiconque viendra.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">La maison est bien plus gaie maintenant qu’elle est meublée. Après j’ai travaillé d’arrache pied car l’automne est sans vent et superbe. Aussi ai je en train <hi rend="italics">7 toiles de 30 carrées</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Tout d’abord le café de nuit où j’ai logé<c type="kk">/</c> avec effet de lampes – peint la nuit<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">3 vues du jardin public devant ma maison.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">En voici une de ces vues. Un buisson de cyprès ou de Cèdre en boule. d’un vert bouteille<c type="kp">_</c> Dans le gazon vert citronné<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Derriere une rangée de lauriers roses et 2 figurines<c type="kp">_</c> Un ciel bleu de cobalt cru.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Vous voyez que c’est encore bien plus simple qu’auparavent<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Puis des terres labourées<c type="kk">/</c> un paysage avec rien que les mottes de terre<c type="kk">/</c> les sillons couleur d’un vieux sabot sous le ciel myosotys avec des flocons blancs.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Puis une vue de ma maison et de l’entourage ensoleillé de souffre<c type="kk">/</c> le ciel cobalt dur et clair<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Cela c’est d’un difficile!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Puis une vue du café sur la Place du forum où nous avions l’habitude d’aller<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">peint la</hi> <hi rend="italics">nuit</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Puis enfin une etude du <hi rend="italics">Rhône</hi><c type="kk">/</c> de la ville eclairée au gaz et se refletant dans la rivière bleue.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Avec le ciel etoilé dessus – avec la Grande Ourse – à scintillement rose et vert sur le champ bleu de cobalt du ciel nocturne tandis que la lumiere de la ville et ses reflets brutals sont d’un or rouge et d’un vert bronzé<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>Peint la nuit<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Le jardin aux lauriers roses et au buisson en boule est empâté comme de la barbotine.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Votre portrait est dans ma chambre à coucher avec celui de Milliet le zouave que je viens de faire.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Je voudrais bien vous prier de me faire un échange d’une de vos etudes des charbonnages<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> attendez<c type="kk">/</c> je vous enverrai de mon côté d’abord une étude alors<c type="kk">/</c> que<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> je serai sûr que cela en sera une qui vous paraitra tout inconnue. Car si vous voyiez les études de nuit vous aimeriez peut etre mieux cela que les etudes de soleil. Enfin laissez moi faire. Car j’espère bien que nos rapports une fois commencés dureront toujours<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Car tout ce que vous ferez va m’interesser extraordinairement puisque j’aime tellement ce triste pays du Borinage qui toujours me sera inoubliable.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Si je viens à Paris l’année prochaine alors je suis à peu près decidé de pousser jusqu’à Mons. Et peutetre jusqu’à mon pays pour y prendre des endroits connus d’avance. Ainsi dans le Borinage <hi rend="italics">Marcasse</hi> ou S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Antoine au Petit Wasmes.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Et puis la cour de l’Agrappe chez vous à Frameries<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> C’est en somme dans le Borinage que j’ai pour la première fois commencé à travailler sur nature. Mais naturellement tout cela je l’ai depuis longtemps détruit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Mais cela me remue le coeur qu’enfin tous ces endroits vont être peints.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Vous allez voir comme les idées vous viendront. Je vous ecris très à la hâte mais je voulais répondre de suite.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Ci inclus un bien mauvais croquis de la nuit etoilée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Tous ces tableaux sont des toiles de 30 carrées.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Eussiez vous resté ici jusqu’à présent vous auriez remporté d’autres etudes. Car je vous dis<c type="kk">/</c> la nature a été <hi rend="italics">extraordinairement</hi> belle<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai plus d’une fois fait une toile de 30 dans la journée mais alors c’etait que dès le matin jusqu’au coucher du soleil je n’ai bougé de la seance que pour manger un morceau.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Mon frère m’a écrit qu’il vous avait vu en passant. Eh bien l’année prochaine j’espère bien que nous nous reverrons<c type="kk">/</c> n’oubliez surtout pas de m’écrire votre adresse si vous changiez de place ou de me donner au juste votre adresse permanente<c type="kk">/</c> à la Louvière si j’ai bonne memoire<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Car cela sera excellent de travailler avec continuité dans les charbonnages et puis<c type="kk">/</c> pour voir tout autre chôse<c type="kk">/</c> venir au pays des lauriers roses et du soleil de souffre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Est ce que votre soeur<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> va faire les charbonniers  aussi. Il y a bien là du travail pour deux. J’estime qu’il soit bien heureux pour vous que vous soyez à deux pour faire de la peinture dans votre maison.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Eh bien je dois aller travailler dans la vigne près de Mont Major. Elle est toute pourpré jaune vert sous le ciel bleu<c type="kk">/</c> un beau motif de couleur.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Bonne poignée de main et bon courage et bien du succes pour le travail<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">t<c type="kp">_</c> à v<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Excusez ma grande hâte<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai meme pas le temps de relire la lettre<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
      <pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
    <pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>
    <pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/>
    <pb f="3v" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-3v-8" facs="#zone-pb-3v-8"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Many thanks for your letter, which gave me great pleasure. I congratulate you on not having hesitated this time — and on having tackled the Borinage.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> That’s a field in which you’ll be able to work for the whole of your life, the extraordinary landscape as well as the human figure!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The female thrutchers in pit-rags, in particular, are superb. If you ever go to Petit-Wasmes, would you find out if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_346">Jean Baptiste Denis</rs> (farmer) and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_629">Joseph Quinez</rs> (miner)<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> are still living there, and tell them on my behalf that I’ve never forgotten the Borinage, and that I’ll always have a wish to see it again? Now I have to tell you some news, that is that I’ve at last furnished the house and that I immediately furnished a bedroom for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> as well, or for whoever will come.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">The house is much more cheerful now that it’s furnished. Afterwards I worked at full tilt, because the autumn is windless and superb. And so I have <hi rend="italics">7 square no. 30 canvases </hi>on the go. First of all the night café where I stayed, with lamp effects — painted at night.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">3 views of the public garden in front of my house.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Here’s one of those views. A round cypress or Cedar bush in bottle green. In the lemony green lawn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">At the back, a row of oleanders and 2 small figures. A blue sky in raw cobalt.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> You can see that it’s much simpler than before.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And ploughed fields, a landscape with nothing but clods of earth, the furrows the colour of an old clog under the forget-me-not sky with white flecks.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And a view of my house and its surroundings under a sulphur sun, the sky hard, bright cobalt.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> That’s a difficult one!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And a view of the café on place du Forum, where we used to go, <hi rend="italics">painted at night</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And lastly, a study of the <hi rend="italics">Rhône</hi>, of the town under gaslight and reflected in the blue river.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">With the starry sky above — with the Great Bear — with a pink and green sparkle on the cobalt blue field of the night sky, while the light of the town and its harsh reflections are of a red gold and a green tinged with bronze. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Painted at night.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">The garden with the oleanders and the round bush is impasted like barbotine.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Your portrait is in my bedroom, with the one of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> the Zouave that I’ve just done.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I’d very much like to ask you to do an exchange with me of one of your studies of the coal-mines.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Wait, I’ll send you a study first then, which I’m sure will be one of those that will seem entirely unfamiliar to you. Because if you saw the night studies, you’d perhaps like them better than the studies of sunlight. Well, let me decide. Because I sincerely hope that our relationship, once embarked upon, will last for good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Because everything you do will be of extraordinary interest to me, since I so much love that sad region of the Borinage, which will always be unforgettable to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">If I come to Paris next year, then I’m more or less determined to push on as far as Mons. And perhaps to my own country, to do places there that I knew before. Thus, in the Borinage, <hi rend="italics">Marcasse </hi>or St-Antoine at Petit-Wasmes.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> And then the Cour de l’Agrappe, at your place in Frameries.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> In short, it was in the Borinage that I began to work from nature for the first time. But I destroyed all that long ago, of course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But it touches my heart that in the end all these places are going to be painted. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">You’ll see how the ideas will come to you. I’m writing to you in great haste, but I wanted to reply right away. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Included herewith a very bad croquis of the starry night.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> All these paintings are square no. 30 canvases.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Had you stayed here until now you’d have taken away other studies. Because I tell you, nature has been <hi rend="italics">extraordinarily </hi>beautiful. More than once I’ve done a no. 30 canvas in a day, but then it was the case that from morning till sunset I didn’t move from the sitting except to eat a bite.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">My brother wrote to me that he had seen you in passing. Ah well, next year I sincerely hope that we’ll meet again; above all don’t forget to write me your address if you move house, or give me your precise permanent address — at la Louvière, if I remember rightly.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Because it will be excellent to work with continuity in the coal-fields and then, in order to see something entirely different, to come to the region of oleanders and the sulphur sun.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">Is your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_870">sister</rs><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> also going to do miners? There’s certainly work for two people there. I believe that it’s very fortunate for you that the two of you both do painting in your house.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Ah well, I have to go to work in the vineyard, near Montmajour. It’s all purplish yellow green under the blue sky, a beautiful, colour motif.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Good handshake and good luck, and much success in your work.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Pardon my great haste; I don’t even have time to re-read the letter.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/><pb f="3r" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-3r-7" facs="#zone-pb-3r-7"/><pb f="3v" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-3v-8" facs="#zone-pb-3v-8"/>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Date of postmark: 2 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The envelope this letter came in has survived. On the front is the postmark ‘ARLES BOUCHES DU RHONE 4E 2 OCT 88.’, and on the back ‘FRAMERIES 4 OCTO 6-M 1888.’ Two postage stamps, one of 10 and one of 15 centimes. The address reads: ‘Monsieur F. Bock/ artiste peintre/Chez M. Moriau/Rue de la Station/ Frameries (par Mons)’.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Boch’s visit to Theo <ref target="let673.xml">(673)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let669.xml#n-16">See letter 669, n. 16,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs>’s stay in the Borinage. Van Gogh addressed the letter care of ‘M. Moriau / Rue de la Station’ (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Additional details</hi>). This ‘Moriau’ was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_540">François Eugène Morriaux</rs>. He lived at 42 rue de la Station in Frameries, and had a tavern (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">AEM</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Also spelt ‘sclauneuses’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>When he died in 1895 the miner <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_629">Joseph Quinez</rs>, born in Wasmes, was living in rue Royale in Wasmes; he was married to Amélie Thiébaut, with whom he had previously lived at number 39 rue de Louise (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">AEM</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The three no. 30 canvases of the park are <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Path in the public garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2716">F 470 / JH 1582</rs>) and a painting he had previously described as ‘a round cedar or cypress bush’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let689.xml">689</ref>) and soon after this as ‘the garden with the round bush and the oleanders’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml">694</ref>). The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_191">F - / JH 1584</rs>) is after this painting, which is now lost.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ploughed fields (‘The furrows’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2719">F 574 / JH 1586</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Yellow House (‘The street’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2721">F 464 / JH 1589</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Café terrace at night</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2714">F 467 / JH 1580</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Starry night over the Rhône </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2723">F 474 / JH 1592</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For ‘barbotine’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let663.xml#n-7">see letter 663, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Eugène Boch (‘The poet’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2710">F 462 / JH 1574</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Paul Eugène Milliet</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(‘The lover’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2720">F 473 / JH 1588</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The exchange with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> occurred in June 1890; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let890.xml">see letter 890</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘dont’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let151.xml#n-2">See letter 151, n. 2,</ref> for the Marcasse/Saint-Antoine mine. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let151.xml#n-3">See letter 151, n. 3,</ref> for the Agrappe coal mine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Starry night over the Rhône</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_192">F - / JH 1594</rs>), after the painting of the same title (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-8">see n. 8</ref> above). On the verso there are lines of writing that have been crossed out, a scrap of a letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs> that was never sent. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="RM16.xml">See RM16</ref> and Jansen <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">et al</hi>. 2000.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>Aside from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2714">Café terrace at night</rs></hi> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-7">n. 7</ref> above) and the two portraits (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-10">n. 10</ref> above), which measure 80.7 x 65.3 cm, 60 x 45 cm and 60 x 49 cm respectively, all the paintings Van Gogh mentions are no. 30 canvases (roughly 92 x 73 cm).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Boch’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_871">parents</rs> lived in La Louvière.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_870">Anna Boch</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>As we learn from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml">letter 694</ref>, Van Gogh was working on <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The green vineyard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2726">F 475 / JH 1595</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    