<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Paul Gauguin. Arles, Wednesday, 3 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let695"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                                        <institution>Institut national d’histoire de l’art (Fonds Roger-Marx)</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>Carton 117, no 1385.</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>695</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>553a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>699</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-03">Wednesday, 3 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1r/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1r/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1r/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1v/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1v/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/695_1v/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Gauguin,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">ce matin j’ai reçu votre excellente lettre que j’ai derechef envoyé à mon frère;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> votre conception de l’impressioniste en général<c type="kk">/</c> dont votre portrait<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> est un symbole<c type="kk">/</c> est saisissante. Je suis on ne peut plus intrigué de voir cela – mais il me semblera j’en suis sûr d’avance que cette oeuvre soit trop importante pour que j’en veuille en echange.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Mais si vous voulez la garder pour nous<c type="kk">/</c> mon frère la vous prendra<c type="kk">/</c> ce que je lui ai immédiatement demandé<c type="kk">/</c> si vous voulez à la premiere occasion et esperons que cela sera sous bien peu.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Car nous chercherons encore une fois à presser la possibilité de votre venue.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Je dois vous dire que meme pendant le travail je ne cesse à songer à cette entreprise de fonder un atelier ayant vous-meme et moi pour habitants fixes mais dont nous desirerons tous les deux faire un abri et un asile pour les copains au moments où ils se trouveront acculés dans leur lutte. Lorsque vous etes parti de Paris<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> mon frère et moi y avons encore passé ensemble un temps qui me demeurera toujours inoubliable. Les discussions avaient pris une envergure plus large – avec Guillaumin<c type="kk">/</c> avec Pissarro pere et fils<c type="kk">/</c> avec Seurat que je ne connaissais pas (j’ai visité son atelier juste quelques heures avant mon départ).<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Dans ces discussions il s’est souvent agi de ce qui nous tient si fort au coeur à mon frere comme à moi<c type="kk">/</c> des mesures à prendre pour sauvegarder l’existence materielle des peintres et de sauvegarder les moyens de production (couleurs<c type="kk">/</c> toiles) et de sauvegarder à eux directement leur part dans le prix 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>que ne prennent leurs tableaux actuellement que longtemps après avoir cessé d’etre la propriété des artistes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Lorsque vous serez ici nous repasserons en revue toutes ces discussions-là<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Quoi qu’il en soit<c type="kk">/</c> lorsque j’ai quitté Paris<c type="kk">/</c> bien bien navré<c type="kk">/</c> assez malade et presqu’alcoolique à force de me monter le cou alors que mes forces m’abandonnaient – alors je me suis renfermé en moi-même et sans encore oser espérer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">à présent dans le vague d’un horizon cependant<c type="kk">/</c> voilà qu’elle me vient<c type="kk">/</c> l’espérance<c type="kk">/</c> cette espérance à éclipse qui dans ma vie solitaire m’a parfois consolée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Or je désirerais vous faire une part fort large de cette croyance que nous allons relativement reussir à fonder une chôse de durée<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Lorsque nous causerons de ces jours étranges de discussions dans les ateliers pauvres et les cafés du <hi rend="italics">petit</hi> boulevard<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> et que vous verrez en plein notre conception<c type="kk">/</c> celle de mon frère et de moi<c type="kk">/</c> qui ne s’est point realisée en tant que formation d’une société –</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Neamoins<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> vous verrez qu’elle est telle que tout ce que l’on fera dans la suite pour remédier à l’état terrible de ces dernieres années sera ou bien cela même que nous avons dit<c type="kk">/</c> ou quelque chôse de paralèle à cela. Tant nous avons pris la chôse par une base immuable. Et vous admettrez<c type="kk">/</c> lorsque vous aurez l’explication entière<c type="kk">/</c> que nous sommes allés alors <hi rend="italics">bien au délà</hi> de ce plan que vous nous<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> avons déjà communiqué<c type="kp">_</c> Que nous ayons été au dela ce n’est que notre devoir de marchands de tableaux car vous savez peut-etre que moi aussi j’ai passé des années dans le commerce et je ne dedaigne pas un metier où j’ai mangé mon pain<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Suffit pour vous dire que je ne crois pas que tout en vous isolant en apparence de Paris vous cesserez de vous sentir en rapport assez direct avec Paris<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">J’ai une fievre de travail extraordinaire ces jours ci<c type="kk">/</c> actuellement je suis aux prises avec un paysage à ciel bleu au-dessus d’une immense vigne verte pourpre jaune<c type="kk">/</c> à sarments noirs &amp; orangés<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Des figurines de dames à ombrelles rouges<c type="kk">/</c> des figurines de vendangeurs avec leur charette l’égayent encore<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Avant-plan de sable gris<c type="kp">_</c> Toujours toile de 30 carrée pour la decoration de la maison.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">J’ai un portrait de moi tout cendré<c type="kk">/</c> la couleur cendrée qui résulte du mélange du véronèse avec la mine orange<c type="kk">/</c> sur fond véronèse pâle tout uni<c type="kk">/</c> à vêtement<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> brun rouge<c type="kk">/</c> mais exagérant moi aussi ma personalité j’avais cherché plutôt le caractère d’un bonze<c type="kk">/</c> simple adorateur du Bouddha éternel<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Il m’a couté assez de mal mais il faudra que je le refasse entièrement si je veux réussir à exprimer la chose. Il me faudra même encore me guérir davantage de l’abrutissement conventionnel de notre ainsi nommé etat civilisé afin d’avoir un meilleur modele pour un meilleur tableau.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Une chôse qui me fait enormement plaisir: j’ai reçu une lettre hier de Bock<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> (sa soeur est dans les vingtistes Belges) qui ecrit s’être établi dans le Borinage pour y peindre charbonniers et charbonnages.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Il reviendra cependant<c type="kk">/</c> à ce qu’il se propose<c type="kk">/</c> dans le midi – pour varier ses impressions et certes dans ce cas viendra à Arles.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je trouve excessivement communes mes conceptions artistiques en comparaison des vôtres<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">J’ai toujours des appetits grossiers de bête<c type="kp">_</c> J’oublie tout pour la beauté extérieure des choses <hi rend="italics">que je ne sais pas rendre</hi> car je la rends laide dans mon tableau et grossière alors que la nature me semble parfaite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Maintenant pourtant l’elan de ma carcasse osseuse est tel qu’il va droit au but<c type="kk">/</c> de là il résulte une sincérité quelquefois originale peutetre dans ce que je fais si toutefois le motif puisse se prêter à mon execution brutale et inhabile<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Je crois que si dès maintenant vous commenciez à vous sentir <hi rend="italics">le chef de cet atelier</hi> dont nous chercherons à faire un abri pour plusieurs<c type="kk">/</c> peu à peu<c type="kk">/</c> à fur et à mesure que notre travail acharné nous fournisse les moyens de completer la chôse – je crois qu’alors vous vous sentirez relativement consolé des malheurs presents de gêne et de maladie en considérant que probablement nous donnons nos vies pour une génération de peintres qui durera encore longtemps<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Ces pays ci ont deja vu et le culte de Venus<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – essentiellement artistique en Grèce – puis les poetes et des artistes de la renaissance<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Là que ces choses ont pu fleurir l’impressionisme le peut aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Pour la chambre où vous logerez j’ai bien exprès fait une décoration<c type="kk">/</c> le <hi rend="italics">jardin d’un poète</hi> (dans les croquis qu’a Bernard il y en a une premiere conception simplifiée ensuite)<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Le banal jardin public renferme des plantes et buissons qui font rever aux paysages où l’on se représente volontiers Botticelli<c type="kk">/</c> Giotto<c type="kk">/</c> Petrarque<c type="kk">/</c> le Dante et Boccace. Dans la décoration j’ai cherché à démêler l’essentiel de ce qui constitue le caractere immuable du pays.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Et j’eusse voulu peindre ce jardin de telle façon que l’on penserait à la fois au vieux poete d’ici (ou plutôt d’Avignon)<c type="kk">/</c> Petrarque<c type="kk">/</c> et au nouveau poète d’ici – Paul Gauguin<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Quelque maladroit que soit cet essai vous y verrez tout de même peut-être que j’ai pensé à vous en préparant votre atelier avec une bien grosse émotion.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Ayons bon courage pour la réussite de notre entreprise et continuez à vous sentir bien chez vous ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Car je suis tellement porté à croire que tout cela durera longtemps.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Bonne poignée de main et croyez moi</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">t<c type="kp">_</c> à v<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Seulement je crains que vous trouverez la Bretagne plus belle<c type="kp">_</c>– quand bien même<c type="kk">/</c> si ici vous ne verriez rien de plus beau que du Daumier<c type="kk">/</c> les figures d’ici sont d’un Daumier absolu souvent. Or pour vous<c type="kk">/</c> vous ne tarderez pas à découvrir au fond de toute la modernité l’antiquité et la renaissance qui dort. Or en tant que quant à celles là libre à vous de les ressuciter<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Bernard m’en parle que lui<c type="kk">/</c> Moret<c type="kk">/</c> Laval et un autre feraient un echange avec moi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> je suis reellement en principe très partisan du systeme d’echanges entre artistes puisque je vois que cela prenait une place considerable dans la vie des peintres japonais<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> je vous enverrai conséquemment les études que j’ai de disponibles à l’état sec de ces jours ci et vous aurez le premier choix<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Mais avec vous je n’en échange aucune si de votre côté cela devrait vous couter une chose aussi importante que votre portrait qui serait trop beau<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Sûr</hi> je n’oserais pas<c type="kp">_</c> Car mon frere vous le prendra volontiers contre tout un mois<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">This morning, I received your excellent letter, which I’ve immediately sent to my brother;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> your conception of the Impressionist in general, of which your portrait<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> is a symbol, is striking. I couldn’t be more intrigued to see it — but it will seem to me, I’m already sure, that this work is too important for me to wish to have it as an exchange.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"> But if you wish to keep it for us, my brother will buy it from you, as I immediately asked him, at the first opportunity if you wish, and let’s hope that will be very soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Because we’ll try once again to urge the possibility of your coming.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I must tell you that even while working I never cease to think about this enterprise of setting up a studio with yourself and me as permanent residents, but which we’d both wish to make into a shelter and a refuge for our pals at moments when they find themselves at an impasse in their struggle. When you left Paris,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> my brother and I spent more time there together that will always remain unforgettable to me. Our discussions took on a broader scope — with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>, with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268 bio.xml#_1267">Pissarro</rs>, father and son, with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1353">Seurat</rs>, whom I didn’t know (I visited his studio just a few hours before my departure).<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> In these discussions, it was often a matter of the thing that’s so dear to our hearts, both my brother’s and mine, the steps to be taken in order to preserve the financial existence of painters, and to preserve the means of production (colours, canvases), and to preserve directly to them their share in the price 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> that their paintings at present fetch only when they have long ceased to be the property of the artists.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">When you’re here we’ll go back over all those discussions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">In any event, when I left Paris very, very upset, quite ill and almost an alcoholic through overdoing it, while my strength was abandoning me — then I withdrew into myself, and without daring to hope yet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">At present, dimly on the horizon, here it comes to me nevertheless — hope —that intermittent hope that has sometimes consoled me in my lonely life.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Now I’d like to see you taking a very large share in this belief that we’ll be relatively successful in founding something lasting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">When we’ll talk about those strange days of discussions in the poor studios and the cafés of the <hi rend="italics">Petit</hi> Boulevard,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and you’ll see in full our idea, my brother’s and mine, which hasn’t in any way been carried out, in terms of forming an association.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Nevertheless, you’ll see that it is such that everything that we’ll do in future to remedy the terrible state of these past few years will either be just what we said, or something similar to it. So unshakeable a basis will we have given the thing. And you’ll admit, when you have the full explanation, that we’ve gone <hi rend="italics">well beyond </hi>the plan we’ve already told you about. It’s no more than our duty as picture dealers to have gone further, because you perhaps know that I too spent years in the trade, and I don’t look down on a profession in which I’ve eaten my daily bread. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Suffice it to say that I don’t believe that even when apparently cutting yourself off from Paris you will cease to feel that you’re in fairly direct contact with Paris. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I have an extraordinary fever for work these days, at present I’m grappling with a landscape with blue sky above an immense green, purple, yellow vine with black and orange shoots.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Little figures of ladies with red sunshades, little figures of grape-pickers with their cart further liven it up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"> Foreground of grey sand. Once again square no. 30 canvas for the decoration of the house.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I have a portrait of myself, all ash-coloured. The ashy colour that comes from mixing Veronese with orange lead, on a pale background of uniform Veronese, with a red-brown garment.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> But exaggerating my personality also, I looked more for the character of a bonze, a simple worshipper of the eternal Buddha.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> It cost me a good deal of trouble, but I’ll have to do it all over again if I want to express the thing. I’ll have to cure myself even further of the conventional numbness of our so-called civilized state, in order to have a better model for a better painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Something that gave me enormous pleasure; I received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs> yesterday (his sister is one of the Belgian Vingtistes), who writes that he’s settled in the Borinage to paint miners and coal-mines there.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> He’ll return, though, to what he has in mind in the south — to vary his impressions, and in that case will certainly come to Arles.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I find my artistic ideas extremely commonplace in comparison with yours.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I always have an animal’s coarse appetites. I forget everything for the external beauty of things, <hi rend="italics">which I’m unable to render</hi> because I make it ugly in my painting, and coarse, whereas nature seems perfect to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Now, however, the energy of my bony carcass is such that it goes straight to the target; from that comes a perhaps sometimes original sincerity in what I make, if, that is, the subject lends itself to my rough and unskilful execution. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I believe that if from now on you began to think of yourself as <hi rend="italics">the head of this studio</hi>, which we’ll attempt to make a refuge for several people, little by little, bit by bit, as our unremitting work provides us with the means to bring the thing to completion — I believe that then you’ll feel relatively consoled for your present misfortunes of penury and illness, considering that we’re probably giving our lives for a generation of painters that will survive for many years to come.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">These parts of the world have already seen both the cult of Venus<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> —essentially artistic in Greece — and the poets and artists of the Renaissance.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Where these things have been able to flower, Impressionism can do so too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">About the room where you’ll stay, I’ve made a decoration especially for it, the <hi rend="italics">garden of a poet</hi> (in the croquis <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> has there’s a first idea for it, later simplified).<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> The unremarkable public garden contains plants and bushes that make one dream of landscapes in which one may readily picture to oneself <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_886">Botticelli</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_569">Dante</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs>. In the decoration I’ve tried to tease out the essence of what constitutes the changeless character of the region.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">And I’d have wished to paint this garden in such a way that one would think both of the old poet of this place (or rather, of Avignon), <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs>, and of its new poet — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">However clumsy this effort, you’ll still see, perhaps, that while preparing your studio I’ve thought of you with very deep feeling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Let’s be of good heart for the success of our enterprise, and may you continue to feel very much at home here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Because I’m so strongly inclined to believe that all this will last for a long time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Good handshake, and believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Only I’m afraid that you’ll find Brittany more beautiful — even though you may well see nothing more beautiful than things out of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, figures here are often pure Daumier. Now, as for you, it won’t take you long to discover, under all the modernity, the ancient world and the Renaissance, which is sleeping. Now, as far as they’re concerned, you’re at liberty to reawaken them.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> tells me that he, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1237">Moret</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs> and someone else would do an exchange with me.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> I am really, in principle, a great supporter of the system of exchanges among artists, since I see that it occupied a considerable place in the life of the Japanese painters.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> So one of these days I’ll send you such studies as I have to spare, in the dry state, and you’ll have first choice. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">But I won’t exchange a single one with you if on your part it would mean costing you something as significant as your portrait, which would be too beautiful. <hi rend="italics">For sure,</hi> I wouldn’t dare, because my brother will gladly buy it from you against a whole month’s allowance.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was written the day after Van Gogh had received a letter from Eugène Boch <ref target="#l-97">(l. 97)</ref>; this was on 2 October (<ref target="let693.xml">see letter 693</ref>), which means that the present letter must date from Wednesday, 3 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Probably sent with <ref target="let696.xml">letter 696</ref> to Bernard. It is not possible to tell which of the two letters was written first. On 8 October 1888 Gauguin sent Van Gogh’s letter to Emile Schuffenecker: ‘I’m sending you a letter from Vincent so that you can see how I stand with him and everything that’s going on at the moment’. (Je vous envoie une lettre de Vincent pour vous faire voir où j’en suis avec lui et tout ce qui se projete en ce moment.) See <hi rend="italics">Correspondance Gauguin </hi>1984, p. 249.</p>
    <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Cf. Cl.-R. Marx, ‘Van Gogh et Gauguin. Lettres inédites de Van Gogh’, <hi rend="italics">Europe. Revue mensuelle</hi>, 17e année, no 194, 15 February 1939, pp. 166-171.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Exchange of portraits with Bernard and Gauguin <ref target="let680.xml">(680)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Plans for a society of artists <ref target="let584.xml">(584)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let692.xml">692</ref>; Vincent sent it on to Theo with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml">letter 694</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2262">Self-portrait with portrait of Bernard, ‘Les misérables’</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let692.xml#n-1">see letter 692, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> left Paris for Brittany on 26 January. See Merlhès 1989, p. 61.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let589.xml#n-19">See letter 589, n. 19,</ref> for Vincent and Theo’s visit to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1353">Seurat</rs>’s studio.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Vincent formulated the same idea in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml">letter 694</ref> to Theo, possibly referring to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>’ painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_315">Hope</rs></hi>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let694.xml#n-11">See letter 694, n. 11.</ref></p>
  
<p rend="indent">‘Cette espérance à éclipse’ may be an allusion to the expression ‘comme un phare à éclipse’ in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Jules Michelet</rs>’s  <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_312"><hi rend="italics">La sorcière</hi></ref>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let300.xml#n-10">see letter 300, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For the term ‘Petit Boulevard’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let584.xml#n-6">see letter 584, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Alors’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘nous vous’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The green vineyard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2726">F 475 / JH 1595</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>After this Van Gogh crossed out ‘presque violet’ (almost violet).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2715">F 476 / JH 1581</rs>). Van Gogh’s reference to ‘the character of a bonze, a simple worshipper of the eternal Buddha’ may have been prompted by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1807">Emile Burnouf</rs>’s article, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_512">Le bouddhisme en Occident</ref>’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> 58 (15 July 1888), no. 88, pp. 340-372. Van Gogh was in any event familiar with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_695">Henry Cochin</rs>’s article on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs> (‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_561">Boccace d’après ses oeuvres et les témoignages contemporains</ref>’) in the same issue; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let683.xml#n-15">see letter 683, n. 15.</ref> Merlhès regards Burnouf’s article as the direct source for the self-portrait; see Merlhès<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1989, pp. 114-118, however the words Van Gogh used do not occur in the article. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi> might also have inspired him to depict himself thus; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml#n-20">see letter 628, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Boch’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let693.xml">Letter 693</ref> is Van Gogh’s reply to the (lost) letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Boch</rs>. Boch’s sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_870">Anna</rs> was a member of the artists’ association Les Vingt from 1886 to 1894. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let580.xml#n-6">See letter 580, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>A reference to the Venus of Arles as an example of the classical remains in the town; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let683.xml#n-21">see letter 683, n. 21.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
  
<p>It emerges from the following paragraph that Van Gogh is referring to the poets <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_569">Dante</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_721">Petrarch</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_544">Boccaccio</rs> and the painters <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_886">Botticelli</rs>, whom he discussed in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let683.xml">letter 683</ref> after reading <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1804">Cochin</rs>’s article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_561">Boccace d’après ses oeuvres et les témoignages contemporains</ref>’. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let683.xml#n-15">See letter 683, n. 15.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
  
<p>At this point the decoration called ‘the poet’s garden’ consisted of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>) and a now unknown painting of the park (cf. the letter sketches in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let689.xml">letters 689</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let693.xml">693</ref> for the composition). Van Gogh regarded the canvases as companion pieces (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let689.xml">letter 689</ref>) and gave them the title of ‘the poet’s garden’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let696.xml">letter 696</ref>). They were joined later by two more paintings: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden with a couple strolling (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2730">F 479 / JH 1601</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Row of cypresses with a couple strolling (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2738">F 485 / JH 1615</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let709.xml#n-6">See letter 709, nn. 6</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let709.xml#n-7">7.</ref> On the development and significance of this series, see Van Uitert 1983, pp. 37-41, and Dorn 1990, pp. 117-123, 378-382.</p>

<p rend="indent"><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> owned the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Newly mown lawn with a weeping tree</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2667">F 1450 / JH 1509</rs>), which shows the same corner of the park; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let641.xml#n-1">see letter 641, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Vincent had previously told Theo that he wanted to capture ‘the real character of things here’ in his views of the park (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let689.xml">letter 689</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let698.xml#n-1">See letter 698, n. 1,</ref> for this exchange with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1237">Moret</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_936">Chamaillard</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>In his influential book <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_482">L’Art japonais</ref></hi> (1883) <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1766">Louis Gonse</rs> wrote about Japanese artists’ custom of exchanging prints known as ‘surimonos’: ‘Small sheets, drawn or engraved by members of societies of artists, poets and tea-drinkers, are called <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">surimonos</hi> ... At New Year, the members of these societies were normally in the habit of giving each other presents. It was also good manners to make a drawing for the occasion, which one would have engraved and of which one would print a limited number of proofs for selection. In the hands of members, these proofs, called <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">surimonos</hi>, perpetuated the memory of their periodic meetings.’ (On appelle <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">sourimonos</hi>, de petites feuilles dessinées ou gravées par des membres de sociétés d’artistes, de poètes et de buveurs de thé ... Au retour de la nouvelle année, les membres de ces sociétés avaient généralement l’habitude de s’offrir quelque présent. Il était aussi de bon ton de composer quelque dessin de circonstance que l’on faisait graver et que l’on tirait à un nombre limité d’épreuves de choix. Ces épreuves, dites sourimonos, perpétuaient entre les mains des sociétaires le souvenir de leurs réunions périodiques.) <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’art japonais</hi>. Paris 1886, p. 324. Cf. Silverman 2000, pp. 42-43.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    