<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Wednesday, 10 or Thursday, 11 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let702"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b594 a-b V/1962 (sheets 1, 2) and b586 c V/1962 (sheet 3).</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>702</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>550</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>707</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-10">Wednesday, 10 or Thursday, 11 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0594 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0594 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000807_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0594 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0594 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000808_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0586 c" xml:id="surf-pb-3r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000794_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3r-9">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000794_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0586 c" xml:id="surf-pb-3v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000794_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-3v-10">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000794_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Lorsque de ces jours ci j’y pense très souvent que toutes les dépenses de la peinture pèsent sur toi alors tu ne saurais t’imaginer combien j’en ai une inquiétude. Lorsqu’il nous arrive de telles chôses comme ce que dans ta dernière lettre tu raccontes de Bague<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> alors nous devons brûler de vendre. Ou bien plutôt nous devons brûler de pouvoir trouver quelque secours soit de Thomas soit d’un autre dans le genre moitié marchand moitie amateur<c type="kp">_</c> Ainsi C<c type="kp">_</c>M<c type="kp">_</c> sans même nous aider autrement pourrait nous prendre encore une fois une étude.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Je ne sais si tu as jamais lu les frères Zemganno des de Goncourt qui retracent vaguement leur propre histoire peutêtre. Si tu connais cela tu sauras que je redoute plus que je ne saurais te l’exprimer que l’effort de nous procurer de l’argent ne t’éreinte trop.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Si je n’étais pas tourmenté affreusement et toujours par cette inquietude-là je dirais que cela marche car le travail deviendra meilleur et la santé est bien mieux qu’à Paris. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Je m’aperçois de plus en plus que le travail va infiniment mieux lorsqu’on se nourrit bien<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’on a sa couleur<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’on a son atelier et tout cela<c type="kp">_</c> Mais est ce que j’y tiens à ce que mon travail marche. <hi rend="italics">Non</hi> et mille fois <hi rend="italics">non</hi>. Je voudrais en arriver à te faire bien sentir cette vérité qu’en donnant l’argent aux artistes tu fais toi-meme oeuvre d’artiste et que je desirerais seulement que mes toiles deviennent telles que tu ne sois pas trop mécontent de <hi rend="italics">ton</hi> travail<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Et ce n’est pas tout<c type="kk">/</c> je voudrais encore que tu sentes que avec l’argent que l’on déplace on en gagne et qu’ainsi faisant nous arriverons à une indépendance plus nette que celle que donne le commerce en soi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Et ce que l’on fera plus tard pour renouveler le commerce pourrait bien être justement que les marchands vivent avec les artistes<c type="kk">/</c> l’un pour ce qu’on peut appeler le côté ménage<c type="kk">/</c> pour procurer atelier<c type="kk">/</c> nourriture<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>couleur &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> l’autre pour fabriquer<c type="kp">_</c> Hélas nous n’en sommes pas là avec l’ancien commerce qui suivra toujours la vieille routine qui ne profite à personne de vivant et qui aux morts ne fait aucun bien pas non plus. Mais quoi<c type="kk">/</c> cela peut nous laisser relativement froid n’ayant pas le devoir de changer ce qui existe ou de combattre contre un mur. Enfin il faudrait se faire sa part de soleil sans contrarier personne<c type="kp">_</c> Et je m’imagine toujours que tu n’as pas toute la tienne de part au soleil puisque ton travail parisien chez les Goupil est trop éreintant. J’ai alors lorsque je songe à cela une rage marchande<c type="kk">/</c> je veux alors gagner de l’argent pour que tu sois plus libre d’aller et de faire ce que tu veux. Je sens que nous brûlons de vendre ou de trouver du secours nous donnant de l’air.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Voilà peutêtre que je crois trop près ce qui pourrait être encore loin et alors je me sens venir cette inquiétude de trop dépenser.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Cependant les tableaux viennent mieux si l’on se soigne et se porte bien. Mais pour toi<c type="kk">/</c> pour ton travail<c type="kk">/</c> pour toute ta vie également il ne faut pas que tu aies trop de soucis. Comment vont ces douleurs sciatiques<c type="kk">/</c> ont elles cessées<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Quoiqu’il en soit<c type="kk">/</c> tu m’aideras plus en te portant bien<c type="kk">/</c> en vivant bien<c type="kk">/</c> les envois de couleur dussent ils en souffrir<c type="kk">/</c> que d’etre trop à l’étroit pour moi. Je crois que le jour viendra où on voudra du travail – bon – mais peut être est ce encore éloigné et en attendant ne sois pas trop dans la gêne.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Car les affaires aussi cela te viendra tout seul et comme en rêve<c type="kk">/</c> plus vite et mieux si tu te soigne que lorsque tu te gênes. Et ayant l’âge que nous avons, quoi, nous pouvons avoir enfin un certain calme<c type="kk">/</c> une certaine sagesse pour faire les chôses. Je crains maintenant (et je les évite) la misere<c type="kk">/</c> la mauvaise santé et tout cela et j’espère que tu aies les mêmes sentiments.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Ainsi j’ai presqu’un remords d’avoir aujourd’hui acheté ce meuble quoiqu’il soit bon parceque j’ai dû te demander de m’envoyer de l’argent plus tôt que sans cela.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Saches bien ceci<c type="kp">_</c> Si tu te portais mal ou si tu eusses trop de peine et de chagrin rien ne marcherait plus. Et si tu te portes bien les affaires finiront par te venir toutes seules et les idees pour en faire<c type="kk">/</c> des affaires<c type="kk">/</c> te viendront infiniment davantage en mangeant bien qu’en ne pas mangeant assez.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Crie moi donc halte si je vais trop loin. Si non c’est naturellement tant mieux car pour moi aussi certes je peux bien mieux travailler à l’aise que trop gêné.– Mais ne va pas croire que je tienne au travail plus qu’à notre bien être ou au moins surtout qu’à notre sérénité. Gauguin une fois ici sentira cette meme chôse – et il se remettra.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Le jour viendra peutetre bien pour lui où il voudra et pourra redevenir le père de famille qu’il est reellement<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Je suis tres très curieux de savoir ce qu’il a fait en Bretagne. Bernard en écrivait beaucoup de bien. Mais faire de la peinture riche se fait si difficilement dans le froid et dans la misère – et possible qu’en somme son vrai chez soi se trouvera au bout du compte être le midi plus chaud et plus heureux.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Si tu voyais les vignes! il y a des grappes <hi rend="italics">d’un kilo</hi> même – le raisin est magnifique cette année par les beaux jours de l’automne venant à la fin d’un été qui laissait beaucoup à désirer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je regrette d’avoir dépensé de l’argent pour cette commode mais cela peut nous épargner d’en acheter une plus chère – le <hi rend="italics">moins</hi> aurait été 35.– Et lorsque Gauguin viendra il fallait pourtant qu’il y eût quelque chôse pour qu’il puisse y mettre son linge et enfin sa chambre sera plus complète ainsi. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> (Je m’aperçois que cette armoire a des panneaux juste comme ceux sur lesquels a peint Monticelli<c type="kp">_</c>)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Une fois que nous aurons un moment plus riche je prendrais celle ci pour moi et lui prendrait celle de 35 francs. à ce prix-là il y en a <hi rend="italics">toujours</hi> d’occasion mais <hi rend="italics">non pas</hi> toujours au prix où j’ai acheté celle ci.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">J’y ai pensé que si maintenant il commence à y avoir chez toi de certaines études qui prendraient trop de place chez toi et te gêneraient<c type="kk">/</c> on pourrait les ôter des chassis et les envoyer ici où nous avons de la place assez pour les garder. Je dis cela pour certaines chôses de l’année passée ou enfin pour tout ce qui te gênerait. Paris sera bien beau en automne pourtant. La ville ici n’est <hi rend="italics">rien</hi> la nuit<c type="kk">/</c> tout est <hi rend="italics">noir</hi><c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je crois que le gaz en abondance qui en somme est du jaune et de l’orange<c type="kk">/</c> exalte le bleu car la nuit le ciel me parait ici<c type="kk">/</c> et c’est très drôle<c type="kk">/</c> plus <hi rend="italics">noir</hi> qu’à Paris. Et si jamais je revois Paris je chercherai à peindre des effets du gaz sur le boulevard.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Ah à Marseille cela sera le contraire<c type="kk">/</c> je m’imagine que cela sera plus beau que Paris<c type="kk">/</c> la Cannebière<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Je pense si souvent à Monticelli et lorsque je songe à ce que l’on racconte de sa mort il me semble que non seulement il faut écarter l’idee qu’il soit mort <hi rend="italics">buveur</hi> dans le sens <hi rend="italics">d’abruti</hi> par la boisson mais encore il faut savoir que la vie se passe encore davantage que dans le nord tout naturellement en plein air et dans les cafés.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Mon ami le postier<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> par exemple vit beaucoup dans les cafés et certes est plus ou moins buveur et l’a été sa vie durant. Mais il est tellement le contraire d’<hi rend="italics">abruti</hi> et son exaltation est si naturelle<c type="kk">/</c> si intelligente<c type="kk">/</c> et il raisonne alors si largement à la Garribaldi<c type="kk">/</c> que volontiers je reduis la légende quant à Monticelli buveur d’absinthe à exactement les proportions de ce cas de mon postier. Mon papier est rempli<c type="kk">/</c> ecris moi le plus tot que cela te sera possible<c type="kp">_</c> poignée de main et bonne chance<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Un jour je saurai peutêtre des details sur ces derniers jours de Monticelli<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="3r" n="9" xml:id="pb-orig-3r-9" facs="#zone-pb-3r-9"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">un jour madame de Larebey la Roquette<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> me dit: Mais Monticelli<c type="kk">/</c> Monticelli<c type="kk">/</c> mais c’etait un homme qui aurait dû être à la tête d’un grand atelier dans le midi<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">moi j’ai écrit à notre soeur et à toi<c type="kk">/</c> tu te rappelles l’autre jour<c type="kk">/</c> que parfois je croyais sentir que je conti<c type="shy">-</c>nuais Monticelli ici.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Bon – mais tu vois actuellement – cet atelier en question<c type="kk">/</c> nous le fondons.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Ce que fera Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> ce que moi aussi je ferai<c type="kk">/</c> cela se tiendra avec cette 
<pb f="3v" n="10" xml:id="pb-orig-3v-10" facs="#zone-pb-3v-10"/>belle oeuvre de Monticelli et nous chercherons à prouver aux bonnes personnes que Monticelli n’est pas mort avachi sur les tables des cafés de la Cannebière tout à fait mais que petit bonhomme vit encore<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Et avec nous memes la chose ne finira meme pas<c type="kk">/</c> nous la mettons en train sur base assez solide.–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">When lately I very often think that all the costs of painting weigh on you, you couldn’t imagine what anxiety I have about it. When things like what you describe about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_254">Bague</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> in your last letter happen to us, then we must be on the point of selling. Or much rather, we must be on the point of being able to find some help, either from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_780">Thomas</rs> or from someone else, of the half-dealer, half-collector sort. Thus <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>, even without helping us in any other way, could buy another study from us.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I don’t know if you’ve ever read Les frères Zemganno by the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617">De Goncourt</rs>s, who perhaps loosely retrace their own history. If you know it, you’ll know, more than I’d know how to express to you, that I fear that the effort of obtaining money for us will be too exhausting for you.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">If I wasn’t dreadfully, and always, tormented by that anxiety, I would say things were going well, because the work will improve and my health is much better than in Paris.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I realize more and more that work goes infinitely better when you feed yourself well, when you have your paint, when you have your studio, and all that. But is my heart set on my work going well? <hi rend="italics">No</hi>, and a thousand times <hi rend="italics">no</hi>. I’d like to succeed in making you clearly feel this truth, that in giving money to artists you yourself are doing an artist’s work, and that I’d wish only that my canvases might become of such a kind that you aren’t too unhappy with <hi rend="italics">your</hi> work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">And that’s not all; I’d also like you to feel that we earn from the money that we transfer, and that by so doing, we’ll achieve a more complete independence than that provided by the trade as such.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And what we’ll do later to revive the trade could well be precisely that dealers live with artists, the one for what one may call the housekeeping side, to supply studio, food, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> paint &amp;c., the other to produce. Alas, we’re not at that stage with the old trade, which will always follow the old routine that benefits nobody among the living and does no good for the dead, either. But what of it; that may leave us more or less cold, not having a duty to change what exists or to battle against a wall. Anyway, we’d have to get our share of sunshine without vexing anyone. And I always figure to myself that you don’t have your whole share of sunshine, since your work in Paris with the Goupils is too exhausting. So when I think about that, I have a dealer’s rage; then I want to earn money so that you can be freer to go and do what you want. I feel that we’re on the point of selling or of finding help that will give us breathing space.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">There you are, perhaps I believe that what may still be far away is nearer than it in fact is, and then I feel this anxiety coming over me, of spending too much. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">However, paintings come off better if one takes care of oneself and keeps well. But for you, for your work, for your whole life as well, you mustn’t have too many worries. How are those sciatic pains? Have they stopped?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Whatever happens, you’d help me more by keeping well, by living well; even if the consignments of colours had to suffer as a result, than by being too much in straits on my account. I believe that the day will come when people will want the work — well — but perhaps that’s still far away, and meanwhile, don’t be too hard up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Because business, too, will come to you by itself and as if in a dream, better and more quickly if you take care of yourself than if you make yourself hard up. And look, at our age, surely we can finally have a certain calm, a certain wisdom about doing things. I fear now (and I avoid them) poverty, bad health and all that, and I hope you have the same sentiments. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">So I almost have a feeling of remorse at having today bought this piece of furniture, although it’s good, because I had to ask you to send me money sooner than if it hadn’t been for that.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Be sure of this. If you were ill or if you had too much pain and trouble, nothing would work any more. And if you are well, business will eventually come to you by itself, and ideas for doing some business will come to you infinitely more by eating well than by not eating enough.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">So shout at me to stop if I’m going too far. If not, it’s naturally much better, because for me too, I can of course work much better if I’m comfortable rather than too hard up. But don’t go believing that I’m more attached to my work than to our well-being, or at least to our peace of mind, above all. Once <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s here he’ll feel the same thing — and he’ll recover. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The day may well come for him when he’ll wish, and will be able, to become the family man again that he really is.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I’m very, very curious to know what he has done in Brittany. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> writes many good things about it. But doing rich painting is so difficult to do in the cold and in poverty — and possible that in fact his real home will prove to be, when all’s said and done, the warmer and happier south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"> If you saw the vineyards! There are bunches <hi rend="italics">weighing a kilo</hi>, even — the grape is magnificent this year, from the fine autumn days coming at the end of a summer that left much to be desired.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I regret having spent money on this chest of drawers, but it can save us buying a dearer one — the <hi rend="italics">least </hi>would have been 35. And when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> comes, he would in any case have to have something there to put his linen in, and anyway his bedroom will be more complete like this. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> (I notice that this cupboard has panels just like those on which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> painted.)<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Once we have a richer moment I’d take this one for myself and he’d take the one at 35 francs. At that price there’s <hi rend="italics">always </hi>something second-hand, but <hi rend="italics">not </hi>always at the price at which I bought this one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I’ve been thinking that if at your place there are now beginning to be certain studies that might be taking up too much room at your place and getting in your way, they could be taken off their stretching frames and sent here, where we have enough room to store them. I’m saying that about certain things from the past year, or, indeed, for everything that might be in your way. Paris will be very beautiful in the autumn, all the same. The town here is <hi rend="italics">nothing </hi>at night, everything’s <hi rend="italics">dark</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I believe that an abundance of gaslight, which, after all, is yellow and orange, intensifies blue, because at night the sky here seems to me, and it’s very funny, <hi rend="italics">darker </hi>than in Paris. And if I ever see Paris again, I’ll try to paint effects of gaslight on the boulevard. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ah, it must be the opposite in Marseille; I imagine that it must be more beautiful than Paris, La Canebière.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I so often think of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, and when I reflect on what they say about his death it seems to me that not only must we put aside the idea that he died <hi rend="italics">a drinker</hi> in the sense of <hi rend="italics">stupefied </hi>by drink, but we should also know that, even more than in the north, life is quite naturally spent in the open air and in cafés.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> My friend the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">postman</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> for example, lives a great deal in cafés and is certainly more or less a drinker and has been so all his life. But he’s so much the opposite of <hi rend="italics">stupefied</hi>, and his elation is so natural, so intelligent, and then he argues with such a broad sweep, à la <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_379">Garibaldi</rs>, that I’m quite prepared to reduce the legend of Monticelli the absinthe drinker to exactly the proportions of this case of my postman. My paper’s full, write to me as soon as is possible for you. Handshake and good luck.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">One day I’ll perhaps know the details about those last days of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">
<pb f="3r" n="9" xml:id="pb-trans-3r-9" facs="#zone-pb-3r-9"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">One day <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343">Mrs de Larebey la Roquette</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> said to me: <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, now, Monticelli, but he was a man who should have been at the head of a big studio in the south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The other day, you remember, I wrote to our sister and to you that sometimes I believed I had the feeling that I was continuing Monticelli here.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Good — but you see now — the studio in question, we’re setting it up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">What <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> will do, what I’ll also do myself, will be in keeping with that 
<pb f="3v" n="10" xml:id="pb-trans-3v-10" facs="#zone-pb-3v-10"/> fine oeuvre by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, and we’ll try to prove to the good folk that Monticelli didn’t quite die, slumped over the tables of the cafés along La Canebière, but that the little old chap is still alive.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And the thing won’t end with us either; we’re starting it off on quite a solid footing.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In <ref target="let701.xml">letter 701</ref> Van Gogh says he has ‘just’ bought a piece of furniture. The present letter appears to have been written later on the same day, since Van Gogh meanwhile appears to be regretting his purchase <ref target="#l-103">(ll. 103-104)</ref>. We have therefore dated this letter, like <ref target="let701.xml">701</ref>, Wednesday, 10 or Thursday, 11 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">We have added a sheet <ref target="#l-206">(ll. 206-227)</ref> – printed in earlier editions as the last page of <ref target="let686.xml">letter 686</ref> – to the present letter. The sheet must in any event belong with a letter written after <ref target="let689.xml">letter 689</ref>, as emerges from the remark in <ref target="#l-210">ll. 210-213</ref> about continuing the work of Monticelli. Vincent said this to Theo in <ref target="let689.xml">letter 689</ref>. In our view, Vincent continues in the postscript to express his admiration for Monticelli, a subject that he also broached in <ref target="#l-203">ll. 203-205</ref> after he had already signed the letter at the bottom of the page. Furthermore, the pre-printed squares on the paper of the main body of the letter are the same as those on the sheet we have added; they are different from the squares on the sheets that make up <ref target="let686.xml">letter 686</ref>.</p>
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Attempts to sell work through Thomas <ref target="let639.xml">(639)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s health problems <ref target="let611.xml">(611)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s illness <ref target="let581.xml">(581)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let699.xml#n-6">See letter 699, n. 6,</ref> for the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_254">Bague</rs> question.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Vincent had sent drawings and studies to his uncle, the art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Cornelis Marinus van Gogh</rs>, several times in 1882-1883: cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let388.xml#n-1">letter 388, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617">Edmond de Goncourt</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_510">Les frères Zemganno</ref></hi> (1879) tells the life story of the acrobats Nello and Gianni. Edmond’s aim in writing this novel was to portray his emotional relationship with his brother Jules in a poetic manner.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh refers to the fact that the brothers are always short of money and can only support themselves through hard work. Nello is injured attempting a dangerous stunt and becomes a permanent invalid. Because the brothers are dependent on one another in their work, they are forced to abandon their careers as acrobats.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had bought a dressing table and asked whether Theo could send the sum he had spent by money order (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let701.xml">letter 701</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let625.xml#n-22">See letter 625, n. 22,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039 bio.xml#_1040">Gauguin</rs>’s family.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must be referring to the panels <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> used for his paintings. With the exception of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_305">Arabs and horseman</rs></hi>, all the Monticellis in the Van Gogh brothers’ collection were done on panels (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-5">see letter 578, n. 5</ref>). He often used walnut panels, which he bought from a furniture maker. See Alauzen and Ripert 1969, p. 156.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let670.xml#n-7">See letter 670, n. 7,</ref> for ‘La Canebière’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-14">See letter 600, n. 14,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s drinking.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Joseph Roulin.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This is a reference to the art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343">Evelina Delarebeyrette</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-14">See letter 600, n. 14,</ref> for the nickname ‘La Roquette’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let670.xml">letter 670</ref> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>, and in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let689.xml">letter 689</ref> to Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    