<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Sunday, 21 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let709"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b601 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>709</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>556</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>714</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-21">Sunday, 21 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0601" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0601" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000820_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci de ta lettre et du billet de 50 fr. qu’elle contenait<c type="kp">_</c> Merci de m’avoir encore écrit sur le tableau de ces artistes Hollandais<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’ai fait mettre le gaz dans l’atelier et dans la cuisine<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui me coûte 25 francs d’installation.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Si Gauguin et moi travaillons une quinzaine tous les soirs ne les regagnerons nous pas? Seulement comme d’ailleurs G. peut maintenant venir de jour en jour j’aurai absolument absolument encore besoin de 50 francs au moins.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je ne suis pas malade mais je le deviendrais sans le moindre doute si je ne prenais pas une forte nourriture et si je ne cessai pas de peindre pour quelques jours. Enfin je suis encore une fois à peu près reduit au cas de la folie d’Hugue van der Goes dans le tableau d’Emile Wauters<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Et si n’était que j’eusse une nature un peu double comme serait et d’un moine et d’un peintre<c type="kk">/</c> je serais – et cela depuis longtemps – entierement et en plein reduit au cas sus mentionné. </p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Enfin même alors je ne crois pas que ma folie serait celle de la persecution puisque mes sentiments à l’état d’exaltation donnent plutôt dans les préoccupations d’éternité et de vie éternelle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Mais quand même il faut que je me méfie de mes nerfs &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Seulement je dis cela parceque tu aurais tort de croire que j’aurais eu la moindre <hi rend="italics">méfiance</hi> de ces deux peintres Hollandais<c type="kp">_</c> Seulement ce n’est en vérité qu’après ta deuxieme lettre que je puisse me former une idée de ce qu’ils font et je suis bien curieux de voir les photographies d’après leurs dessins.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">J’ai bien envie de t’ecrire une lettre exprès que tu pourras leur faire lire pour expliquer encore une fois pourquoi je crois moi au midi pour l’avenir et le présent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Et pour dire en même temps combien je crois qu’on a raison de voir dans le mouvement impressioniste une tendance vers les choses grandes et non pas <hi rend="italics">seulement</hi> une école qui se bornerait à faire des expériences optiques. Ainsi pour eux qui font alors de la peinture d’histoire ou au moins l’ont faite dans le temps<c type="kk">/</c> s’il y a des bien mauvais peintres d’histoire comme Delaroche et Delort n’en a t il<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> pas egalement des bons comme Eug<c type="kp">_</c> Delacroix et Meissonnier.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Enfin puisque decidemment j’ai l’intention de ne pas peindre au moins durant 3 jours<c type="kk">/</c> peut etre me reposerai je en t’écrivant et à eux en meme temps<c type="kp">_</c> Car tu sais que cela m’intéresse assez<c type="kk">/</c> l’influence qu’aura l’impressionisme sur les peintres Hollandais et sur les amateurs Hollandais<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Voici croquis bien vague de ma derniere toile<c type="kp">_</c> Une rangée de cyprès verts contre un ciel rose avec un croissant citron pâle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Avant plan de terrain vague et du sable et quelques chardons<c type="kp">_</c> Deux amoureux<c type="kk">/</c> l’homme bleu pâle à chapeau jaune<c type="kk">/</c> la femme a un corsage rose et une jupe noire.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Cela fait la quatrieme toile du “jardin du poete”<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> qui est la décoration de la chambre à Gauguin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Cela me fait horreur de devoir encore te demander de l’argent mais je n’y puis rien et avec cela je suis encore éreinté. Pourtant je croirais que le travail que je fais en depensant un plus<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> nous paraîtra un jour meilleur marché que le précédent<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">d’Ailleurs je t’avais déjà dit que si la chôse eût été possible de faire une affaire avec Thomas j’aurais eu un grand desir de pouvoir encore mettre meme 200 de plus dans le travail avant la venue de Gauguin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Cela n’ayant pas pu avoir eu lieu j’ai tout de même poussé aussi avant que j’ai pu ce que j’avais en train dans le grand désir de pouvoir lui montrer du neuf. et de ne pas subir son influence (car certes il aura j’espère de l’influence sur moi) avant de pouvoir lui montrer indubitablement mon originalité propre. Quand même celle là il la verra dans la décoration telle qu’elle est maintenant.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Je t’en prie<c type="kk">/</c> si au moins la chôse t’est possible envoie moi encore cinquante francs de suite<c type="kk">/</c> je ne sais pas trop comment je pourrais m’en tirer sans cela<c type="kp">_</c> Cela me fait plaisir que tu aies relu Tartarin.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Enfin<c type="kp">_</c> J’espere que tu pourras m’ecrire pas plus tard que par retour courrier<c type="kp">_</c> Je te serre bien la main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you for your letter and for the 50-franc note it contained. Thank you for having written me more about those <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075 bio.xml#_1103">Dutch artists</rs>’ painting.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve had gas put in, in the studio and the kitchen, which is costing me 25 francs for installation.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and I work every evening for a fortnight, won’t we earn it all back again? But since, what’s more, G. may come any day now, I’ll absolutely absolutely need at least another 50 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m not ill, but I’d become so without any doubt if I didn’t take hearty food and if I didn’t stop painting for a few days. In fact, I’m once again nearly reduced to the state of madness of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1468">Hugo van der Goes</rs> in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1424">Emile Wauters</rs>’s painting.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And if it wasn’t for the fact that I had something of a dual nature, something of both the monk and the painter, I should be — and that long since — utterly and entirely reduced to the above-mentioned state.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">But even for all that, I don’t believe that my madness would be of the persecution kind, since my feelings in a state of excitement have more to do with preoccupations about eternity and eternal life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">But even so, I must be wary of my nerves, &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I only say that because you’d be wrong to believe that I’d have had the slightest <hi rend="italics">wariness </hi>about these two Dutch painters. But in truth, it’s only after your second letter that I can form an idea of what they’re doing, and I’m very curious to see the photographs of their drawings.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I have a great urge to write you a letter just so that you can have them read it, to explain once again why I myself believe in the south for the future and the present.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And at the same time to say how strongly I believe that we’re right to see in the Impressionist movement a tendency towards great things, and not <hi rend="italics">only </hi>a school that would limit itself to making optical experiments. Similarly with those who do history painting, then, or at least have done it in the past; while there are some very bad history painters, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_980">Delort</rs>, are there not also good ones, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">E. Delacroix</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs>?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Well then, since I have the firm intention not to paint for at least 3 days, perhaps I’ll rest by writing to you and to them at the same time. Because you know that that interests me a good deal, the influence that Impressionism will have on Dutch painters and on Dutch art lovers.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Here’s very rough croquis of my last canvas. A row of green cypresses against a pink sky with a pale lemon crescent moon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Foreground a piece of waste land, and some sand and a few thistles. Two lovers, the man pale blue with a yellow hat, the woman has a pink bodice and a black skirt.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> That makes the fourth canvas of the ‘poet’s garden’,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> which is the decoration for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s bedroom.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">It horrifies me to have to ask you for money again, but I can do nothing about it, and what’s more, I’m worn out again. However, I’d believe that the work that I’m doing while spending a little more will one day seem to us less costly than my previous work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Besides, I’d already told you that if the thing had been possible, to do a deal with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_780">Thomas</rs>, I’d have had a strong desire to be able to put even 200 more into the work before <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s arrival.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">As that couldn’t be done, I nevertheless pressed ahead as far as I could with what I had on the go, in a strong desire to be able to show him something new. And not to fall under his influence (because of course he’ll have an influence on me, I hope) before being able to show him beyond any doubt my own originality. He’ll see that anyway from the decoration as it is now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Please, at least if the thing’s possible for you, send me another fifty francs right away; I don’t quite know how I’ll be able to get by otherwise. I’m pleased that you’ve read Tartarin again.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Anyway. I hope you’ll be able to write to me no later than by return of post. I shake your hand firmly.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for his letter and the money; it emerges from various passages in which he responds to what his brother had written (among them <ref target="#l-3">ll. 3-4</ref> and <ref target="#l-39">ll. 39-41</ref>) that this was <ref target="let708.xml">letter 708</ref>. <ref target="let708.xml">Letter 708</ref> is dated 19 October so it cannot possibly have reached Arles before 20 October. Since Theo in turn replied to the present letter on 23 October (<ref target="let711.xml">see letter 711</ref>) – and Vincent probably wrote again on Monday, (<ref target="let710.xml">see letter 710</ref>) – we have dated it Sunday, 21 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Attempts to sell work through Thomas <ref target="let639.xml">(639)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo had written about the two Dutch artists <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let708.xml">letter 708</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It emerges from Van Gogh’s correspondence that Arles had street lighting and the cafés had gaslight (see e.g. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let656.xml">letters 656</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let691.xml">691</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had said that he would be setting out for Arles on 20 October (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let706.xml">letter 706</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let011.xml#n-8">See letter 11, n. 8,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1424">Emile Wauters</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_447">The painter Hugo van der Goes in the red cloister</rs></hi>, depicting the mentally-ill fifteenth-century painter. Van Gogh had previously compared himself to both the painter and the abbot in the picture; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let650.xml">see letter 650</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>‘Your second letter’ refers to <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let708.xml">letter 708</ref>, in which Theo promised to send Vincent two photographs of drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘n’y en a-t-il’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Row of cypresses with a couple strolling (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_199">F - / JH 1616</rs>) is after the painting of the same title <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2738">F 485 / JH 1615</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
  
<p>The other three paintings of the ‘poet’s garden’ were <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi>, (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>), a now lost painting of the park (cf. the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_187">F 1465 / JH 1583</rs>) and the letter sketch in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let693.xml">letter 693</ref>) for the composition) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The public garden with a couple strolling (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2730">F 479 / JH 1601</rs>). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let703.xml#n-10">letter 703, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
    
<p>Read: ‘un peu plus’ or ‘plus’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">See letter 583, n. 9,</ref> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_459">Tartarin de Tarascon</ref></hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    