<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Monday, 29 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let715"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b603 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>715</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>558</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>720</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-10-29">on or about Monday, 29 October 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0603 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0603 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000822_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0603 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000823_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000823_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0603 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000823_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000823_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Pour <hi rend="italics">malade</hi> je t’ai déjà dit que je ne pensais pas l’être mais je le serais devenu si mes dépenses avaient dû continuer<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Puisque j’étais dans une atroce inquiétude de te faire faire un effort au-dessus de tes forces<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je sentais d’un côté que je ne pouvais faire mieux que de pousser à bout la chose commencée<c type="kk">/</c> d’engager Gauguin à nous joindre<c type="kk">/</c> et d’autre part<c type="kk">/</c> comme tu peux le savoir par experience<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’on se meuble ou s’installe c’est que c’est plus difficile qu’on ne pense. Maintenant j’ose enfin respirer puisque nous avons eu une rude chance tous par la vente que tu as pu faire pour Gauguin. De façon ou d’autre<c type="kk">/</c> toujours tous les trois<c type="kk">/</c> lui<c type="kk">/</c> toi et moi pouvons un peu nous recueillir pour nous rendre compte avec calme de ce que nous venons de faire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">N’aies pas de crainte de ce que j’aurais des préoccupations d’argent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Gauguin venu le but est <hi rend="italics">provisoirement</hi> <hi rend="italics">atteint</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Lui et moi en combinant nos dépenses à deux ne dépenserons même pas ce que me coutait la vie ici à moi tout seul.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Lui pourra mettre même de côté de l’argent à fur et à mesure qu’il vend. Qui lui servira mettons dans un an pour s’installer à la Martinique et que sans cela il ne pourrait mettre de côté<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Toi tu auras mon travail et un tableau de lui en plus chaque mois<c type="kp">_</c>– Et moi je ferai le même travail sans avoir tant de mal et sans faire tant de frais. Mais dans le temps il me semblait que la combinaison que nous venons de faire était de bonne politique. La maison marche fort fort bien et devient non seulement comfortable mais aussi une maison d’artiste. Ne crains donc rien pour moi ni pour toi non plus.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">J’ai en effet eu une horrible inquietude pour toi car si Gauguin n’avait pas eu les mêmes idées j’aurais occasionné d’assez fortes dépenses pour rien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Mais Gauguin est étonnant comme homme<c type="kk">/</c> il ne s’emballe pas et il attendra ici<c type="kk">/</c> fort tranquillement et tout en travaillant dur<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>le bon moment de faire un immense pas en avant.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Le repos il en avait autant besoin que moi<c type="kp">_</c> Avec son argent qu’il vient de gagner<c type="kk">/</c> certes il aurait pu se payer le repos en Bretagne egalement <hi rend="italics">mais comme cela</hi> <hi rend="italics">est actuellement il est sûr de</hi> <hi rend="italics">pouvoir attendre sans retomber dans la dette fatale</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Nous ne dépenserons <hi rend="italics">à deux</hi> pas plus de 250 par mois<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Et dépenserons <hi rend="italics">beaucoup moins</hi> en couleur puisque nous allons en faire nous mêmes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">N’ayes donc toi de ton côté aucune inquiétude sur nous et prends haleine aussi<c type="kk">/</c> dont tu auras rudement besoin<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">De mon côté je voudrais seulement te demander également que je ne demande qu’à continuer à un prix par mois tout ordinaire de 150 (et le même pour Gauguin)<c type="kp">_</c> Ce qui dans tous les cas reduit ma dépense personelle. Tandis que ses tableaux certes monteront.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Alors après si tu gardes mes tableaux pour toi soit à Paris soit ici<c type="kk">/</c> je serai beaucoup plus content de pouvoir carrément dire que tu préfères garder mon travail pour nous que de le vendre<c type="kk">/</c> que d’avoir à me mêler de la lutte d’argent dans ce moment. Certes.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">D’ailleurs si ce que je fais soit bon alors nous n’y perdrons rien en tant que quant à l’argent car comme du vin qu’on aurait en cave cela cuverait tranquillement<c type="kp">_</c> D’un autre côté ce n’est que comme de juste que je me donne un peu de mal pour faire une peinture telle que <hi>même</hi> au point de vue de l’argent il soit préférable qu’elle soit sur ma toile que dans les tubes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Maintenant j’ose espérer en terminant que dans 6 mois et Gauguin et toi et moi nous verrons que nous avons fondé un petit atelier qui durera et qui restera un poste ou une station nécessaire<c type="kk">/</c> au moins utile pour tous ceux qui voudront voir le midi<c type="kp">_</c> Je te serre la main bien fortement<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Ce que pense Gauguin de ma décoration en général je ne le sais pas encore<c type="kk">/</c> je sais seulement qu’il y a déjà quelques études qu’il aime reellement<c type="kk">/</c> ainsi le semeur<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> les tournesols<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> la chambre à coucher<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Et l’ensemble je n’en sais encore rien moi-même parceque il me faut encore des toiles des autres saisons<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Gauguin a déjà presque trouvé son Arlesienne<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> et je voudrais vouloir<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> déjà en être là<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">mais de mon côté je trouve très facilement le paysage ici et assez varié<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Donc enfin mon petit travail va son train.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">J’ose croire que tu aimeras le nouveau semeur<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">j’ecris en hâte<c type="kk">/</c> nous avons des tas de travail. Nous avons lui et moi l’intention d’aller tres souvent faire flannelle dans les bordels pour les étudier.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">As for <hi rend="italics">ill</hi>, I already told you I didn’t think I was, but I would have become so if my expenses had had to continue.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Since I was in a state of terrible anxiety about making you make an effort beyond your strength.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">On the one hand, I felt that I couldn’t do better than push to complete what we started, to urge <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> to join us, and on the other hand, as you may know from experience, when you furnish a house or move in, it’s the case that it’s more difficult than you think. Now I dare breathe at last, as we’ve all had a stroke of darned good fortune with the sale you were able to make for Gauguin. One way or another, all three of us, he, you and I, will still be able to pull ourselves together a bit, in order to calmly take in what we’ve just done.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Have no fear that I may have money worries.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Now that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> has come, the goal has been <hi rend="italics">achieved for the time being</hi>. By combining our expenses, he and I, the two of us won’t even spend what living here was costing me just on my own. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">He’ll even be able to put some money aside, the more he sells. Which, in a year, let’s say, he can use to settle in Martinique, and which he couldn’t put aside otherwise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">You’ll have my work, and a painting by him in addition, every month. And I’ll do the same work without having so much trouble, and without running up so many expenses. But in the past it seemed to me that the partnership that we’ve just entered into was a good policy. The house is going very, very well and is becoming not only comfortable but also an artists’ house. So have no fears for me, nor for yourself, either.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I had, in fact, a terrible feeling of anxiety for you, because if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> hadn’t had the same ideas, I would have caused you some rather heavy expenses for nothing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is astonishing as a man; he doesn’t get worked up, and he’ll wait here, very calmly, while at the same time working hard, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> for the right moment to take a huge step forward.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">He needed rest as much as I did. With the money that he’s just earned, he would have been able to pay for rest in Brittany, too, of course, <hi rend="italics">but as things are now, he’s sure to be able to wait without falling into the inevitable debt again.</hi> We won’t spend more than 250 a month <hi rend="italics">between the two of us</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And will spend <hi rend="italics">much less</hi> on paint, since we’re going to make it ourselves.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">So have no worries about us on your part, and catch your breath, too, which you’ll darned well need.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">For my part, I’d wish just to ask you too that I’m asking for no more than to continue at a very ordinary sum per month of 150 (and the same for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>). Which in any case reduces my personal spending. While his paintings will certainly go up. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Later, then, if you keep my paintings for yourself, either in Paris or here, I’ll be much happier to be able to say bluntly that you prefer to keep my work for us than to sell it, than to have to get involved in the struggle for money at this moment. Most certainly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Besides, if what I do is good, then we’ll lose nothing by it, in terms of money, because, like wine that you would have in the cellar, it would quietly ferment. On the other hand, it’s only fair that I give myself a little trouble to make a painting such that <hi>even</hi> from the point of view of the money, it was preferable that it should be on my canvas rather than in the tubes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now in closing I dare hope that in 6 months’ time <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, you and I, we’ll see that we’ve founded a little studio that will last and that will continue to be an essential stopping-off point or station, useful at least to all those who’ll wish to see the south. I shake your hand very firmly.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I don’t yet know what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> thinks about my decoration in general; I only know that there are some studies that he really does like, namely, the Sower,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> the Sunflowers,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> the Bedroom.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">And the whole thing, I don’t know anything about it myself yet, because I need more canvases of the other seasons.</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> has already just about found his Arlésienne,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and I could wish that I too had got as far. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">But for my part, I find the landscape here very easily, and quite varied.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">So at last my little work potters along.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">I dare believe that you’ll like the new Sower.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I’m writing in haste, we have heaps of work. He and I plan to go to the brothels a lot, but only to study them.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent is replying to Theo’s letter of 27 October <ref target="let713.xml">(713)</ref>, and the opening words – about Theo’s concern for Vincent’s health – appear to indicate that he did so soon after he received it. We have consequently dated the present letter on or about Monday, 29 October 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s sale of Gauguin’s <hi rend="italics">Breton women chatting </hi><ref target="let711.xml">(711)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decoration of the Yellow House <ref target="let665.xml">(665)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent had written this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let712.xml">letter 712</ref>, in response to which Theo expressed his concern about Vincent’s health in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let713.xml">letter 713</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2739">F 494 / JH 1617</rs>). This is the ‘new Sower’ that Vincent refers to later in the letter. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh must be referring here to the two no. 30 canvases of sunflowers that he had earmarked for his decoration: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>). Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let703.xml">letter 703</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>On 27 October <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had told Theo that he wanted to use the first few days ‘to acquaint myself with the character of the country’ (pour m’initier au caractère du pays). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Correspondance Gauguin </hi>1984, p. 266. Van Gogh must mean that Gauguin had succeeded in capturing his idea of the Arlésienne in a sketch – possibly the drawing of an Arlésienne in his sketchbook (Jerusalem, The Israel Museum), published as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le carnet de Paul Gauguin</hi> (1952). Gauguin’s drawing and painting of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Madame Ginoux</rs> were done a week later, so they cannot be what is meant here. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘pouvoir’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    