<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, on or about Saturday, 3 November 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let717"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b606 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>717</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>559</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>722</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-12-03">on or about Saturday, 3 November 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0606" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0606" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000826_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Gauguin et moi te remercions beaucoup de ton envoi de 100 fr. et également de ta lettre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Gauguin est très heureux de ce que tu aimes son envoi de Bretagne<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> et que d’autres qui l’ont vu l’ont aimé aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Il a dans ce moment en train des femmes dans une vigne<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> absolument de tête mais s’il ne le gâte pas ni ne le laisse là inachevé cela sera très beau et très étrange. Egalement un tableau du même café de nuit que j’ai peint aussi.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Moi j’ai fait deux toiles d’une chûte des feuilles que Gauguin aimait je crois<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> et travaille actuellement à une vigne toute pourpre et jaune<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Ensuite j’ai enfin une Arlésienne<c type="kk">/</c> une figure (toile de 30) sabrée dans <hi rend="italics">une</hi> heure<c type="kk">/</c> fond citron pâle – le visage gris – l’habillement noir noir noir<c type="kk">/</c> du bleu de prusse tout cru<c type="kp">_</c> Elle s’appuye sur une table verte et est assise dans un fauteuil de bois – orangé.–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Gauguin a acheté pour la maison une commode<c type="kk">/</c> divers ustensiles de ménage puis 20 mètres de toile très forte<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> un tas de choses dont nous avions besoin<c type="kk">/</c> qu’en tous les cas il était plus commode d’avoir<c type="kp">_</c> Seulement nous avons pris note de tout ce qu’il a payé<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui revient à à peu près 100 francs que soit à nouvel an soit par exemple au mois de mars nous lui rendrions et alors la commode &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> naturellement serait à nous.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Je trouve cela juste en somme puisque lui a l’intention de mettre de l’argent de côté quand il vendra<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Jusqu’au moment (mettons dans un an) qu’il aura assez pour risquer un second voyage à la Martinique.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Nous travaillons beaucoup et la vie à deux marche très bien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Je suis bien heureux de savoir que tu n’es pas seul dans l’apartement.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Les dessins de de Haan sont <hi rend="italics">bien beaux</hi><c type="kk">/</c> je les aime beaucoup.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Maintenant faire cela avec de la couleur<c type="kk">/</c> arriver à autant d’expression sans la ressource du clair obscur blanc et noir<c type="kk">/</c> bigre cela n’est pas commode. Et même il arrivera <hi rend="italics">à un autre dessin</hi> s’il exécute son plan de traverser l’impressionisme <hi rend="italics">comme une école</hi><c type="kk">/</c> considérant ses nouveaux essais de couleur comme absolument des études. Mais selon moi il a plusieurs fois raison de faire tout cela.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Seulement il y a plusieurs soi disant impressionistes qui n’ont pas sa science de la figure et c’est justement celle-là<c type="kk">/</c> cette science de la figure qui plus tard remontera sur l’eau et de laquelle il se trouvera toujours bien. Je suis tres desireux de les connaitre un jour<c type="kk">/</c> de Haan et Isaacson. Si jamais ils venaient ici Gauguin leur dirait certes: allez à Java faire de l’impressionisme<c type="kp">_</c> Car Gauguin tout en travaillant dur ici a toujours la nostalgie des 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>pays chauds. Et voilà c’est incontestable que lorsque l’on viendrait à Java par exemple avec la preoccupation d’y faire de la couleur<c type="kk">/</c> on verrait un tas un tas de chôses nouvelles<c type="kp">_</c> Ensuite dans ces pays plus lumineux sous le soleil plus fort<c type="kk">/</c> l’ombre propre ainsi que l’ombre portée des objets et des figures devient toute autre et est tellement colorée qu’on est tenté à la supprimer tout simplement. Cela arrive déjà ici.– Enfin je n’insiste pas sur l’importance de la question de la peinture tropicale<c type="kk">/</c> de Haan et Isaacson<c type="kk">/</c> j’en suis sûr d’avance<c type="kk">/</c> en sentiront l’importance.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">En aucun cas<c type="kk">/</c> venir ici à une epoque ou une autre ne leur fera aucun tort<c type="kk">/</c> ils trouveront certes des chôses intéressantes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Gauguin et moi vont diner aujourd’hui chez nous. et nous sentons surs et certains que cela nous réussira autant de fois que cela nous paraitra préférable ou meilleur marché.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Pour ne pas retarder cette lettre je la terminerai pour aujourd’hui<c type="kp">_</c> Bientot j’espère encore t’ecrire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ton arrangement pour l’argent est tout à fait bien.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Je crois que tu aimerais la chute des feuilles que j’ai faite.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">C’est des troncs de peupliers lilas coupés par le cadre là où commencent les feuilles.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Ces troncs d’arbres comme des piliers bordent une allée où sont à droite &amp; à gauche alignés de vieux tombeaux romains d’un lilas bleu<c type="kp">_</c>– Or le sol est couvert comme d’un tapis par une couche epaisse de feuilles 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>orangées et jaunes – tombées<c type="kp">_</c> Comme des flocons de neige il en tombe toujours encore.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Et dans l’allée des figurines d’amoureux noirs<c type="kp">_</c> Le haut du tableau est une prairie très verte et pas de ciel ou presque pas.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">La deuxieme toile est la meme allée mais avec un vieux bonhomme et une femme grosse et ronde comme une boule.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Mais Dimanche si tu avais été avec nous!– nous avons vu une vigne rouge<c type="kk">/</c> toute rouge comme du vin rouge<c type="kp">_</c> Dans le lointain elle devenait jaune et puis un ciel vert avec un soleil<c type="kk">/</c> des terrains après la pluie violets et scintillant jaune par ci par là où se refletait le soleil couchant.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Nous te serrons bien la main en pensée et à bientot<c type="kk">/</c> le plus tôt que je pourrai je t’ecris de nouveau et aussi à nos Hollandais.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and I thank you very much for sending 100 francs, and also for your letter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is very happy that you like his consignment from Brittany,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and that others who’ve seen it have liked it too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">At the moment he’s working on some women in a vineyard,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> entirely from memory, but if he doesn’t spoil it or leave it there unfinished it will be very fine and very strange. Also a painting of the same night café that I too have painted.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’ve done two canvases of a leaf-fall, which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> liked I think,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and am now working on a vineyard, all purple and yellow.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Then I have an <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs> at last, a figure (no. 30 canvas) knocked off in <hi rend="italics">one</hi> hour, background pale lemon — the face grey — the clothing dark dark dark, just unmixed Prussian blue. She’s leaning on a green table and is sitting in a wooden armchair — coloured orange.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> has bought a chest of drawers for the house, various household utensils and 20 metres of very strong canvas,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> a whole lot of things we needed, which it was more convenient to have anyway. Only we’ve made a note of all that he paid, which comes to nearly 100 francs, which we’d pay him back at New Year, or in the month of March for example, and then the chest of drawers &amp;c. would belong to us of course.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I consider this quite right in fact, since he intends to put some money aside when he sells.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Up to the moment (let’s say in a year) when he’ll have enough to risk a second trip to Martinique.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">We’re working a great deal, and our life together is going very well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m very happy to know that you’re not alone in the apartment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>’s drawings are <hi rend="italics">very fine</hi>, I like them a lot.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Now doing that with colour, arriving at the same degree of expression without resorting to black and white chiaroscuro, my goodness, that’s not easy. And he’ll even arrive <hi rend="italics">at another type of drawing</hi> if he carries out his plan of passing through Impressionism <hi rend="italics">like a school</hi>, regarding his new attempts at colour absolutely as studies. But as I see it he’s right several times over to do all that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Only there are several people who call themselves Impressionists who don’t have his knowledge of the figure, and it’s precisely that, that knowledge of the figure, that will later come back up to the surface and that he’ll always benefit from. I very much want to get to know them one day, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>. If ever they came here, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> would certainly say to them: go to Java and do some Impressionism. Because Gauguin, while he works hard here, always has a nostalgic longing 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> for hot countries. And there you are, it’s undeniable that if one came to Java, for example, with the preoccupation to work there with colour, one would see a heap, a whole heap, of new things. Then in those brighter countries under the stronger sun, the shaded parts as well as the shadow cast by objects and figures become completely different, and the coloration is so intense that one’s tempted quite simply to suppress it. That’s already happening here. Anyway, I won’t press the point about the importance of the question of tropical painting, De Haan and Isaäcson, I’m already sure, will sense its importance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">In any case, to come here at some time or another would do them no harm, they’ll certainly find interesting things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and I are going to dine at home today, and we feel sure and certain that we will manage this as often as it seems preferable or cheaper to us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">So as not to delay this letter I’ll finish it for today. I hope to write to you again soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Your arrangement for the money is absolutely fine.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I think that you’d like the leaf-fall that I’ve done.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">It’s lilac poplar trunks cut by the frame where the leaves begin.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">These tree-trunks, like pillars, line an avenue where old Roman tombs coloured lilac-blue are lined up to right and left. Now the ground is covered as if by a carpet with a thick layer of orange and yellow leaves 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> — fallen. Some are still falling, like snowflakes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">And in the avenue dark figurines of lovers. The top of the painting is a very green meadow and no sky, or almost none.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">The second canvas is the same avenue but with an old fellow and a fat woman, round as a ball.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">But if only you’d been with us on Sunday! We saw a red vineyard, completely red like red wine. In the distance it became yellow, and then a green sky with a sun, fields violet and sparkling yellow here and there after the rain in which the setting sun was reflected.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">We shake your hand firmly in thought, and more soon, I’ll write to you again as soon as I can, and also to our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075 bio.xml#_1103">Dutchmen</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent thanks Theo for sending 100 francs, which must have been the first part of his allowance for November: by the beginning of November the two artists had most likely used up the last allowance of 50 francs, received on 27 or 28 October. Cf. also <ref target="#n-9">n. 9.</ref></p><p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The letter, moreover, must have been written shortly after the letter to Bernard of 1 or 2 November (<ref target="let716.xml">716</ref>), because Van Gogh mentions the same paintings, but he has meanwhile painted an Arlésienne (in one hour) and is now working on the red vineyard, which he says he saw on Sunday (<ref target="#l-113">l. 113</ref>). This must have been Sunday, 28 October, which precludes a dating after Sunday, 4 November. On these grounds we have dated the letter to about Saturday, 3 November 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s plan to return to the tropics <ref target="let716.xml">(716)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">De Haan’s stay with Theo <ref target="let711.xml">(711)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Regarding the batch of paintings <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> sent to Theo from Pont-Aven, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let704.xml#n-1">see letter 704, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Human miseries</hi>, 1888 (W317/W304) (Copenhagen, Ordrupgaard Sammlungen). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2242">Ill. 2242</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Night café, Arles</hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let716.xml#n-4">see letter 716, n. 4.</ref> Van Gogh’s painting of the Café de la Gare is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The night café </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2741">F 486 / JH 1620</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2742">F 487 / JH 1621</rs>). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had written to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> that the canvases were hanging in his room; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let716.xml">see letter 716</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2744">F 489 / JH 1625</rs>). See exhib. cat. Chicago 2001, p. 186. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Marie Ginoux</rs>, the wife of the cafe’s proprietor, posed for this portrait.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Regarding this coarse jute, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let716.xml#n-8">see letter 716, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Theo had sent two photographs of drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let708.xml">see letter 708</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>It had been agreed that Theo would send 300 francs a month (150 francs for each), in three 100-franc instalments. It is most likely that Theo reverted to the system that he and Vincent had used earlier for three monthly payments (starting in June 1882; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let234.xml">see letter 234</ref>). This meant that Vincent usually received his allowance in instalments arriving around the 1st, 11th and 21st of every month, though sometimes a payment was deferred. Theo thus sent money three times a month in November and December 1888. See also Dorn<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1990, p. 479.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2742">F 487 / JH 1621</rs>). The location described by Van Gogh is the Roman burial ground Les Alyscamps (the Elysian Fields or Champs-Elysées), to the south-east of Arles.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2741">F 486 / JH 1620</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    