<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Paul Eugène Milliet to Vincent van Gogh. Guelma, Tuesday, 11 December 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let725"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b1326 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>725</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>590c</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>729</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul-Eugène Milliet</rs>
                            <date when="1888-12-11">Tuesday, 11 December 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Guelma</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1326 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1326 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001320_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1326 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1326 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001321_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1"><hi rend="italics">11 Décembre.</hi></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Ami,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je suis resté si longtemps sans vous écrire, que je sens le besoin de vous dire mille choses pour me faire pardonner mon silence. Cependant je commence en vous priant d’agréer mes excuses. Depuis mon arrivée ici,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> j’ai fait et je continue à faire un métier de nègre, c’est ainsi que de six heures du matin à 4 h<hi rend="super">res</hi> ½ du soir<c type="kk">/</c> je sors à peine de la caserne le temps de déjeuner<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>tout ce temps se passe debout, au grand soleil, à crier comme un diable, aussi le soir c’est avec un certain plaisir que je vois venir le moment de m’enfiler dans les draps, de là mon peu de temps pour écrire.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je ne vous parle pas de mon voyage qui s’est tres bien fait. Inutile. L’Algérie comme tous les autres pays, n’est interessante que pour le visiteur, de loin, comme ça, sur le papier, ça se rend mal. Est-ce vrai?</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’ai pensé à Bernard.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Je m’en suis occupé dans la mesure du possible. Le chef de Bataillon qui me commande, est tres bien disposé en sa faveur après ce que je lui en ai dit. Que votre ami vienne au 3<hi rend="super">e</hi> Zouaves, il viendra surement près de moi en suite, et là nous tâcherons de lui rendre la vie aussi douce que le métier le permettra. C’est grand dommage qu’il n’y soit pas maintenant, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>parceque étant chargé des recrues, comme je le suis<c type="kk">/</c> la tâche serait rudement simplifiée encore.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Guelma est une ville absolument indifférente: le moindre village de France serait aussi agréable. Ce qui est vraiment beau, c’est la nature, le soleil, la lumière, les types d’Arabes, ces gens à vêtements flottants sont superbes. Mais ce qui <hi rend="italics">m’etonne</hi> c’est qu’à l’inverse de ce que l’on voit en Europe, les tableaux semblent se composer dans l’ombre avec un centre obscur 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>et des coins en lumière. on dirait, si j’ose m’exprimer ainsi, du Rembrand renversé? Du moins voila comment je sens les choses.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">De ma fenêtre j’ai une vue superbe: mon horizon est formé d’une ligne de petites montagnes courant parallèlement de l’Est à l’Ouest et perdues dans le bleu. D’un autre côté, j’ai une étendue parfaitement plate, d’une couleur assez douteuse, les plans les plus rapprochés de l’oeil sont jaunâtres; les parties 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>fuyantes se fondent dans des gris violets (cette couleur existe-t-elle au moins, en tous cas elle me semble telle)<c type="kk">/</c> une dernière ligne cendrée, mais si mince qu’il faudrait un seul petit trait, détermine la profondeur réelle du paysage qui est vraiment tres grande. Tout ça, c’est épatant. Je voudrais savoir dessiner pour le rendre, mais je ne sais pas. hélas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Comment allez vous 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>mon cher Ami, et Goguin<c type="kk">/</c> comment trouve-t-il l’existence de là-bas. S’y fait-il?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ecrivez moi, si vous avez le temps, vous me ferez un tres grand plaisir.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Bien entendu, je n’ai pas le moindre bouquin à me mettre sous l’oeil, pas même des Balzac à 1<hi rend="super">f</hi><hi rend="super"> </hi>2 s.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Quel trou! quel trou! Impossible d’en avoir avec ça. – Avez vous déniché Bel Ami?<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Rappelez moi<c type="kk">/</c> je vous prie<c type="kk">/</c> à l’excellent souvenir de Monsieur votre frère.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Poignée de main vigoureuse à Goguin, et croyez moi mon cher ami, votre tout dévoué, et fidèle</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">P. Milliet</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">S<hi rend="super">s</hi>Lieut<hi rend="super">t</hi> 3° Zouaves</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14"><hi rend="italics">Guelma.</hi></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">P<hi rend="super">ce</hi> de Constantine.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1"><hi rend="italics">11 December.</hi></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear friend,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I haven’t written to you for such a long time that I feel the need to tell you a thousand things to gain forgiveness for my silence. However I’ll begin by asking you to accept my apologies. Since my arrival here<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I’ve toiled and continue to toil like a negro, hence from six o’clock in the morning to four thirty in the afternoon, I scarcely leave the barracks for long enough to eat 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>, I spend the whole time standing in the blazing sun, shouting like a devil, so in the evening it’s with a certain pleasure that I see the moment coming when I can slide between the sheets, hence my shortage of time to write.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I shan’t tell you about my journey, which went very well. Pointless. Like all other countries, Algeria is only interesting for the visitor, from far away, like this, on paper, it comes across badly. Is that true? 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I’ve been thinking about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve been working on his behalf as much as possible. The officer who commands my battalion is very well disposed towards him after what I said about him. Tell your friend to come to the 3rd Zouaves, he’ll then surely be near me, and when he does we’ll try to make his life as gentle as the job permits. It’s a great pity that he isn’t here now, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> because being in charge of the recruits as I am, the task would be a hell of a lot more simplified still.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Guelma is an absolutely indifferent town: any small village in France would be as pleasant. What really is beautiful is nature, the sun, the light, the types of Arabs, these people with billowing robes are superb. But what <hi rend="italics">astonishes</hi> me is that, contrary to what you see in Europe, the paintings seem to be composed in the shade with a dark centre 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> and corners in the light. It’s just like, if I dare say so, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> in reverse. At least that’s how I feel about things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">From my window I have a superb view: my horizon is formed by a line of small mountains running parallel from east to west and lost in the blue. From another side, I have a perfectly flat stretch of ground, of a rather indefinable colour, the areas nearest to the eye are yellowish; 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> the parts that fade into the distance melt into violet greys (does this colour actually exist? In any case that’s what it seems to me), one last ash-grey line, but so thin it would take only a single slender stroke, determines the true depth of the countryside, which is truly very extensive. All of this is marvellous. I wish I could draw so as to depict it, but I can’t, alas.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">How are you 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> my dear friend, and how is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> finding life down there? Is he getting used to it?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Write to me, if you have the time, you’ll give me very great pleasure.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Of course, I haven’t a single book to cast my eyes over, not even <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>s at 1 franc 2 sous each.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> What a hole, what a hole! On top of that, impossible to get any. Have you unearthed Bel-ami?<ptr target="#note-t-4"/>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Recall me, if you would, to your esteemed brother’s excellent memory.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Hearty handshake for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, and believe me, my dear friend, your entirely devoted and faithful</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">P. Milliet</rs></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">2nd Lieut. 3rd Zouaves</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><hi rend="italics">Guelma</hi></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Place de Constantine.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘<hi rend="italics">11 Décembre</hi>’. In this letter Milliet recorded his first impressions of Guelma, for which he had departed on 1 November 1888. This places the letter in that same year.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Bernard’s military service <ref target="let575.xml">(575)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The Zouave lieutenant <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> had left Arles on 1 November 1888 for Guelma, a city in the north-east of Algeria.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had asked <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> if he would take charge of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, if the latter were to serve with the Zouaves in Africa during his spell of military service. In exchange for drawing lessons, Milliet would then ensure that Bernard could devote himself to painting. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml">See letter 628</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>1 franc 2 sous (1 franc 10 centimes). Compare the editions in the series ‘Oeuvres complètes’ of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Honoré de Balzac</rs>, which cost ‘1 franc 25 centimes per volume’ in 1884 at Calmann Lévy’s in Paris (this price appears on the cover of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le médecin de campagne</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Maupassant</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_446">Bel-ami</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let568.xml#n-11">see letter 568, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In August 1888 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> had brought Theo a batch of Vincent’s paintings (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let652.xml">see letter 652</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    