<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Saturday, 19 January 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let738"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b619 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>738</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>572</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>742</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-01-19">Saturday, 19 January 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0619 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0619 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000843_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0619 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000844_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000844_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0619 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000844_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000844_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">je dois encore t’écrire un mot aujourd’hui. Hier ils ont encore présenté la facture du gaz de dix francs (ou 9.90) que j’ai payée aussi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Cela encore ajouté au compte que je te faisais dans ma lettre précédente reduit à bien bien peu de chôse ce qui me reste du billet de 50 francs pour me nourrir<c type="kp">_</c> Si tu peux envoie moi encore quelque chôse<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai tout expliqué là-dessus j’espère clairement assez.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je suis encore très faible et j’aurai du mal à reprendre mes forces si le froid continue<c type="kp">_</c> Rey me donnera du vin de quinquina<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> qui fera de l’effet j’ose croire.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’aurais encore bien des chôses à te dire en reponse à ta lettre mais j’ai un tableau sur le chevalet<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> &amp; suis pressé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Tu ne m’avais pas encore dit qu’Andre Bonger s’était marié avant maintenant.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Cela ne doit pas être très gai lorsqu’il se plaint de la cherté du ménage<c type="kp">_</c> Jo Bonger m’a écrit un mot en reponse à ce que je l’avais félicitée<c type="kk">/</c> c’est bien bon de sa part<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Il m’a toujours semblé que tu devais à ta position sociale &amp; à celle que tu a dans la famille de te marier<c type="kk">/</c> ensuite depuis des années c’etait le désir de la mère.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Et en faisant ainsi ce que tu dois faire<c type="kk">/</c> tu auras peutêtre plus de tranquilité<c type="kk">/</c> même dans mille &amp; une difficultés<c type="kk">/</c> qu’auparavant.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Cependant la vie n’est pas commode pas pour moi non plus.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Que n’aurais je pas donné pour pouvoir passer une journee ici avec toi et te montrer le travail en train et la maison &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">maintenant je prefererais que tu n’eusses encore rien vu de ce que j’ai ici que d’en emporter une impression dans des conditions aussi desolantes. Enfin.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Que fait Guillaumin<c type="kp">_</c> tu sais qu’il a un fils maintenant<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Bernard est de plus en plus emmerdé par son père<c type="kk">/</c> cela devient encore davantage un enfer dans cette maison.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Et le pire c’est qu’il n’y a pas grand chôse à y faire<c type="kk">/</c> aussitôt qu’on y foure la main on la foure dans de vrais guêpiers<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Ils vont maintenant essayer<c type="kk">/</c> Gauguin &amp; Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> d’exempter Bernard du service pour cause d’etroitesse (?) de poitrine. Bon – mais mille fois 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>mieux valait-il pour lui qu’il fasse son service carrement en Algerie avec Milliet.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je deviens encore ridicule vis à vis de Milliet parceque celui là ne cesse de me demander des nouvelles là-dessus.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Roulin est sur le point de partir<c type="kp">_</c> Son salaire etait ici de 135 francs par mois<c type="kk">/</c> elever 3 enfants avec ça et en vivre lui et sa femme! ce que cela a été tu le concois. Et ce n’est pas tout<c type="kk">/</c> l’augmentation c’est un remède pire que le mal même..... Quelles administrations.. et dans quel temps vivons nous. Moi j’ai rarement vu un homme de la trempe de Roulin<c type="kk">/</c> il y a en lui enormement de <hi rend="italics">Socrate</hi><c type="kk">/</c> laid comme un satyre ainsi que le disait Michelet... jusqu’à qu’au dernier jour un dieu s’y vit dont s’illumina le Parthenon &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Si Chatrian que tu as rencontré<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> avait vu cet homme-là....</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">Ecris moi de suite de suite</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Je t’en prie car ce que tu as envoyé n’etait reellement pas tout à fait suffisant comme j’ai cherché à l’expliquer en clarté absolue.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">j’oublie encore de dire que hier j’ai eu une lettre de Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> toujours pour les masques et gants d’armes.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> plein de projets variants et variés. et déjà à l’horizon il voit la fin de son argent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Naturellement....</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Il redoute déjà de ne pas pouvoir aller à Bruxelles pour cette raison<c type="kp">_</c> Et puis après s’il ne peut meme pas aller à Bruxelles<c type="kk">/</c> comment ira-t-il en Danemark<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> et aux tropiques.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">La meilleure chose qu’il pourrait encore faire et celle que justement il ne fera pas. Ce serait de retourner tout simplement ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Enfin nous n’en sommes pas en<c type="shy">-</c>core là car il ne me dit pas encore qu’il entrevoit la dèche à l’horizon<c type="kk">/</c> seulement c’est plus que lisible entre les lignes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Il est provisoirement encore chez les Schuffenecker et va faire les portraits de toute la famille.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> il a donc encore du temps pour réfléchir<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Je ne lui ai pas encore répondu<c type="kp">_</c> Ce qui est certain heureusement c’est que j’ose croire que au fond Gauguin et moi comme natures nous nous aimons suffisamment pour pouvoir en cas de necessité recommencer encore ensemble.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Cela me fait bien plaisir que tu n’aies pas oublié la leçon d’anatomie pour M. Rey.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> J’aurai toujours moi<c type="kk">/</c> dans la suite<c type="kk">/</c> besoin d’un médecin de temps en temps et justement parceque lui me connait bien maintenant ce serait une raison de plus pour moi de rester tranquillement ici.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">je t’écrirai de nouveau bientôt mais pour l’argent du mois fais tes conclusions toi-même<c type="kk">/</c> je ne dépenserai net pas plus qu’un autre mois<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I must write you another line today. Yesterday they also presented the gas bill for ten francs (or 9.90), which I also paid.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">That, added to the accounts I did for you in my previous letter, reduces to very, very little what I have left of the 50-franc note to feed myself. If you can, send me a bit more, I’ve explained everything about it clearly enough, I hope.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’m still very weak, and I’ll have difficulty in regaining my strength if the cold continues. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Rey</rs> will give me some quinine wine,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which I dare believe will have some effect.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I would have a lot more things to say to you in response to your letter, but I have a painting on the easel<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and am in a hurry.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">You hadn’t told me yet, before now, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">André Bonger</rs> was married.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> It can’t be very jolly when he complains about the high cost of running a home. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo Bonger</rs> wrote me a line in response to the fact that I had congratulated her, that’s very kind of her.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> It has always seemed to me that you owed it to your social position and to the one you have in the family to marry, and it has been <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>’s wish for years.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">And by doing thus what you must do, you’ll perhaps have more tranquillity than before, even amidst a thousand-and-one difficulties.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">However, life isn’t easy for me either. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">What wouldn’t I have given to be able to spend a day here with you and to show you the work in progress and the house, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now I would prefer that you hadn’t yet seen anything of what I have here than to leave with an impression of it in such distressing conditions. Ah well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> doing? You know he has a son now.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> is being pestered more and more by his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_16">father</rs>, it’s becoming even more of a hell in that house.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And the worst is that there isn’t much one can do about it, as soon as you put your hand in there you put it into a real wasps’ nest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">They’re now going to try, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, to exempt Bernard from military service because of narrowness (?) of the chest. Good — but it would be a thousand times 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> better for him if he did his service straightforwardly in Algeria with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m becoming ridiculous as regards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs>, because the latter constantly asks me for news about it.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> is on the point of leaving. His salary here was 135 francs a month, to raise 3 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_649 bio.xml#_650 bio.xml#_651">children</rs> with that and live on it, himself and his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">wife</rs>! You can imagine what that was like. And that isn’t all, the pay rise is a remedy worse than the ill itself... What a civil service. And in what times we live. I’ve rarely seen a man of Roulin’s stamp, there’s an enormous amount of <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs></hi> in him, ugly as a satyr as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs> said... until on the last day a god was to be seen there, by whom the Parthenon was illuminated, &amp;c. &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_591">Chatrian</rs>, whom you met,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> had seen that man...</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"><hi rend="italics">Write to me at once at once.</hi> Please, because what you sent was really not entirely sufficient, as I’ve tried to explain to you with absolute clarity.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I forget to say that yesterday I had a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, still about the fencing masks and gloves.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Full of varying and varied plans. And already he sees the end of his money on the horizon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Naturally...</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">He already fears not being able to go to Brussels for that reason. And after that, if he can’t even go to Brussels, how will he go to Denmark<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and to the tropics?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">The best thing he could still do and the very one which he won’t do. That would be quite simply to return here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Anyway, we haven’t got to that yet, for he doesn’t yet tell me that he glimpses penury on the horizon, only it’s more than readable between the lines.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">He’s still at the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1357">Schuffenecker</rs>s’ temporarily, and is going to do portraits of the entire family.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> So he still has time to think things over.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I haven’t replied to him yet. What is fortunately certain is that I dare believe that at heart <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and I like each other enough as characters to be able to start over again together if necessary.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">It gives me great pleasure that you haven’t forgotten The anatomy lesson for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Mr Rey</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Later I myself will always have need of a doctor from time to time, and precisely because he knows me well now would be one more reason for me to remain quietly here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I’ll write to you again soon, but as for the monthly money, draw your own conclusions; I won’t spend more net than any other month.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Because Jo van Gogh-Bonger dated the letter to Saturday, 19 January 1889 in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914 – it is possible she had a postmark to rely on – we have retained this dating. In any case it must have been written after <ref target="let736.xml">letter 736</ref> of Thursday, 17 January, in which Vincent had given a summary of his expenses, as appears from the remark about the gas bill <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-5)</ref>, a subject not yet mentioned on the 17th. Here he says he received it ‘yesterday’. The phrase ‘I must write you another line today’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>) implies, moreover, that only a little time elapsed between the two letters.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s journey to Arles <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The refusal of Bernard’s father to support his son <ref target="let687.xml">(687)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Bernard’s military service <ref target="let575.xml">(575)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="ogt_6">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Roulin’s departure for Marseille <ref target="let736.xml">(736)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="ogt_7">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s plan to return to the tropics <ref target="let716.xml">(716)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Quinine wine (vin de quinquina) is a medicinal wine prepared from the bark of the cinchona tree. The drink has an invigorating and antipyretic (fever-reducing) effect.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This painting was possibly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Van Gogh’s chair </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2749">F 498 / JH 1635</rs>), which he  mentioned working on in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let736.xml">letter 736</ref>, or <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Blue gloves and a basket of oranges and lemons</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2768">F 502 / JH 1664</rs>), which he had just finished when he wrote <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let741.xml">letter 741</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Anne (Annie) Marie Louise van der Linden</rs> had been officially engaged since May 1886; their marriage took place on 3 May 1888 in Amsterdam. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 21.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> had written to Vincent on 15 January. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 90.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is mistaken about the sex: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>’s child, born on 14 October 1888, was a daughter, called Madeleine.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had asked <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_515">Milliet</rs> if he would take charge of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> in Africa, if the latter went to serve with the Zouaves. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml">See letter 628</ref>. Apparently no answer from Bernard was forthcoming.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh compared <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_754">Socrates</rs> a number of times; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let652.xml#n-7">see letter 652, n. 7.</ref> The passage on Socrates and the Parthenon is an allusion to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_707">Michelet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_11">L’amour</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let368.xml#n-4">see letter 368, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_591">Alexandre Chatrian</rs>, of the writers’ duo <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_594 bio.xml#_591">Erckmann-Chatrian</rs>. Theo had told Vincent about his meeting with the author (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let723.xml">see letter 723</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let737.xml">letter 737</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>According to Van Gogh, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> was thinking of settling in Brussels and travelling from there to Denmark to see his family. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let723.xml">See letter 723</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            
    
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_103">The Schuffenecker family</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let737.xml#n-8">see letter 737, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Vincent had asked Theo to buy the engraving after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Anatomy lesson</hi> for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Dr Rey</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let732.xml#n-14">see letter 732, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    