<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Arnold Koning. Arles, on or about Tuesday, 22 January 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let740"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement/>
                                        <institution/>
                                        
                                        <idno/>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>740</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>571a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>745</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-01-22">on or about Tuesday, 22 January 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Arnold Koning</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1r/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1r/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1r/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1v/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1v/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/740_1v/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Amice Koning,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">merci dat ge me heel uit ’t noorden van ons oude vaderland hebt nieuwejaargewenscht.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Uw briefkaart ontving ik in ’t gasthuis van Arles alwaar ik te dier tijde ingekwartierd was van wege een reeds ten naaste bij voorbij geganen aanval van hersen- of anderszins koorts<c type="kp">_</c> En omtrent de oorzaken en uitwerkingen van ’t onderhavige ziektegeval zullen we best doen ’t aan eventueele discussiën der hollandsche catechiseermeesters over te laten of ik al dan niet – gek, ingebeeld gek, ofwel in eene slechts uit beeldhouwwerk bestaande inbeelding als gek beschouwd ben geweest of nog ben</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">en indien niet<c type="kk">/</c> of ik ’t vóór dien tijd reeds was;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> al dan niet ten huidigen dage ben<c type="kk">/</c> of hiernamaals nog worden zal.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">U aldus meer dan voldoende ingelicht hebbende betreffende mijn gemoeds- en ligchaamstoestand... zal ’t u minder wonderbaarlijk voorkomen ik U niet vroeger heb geantwoord. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Maar intusschen moeten we niet vergeten voet bij stek te houden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En van daar uitgaande vraag ik u: wat voert ge tegenwoordig uit in de schilderkunst en hoe werkt ge met de kleuren.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Van Uw studies aan Theo gezonden (<hi rend="italics">geloof ik</hi>) heb ik absoluut niets gezien ondanks mijn aanmaning aan u om een ruil.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ligt dit aan Theo die andere dingen mogelijk aan t’hoofd had of aan den niet onaanmerkelijken afstand tusschen ons.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Weet ge reeds dat Theo geengageerd is en in betrekkelijk korten tijd trouwen zal met een amsterdamsch meisje?–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Na deze vraag betreffende uw werk enkele woorden betreffende ’t mijnen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb op ’t oogenblik op touw of liever op ’t ezel een vrouweportret.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Dat ik heb genoemd “la berceuse” of zoo als we in t’hollandsch ’t met van Ede (ge weet wel<c type="kk">/</c> die dat bewuste boek schreef dat ik u liet lezen) – of 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>in ’t hollandsch van v. Eden zouden noemen eenvoudig “ons wiegelied” of de wiegster<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">’t is eene vrouw in groen gekleed (buste olijfgroen en de rok bleek veroneesgroen). Het haar is geheel oranje en in vlechten. De gelaatskleur tot chromaatgeel opgevoerd met natuurlijk eenige gebroken toonen om te modeleeren. De handen die ’t wiegetouw houden dito dito<c type="kp">_</c> Het fond is beneden vermilloen (voorstellende eenvoudig een plavuizen vloer of steenen vloer)<c type="kp">_</c> De muur is bedekt met een behangselpapier<c type="kk">/</c> natuurlijk berekend door mij in verband met de rest der kleuren. Dit behangselpapier is blaauwgroen met rose dahlias en met oranje gestippeld en met ultramarijn. Ik meen in dezen vrij evenwijdig geloopen te hebben met v. Eden<c type="kk">/</c> en zijn schrijfwijs gevolgelijk niet als onevenwijdig beschouwd met mijn schilderwijs in zake kleur.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Heb ik met kleur reeds een wiegeliedje gezongen<c type="kk">/</c> laat ik aan de critici over<c type="kk">/</c> vooral aan die voornoemd.– Doch we hebben er in der tijd genoeg over gepraat niet waar.–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Over die eeuwige kwestie der kleuren die<c type="kk">/</c> in zooverre onze bedaardheid gaan kan<c type="kk">/</c> ons leidt.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">In alle geval heb ik uit het gasthuis uitgaande mijn eigen dokter gepor<c type="shy">-</c>traitteerd.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> En mijn evenwigt als schilder nog niet ten eenemale verloren.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Maar ik heb natuurlijk nog heel wat andere studies of schilderijen geschilderd in al dien tijd. Onder anderen dezen zomer twee bloemstukken met niets dan <hi rend="italics">Zonnebloemen</hi> in een geel aarden pot.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Geschilderd met de drie chromaatgeelen<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> geel oker en veroneesgroen en anders niets<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik ben voorloopig nog steeds te Arles en tot verdere correspondentie per brief of geschilderde studie tot uw dispositie. Theo heeft Breitner bezocht onlangs<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> en me gezegd van zijn werk dat hij Breitner nog de beste schilder &amp; denker van aldaar bij u vond<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Gegroet amice<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Uw vriend</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Steeds adres</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">2 place Lamartine</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Arles.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">als ge Breittner ontmoet moogt ge hem dit epistel laten lezen of ’t hem mededeelen zooals ik ’t schrijf<c type="kk">/</c> zonder al teveel uw eigen verbeeldingskracht daarbij in ’t spel te brengen.–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thank you for sending me New Year’s greetings from the far north of our old native country.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I received your postcard in the hospital in Arles, where I was quartered at the time because of an attack of brain or some other fever that had already pretty much passed off. And as regards the causes and effects of the illness in question, we’ll do best to leave it to possible discussions by the Dutch catechists as to whether or not I have been or still am — mad, fancy myself mad, or regarded as mad in a flight of fancy consisting only of sculpture.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And if not, whether I already was before that time;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> am or am not at present, or will be hereafter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Having thus informed you more than enough about my mental and physical state... it will appear less odd to you that I didn’t reply to you sooner. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> But meanwhile we mustn’t forget to stick to our guns.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And starting from there, I ask you: what are you doing in painting at the moment, and how are you working with colour?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ve seen absolutely nothing of your studies sent to Theo (<hi rend="italics">I believe</hi>), despite urging you to make an exchange.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Is this to do with Theo, who possibly had other things on his mind, or with the not inconsiderable distance between us?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Did you know that Theo is engaged and will marry an Amsterdam <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">girl</rs> quite soon?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">After this question about your work, a few words about mine. At present I have a portrait of a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">woman</rs> on the go, or rather on the easel.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Which I’ve called ‘la berceuse’, or as we say in Dutch with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_588">Van Eeden</rs> (you know, who wrote that book I got you to read) — or 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> would simply call in Van Eeden’s Dutch ‘our lullaby’, or the woman by the cradle.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It’s a woman dressed in green (bust olive green and the skirt pale Veronese green). Her hair is entirely orange and in plaits. The complexion worked up in chrome yellow, with a few broken tones, of course, in order to model. The hands that hold the cradle cord ditto ditto. The background is vermilion at the bottom (simply representing a tiled floor or brick floor). The wall is covered with wallpaper, obviously calculated by me in connection with the rest of the colours. This wallpaper is blue-green with pink dahlias and dotted with orange and with ultramarine. I believe I’ve run fairly parallel to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_588">Van Eeden</rs> in this, and consequently don’t regard his style of writing as unparallel to my style of painting in the matter of colour.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Whether I’ve actually sung a lullaby with colour I leave to the critics, particularly to those aforementioned. But we’ve talked enough about this in the past, haven’t we?<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> About the eternal question of colour that guides us, in so far as our composure can go. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">In any event, on leaving the hospital I painted my own <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">doctor</rs>’s portrait.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> And haven’t yet altogether lost my equilibrium as a painter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">But obviously I’ve painted a lot more other studies or paintings in all this time. Among other things this summer, two flower-pieces with nothing but <hi rend="italics">Sunflowers</hi> in a yellow earthenware pot.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Painted with the three chrome yellows,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> yellow ochre and Veronese green and nothing else.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">For the time being I’m still in Arles and at your disposal for further correspondence by letter or painted study. Theo went to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> recently,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and said of his work that he thought Breitner the best painter and thinker among you over there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Regards, my dear friend, with a handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Your friend</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Address still</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">2 Place Lamartine</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Arles.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">If you see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs>, you may let him read this epistle or tell him about it just as I write it, without bringing too much of your own imagination into play.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says that he is working on his painting of the Berceuse <ref target="#l-43">(ll. 43-45)</ref>. Because he also reports this to Gauguin and Theo in the letters of Monday, 21 and Tuesday, 22 January (<ref target="let739.xml">letters 739</ref> and <ref target="let741.xml">741</ref>), we have dated the present letter to about Tuesday, 22 January 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In addition to several additions in ink, Van Gogh made a number of even later additions in pencil (<ref target="#n-5">see nn. 5</ref> and <ref target="#n-12">12</ref>).</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> had sent a postcard from Winschoten on 31 December 1888 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let727.xml">letter 727</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
      
<p>In 1880 <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was planning to have his son committed to the Belgian lunatic asylum of Geel. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let155.xml#n-1">See letter 155, n. 1</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let185.xml#n-3">185, n. 3</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For the studies that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> sent to Theo, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let666.xml#n-9">see letter 666, n. 9.</ref> The proposal to exchange work with Koning came up in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml">letters 600</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let614.xml">614</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh does not mean that a woman rocking a baby or a lullaby occur in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_588">Frederik van Eeden</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_461">De kleine Johannes</ref></hi>. This is not the case. He wants to translate the French word ‘berceuse’ into the language of the writer whose book is a point of reference shared by him and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>: the Dutch of Van Eeden’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De kleine Johannes</hi> (on this book, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let626.xml#n-16">see letter 626, n. 16</ref>).</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh later added in pencil ‘of de wiegster’ (or the woman rocking the baby).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Here, too, Van Gogh is not interested in a thematic comparison between his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Berceuse</hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_461">De kleine Johannes</ref></hi>; he compares <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_588">Van Eeden</rs>’s ‘style of writing’ with his ‘style of painting’, and is thus referring to a similarity in style and technique. What Van Gogh means is clarified in another passage by his comments on these aspects of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La berceuse</hi>. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let739.xml">letter 739</ref> he wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>: ‘As an Impressionist arrangement of colours, I have never devised anything better’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-72">(ll. 72-74)</ref>. The then innovative style of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De kleine Johannes</hi> does indeed have Impressionistic traits, particularly in the many descriptions of nature, with their countless colour adjectives. Van Gogh’s comparison was actually prompted mainly by his need to win Koning over to his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Berceuse</hi>, albeit from a distance, by putting the painting on a par with something Koning apparently admired.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>’s stay in Paris, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-8">see letter 578, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Félix Rey</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2766">F 500 / JH 1659</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let595.xml">letter 595</ref> Van Gogh names the three chrome yellows as orange, yellow and lemon.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Theo met <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> while staying in Amsterdam from 6 to 11 January 1889. Breitner was then working in a studio at Eerste Parkstraat 438. They had already known each other for a long time. See Jessica Voeten, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Het Witsenhuis</hi>. Amsterdam and Antwerp 2003, p. 29.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh later pencilled in the sentence ‘als ... brengen’ (If you ... into play’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    