<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Tuesday, 22 January 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let741"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b620 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>741</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>573</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>744</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-01-22">Tuesday, 22 January 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0620 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0620 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000845_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0620 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000846_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000846_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0620 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000846_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000846_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000846_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci de ta lettre et du billet de 50 fr<c type="kp">_</c> qu’elle contenait. Naturellement jusqu’à l’arrivee de ta lettre après le 1<hi rend="super">er</hi> je suis maintenant à couvert. Ce qui est arrivé pour cet argent c’était absolument un grand hasard et un malentendu dont ni toi ni moi ne sommes responsables. Telegraphier<c type="kk">/</c> comme tu dis justement<c type="kk">/</c> par le meme hasard je ne le pouvais pas car j’ignorais si tu etais encore à Amsterdam ou de retour à Paris<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> C’est avec le reste passé maintenant et une preuve de plus du proverbe qu’un malheur ne vient jamais seul. Hier Roulin est parti (naturellement ma dépêche d’hier etait envoyée avant l’arrivée de ta lettre de ce matin). c’était touchant de le voir avec ses enfants le dernier jour<c type="kk">/</c> surtout avec la toute petite quand il la faisait rire et sauter sur ses genoux et chantait pour elle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Sa voix avait un timbre étrangement pur et emu où il y avait à la fois pour mon oreille un doux et navré chant de nourrice et comme un lointain résonnement du Clairon de la France de la révolution. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Il n’était pourtant pas triste<c type="kk">/</c> au contraire<c type="kk">/</c> il avait mis son uniforme tout neuf qu’il avait reçu le jour même et tout le monde lui faisait fête.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je viens de terminer une nouvelle toile qui a un petit air presque chic<c type="kk">/</c> un panier d’osier avec citrons &amp; oranges – une branche de cyprès et une paire de gants bleus<c type="kk">/</c> tu as déjà vu de ces paniers de fruits de moi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Ecoutez – ce que tu sais que je cherche<c type="kk">/</c> moi<c type="kk">/</c> c’est de retrouver l’argent qu’a couté mon éducation de peintre<c type="kk">/</c> ni plus ni moins<c type="kp">_</c> Cela c’est mon droit avec le gain du pain de chaque jour.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Il me paraitrait juste que cela retourne je ne dis pas dans tes mains puisque nous avons fait ce que nous avons fait à nous deux et que cela nous cause tant de peine de causer de l’argent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Mais que cela aille dans les mains de ta femme qui d’ailleurs se joindra à nous autres pour travailler avec les artistes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Si je ne m’occupe pas encore de la vente directement c’est que mon lot de tableaux n’est pas encore au complet mais il avance et je me suis remis au travail avec ce nerf-là en métal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">J’ai veine et deveine dans ma production mais non pas <hi rend="italics">seulement</hi> déveine. Si par exemple notre bouquet de Monticelli<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> vaut pour un amateur 500 francs<c type="kk">/</c> et il les vaut<c type="kk">/</c> alors j’ose t’assurer que mes tournesols<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>pour un de ces ecossais ou americains vaut 500 francs aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Or pour être chauffé suffisamment pour fondre ces ors-là et ces tons de fleurs – le premier venu ne le peut pas<c type="kk">/</c> il faut l’energie et l’attention d’un individu tout entier.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Lorsqu’après ma maladie je revis mes toiles<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui me semblait le mieux etait la chambre à coucher.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Il me semble que ton appartement serait encombré surtout après que ta femme y demeurera aussi si je t’envoyais tout cela à Paris. Puis cela ferait connaitre les toiles qui seraient fanés et discutées en bas<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> comme rien<c type="kk">/</c> avant le temps et l’heure.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">La somme avec laquelle nous travaillons est certes assez respectable mais il s’en ecoule beaucoup et pour faire que d’année en année <hi rend="italics">tout</hi> ne s’écoule pas entre les mailles c’est à cela surtout nous devons<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> veiller. C’est aussi que si le mois s’avance je cherche toujours à établir plus ou moins un équilibre par la production<c type="kk">/</c> au moins relatif. Tant de contrariétés certes me rendent un peu inquiet et craintif mais je ne desespère pas encore.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Le mal que je prevois c’est qu’il faudra beaucoup de <hi rend="italics">prudence</hi> pour eviter que les frais qu’on a lorsqu’on vend ne dépassent pas la vente elle-même lorsque ce jour sera venu. Cela<c type="kk">/</c> que de fois ne avons nous pas été à même de voir cette triste chose-là dans la vie des artistes.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">J’ai en train le portrait de la femme Roulin où je travaillais avant d’être malade.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">j’avais arrangé là-dedans les rouges depuis le rose jusqu’à l’orangé<c type="kk">/</c> lequel montait dans les jaunes jusqu’au citron avec des verts clairs et sombres. Si je pouvais terminer cela<c type="kk">/</c> cela me ferait bien plaisir mais je crains qu’elle ne voudra plus poser<c type="kk">/</c> son mari absent.–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Tu vois juste que le depart de Gauguin est terrible<c type="kk">/</c> juste parce que cela nous refout en bas alors que nous avions crée et meublé la maison pour y loger les amis au mauvais jour.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Seulement quand meme nous gardons les meubles &amp;c. Et quoique aujourd’hui tout le monde aura peur de moi<c type="kk">/</c> avec le temps cela peut disparaitre.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Nous sommes tous mortels et sujets à toutes les maladies possibles<c type="kk">/</c> qu’y pouvons nous lorsque ces dernières ne sont pas précisement d’espèce agreable. Le mieux est de chercher à s’en guerir.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Je trouve aussi du remords en songeant à la peine que de mon côté j’ai occasionné quelqu’involontairement que ce soit – à Gauguin<c type="kp">_</c> Mais auparavant aux derniers jours je ne voyais qu’une seule chôse c’est qu’il travaillait le coeur partagé entre le désir d’aller à Paris pour l’exécution de ses plans et la vie à Arles. Que resultera-t-il de tout cela pour lui.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Tu sentiras que quoique tu aies des bons appointements<c type="kk">/</c> pourtant nous manquons de capital ne fut-ce en marchandise<c type="kk">/</c> et que pour reellement faire changer la triste position des artistes que nous connaissons il faudrait encore être plus puissant. Mais alors souvent on se heurte justement à la mefiance de leur part et à ce qu’il complotent toujours entre eux. ce qui arrive toujour au resultat de – <hi rend="italics">vide</hi>. Je crois qu’à Pont Aven ils avaient déjà à 5 ou 6 formé un nouveau groupe<c type="kk">/</c> tombé peut etre déjà<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Ils ne sont pas de mauvaise foi mais c’est là une chôse sans nom et un de leurs defauts d’enfants terribles<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Maintenant le principal sera que ton marriage ne traine pas. En te mariant tu rends la mère tranquille et heureuse et enfin ce que necessite un peu ta position dans la vie et dans le commerce. Sera ce apprecié par la société à laquelle tu apartiens<c type="kk">/</c> cela pas plus peutetre que les artistes s’en doutent que parfois j’ai travaillé et souffert pour la communauté... Aussi de moi ton frère tu ne desireras pas les felicitations absolument banales et les assurances que tu seras tout droit transporté dans un paradis.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Et avec ta femme tu cesseras d’être seul<c type="kk">/</c> ce que je souhaiterais tant à la soeur Wil aussi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">J’espere toujours que peutêtre nous pourrions<c type="kk">/</c> faute de la faire rencontrer et marier un médecin<c type="kk">/</c> au moins peut etre la faire rencontrer un peintre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Cela<c type="kk">/</c> après ton propre mariage<c type="kk">/</c> serait ce que je desirerais maintenant plus que tout le reste.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Ton mariage fait<c type="kk">/</c> il s’en fera peut-etre d’autres dans la famille et dans tous les cas tu verras ton chemin clair et la maison ne sera plus vide.–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Quoi que je pense sur quelques autres points<c type="kk">/</c> notre pere et notre mère ont été exemplaires comme gens mariés<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Et je n’oublierai jamais la mère à l’occasion de la mort de notre père où elle ne disait qu’une seule petite parole qui pour moi a fait que j’ai recommencé à aimer davantage la vieille mère ensuite<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin comme gens mariés nos parents étaient exemplaire comme Roulin et sa femme pour citer un autre specimen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Eh bien va droit dans ce chemin-là<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Pendant ma maladie j’ai revu chaque chambre de la maison à Zundert<c type="kk">/</c> chaque sentier<c type="kk">/</c> chaque plante dans le jardin<c type="kk">/</c> les aspects d’alentour<c type="kk">/</c> les champs<c type="kk">/</c> les voisins<c type="kk">/</c> le cimetiere<c type="kk">/</c> l’eglise<c type="kk">/</c> notre jardin potager derriere – jusqu’au nid de pie dans un haut accacia dans le cimetière<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Cela puisque de ces jours-là j’ai encore les souvenirs les plus primitifs de vous autres tous; pour se souvenir de tout cela il n’y a plus ainsi que la mère et moi.– Je n’insiste pas puisqu’il est mieux que je ne cherche pas à retablir tout ce qui m’a passé dans la tête alors.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Sache seulement que je serais tres heureux lorsque ton mariage sera accompli<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Ecoute maintenant<c type="kk">/</c> si vis à vis de ta femme il serait peut-être bon que de temps à autre il y eût un tableau de moi chez les Goupil<c type="kk">/</c> alors je laisserai là ma vieille dent que j’ai contre eux de la façon suivante. J’ai dit que je ne voulais pas y revenir avec un tableau trop innocent<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>Mais si tu veux tu peux y exposer les deux toiles de tournesols.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">Gauguin serait content d’en avoir une et j’aime bien à faire à Gauguin un plaisir d’une certaine force. Alors il desire une de ces deux toiles<c type="kk">/</c> eh bien j’en referai une des deux<c type="kk">/</c> celle qu’il désire.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Tu verras que ces toiles taperont à l’oeil<c type="kp">_</c> Mais je te conseillerais de les garder pour toi<c type="kk">/</c> pour ton intimité de ta femme et de toi.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">C’est de la peinture un peu changeante d’aspect<c type="kk">/</c> qui prend richesse en regardant plus longtemps. Tu sais que Gauguin les aime extraordinairement d’ailleurs. Il m’en a dit entre autres:</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">“cà – .. c’est.. la fleur”.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Tu sais que Jeannin a la pivoine<c type="kk">/</c> que Quost a la rose tremiere mais moi j’ai un peu le tournesol. Et en somme cela me fera un plaisir de continuer les échanges avec Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> meme si quelquefois cela me coûte cher à moi aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.39" n="39">As tu vu lors de ta hative visite le portrait en noir et jaune de M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Ginoux?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.40" n="40">C’est là un portrait peint en 3 quarts d’heure<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.41" n="41">Il faut que je finisse pour le moment<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.42" n="42">Le retard de l’envoi d’argent est un hasard et ainsi ni toi ni moi n’y ont rien pu<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.43" n="43">Poignée de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.44" n="44">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.45" n="45">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter and for the 50-franc note it contained. Naturally I’m now covered until the arrival of your letter after the 1st. What happened as regards that money was absolutely sheer chance and a misunderstanding for which neither you nor I are responsible. To telegraph, as you rightly say, I couldn’t do by the same sheer chance, for I didn’t know if you were still in Amsterdam or back in Paris.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It is, with the rest, over now, and one more proof of the proverb that misfortunes never come singly. Yesterday <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> left (naturally my dispatch of yesterday was sent before the arrival of your letter this morning). It was touching to see him with his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_649 bio.xml#_650 bio.xml#_651">children</rs> on the last day, above all with the very little one when he made her laugh and bounce on his knees and sang for her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">His voice had a strangely pure, moved timbre which to my ear contained a sweet, distressed wet-nurse’s song and something like a distant echo of the clarion of revolutionary France. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> He wasn’t sad, though, on the contrary, he had put on his brand-new uniform, which he’d received the same day, and everyone was making much of him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve just finished a new canvas which has an almost chic little look to it, a willow basket with lemons and oranges — a cypress branch and a pair of blue gloves, you’ve already seen some of these fruit-baskets of mine.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Listen — what you know I’m trying to do, myself, is to recoup the money that my training as a painter has cost, neither more nor less. That’s my right, along with earning my bread each day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It would appear just to me that it should come back, I don’t say into your hands, since we’ve done what we’ve done together, and we find it so upsetting to talk of money.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But may it go into the hands of your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs>, who anyway will join with us to work with the artists.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">If I’m not yet busying myself with selling directly it’s because my tally of paintings isn’t yet complete, but it’s coming along and I’ve set to work again with this iron resolve.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I have good and bad luck in my production, but not bad luck <hi rend="italics">alone</hi>. If, for example, our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> bouquet<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> is worth 500 francs to an art lover, and it’s worth that, then I dare assure you that my sunflowers<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> are also worth 500 francs to one of those Scots or Americans. Now, to be sufficiently heated up to melt those golds and those flower tones, not just anybody can do that, it takes an individual’s whole and entire energy and attention.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">When I saw my canvases again after my illness, what seemed to me the best was the bedroom.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">It seems to me that your apartment would be cluttered if I were to send all of this to you in Paris, especially after your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> will be staying there too. Then it would get the canvases known that would have lost their bloom and be talked about downstairs<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> as if they were nothing, before the time and the hour.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">The sum we’re working with is certainly quite respectable, but a lot of it runs away and we must above all be watchful to ensure that not <hi rend="italics">everything</hi> slips through the net from year to year. It’s also the fact that even if the month goes on I’m always trying to strike more or less a balance through production, at least relative. So many annoyances certainly make me a little anxious and fearful, but I’m not yet in despair.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">The trouble I foresee is that much <hi rend="italics">prudence</hi> will be required to prevent the expenses we have when selling from exceeding the sale itself when the day comes. As regards that, how many times have we been in a position to see that sad thing in the lives of artists.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I have the portrait of Roulin’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">wife</rs> on the go that I was working on before being ill.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">In it I had ranged the reds from pink to orange, which rose into the yellows as far as lemon with light and dark greens. If I could finish that, it would give me great pleasure but I fear she won’t want to pose any more, with her husband away. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">You’re right in seeing that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s departure is terrible, right because it pushes us back down when we had created and furnished the house to take in friends in bad times.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Only we’ll keep the furniture &amp;c. all the same. And although today everyone will be afraid of me, that may disappear with time.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">We’re all mortal and subject to all possible illnesses, what can we do about it when the latter aren’t precisely of a pleasant kind. The best thing is to try to recover from them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I find remorse, too, in thinking of the trouble that I’ve occasioned on my side, however involuntarily it may be — to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>. But prior to the last days I could see only one thing, that he was working with his heart divided between the desire to go to Paris to carry out his plans, and life in Arles. What will the outcome of all that be for him?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">You’ll feel that although you have a good salary we still lack capital, except in goods, and that we need to be even more powerful to really change the sad position of the artists we know. But then one often just comes up against distrust on their part, and the fact that they’re always plotting among themselves, which always arrives at the result of — <hi rend="italics">emptiness</hi>. I think that at Pont-Aven 5 or 6 of them had already formed a new group, perhaps broken up already.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">They aren’t dishonest, but that’s a thing without name and one of their defects as ‘enfants terribles’. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Now the main thing will be that your marriage isn’t delayed. By marrying you’re putting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>’s mind at rest and making her happy, and anyway what your position in life and business rather necessitates. Will that be appreciated by the society to which you belong? Perhaps no more than the artists suspect that from time to time I’ve worked and suffered for the community... So from me, your brother, you won’t wish for the absolutely banal congratulations and the assurances that you’ll be transported straight to paradise.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">And with your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> you’ll cease to be alone, which I’d so wish for our sister <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">I still hope that perhaps, if we can’t make her meet and marry a doctor, we might at least perhaps be able to make her meet a painter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">That, after your own marriage, would be what I would wish for now more than all the rest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Once your marriage is done, there will perhaps be others in the family, and in any case, you’ll see your path clear and the house will no longer be empty. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Whatever I think on a few other points, our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs> and our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> have been exemplary as married people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And I’ll never forget <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> on the occasion of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>’s death, when she said only one small word, which for me made me begin to love our old mother again more than before. Anyway, as married people our parents were exemplary, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> and his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">wife</rs> to quote another specimen.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Well, go straight ahead along that road.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">During my illness I again saw each room in the house at Zundert, each path, each plant in the garden, the views round about, the fields, the neighbours, the cemetery, the church, our kitchen garden behind — right up to the magpies’ nest in a tall acacia in the cemetery.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">That’s because I still have the most primitive memories of all of you, of those days; to remember all this there’s now only <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and me. I shan’t go on since it’s better that I don’t try to restore everything that passed through my mind then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Know only that I’ll be very happy when your marriage has taken place.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">Listen now, if as regards your wife it would perhaps be good for a painting of mine to be at the Goupils’ from time to time, then I’ll drop my old grudge that I have against them in the following way. I said that I didn’t want to return there with too innocent a painting.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> But you can exhibit the two canvases of sunflowers there if you wish.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> would be pleased to have one of them, and I very much enjoy doing Gauguin quite a big favour. So, he wants one of those two canvases, well I’ll do one of them over again, the one he wants.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">You’ll see that these canvases will catch the eye. But I’d advise you to keep them for yourself, for the privacy of your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> and yourself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">It’s a type of painting that changes its aspect a little, which grows in richness the more you look at it. Besides, you know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> likes them extraordinarily. He said to me about them, among other things:</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">‘that — ... that’s... the flower’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">You know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1112">Jeannin</rs> has the peony, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1282">Quost</rs> has the hollyhock, but I have the sunflower, in a way. And all in all it will give me pleasure to continue the exchanges with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> even if sometimes it costs me dear too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">Did you see, during your fleeting visit, the portrait in black and yellow of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Mrs Ginoux</rs>?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">That’s a portrait painted in 3 quarters of an hour.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">I must finish for the moment.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">The delay in sending the money is sheer chance, and thus neither you nor I could do anything about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.44" n="44">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.45" n="45">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent reports that Roulin left ‘yesterday’. The letter can therefore be dated to Tuesday, 22 January 1889 (<ref target="let743.xml">See letter 743</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>). This agrees with the fact that Theo forwarded this letter on Wednesday, 23 January to his fiancée, Jo Bonger (see <hi rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 106).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Roulin’s departure for Marseille <ref target="let736.xml">(736)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s departure from Arles <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s request for a sunflower painting <ref target="let736.xml">(736)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="ogt_6">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s journey to Arles <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let736.xml">letters 736</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let738.xml">738</ref> Vincent had urgently requested money from Theo, because the money that he expected to receive around 10 January did not arrive until the 17th.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Blue gloves and a basket of oranges and lemons</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2768">F 502 / JH 1664</rs>). In Paris Van Gogh had painted two still lifes of baskets of fruit: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of apples </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2558">F 378 / JH 1340</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of apples </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2559">F 379 / JH 1341</rs>). In Arles he made <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Basket of oranges</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2567">F 395 / JH 1363</rs>), which he compared in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let592.xml">letter 592</ref> with the Paris still lifes and included in the first batch of paintings he sent to Theo (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let606.xml">see letter 606</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_306">Vase of flowers</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-4">see letter 578, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh no doubt means ‘the two canvases of sunflowers’ mentioned later in the letter:<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>). They were hanging in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s room in the Yellow House, and Vincent assumed that Theo had seen them during his visit to Arles (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let743.xml">see letter 743</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This refers to Theo’s downstairs neighbour, the art dealer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Alphonse Portier</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘que nous devons’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The fear that others were afraid of him is confirmed by Theo, who wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo Bonger</rs> a short time later, on 14 February 1889: ‘If I had time, I should go and see him and go hiking with him, for instance. That’s the only thing I can think of that would really give him peace of mind. If one of the painters might like to do that I shall send him there. But those he gets on with are slightly afraid of him, which <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s visit to him did nothing to change, on the contrary’ (see FR b2035; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 160).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The ‘new group’ must refer to the painters from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s circle, who had stayed behind in Pont-Aven: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1237">Henry Moret</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1823">Emile Jourdan</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1824">Charles Filiger</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_936">Ernest Ponthier de Chamaillard</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Charles Laval</rs>. See exhib. cat. Paris<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>2003, pp. 92-96.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>To Theo’s suggestion to exhibit <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Small pear tree in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2590">F 405 / JH 1394</rs>) at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>, Van Gogh had answered in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let721.xml">letter 721</ref> that he found it unnecessary.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had set his heart on <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let739.xml">see letter 739</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had exchanged paintings in November 1887 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let576.xml#n-2">see letter 576, n. 2</ref>) and in October 1888 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let697.xml">see letter 697</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2744">F 489 / JH 1625</rs>). Cf. also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let717.xml">letter 717</ref>, in which Van Gogh wrote that he had painted the portrait in just one hour.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    