<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Sunday, 3 February 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let745"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b623 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>745</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>576</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>749</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-02-03">Sunday, 3 February 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0623 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0623 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000851_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0623 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0623 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000852_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">j’aurais préféré te répondre aussitôt à la bien bonne lettre contenant 100 francs mais justement étant très fatigué à ce moment-là et le medecin<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> m’ayant ordonné absolument de me promener sans travail mental<c type="kk">/</c> ce n’est par suite de cela qu’aujourd hui que je t’ecris<c type="kp">_</c> Pour le travail le mois n’a en somme pas été mauvais et le travail me distrait ou plutôt me tient reglé<c type="kk">/</c> alors je ne m’en prive pas<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’ai fait la berceuse <hi rend="italics">trois fois</hi><c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> or M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Roulin étant le modèle et moi n’etant que le peintre je lui ai laissé choisir entre les trois<c type="kk">/</c> elle et son mari<c type="kk">/</c> seulement en conditionnant que de celle qu’elle prendrait j’en ferais encore une répétition pour moi laquelle actuellement j’ai en train<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Tu me demande si j’ai lu la Mireille de Mistral – je suis comme toi<c type="kk">/</c> je ne peu pas la lire que par fragments de la traduction<c type="kp">_</c> Mais toi l’as tu déjà <hi rend="italics">entendue</hi> car peut-etre sais-tu que Gounod a mis cela en musique.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Je crois au moins.– Cette musique-<c type="shy">-</c>là naturellement je l’ignore et même en l’ecoutant je regarderais plutôt les musiciens que d’écouter<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Mais je peux te dire ceci que la langue originale d’ici en paroles est d’un musical dans la bouche des arlésiennes que cela ma foi oui je en attrappe par moments des fragments.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Peut etre dans la berceuse il y a un essai de petite <hi rend="italics">musique</hi> de couleur d’ici<c type="kk">/</c> c’est mal peint et les chromos du bazar sont infiniment mieux peints techniquement mais quand même<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Ici – la ainsi nommée <hi rend="italics">bonne</hi> ville d’Arles est un drôle d’endroit que pour de bonnes raisons l’ami Gauguin appelle le plus sale endroit du midi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Or Rivet<c type="kk">/</c> s’il voyait la population serait certes à des moments désolé en redisant “vous êtes tous des malades” – comme il le dit de nous. Mais si vous attrappez la maladie du pays ma foi après vous ne pouvez plus l’attrapper.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Ceci pour te dire que pour moi je ne me fais pas d’illusions<c type="kp">_</c> Cela va fort fort bien et je ferai tout ce que dira le médecin mais...</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">lorsque je suis sorti avec le bon Roulin de l’hopital je me figurais que je n’avais rien eu<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">après</hi> seulement j’ai eu le sentiment que j’avais été malade. Que veux tu<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai des moments où je suis tordu par l’enthousiasme ou la folie ou la profetie comme un oracle grec sur son trépied.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">j’ai alors une grande présence d’esprit en paroles et parle commes les arlésiennes mais je me sens si faible avec tout cela<c type="kp">_</c> Surtout lorsque les forces physiques reprennent<c type="kp">_</c> Mais au moindre symptome grave j’ai déjà dit à Rey que je reviendrais et alors me soumettrais aux medecins alienistes d’Aix<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> ou à lui-même<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Qu’est ce que cela peut nous faire autre chôse que du mal et nous causer que de la souffrance<c type="kk">/</c> si nous ne nous portons pas bien<c type="kk">/</c> à toi ou à moi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Notre ambition a tellement sombré<c type="kp">_</c> Alors travaillons bien tranquillement<c type="kk">/</c> soignons nous tant que nous pouvons et ne nous épuisons pas en efforts stériles de générosité réciproque.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Toi tu feras ton devoir et moi je ferai le mien<c type="kk">/</c> en tant que quant à cela nous avons déjà tous les deux payé autrement qu’en paroles et<c type="kk">/</c> au bout de la route<c type="kk">/</c> possible qu’on se reverra tranquillement<c type="kp">_</c> Mais moi alors que dans mon délire toutes choses tant aimées remuent<c type="kk">/</c> je n’accepte pas cela comme réalité et ne fais pas le faux prophète.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">la maladie ou la mortalité ma foi cela ne m’épate pas mais l’ambition n’est pas compatible<c type="kk">/</c> heureusement pour nous<c type="kk">/</c> avec les metiers que nous faisons.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">D’ailleurs il y a tant de gens qui pensent ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> dans plusieurs cathégories de la societé<c type="kk">/</c> du plus haut jusqu’au plus bas<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Mais comment se fait-il que tu penses aux clausules du mariage et à la possibilite de mourir à ce moment<c type="kk">/</c> n’aurais tu pas mieux fait d’enfiler ta femme tout simplement préalablement<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin cela c’est dans les moeurs du nord et dans le nord c’est pas moi qui dise qu’on n’aie pas de bonnes moeurs.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Cela reviendra allez.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Mais moi qui n’ai pas le sou<c type="kk">/</c> dans ce cas ci je dis toujours que l’argent est une monnaie et la peinture en est une autre. Et je suis déjà à meme à te faire un envoi dans le sens mentionné dans les ecritures précédentes.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Mais il s’agrandira si les forces me reviennent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Ainsi je voudrais seulement qu’en cas que Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> qui a un complet béguin pour mes tournesols<c type="kk">/</c> me prenne ces deux tableaux<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> qu’il te donne à ta fiancee ou à toi deux tableaux de lui pas médiocres mais mieux que médiocres<c type="kp">_</c> Et s’il prend une édition de la berceuse à plus forte raison il doit de son côté aussi donner du bon.–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Sans cela je ne pourrais pas compléter cette série de laquelle je te parlais<c type="kk">/</c> qui doit pouvoir passer dans la meme petite vitrine que nous avons tant regardée.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">La valeur d’un tableau dans un cas comme ça est hors de cause et je me déclare pas expert. Demeure que ma position sociale peut m’etre aussi chère qu’à toi serait la tienne de bon employé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Et que je ne dis que ceci<c type="kk">/</c> je tiens autant que toi à une honetteté de frères vis à vis l’argent de Boussod. Ça nous n’y avons jamais mal servi<c type="kp">_</c> Et nous nous somme trop ereinté pour bien agir que de pouvoir nous facher au titre de voleurs ou incapables<c type="kk">/</c> d’ailleurs je n’insiste pas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Pour les Independants il me semble que six tableaux c’est la moitié de trop<c type="kp">_</c> A mon goût la moisson<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> et le verger blanc<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> sont assez avec la petite provencale<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> ou le semeur<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> si tu veux. Mais cela m’est si egal. j’y tiens seulement à te causer un jour une impression plus profondément consolante dans notre métier de peinture que nous faisons par une collection d’une 30<hi rend="super">taine</hi> d’etudes plus serieuses.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">cela prouvera toujours à nos vrais amis comme Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> Guillaumin<c type="kk">/</c> Bernard &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> que nous sommes dans le travail de production.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Eh bien pour la petite maison jaune<c type="kk">/</c> en payant mon loyer le gerant du proprietaire<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> a été tres bien et s’est conduit en arlesien<c type="kk">/</c> me traitant d’égal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Alors je lui ai dit que je n’avais pas besoin ni de bail ni de promesse de preference écrite et que moi en cas de maladie ne payerais pas qu’à l’amiable.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Ici les gens ont du fond du côté du coeur et une chôse dite est plus sure qu’une chose écrite<c type="kp">_</c> Donc je garde la maison provisoirement puisque j’ai besoin pour ma guérison mentale de me sentir ici chez moi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Maintenant pour ton déménagement de la Rue Lepic à la rue Rodier<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> je ne peux pas avoir d’opinion<c type="kk">/</c> n’ayant pas vu<c type="kk">/</c> mais le principal est que justement toi aussi déjeunes chez toi avec ta femme<c type="kp">_</c> En restant à Montmartre tu auras plus vite été décoré et ministre des beaux arts mais comme tu ne tiens pas à cela mieux vaut la tranquilité chez soi<c type="kk">/</c> alors je te donne tout à fait raison.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Moi aussi je suis un peu comme ca – au gens du pays qui me demandent après ma santé je dis toujours que je commencerai par en mourir avec eux et qu’après ma maladie sera morte.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Cela ne veut pas dire que je n’aurai pas des temps considerables de repit<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Mais une fois qu’on est malade pour de vrai on sait bien que l’on  ne peut pas attrapper deux fois la maladie<c type="kk">/</c> c’est la meme chose que la jeunesse ou la vieillesse<c type="kk">/</c> la santé ou la maladie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Seulement sache le bien que moi comme toi <hi rend="italics">je fais ce que me dit le</hi> <hi rend="italics">médecin</hi> tant que je peux. et que je considère cela comme une partie du travail et du devoir qu’on a à accomplir<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Je dois dire ceci que les voisins &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> sont d’une bonté particulière pour moi<c type="kk">/</c> tout le monde souffrant ici soit de fievre soit d’hallucination ou folie<c type="kk">/</c> on s’entend comme des gens d’une même famille.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">J’ai été hier revoir la fille où j’étais allé dans mon égarement<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> On me disait là que des chôses comme ça ici dans le pays n’a rien d’étonnant. Elle en avait soufferte et s’etait évanouie mais avait repris son calme. Et d’ailleurs on dit du bien d’elle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Mais pour me considérer moi comme tout à fait sain<c type="kk">/</c> il ne faut pas le faire<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">Les gens du pays qui sont malades comme moi me disent bien la vérité<c type="kp">_</c> On peut vivre vieux ou jeune mais on aura toujours des moments où l’on perd la tête.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Je ne te demande donc pas de dire de moi que je n’ai rien ou n’aurai rien<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Seulement le Ricord de cela c’est probablement Raspail<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Les <hi rend="italics">fievres</hi> de pays je ne les ai pas encore euses et cela aussi je pourrais encore les attrapper<c type="kp">_</c> Mais ici on est déjà malin dans tout cela à l’hospice et donc du moment qu’on n’a pas de fausse honte et dit franchement ce qu’on sent on n’y peut mal.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.39" n="39">Je termine cette lettre pour ce soir<c type="kk">/</c> avec bonne poignee de main en pensee<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.40" n="40">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.41" n="41">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I would have preferred to reply to you immediately about the very kind letter containing 100 francs, but as I was very tired at that precise moment, and as the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">doctor</rs><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> had absolutely ordered me to go for walks without mental work, because of that it’s only today that I write to you. As for work, the month hasn’t been bad after all, and the work distracts me, or rather keeps me in order, so I don’t deprive myself of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve done the Berceuse <hi rend="italics">three times</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> now since <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">Mrs Roulin</rs> was the model and I was only the painter, I let her choose between the three, her and her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">husband</rs>, only on condition that I’d do a repetition for myself of the one she took, which I’m working on at present.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">You ask me if I’ve read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_705">Mistral</rs>’s Mireille – I’m like you, I can only read it in fragments of the translation. But have you <hi rend="italics">heard</hi> it yet, for perhaps you know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_91">Gounod</rs> has set it to music.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I think so anyway. Naturally I don’t know this music, and even if I was listening to it I would rather be looking at the musicians than listening. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> But I can tell you this, that the original language from here in words sounds so musical in the mouths of the Arlésiennes that my word yes, from time to time I catch fragments of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Perhaps in the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">Berceuse</rs> there’s an attempt at a little <hi rend="italics">music</hi> of colour from here, it’s badly painted, and chromos bought at the penny bazaar are infinitely better painted technically, but all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Here – the so-called <hi rend="italics">good</hi> town of Arles is a funny place which for good reasons friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> calls the filthiest place in the south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Now <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Rivet</rs>, if he saw the population, would certainly be sorry at times, saying over and over, ‘you’re all sick’ – as he says of us. But if you catch the local sickness, my word, afterwards you won’t be able to catch it again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">This is to tell you that as for myself, I don’t have any illusions. It’s going very, very well and I’ll do everything that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">doctor</rs> says but...</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">When I came out of the hospital with good <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> I fancied that I hadn’t had anything, only <hi rend="italics">afterwards</hi> did I have the feeling that I’d been ill. What can you say, I have moments when I’m twisted by enthusiasm or madness or prophecy like a Greek oracle on her tripod.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Then I have a great presence of mind in words and talk like the Arlésiennes, but I feel so weak with all that. Especially when my physical powers return. But I’ve already told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Rey</rs> that at the slightest serious symptom I’d come back and then subject myself to the alienist doctors of Aix<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> or to himself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">What else can it do to us but bad things, and only cause us pain, you and me, if we aren’t well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Our ambition has sunk so low. So let’s work very calmly, look after ourselves as much as we can and not wear ourselves out in sterile efforts at reciprocal generosity.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">You’ll do your duty and I’ll do mine, as far as that’s concerned both of us have already paid for it other than in words and, at the end of the road, possibly we’ll see each other calmly again. But myself, whereas in my delirium all things I love so much are in turmoil, I can’t accept that as reality and am not acting the false prophet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Sickness or mortality, my word, that doesn’t surprise me, but ambition isn’t compatible, fortunately for us, with the professions we follow. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Besides, there are so many people who think this way, in several categories of society, from the highest to the lowest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">But how come that you’re thinking about the little clauses of marriage and the possibility of dying at this moment, wouldn’t you have done better quite simply to have screwed your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> in advance? Anyway, that’s part of the customs of the north, and I’m not the one to say they don’t have good customs in the north.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">It will come back, really.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">But as for me without a sou, in this case I still say that money is one kind of currency and painting another. And I’m already able to send you a consignment in the sense mentioned in the previous writings.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> But it will get bigger if my strength comes back to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">So I would like only, should <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, who has a complete infatuation with my sunflowers, take these two paintings from me,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> that he gives your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">fiancée</rs> or you two of his paintings, not mediocre ones but better than mediocre. And if he takes a version of the Berceuse all the more reason why he should also give something good on his part.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Without that I couldn’t complete this series I was telling you about, which must be able to go into the same little shop window we’ve looked into so often.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">The value of a painting in a case like this doesn’t come into it and I declare that I’m no expert. It remains that my social position may be as dear to me as yours as a good employee is to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">And let me say just this, I attach as much importance as you do to a brotherly honesty as regards <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod</rs>’s money. We have never served it ill. And we’ve worn ourselves out too much to do the right thing to be able to get angry at being called thieves or incompetents, what’s more, I won’t go on about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">For the Independents, it seems to me that six paintings is too many by half. To my taste the harvest<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and the white orchard<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> are enough, with the little Provençal girl<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> or the sower<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> if you want. But it’s all the same to me. I just really want one day to give you a more consolatory impression in our trade of painting in which we work, by means of a collection of around 30 more serious studies.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">In any case, that will prove to our real friends like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> &amp;c. that we’re engaged in the work of production. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">Ah well, as for the little yellow house, when I paid my rent the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_755">landlord’s agent</rs><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> was very nice and behaved like an Arlesian, treating me as an equal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">So I told him that I had no need of a lease, nor of a written statement of intent, preferably in writing, and that in the case of illness I would only pay by friendly agreement.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Here the people have their hearts in the right place, and a spoken word is more binding than a written one. So I’m keeping the house for the time being, since I need to feel at home here for the sake of my mental recovery.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">Now as regards your move from rue Lepic to rue Rodier<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I can’t have an opinion, not having seen it, but the main thing is precisely that you also lunch at home with your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs>. By staying in Montmartre you’ll be decorated and Minister for Fine Arts more quickly, but as you don’t much care about that it’s better to have tranquillity at home, so I think you’re completely right. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">I too am a little like that – to the local people who ask after my health I always say that I’ll begin by dying of it with them and that afterwards my sickness will be dead.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">That doesn’t mean to say that I won’t have considerable periods of respite.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">But once you’re seriously ill you well know that you can’t catch the sickness twice, being healthy or sick is the same thing as being young or old.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Only be well aware of the fact that like you, <hi rend="italics">I’m doing what the doctor tells me</hi> as much as I can. And that I consider that as a part of the work and the duty one has to carry out.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I must say this, that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647 bio.xml#_648 bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383 bio.xml#_52 bio.xml#_329">neighbours</rs> &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> are particularly kind towards me, everyone here suffering either from fever or hallucinations or madness, we get along like members of the same family.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Yesterday I went back to see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1831">girl</rs> I went to when I went out of my mind.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> I was told there that things like that aren’t at all surprising around here. She had suffered from it and had fainted but had regained her composure. And what’s more, people say good things of her.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">But as to considering myself completely healthy, we shouldn’t do it. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">The local people who are ill like me indeed tell me the truth. You can live to be old or young, but you’ll always have moments when you lose your head.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">So I don’t ask you to say of me that there’s nothing wrong with me, or won’t be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Only the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_631">Ricord</rs> of that is probably <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_625">Raspail</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> I haven’t yet had the local <hi rend="italics">fevers</hi>, and I could still catch them too. But here they’re already well-versed in all that at the hospital, and so from the moment when you have no false shame and say frankly what you feel, you can’t go wrong.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">I’m closing this letter for this evening, with good handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo van Gogh-Bonger, who presumably had the postmark at her disposal, dated the letter to Sunday, 3 February 1889 (<hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914). We have retained this dating, which agrees with the receipt of Theo’s letter containing 100 francs – Vincent hoped to receive it ‘as early as possible after 1 February’ (<ref target="let744.xml#l-103">letter 744, ll. 103-104</ref>), to which he would have liked to reply immediately (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-6</ref>).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Gauguin’s request for a sunflower painting <ref target="let736.xml">(736)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Entry for the 1889 Indépendants exhibition <ref target="let732.xml">(732)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Dr <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Félix Rey</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The three versions of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> are <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2774">F 506 / JH 1670</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2773">F 505 / JH 1669</rs>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647 bio.xml#_648">The Roulins</rs> chose <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2773">F 505 / JH 1669</rs>); the repetition of it (the fourth version) is <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2776">F 507 / JH 1672</rs>. See Hoermann Lister 2001, p. 73.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_705">Frédéric Mistral</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_513">Mirèio. Pouèmo prouvençau</ref></hi> (1859) is an epic poem of twelve cantos, written in Provençal dialect. There were editions containing a parallel text in French (cf. ed. Paris 1864). The tragic love story serves as the basis of the opera <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mireille</hi> (1864) by the French composer <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_91">Charles Gounod</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The prophetess Pythia, seated on a golden tripod in the Temple of Apollo at Delphi, uttered incoherent words that had to be interpreted by priests. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>From Van Gogh’s first stay in hospital, there had been tentative plans to have him taken to an asylum in Aix-en-Provence. On 29 December 1888 the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_212">mayor</rs> of Arles was asked to take measures to this end; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let728.xml#n-1">see letter 728, n. 1.</ref> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> wrote about it to Theo on 28 December, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> was informed as well, as is apparent from her letter to Theo, written a day later (FR b1066 and FR b2425). At the end of February 1889 there was again talk of transferring Van Gogh to Aix; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let750.xml#n-3">see letter 750, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written in his previous letters about his ambition to produce in the near future a series of presentable (and thus saleable) paintings. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let741.xml">See letters 741</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let743.xml">743</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let744.xml">744</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The repetitions made for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> were <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2772">F 455 / JH 1668</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2771">F 458 / JH 1667</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let736.xml#n-12">See letter 736, n. 12.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> would indeed receive a version of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La berceuse</hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml#n-4">see letter 776, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Reference to works from the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_376">Faure</rs> Collection exhibited in rue Laffitte; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let743.xml#n-11">see letter 743, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The harvest </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2621">F 412 / JH 1440</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The white orchard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2576">F 403 / JH 1378</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Mousmé </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2671">F 431 / JH 1519</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sower with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2646">F 422 / JH 1470</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>The agent in charge of the Yellow House was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_755">Bernard Soulè</rs>; the owner was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_225">Marie Louise Verdier</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let602.xml#n-19">see letter 602, n. 19.</ref> There was talk of renting Van Gogh’s house to a tobacconist; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let735.xml">see letter 735</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>This move did not take place; on 4 February Theo rented an apartment at 8 cité Pigalle. He moved into the apartment with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> on 20 April 1889. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 27, 137. In January Theo had drawn a floor plan for Jo of the layout of the apartment (FR b1900; see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 128 (with illustration opposite p. 144). He also gave his parents-in-law detailed information about the new apartment, including a floor plan. Jo’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> were particularly pleased about the short distance to boulevard Montmartre, which meant that Theo could at least lunch regularly with Jo at home – and ‘That’s a load off your mind, isn’t it, the worry about renting, and the nicest thing is that you will be able to see some greenery in the summer’ (FR b2892, 9 February 1889; FR b2894, 26 February 1889).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Regarding Van Gogh’s neighbours, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let744.xml#n-6">see letter 744, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>The ‘Chronique locale’ in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Forum Républicain </hi>of Sunday, 30 December 1888 reported that in the night of 23 December Van Gogh had offered his severed ear to ‘a certain <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1831">Rachel</rs>’ (la nommée Rachel) at ‘brothel No. 1’ (maison de tolérance No. 1) in rue du Bout d’Arles. The brothel was on the corner of rue des Glacières and rue du Bout d'Arles. Police officer Alphonse Robert later recalled that the girl worked under the name of Gaby (Doiteau and Leroy 1939, p. 6). The identity of the prostitute Rachel/Gaby remains a mystery. For an interpretation see Murphy 2016, pp. 66-69, 217-227.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            
      
<p>The French venereologist <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_631">Philippe Ricord</rs> proved that syphilis and gonorrhoea were distinct diseases. He demonstrated the specific nature of syphilis and distinguished three stages of the disease. Ricord set forth his findings in such publications as <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Monographie du chancre</hi> (1837) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Traité pratique des maladies vénériennes</hi> (1838). For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_625">Raspail</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let735.xml#n-11">see letter 735, n. 11.</ref> Van Gogh most likely means: just like Ricord cures venereal disease, Raspail will be able to give me the best advice, namely home medication. Van Gogh depicted Raspail’s book <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_589">Manuel annuaire de la santé</ref></hi> in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with onions and Annuaire de la santé</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2763">F 604 / JH 1656</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    