<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Friday, 22 March 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let751"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b627 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>751</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>580</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>755</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-03-22">Friday, 22 March 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0627" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0627" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000857_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>
    
<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci de ta lettre – que je viens de recevoir. A plus forte raison puisque je préfère dans ce cas ci avoir tort que raison<c type="kk">/</c> certes nous sommes absolument absolument d’accord en tant que quant au raisonnement que tu fais dans ta lettre. C’est aussi comme cela que j’envisage moi la chôse<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Il y a de neuf que M. Salles s’occupe je crois de me trouver un appartement dans un autre quartier de la ville. Cela je l’approuve car je ne serais pas contraint ainsi à un déménagement immédiat – je garderais un pied à terre – et puis certes je pourrais faire un tour jusqu’à Marseille ou plus loin pour trouver mieux. Il est bien brave et bien devoué M. Salles et c’est un heureux contraste avec d’autres ici. Enfin. Voilà tout ce qu’il y a de neuf pour le moment. Si de ton côté tu écrirais<c type="kk">/</c> cherche à influencer que j’aie le droit de sortir en ville néamoins.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Pour autant que j’en puisse juger je ne suis pas fou proprement dit.</p>
    
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Tu verras que les toiles que j’aie faites dans les intervalles sont calmes et pas inferieures à d’autres.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Le travail me <hi rend="italics">manque</hi> plutôt qu’il ne me fatigue.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Cela me ferait certes plaisir de voir Signac s’il faut que quand même il passe par ici.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Il faut alors qu’ils me laissent sortir avec lui pour lui montrer mes toiles.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Puis peut-être aurait ce été bien que je l’accompagne où il va et que nous eussions cherché à nous deux un nouvel endroit mais voilà justement cela n’étant guère probable<c type="kk">/</c> à quoi bon qu’il se dérange exprès pour venir me voir.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Ce que je trouve excellent dans ta lettre c’est que tu dis que sur la vie il ne faut aucunément se faire des illusions<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Il s’agit de gober la réalité de son sort et voilà. J’ecris à la hâte pour faire partir cette lettre qui pourtant ne te parviendra peut être que Dimanche et que Signac sera déjà parti. Je n’y peux rien.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Tout ce que je demanderais serait que des gens que je connais même pas de nom (car ils ont bien eu soin de 
<pb f="1r" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-3" facs="#zone-pb-1r-3"/>faire ainsi que je ne sache pas qui a envoyé cet ecrit en question) ne se mêlent pas de moi quand je suis en train de peindre<c type="kk">/</c> de manger ou de dormir ou de tirer au bordel un coup (n’ayant pas de femme).– Or ils se mêlent de tout cela<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Mais quand bien même je m’en moque profondément – si ce n’était pour le chagrin que bien involontairement je te cause ainsi ou plutôt qu’eux ils causent – et pour le retard dans le travail &amp;c.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Ces émotions répétées et inattendues<c type="kk">/</c> si elles devraient continuer<c type="kk">/</c> pourraient changer un ébranlement mental passager momentané en maladie chronique. Sois assuré que si rien n’intervient je serais à même actuellement de faire le même travail &amp; peut etre mieux dans les vergers que j’ai fait l’autre année.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Maintenant soyons fermes autant que possible et en somme ne nous laissons pas trop marcher sur le pied. Dès le commencement j’ai eu de l’opposition bien méchante ici<c type="kp">_</c> Tout ce bruit fera du bien naturellement à l’“impressionisme” mais toi et moi personellement nous souffrirons pour un tas de cons et de lâches<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Il y a de quoi garder son indignation pour soi n’est ce pas. Déjà j’ai vu sur un journal ici un article très bien reellement sur la litterature décadente ou impressioniste<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – mais à toi ou à moi<c type="kk">/</c> que nous font ces articles de journaux &amp;c. Comme dit mon brave ami Roulin “c’est servir de piedestal à d’autres”. Au moins desirait on savoir à quoi ou à qui pourtant n’est-ce pas. alors on ne saurait s’y opposer<c type="kp">_</c> Mais servir de pied de stal à quelque chôse qu’on ignore c’est agaçant<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Enfin tout cela n’est rien pourvu que tu marches bien droit à ton but – ton foyer assuré c’est beaucoup gagné pour moi aussi et cela fait nous pouvons peutetre retrouver une voie plus paisible après ton marriage<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Si tôt ou tard je devenais réellement fou je crois que je ne voudrais pas rester ici à l’hôpital mais justement pour le moment je veux encore <hi rend="italics">sortir</hi> d’ici librement. Car si je me comprends encore un peu il y aura entre ici &amp; là un intervalle.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Le mieux pour moi serait certes de ne pas rester seul mais je préférerais demeurer éternellement dans un cabanon que de sacrifier un autre existence à la mienne. Car le métier de peintre est triste et mauvais au temps qui court<c type="kp">_</c>– Si j’étais catholique j’aurais la ressource de me faire moine mais ne l’étant pas précisément<c type="kk">/</c> comme tu le conçois<c type="kk">/</c> je n’ai pas cette ressource. l’administration de l’hospice est – comment dirai je – jesuite<c type="kk">/</c> ils sont très très fins<c type="kk">/</c> très savants<c type="kk">/</c> très puissants<c type="kk">/</c> même impressioniste..... ils savent prendre des renseignements d’une subtilité inouië – mais – mais – cela m’étonne et me confond – pourtant.......</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Enfin voila un peu la cause de mon silence<c type="kk">/</c> donc tiens toi separé de moi pour les affaires et en attendant je suis après tout un homme aussi<c type="kk">/</c> tu sais<c type="kk">/</c> je me debrouillerai<c type="kk">/</c> pour ce qui me regarde<c type="kk">/</c> à moi seul pour des questions de conscience.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je te serre bien la main en pensée<c type="kk">/</c> dis à ta fiancée<c type="kk">/</c> à la mère et à la soeur de ne pas s’inquieter pour moi et de croire que je suis en bonne voie de guerison<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter – which I’ve just received. All the more so since in this case I prefer to be wrong than to be right: certainly we’re absolutely, absolutely in agreement as regards the reasoning you give in your letter. I also envisage the thing that way.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">What’s new is that I think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs> is trying to find me an apartment in another part of town. I approve of that, for in that way I wouldn’t be forced to move house immediately – I would keep a pied-à-terre, and then I could certainly make a trip as far as Marseille or further to find better. Mr Salles is very kind and very loyal, and it’s a happy contrast with others here. Anyway. That’s all that’s new for the moment. If on your side you would write, try to influence them so that I have the right to go out into the town nevertheless.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">As far as I can judge I’m not mad, strictly speaking.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You’ll see that the canvases I’ve done in the intervals are calm and not inferior to others.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I <hi rend="italics">miss</hi> work rather than it tires me. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">It would certainly give me pleasure to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs> if he must pass through here anyway.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> They must then let me go out with him to show him my canvases.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Then perhaps it would have been good that I should accompany him where he’s going, and that the two of us could have sought a new place, but there, since that’s actually scarcely probable, what’s the good of him putting himself out expressly to come and see me?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">What I find excellent in your letter is that you say that one mustn’t on any account have illusions about life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">One must seize the reality of one’s fate and that’s that. I’m writing in haste to send this letter, which will perhaps not reach you until Sunday all the same, by which time <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs> will already have left. I can’t do anything about that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">All that I would ask is that people I don’t even know by name (for they took great care to 
<pb f="1r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-3" facs="#zone-pb-1r-3"/> act so that I don’t know who sent that document in question) don’t meddle with me when I’m in the middle of painting, eating or sleeping or having a fuck in the brothel (not having a wife). Yet they meddle with all that.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">But despite all that I don’t give a damn at all – were it not for the pain I’m quite involuntarily causing you thus, or rather that they’re causing – and for the delay in work &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">These repeated and unexpected emotions, if they should continue, could change a fleeting, momentary mental disturbance into a chronic illness. Rest assured that if nothing happens I would now be able to do the same work in the orchards, and perhaps better, that I did the other year.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Now let’s be as firm as possible, and in short not allow people to tread on our toes too much. Right from the beginning I had very malicious opposition here. All this fuss will naturally do good to ‘Impressionism’, but you and I personally, we’ll suffer for a bunch of bastards and cowards.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">There’s something to be said for keeping one’s indignation to oneself, isn’t there? Already I’ve seen in a newspaper here a really very good article on decadent or Impressionist literature<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> – but what do these newspaper articles &amp;c. do to you and me? As my good friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> says, ‘it is acting as a pedestal for others’. At least one would wish to know for what or for whom, wouldn’t one? Then one couldn’t oppose it. But being a pedestal for something you aren’t aware of is annoying. 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Anyway, all of that is nothing provided you walk straight towards your goal – once your home is secured, there’s a lot won for me too, and once that’s done we can perhaps rediscover a more peaceful path after your marriage.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">If sooner or later I became really mad I think I wouldn’t want to stay here at the hospital, but just for the moment I still want to <hi rend="italics">leave</hi> here freely. For if I still understand myself a little there will be an interval between here and there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">The best for me would certainly be not to remain alone, but I would prefer to remain eternally in a madhouse than to sacrifice another existence to my own. For the trade of painter is sad and bad these days. If I were a Catholic I could resort to making a monk of myself, but since I’m not exactly one, as you know, I don’t have that resort. The administration of the hospital is – how shall I put it – Jesuit, they’re very, very shrewd, very learned, very powerful, even Impressionistic... they know how to obtain information with an unheard-of subtlety – but – but – it astonishes and confuses me – yet...</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Anyway, there you have something of the cause of my silence, so stay apart from me for business matters, and in the meantime I am a man too, after all, you know, I’ll get by on my own, as regards what concerns me in matters of conscience.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I shake your hand heartily in thought, tell your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">fiancée</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> not to worry about me, and to believe that I’m well on the road to recovery.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo has replied to Vincent’s letter of 19 March <ref target="let750.xml">(750)</ref>. The present letter is an immediate reaction to Theo’s reply (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). Signac, who was supposed to visit Vincent on 23 and 24 March, has not yet come <ref target="#l-26">(ll. 26-27)</ref>. On the basis of this information, and considering that Van Gogh did not expect Theo to receive the letter before Sunday <ref target="#l-44">(ll. 44-45)</ref>, we have dated it to Friday, 22 March 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Possible move to another part of town <ref target="let750.xml">(750)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The petition of the neighbourhood residents in Arles <ref target="let750.xml">(750)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In response to Vincent’s previous letter (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let750.xml">750</ref>), Theo must have gone into the issue of what should happen when Vincent was released from hospital. He, too, undoubtedly thought that moving to a different part of town was the best option.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Between the various attacks of his illness, Van Gogh painted the following canvases in any case: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Still life with onions and Annuaire de la santé </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2763">F 604 / JH 1656</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait with bandaged ear </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2764">F 527 / JH 1657</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait with bandaged ear and pipe </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2765">F 529 / JH 1658</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Félix Rey </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2766">F 500 / JH 1659</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Blue gloves and a basket of oranges and lemons</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2768">F 502 / JH 1664</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2772">F 455 / JH 1668</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2771">F 458 / JH 1667</rs>) and three versions of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2773">F 505 / JH 1669</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2774">F 506 / JH 1670</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2776">F 507 / JH 1672</rs>). He had also finished <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gauguin’s chair </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2750">F 499 / JH 1636</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Van Gogh’s chair </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2749">F 498 / JH 1635</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>). It is possible that in this period he also painted the three portraits of Joseph Roulin <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_805">F 435 / JH 1674</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2777">F 436 / JH 1675</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_806">F 439 / JH 1673</rs>; they definitely originated in the spring of 1889, but it is not known exactly when. For these portraits Van Gogh took as his example the large <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Joseph Roulin</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2672">F 432 / JH 1522</rs>). Cf. Hulsker 1993-2, pp. 227-230.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs>’s visit, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let752.xml">see letter 752</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh later added ‘ou de tirer ... tout cela’ (or having ... all that).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>In March-April 1888 Van Gogh had made a series of paintings of orchards in blossom; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-7">see letter 600, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the article ‘Les décadents’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1835">Adrien Frissant</rs>, which had been published in instalments in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Forum Républicain</hi> of 3, 10 and 24 February and 3 March 1888. Frissant ridicules the basic principles, use of language and the conduct of the ‘Ecole décadente’, attacking in particular the incomprehensibility of symbolist poetry. In the last instalment he quotes the poet René Ghil, who had written in his foreword to his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Légendes d’âmes et de sang</hi> not to seek words ‘which narrate’ but rather words ‘which impress’. Frissant therefore speaks of ‘the “Impressionist” language’ to which Van Gogh refers.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    