<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Wednesday, 24 April 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let762"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b732 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>762</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T5</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>764</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-04-24">Wednesday, 24 April 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0732 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0732 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000990_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0732 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000991_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000991_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0732 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000991_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000991_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">le 24 Avril 1889</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’ai été bien touché par ta lettre que nous avons reçu hier,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> tu dis vraiment trop de bien d’une chose qui n’est que toute naturelle<c type="kk">/</c> sans compter que tu me l’as rendu plusieurs fois, et par ton travail et par une fraternité qui vaut plus que tout l’argent que jamais je possederai. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je suis bien peiné en te sachant encore toujours dans un état de santé incomplèt. Quoique rien dans ta lettre ne trahit une faiblesse d’esprit, au contraire, le fait que tu juges nécessaire d’entrer dans une maison de santé est déjà assez grave. Espérons que cela ne sera qu’à titre préventive. Comme je te connais assez pour te croire capable de tout les sacrifices imaginables, j’ai pensé que la possibilité existe que tu aies pensé à cette solution pour gêner moins ceux qui te connaissent. Si cela est le cas, je te suplie de ne pas le faire, car certainement la vie 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>là-dedans ne doit pas être agréable. Sâches donc bien ce que tu fais et si peut être tu ne ferais pas un autre essai avant. Soit en revenant içi pendant quelque temps, soit en allant à Pont Aven pendant l’été<c type="kk">/</c> soit en cherchant une pension chez des gens qui auraient soin de toi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Si tu n’as eu aucune arrière pensée en m’écrivant comme tu l’as fait je trouve que tu as parfaitement raison d’aller à S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy<c type="kp">_</c> En y restant quelque temps tu pourras reprendre assurance en tes propres forces et rien ne t’empêchera de retourner à Arles au bout de quelque temps si le coeur t’en dit. M. Salles m’a envoyé des prospectus de S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>où il est dit qu’il faut qu’une tierce personne demande l’admission.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Je te mets donc sous ce pli la lettre pour le Directeur de l’établissement, dont tu pourras faire l’usage que tu voudras.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Aussitôt que tu auras décidé ton départ je t’enverrai l’argent nécessaire.– Maintenant je veux encore te dire que nous sommes içi depuis Samedi dernier<c type="kk">/</c> nous sommes installés à peu près et tous les jours, l’appartement prend un aspect plus habité grace à toutes sortes d’inventions de Jo. Nous nous entendons très bien ensemble de sorte, qu’il y a une si complète satisfaction des deux côtés, que nous nous sentons plus heureux que je ne puis te le dire. Nous avons quittée la mère &amp; les soeurs en parfaite 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>santé. Moe parait rajeunir<c type="kp">_</c> Elle est repartie maintenant à Breda après une absence d’un mois à peu près<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Mon mariage lui a fait bien plaisir<c type="kk">/</c> surtout parce que Jo et elle &amp; Wil se conviennent absolument, du reste elle a quelque chose de si sincère dans ses manières qu’il y a beaucoup de personnes sur qui elle fait une très agréable impression. Quoiqu’il y ait bien des choses de la vie qu’elle ignore et sur lesquelles son opinion doit se former, elle a un tel fond de bien vouloir &amp; d’ardeur à bien faire que je ne crains plus les désillusions que je redoutais avant notre mariage<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>Jusqu’à présent tout marche bien mieux que je ne l’avais pensé, et je n’avais pas osé espérer tant de bonheur. Le temps en Hollande m’a manqué pour voir beaucoup de tableaux<c type="kk">/</c> cependant j’ai revu la fiancée Juive<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp; les autres Rembrandt, les F<c type="kp">_</c> Hals à Haarlem<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> que j’ai trouvé plus beau que jamais &amp; le portrait de vieille femme de Rembrandt au Musée de Bruxelles.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Ce dernier est bien beau. Ces vieux portraits c’est ce qu’il y a de plus remarquable &amp; de plus caractéristique en Hollande. on est bien loin de cette epoque quand on voit les gens d’àprésent. Il y avait chez C<c type="kp">_</c>M<c type="kp">_</c> une exposition de croquis au fusain de Mauve, des feuilles de ses livres d’esquisse.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Des choses bien touchantes. Jet nous a fait cadeau d’un de ces dessins, dont je suis très très content.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Ecris moi bientôt ce que tu auras décidé définitivement &amp; ne désespère pas, car certes ils viendront encore de meilleurs jours pour toi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Je te serre les deux mains<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">24 April 1889</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I was very touched by your letter, which we received yesterday,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> you really say too many kind things about a thing that’s just entirely natural, not taking into account that you’ve given it back to me several times over, both by your work and by a brotherly affection which is worth more than all the money I’ll ever possess. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">It pains me to know that you’re still in a state of incomplete health. Although nothing in your letter betrays weakness of mind, on the contrary, the fact that you judge it necessary to enter an asylum is quite serious in itself. Let’s hope that this will be merely a preventive measure. As I know you well enough to believe you capable of all the sacrifices imaginable, I’ve thought that there’s a possibility that you may have thought of this solution to encumber less those who know you. If that’s the case, I beg you not to do it, for certainly life 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> in there can’t be agreeable. So be well aware of what you’re doing, and if perhaps you wouldn’t make another try first. Either by coming back here for a while, or by going to Pont-Aven during the summer, or by trying to board with people who would take care of you. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">If you had no ulterior motive in writing to me as you did, I find that you’re absolutely right to go to St-Rémy. By staying there for a while you’ll be able to regain confidence in your own strength, and nothing will prevent you from returning to Arles after a little while if the heart tells you to. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs> has sent me some prospectuses of St-Rémy 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>in which it’s said that a third party must request admission.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I therefore enclose the letter for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">director</rs> of the establishment, which you can use however you wish.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> As soon as you’ve decided to leave I’ll send you the necessary money. Now I also want to tell you that we’ve been here since last Saturday, we’re almost settled in, and every day the apartment takes on a more lived-in aspect, thanks to all sorts of inventions on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s part. We get along very well together, so that there’s such complete satisfaction on both sides that we feel happier than I can tell you. We left <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407 bio.xml#_401">sisters</rs> in perfect 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> health. Ma seems to be getting younger. She has now gone back to Breda after an absence of almost a month.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> My marriage pleased her very much, above all because <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and herself and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> get on perfectly, moreover she has something so sincere in her ways that there are many people on whom she makes a very agreeable impression. Although there are many things of life about which she does not know and on which her opinion must be formed, she has such a fund of good will and ardour to do good that I’m no longer afraid of the disillusionments I feared before our marriage. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> Up to now everything is going much better than I had thought, and I hadn’t dared hope for so much happiness. I didn’t have enough time in Holland to see many paintings, but I saw the Jewish bride<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> once again, and the other <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>s, the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">F. Hals</rs> in Haarlem,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> which I found more beautiful than ever, and Rembrandt’s portrait of an old woman at the museum in Brussels.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> This last one is very fine. These old portraits are what’s most remarkable and most characteristic in Holland. We’re a long way from that age, when we see the people of today. At <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M</rs>.’s there was an exhibition of charcoal croquis by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>, leaves from his sketchbooks.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Very touching things. Jet made us a present of one of those drawings, with which I’m very, very pleased.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Write to me soon about what you’ve definitely decided and don’t despair, for better days will certainly still come for you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I shake both your hands.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘le 24 Avril 1889’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo enclosed a letter of recommendation for Dr Peyron, the director of the asylum at Saint-Rémy (cf. <ref target="#l-47">ll. 47-50</ref> and <ref target="#n-3">n. 3</ref>), as well as a 100-franc note (<ref target="let763.xml">see letter 763</ref>).</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s new apartment <ref target="let745.xml">(745)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Decision regarding Vincent’s admission to the asylum at Saint-Rémy <ref target="let760.xml">(760)</ref> </p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let760.xml">letter 760</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Salles</rs> had sent the prospectus with his letter to Theo of 19 April 1889 (FR b1050). The complete text of an 1866 brochure is included in Coquiot<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1923, pp. 201-211. Cf. also the photographs of a prospectus preserved in the Tralbaut archives (Van Gogh Museum, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Documentation</hi>) and the illustration in exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p>In this letter, dated 24 April 1889, Theo wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Dr Théophile Peyron</rs>, director of the asylum at Saint-Rémy, that he hoped ‘you will have no objection to allowing him the freedom to paint outside the institution when he wishes to do so’ (que vous ne trouverez aucun inconvenient en lui accordant la liberté, de faire de la peinture en dehors de l’établissement quand il le désirera). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="documentation.xml#id24April1889">See <hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, 24 April 1889</ref>.  Peyron received his letter through <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Salles</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let763.xml">see letter 763</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>On 31 March <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> had travelled with Theo from Breda to Amsterdam (FR b2432), where they stayed until after the wedding, which took place on 18 April.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2119">Jewish bride</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let430.xml#n-10">see letter 430, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For the paintings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Hals</rs> in Haarlem, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let130.xml#n-2">see letter 130, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Now ‘Circle of Rembrandt’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The dead woman</hi> (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_364">Ill. 364</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>From 8 to 15 April there were sketches and drawings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Anton Mauve</rs> on display at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M. van Gogh</rs>’s gallery at Keizersgracht 453. The Amsterdam society <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Arti et Amicitiae</hi> had held a viewing of these studies on 28 March. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Groene Amsterdammer</hi>, 14 April 1889 and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Amsterdammer. Dagblad voor Nederland</hi>, 27 March 1889 and 9 April 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Theo probably received as a present <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Study of a flock of sheep</hi> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum), <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2281">Ill. 2281</rs> which has <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_809">Sketch of a landscape with sheep</rs></hi> on the verso.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    