<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Jo van Gogh-Bonger to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Wednesday, 8 May 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let771"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b735 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>771</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T8</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>774</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
                            <date when="1889-05-08">Wednesday, 8 May 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0735 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0735 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000994_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0735 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0735 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000995_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Parijs 8 mei ’89</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Lieve broer,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Eindelijk wordt het tijd dat je nieuwe zusje eens wat met je komt praten en niet altijd maar door Theo haar groeten doet overbrengen<c type="kp">_</c> Toen we nog niet getrouwd waren dacht ik altijd: Ja nu durf ik nog niet goed zoo van alles aan Vincent te schrijven maar nu zijn we toch heusch broer en zuster geworden en zou ik zoo erg graag willen dat je ook mij een beetje kende en als ’t kon een beetje van me hield.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Wat <hi rend="italics">mij</hi> betreft – is het al lang zoo – èn van Wil en van Theo heb ik zooveel van je gehoord – en hier in huis zijn zoo’n massa dingen die aan je herinneren<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>als ik een aardig kannetje of vaasje of zoo iets vind dan is het altijd: dat heeft Vincent nog gekocht of dat vond V<c type="kp">_</c> zoo aardig<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – er gaat haast geen dag om dat we niet over je spreken.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Ik spreek nog altijd maar over “ons huis” en kan er nog maar niet aan wennen om te zeggen “’t appartement”<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> ik wou dat je ’t eens zag hoe aardig en gezellig Theo alles in orde had gemaakt al vóór ik kwam. De slaapkamer vooral is zoo lief, heel licht en veel rose is er in – en ’s morgens van uit bed zie ik juist op ’t mooie bloeiende perzikboompje van je,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> dat me iederen morgen zoo vriendelijk aankijkt. Boven de piano 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>in onze salon (we hebben er een van tante Cornelie ge<c type="shy">-</c>kregen) hangt ook een schilderij van je – een groot waar ik heel veel van houd – ’t is een landschap bij Arles<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> De salle à manger hangt ook vol maar Theo is nog niet tevreden over de schikking en iederen Zondagmorgen wordt doorgebracht met ’t verhangen en verschikken van alles.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> ’t Is zoo heerlijk als Theo Zondags een heelen dag t’huis is – ik weet wel dat ik als kind altijd zooveel van de Zondagen hield omdat ze bij ons t’huis zoo erg gezellig en prettig waren – (iets wat de meeste menschen zich niet konden begrijpen) maar nu nog veel meer. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>’t Was dan ook Maandag voor mij een dubbel feest toen met de opening van de tentoonstelling<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> alle zaken gesloten waren – we zijn natuurlijk <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> naar de tentoonstelling gegaan maar hebben ons op onze eigen manier geamuseerd. Parijs zag er wel mooi uit dien dag – ik hoop zoo dat ik er van zal gaan houden zooals Theo doet – maar soms ben ik er bang voor dat ’t niet zoo zal zijn – ’t is zoo druk en rommelig en ik houd zooveel van de stilte! Ik ben dan ook erg blij dat we in onze stille cité wonen – ’t is wel geen aristocratisch maar een echt typisch buurtje – aan den overkant een groot schildersatelier 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>en vlak vóór ’t huis een paar heele kleine tuintjes – in elk een prieeltje en een paar seringen, die op ’t oogenblik heerlijk in bloei staan. Wat zijn er toch veel mooie bloemen in Parijs – als ik iets goeds van P<c type="kp">_</c> moest opnoemen zou dat wel een van de eerste dingen zijn!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Er zijn al heel veel kennissen van Theo ons komen opzoeken ’s avonds – gisteravond b:v. was ’t een heele reunie – Pizarro en zijn zoon<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Isaacson en de jonge Nibbrig<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> (maar ik weet niet of je dien wel kent) en mijn broer – die al sedert eenigen tijd bij ons komt eten omdat zijn vrouw naar Holland is.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ik wou maar 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>dat ik wat beter Fransch kon spreken – ik kan me wel redden alleen<c type="kk">/</c> met boodschappen doen en met de femme de ménage<c type="kk">/</c> maar een discours gaande houden en dan nog wel als Theo er bij is – dat vind ik verschrikkelijk. Ik heb me ook maar niet gewaagd aan een Franschen brief – hoewel ik eigenlijk wel wist dat je het liever had maar Wil zei me dat ze ook altijd maar Hollandsch schreef. Zoodra ik me een beetje Parisienne voel worden<c type="kk">/</c> begin ik in ’t Fransch – is dat goed?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Lies en Wil hebben een plannetje om samen dezen zomer hier te komen<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>wat zou ik dat gezellig vinden<c type="kk">/</c> vooral om Wil eens hier te hebben – wat zou ze me uitlachen – want zij is zelf zoo’n handig huishoudstertje. Zij kan alles – en ik – ik zal maar eerlijk opbiechten – ik kan niets – ik heb al tweemaal de rijst en eenmaal de pruimen laten verbranden – die arme Theo, hij moet maar alles slikken!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Anders hebben we ’t heel goed samen – we zijn van<c type="shy">-</c>daag nu al drie weken getrouwd – het schijnt me lang en kort geleden – en ’t is ons niets, niets vreemd meer – net of we altijd bij elkaar zijn geweest. ’t Ergste is maar 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>dat ik er nog niets als een getrouwde dame uitzie – gisteren ging ik onzen bakker betalen en de man wou maar niet begrijpen dat ik zelf Madame van Gogh was en noemde me voortdurend Mademoiselle, dat is toch te erg!</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Ik moet voor ’t dejeuner gaan zorgen want over een paar minuten komt Theo t’huis – voor vandaag zeg ik je dus maar goedendag – ik hoop dat ik je niet al te erg heb verveeld – maar ik ben zoo gewend den laatsten tijd om zoowel naar Breda als naar Amsterdam al die kleinigheden te schrijven die ze zoo graag weten<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> dat ik geen serieuzen brief meer <hi rend="italics">kan</hi> schrijven – later zal ’t wel weer beter worden. Met hartelijke groeten en je alle goeds toewenschend<c type="kk">/</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">je liefhebbend zusje</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Jo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Paris 8 May ’89</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Dearest brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It’s high time that your new little <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">sister</rs> came to chat with you and didn’t always just let Theo convey her regards. When we weren’t married yet I always thought: Well, I don’t really dare to write to Vincent about everything yet, but now we really have become brother and sister, and I would so much like you to know me a little and, if possible, love me a little.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">For <hi rend="italics">my</hi> part — it’s been the case for a long time — I’ve heard so much about you, both from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> and from Theo — and here in the house there are masses of things that are reminders of you, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> when I find a nice little jug or a vase or something, then it’s always: Vincent bought that or V. liked that so much<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — scarcely a day passes when we don’t speak of you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I still keep talking about ‘our house’ and just can’t get used to saying ‘the apartment’;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I wish you could see how nice and cosy Theo had already arranged everything before I came. The bedroom, in particular, is so sweet, very light and lots of pink in it — and in bed in the morning I look straight at that beautiful flowering peach tree of yours,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> which looks at me in such a friendly way every morning. There’s also one of your paintings hanging above the piano 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> in our drawing room (we got one from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Aunt Cornelie</rs>) — a large one which I like very much — it’s a landscape near Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> The dining room is full too, but Theo’s not happy with the arrangement yet, and every Sunday morning is spent rehanging and arranging everything.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> It’s so wonderful when Theo’s home for the whole day on Sundays — I remember that I always loved Sundays so much as a child because they were so very cosy and pleasant at home — (something that most people couldn’t understand) but now even more. 
    <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> So Monday it was a double treat for me when all the businesses were closed for the opening of the exhibition<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> — naturally we did <hi rend="italics">not</hi> go to the exhibition but amused ourselves in our own way. Paris did look lovely that day — I do so hope that I’ll grow to love it as Theo does — but sometimes I’m afraid that it won’t be the case — it’s so busy and chaotic, and I love quiet so much! So I’m very glad that we live in our quiet quarter — it’s not an aristocratic one but a real, typical neighbourhood — a large artist’s studio over the road 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> and right in front of the house a couple of very tiny little gardens — in each an arbour and a couple of lilacs, which are presently flowering beautifully. What a lot of beautiful flowers there are in Paris — if I had to name something good about P., that would be one of the first things!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">A great many of Theo’s acquaintances have already come to see us in the evenings — yesterday evening, for instance, was a whole reunion — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> and his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267">son</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> and young <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1245">Nibbrig</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> (but I don’t know whether you know him) and my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">brother</rs> — who’s been coming to eat with us for some time now because his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">wife</rs>’s gone to Holland.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I just wish 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> that I spoke rather better French — I can manage on my own, doing the shopping and with the charwoman, but carrying on a conversation, and particularly when Theo’s there — I find that awful. I haven’t dared try to write a letter in French either — even though I actually knew that you’d prefer it, but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> told me that she always just wrote in Dutch. As soon as I feel a bit of a Parisienne, I’ll start writing in French — is that all right?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> have a little plan to come here together this summer, 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> how I’d like that, particularly having Wil here for a time — how she’d laugh at me — for she’s such a clever little housekeeper herself. She can do everything — and I — I’ll confess honestly — I can’t do anything — I’ve already burnt the rice twice and the plums once — that poor Theo, he just has to swallow everything!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Apart from that we get along very well together — we’ve already been married three weeks today — it seems to me a long and short time ago — and nothing, nothing is strange to us any more — just as if we’ve always been together. The worst thing though is 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/> that I don’t yet look anything like a married lady — yesterday I went to pay our baker and the man simply wouldn’t understand that I was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Madame van Gogh</rs> and kept calling me Mademoiselle, it’s really too bad!</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I must see about lunch because Theo will be home in a few minutes — so I’ll say goodbye to you for today — I hope that I haven’t bored you too much — but of late I’ve got so used to writing to both Breda and Amsterdam about all those little things that they so like to know<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> that I <hi rend="italics">can’t</hi> write a serious letter any more — it will get better again later. With warm regards, and wishing you all the best,</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">your loving little sister</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Parijs 8 Mei ’89’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Most likely enclosed with <ref target="let770.xml">letter 770</ref>.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The collection of the Van Gogh Museum contains a copper vase and an earthenware vase from Theo’s apartment; they were depicted by Vincent in various Paris still lifes (including <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vase with Chinese asters and gladioli </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_810">F 234 / JH 1168</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Fritillaries in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_813">F 213 / JH 1247</rs>)).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s apartment was at 8 cité Pigalle in Montmartre. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let745.xml#n-16">See letter 745, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This was probably<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Small pear tree in blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2590">F 405 / JH 1394</rs>), which Theo had proposed in November 1888 to exhibit at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let721.xml#n-3">See letter 721, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let887.xml">letter 887</ref> that <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The harvest </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2621">F 412 / JH 1440</rs>) hung above the piano. The piano was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">Aunt Cornelie</rs>’s wedding present to Theo and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> (FR b923 and b940).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>At Theo’s apartment in Paris, works by Vincent must have been shifted around continually. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> wrote about this on 25 May 1889 to her sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_24">Mien</rs>: ‘there are always two or three unframed paintings standing around our place, being tried out here and there’ (FR b4288). For example, after receiving a new consignment of paintings (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let767.xml">letter 767</ref>), Theo decided to hang <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">La berceuse</hi> in the guestroom (FR b2848). In her introduction to the letters, Jo wrote: ‘the blossoming orchards hung in the bedroom, the Potato Eaters in the dining room above the fireplace, the large landscape from Arles and the nocturnal view of the Rhône ... in the sitting room’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De brieven </hi>1990, vol. 1, p. 36.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The World Exhibition, held in Paris from 5 May to 5 November 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Camille Pissarro</rs>’s son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267">Lucien</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The Dutch artist <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1245">Ferdinand Hart Nibbrig</rs> was 23 at the time. From October 1888 until July 1889 he was in Paris, where he studied at the Académie Julian and in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Fernand Cormon</rs>’s studio. In a letter to the art critic Albert Plasschaert of 8 January 1904, he wrote: ‘Spent a lot of time in Paris with Theo van Gogh; Vincent was in the South. Saw at Theo’s works by Claude Monet, Pissarro, de Gas etc.’ See J.M. Joosten, ‘Van Gogh publikaties. De eerste kennismaking met het werk van Vincent van Gogh in Nederland’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Museumjournaal</hi> 14-3 (June 1969), p. 156.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> was married to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Annie van der Linden</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let738.xml#n-3">See letter 738, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> lived in Breda; Jo’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs> lived in Amsterdam.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    