<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Sunday, 9 June 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let779"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b642 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>779</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>594</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>781</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-06-09">Sunday, 9 June 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0642 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0642 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000877_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0642 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0642 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000878_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci beaucoup de l’envoi de toiles<c type="kk">/</c> couleurs<c type="kk">/</c> brosses<c type="kk">/</c> tabac &amp; chocolat<c type="kk">/</c> qui m’est parvenu en bon état<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’en ai été bien content car je languissais un peu après le travail<c type="kp">_</c> Aussi est-il que depuis quelques jours je sors dehors pour travailler dans les environs<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Ta dernière lettre était si j’ai bonne mémoire du 21 Mai<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> depuis je n’ai pas encore de tes nouvelles que seulement que M<c type="kp">_</c> Peyron me disait avoir reçu une lettre de toi.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> J’espère que ta santé va bien ainsi que celle de ta femme.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">M. Peyron a l’intention d’aller à Paris voir l’exposition et alors te rendra une visite<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Que te dirai-je de neuf<c type="kk">/</c> pas grand chôse. J’ai en train deux paysages (toiles de 30) de vues prises dans les collines<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">l’un est la campagne que j’aperçois de la fenêtre de ma chambre à coucher. Sur l’avant plan un champ de blé ravagé et flanqué par terre après un orage<c type="kp">_</c> Un mur de cloture et au dela<c type="kk">/</c> de la verdure grise de quelques oliviers<c type="kk">/</c> des cabanes et des collines<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin dans le haut de la toile un grand nuage blanc &amp; gris noyé dans l’azur.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> C’est un paysage d’une simplicité extrême – aussi de coloration. Cela irait comme pendant à cette étude de chambre à coucher qui est endommagée<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Lorsque la chôse représentée en tant que style est absolument d’accord et un avec la façon de la représenter<c type="kk">/</c> n’est ce pas là ce qui fait la tenue d’une chose d’art.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">C’est pourquoi un pain de ménage en fait de peinture est surtout bon lorsqu’il est peint par Chardin<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Maintenant l’art Egyptien par exemple<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui en fait l’extraordinaire<c type="kk">/</c> n’est ce pas que ces sereins rois calmes<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>sages et doux<c type="kk">/</c> patients<c type="kk">/</c> bons<c type="kk">/</c> semblent ne pas pouvoir être autrement qu’ils ne sont; éternellement des agriculteurs adorateurs du soleil<c type="kp">_</c> Comme j’aurais voulu voir à l’exposition une maison Egyptienne construite par Jules Garnier l’architecte – peinte en rouge<c type="kk">/</c> jaune et bleu avec un jardin divisé régulierement en parterres par des rangées de briques – l’habitation des êtres que nous ne connaissons qu’à l’etat de momies ou en granit<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Mais voilà<c type="kk">/</c> pour revenir à ces moutons<c type="kk">/</c> les artistes Egyptiens donc ayant une <hi rend="italics">foi</hi><c type="kk">/</c> travaillant de sentiment et d’instinct<c type="kk">/</c> expriment toutes ces chôses insaisisables: la bonté<c type="kk">/</c> la patience infinie<c type="kk">/</c> la sagesse<c type="kk">/</c> la sérénité<c type="kk">/</c> par quelques courbes savantes et des proportions merveilleuses<c type="kp">_</c> C’est pour dire encore une fois<c type="kk">/</c> alors que la chôse representée et la facon de la representer s’accordent la chôse a du style et de la tenue.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Ainsi aussi la servante dans la grande fresque de Leys lorsqu’elle est gravée par Braquemond devient une nouvelle oeuvre d’art<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – ou le petit liseur de Meissonier lorsque c’est Jacquemart qui le grave<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – puisque la <hi rend="italics">facon de graver</hi> fait un avec la chose representée<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Désirant conserver cette étude de la chambre à coucher<c type="kk">/</c> si tu veux me la renvoyer lorsqu’on m’enverra de la toile<c type="kk">/</c> roulée<c type="kk">/</c> je vais la repeindre. J’avais d’abord voulu la faire rentoiler parceque je ne croyais pas pouvoir la refaire. Cependant ma tête se calmant depuis<c type="kk">/</c> maintenant je peux bien la refaire.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">C’est que dans le nombre des choses qu’on fabrique il y en a toujours qu’on a davantage senties ou voulues et qu’on veut quand même garder.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Lorsque je vois un tableau qui m’intrigue je me demande toujours involontairement “dans quelle maison<c type="kk">/</c> chambre<c type="kk">/</c> coin de chambre<c type="kk">/</c> chez quelle personne ferait-il bien<c type="kk">/</c> serait-il à sa place.”</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ainsi les tableaux de Hals<c type="kk">/</c> de Rembrandt<c type="kk">/</c> de v.d. Meer ne sont chez eux que dans l’ancienne maison Hollandaise.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Or les impressionistes – c’est toujours encore que si un intérieur n’est pas complet sans oeuvre d’art<c type="kk">/</c> un tableau n’y est pas non plus s’il ne fait pas un avec un entourage original et resultant de l’époque dans laquelle il a été produit. Et je ne sais si les impressionistes valent mieux que leur temps ou plutôt ne le valent pas encore.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">En un mot<c type="kk">/</c> y a-t-il des ames et des interieurs de maison plus importants que ce qui a été exprimee par la peinture<c type="kk">/</c> je suis porté à le croire.</p>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">J’ai vu une annonce d’exposition prochaine d’impressionistes nommés Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c> Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> Anquetin et autres noms<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Suis donc porté à croire qu’il s’est encore fait une nouvelle secte pas moins infaillible que les autres déjà existants<c type="kp">_</c> Etait ce de cette exposition-là que tu me parlais<c type="kp">_</c> Quelles tempêtes dans des verres d’eau<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">La santé va bien – comme ci comme ça<c type="kk">/</c> je me sens avec mon travail plus heureux ici que je ne pourrais l’être dehors. En restant assez longtemps ici<c type="kk">/</c> j’aurai pris une conduite réglée et il en résultera à la longue plus d’ordre dans la vie et moins d’impres<c type="shy">-</c>sionabilité<c type="kp">_</c> Et ce serait autant de gagné. D’ailleurs je n’aurais pas le courage de recommencer dehors<c type="kp">_</c> Je suis une fois<c type="kk">/</c> et encore accompagné<c type="kk">/</c> alle dans le village<c type="kp">_</c> rien que la vue des gens et des choses me faisaient un effet comme si j’allais m’évanouir et je me trouvais fort mal. Devant la nature c’est le sentiment du travail qui me tient. Mais enfin c’est pour te dire qu’en dedans de moi il doit y avoir eu quelque emotion trop forte qui m’a foutue cela et je ne sais pas du tout ce qui a pu l’occasionner<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Je m’ennuie à mourir à des moments après le travail et pourtant je n’ai aucune envie de recommencer<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Le médecin qui vient de passer dit qu’il n’ira à Paris que dans quelques semaines<c type="kk">/</c> n’attends donc pas encore sa visite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">J’espère que tu m’ecriras bientôt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Pendant ce mois ci il me faudra bien encore</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">8 tubes blanc d’argent</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">6    ,,     Vert veronese</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">2    ,,     Outremer</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">2    ,,     Cobalt</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">2 Ocre jaune</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">1   ,,   rouge</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">1 terre sienne naturelle</p>
      
<p xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">1 noir d’ivoire<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>


<p xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">C’est drôle que toutes les fois que j’essaye de me raisonner pour me rendre compte des chôses – pourquoi je suis venu ici et qu’en somme ce n’est qu’un accident comme un autre – un terrible effroi et horreur me saisit et m’empêche de réfléchir. Il est vrai que cela tend vaguement à diminuer mais aussi cela me semble prouver qu’il y a effectivement je ne sais quoi de derangé dans ma cervelle.
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> mais c’est stupéfiant d’avoir peur ainsi de rien et de ne pas pouvoir se rappeler<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">Seulement tu peux y compter que je fais mon possible pour redevenir actif et peut etre utile<c type="kk">/</c> dans ce sens au moins que je veux faire de meilleurs tableaux qu’auparavant<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Dans le paysage d’ici bien des choses font souvent penser à Ruysdael mais la figure des laboureurs manque<c type="kp">_</c> Chez nous partout et à tout temps de l’annee on voit des hommes<c type="kk">/</c> des femmes<c type="kk">/</c> des enfants<c type="kk">/</c> des animaux au travail et ici pas le tiers de cela et encore ce n’est pas le travailleur franc du nord<c type="kp">_</c> Cela semble labourer d’une main gauche et lâche<c type="kk">/</c> sans entrain<c type="kp">_</c> Peutêtre est ce là une idée que je m’en suis faite à tort<c type="kk">/</c> je l’espère au moins<c type="kk">/</c> n’étant pas du pays<c type="kp">_</c> Mais cela rend les choses plus froides qu’on oserait croire en lisant Tartarin<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> qui peutêtre a été expulsé déja depuis de longues années avec toute sa famille.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">Ecris moi surtout bientôt car ta lettre tarde bien à venir<c type="kk">/</c> j’espère que tu te portes bien<c type="kp">_</c> C’est une grande consolation pour moi de savoir que tu ne vis plus seul<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Si un mois ou un autre il te serait trop à charge de m’envoyer de la couleur<c type="kk">/</c> toile &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> alors ne les envoie pas car saches le bien qu’il vaut mieux vivre que de faire de l’art abstraite<c type="shy">-</c>ment<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.38" n="38">Et avant tout il faut que ta maison ne soit pas triste ni morte<c type="kp">_</c> Cela d’abord et la peinture ensuite<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.39" n="39">Puis je me sens tenté de recommencer avec les couleurs plus simples<c type="kk">/</c> les ocres par exemple<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.40" n="40">Est ce qu’un van Goyen est laid parceque c’est peint en pleine huile avec fort peu de couleur neutre<c type="kk">/</c> ou un Michel.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.41" n="41">Mon sous bois avec du lierre est complètement terminé<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> j’ai grande envie de te l’envoyer aussitot sec assez pour être roulé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.42" n="42">Avec une bien forte poignée de main à toi et à ta femme<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.43" n="43">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.44" n="44">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks very much for the consignment of canvases, colours, brushes, tobacco and chocolate, which reached me in good order.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I was very glad of it, for I was pining for work a little. Also, for a few days now I’ve been going outside to work in the neighbourhood.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Your last letter was dated 21 May, if I remember rightly.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I’ve had no news of you yet since then, except that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> told me he’d received a letter from you.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I hope that you’re in good health, and your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> intends to go to Paris to see the exhibition and then pay you a visit.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">What can I tell you that’s new, not much. I have two landscapes on the go (no. 30 canvases) of views taken in the hills.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">One is the countryside that I glimpse from the window of my bedroom. In the foreground a field of wheat, ravaged and knocked to the ground after a storm. A boundary wall and beyond, grey foliage of a few olive trees, huts and hills. Finally, at the top of the painting a large white and grey cloud swamped by the azure.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> It’s a landscape of extreme simplicity — in terms of coloration as well. It would be suitable as a pendant to that study of the bedroom that’s damaged.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">When the thing depicted is stylistically absolutely in agreement and at one with the manner of depiction, isn’t that what creates the quality of a piece of art?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">That’s why, as regards painting, a household loaf is above all good when it’s painted by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Now Egyptian art, for example, what makes it extraordinary, is it not that those calm, serene kings, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> wise and gentle, patient, good, seem unable to be other than they are; eternally farmers who worship the sun. How I’d have liked to see an Egyptian house in the exhibition, built by the architect <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1037">Jules Garnier</rs> – painted in red, yellow and blue with a garden divided regularly into beds by rows of bricks – the dwelling of the people we know only in the state of mummies or in granite.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">But there you are, to get back to the point, since the Egyptian artists thus have a <hi rend="italics">faith</hi>, working from feeling and instinct, they express all these intangible things: goodness, infinite patience, wisdom, serenity, with a few masterly curves and marvellous proportions. That’s to say once more, when the thing depicted and the manner of depicting it are in accord, the thing has style and quality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Thus also the servant girl in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Leys</rs>’s great fresco, when she’s engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Braquemond</rs>, becomes a new work of art<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs>’s little reader when it’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1118">Jacquemart</rs> who engraves him<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> – since the <hi rend="italics">manner of engraving</hi> and the thing depicted are as one.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">As I want to keep this study of the bedroom, if you would send it back to me when I’m sent canvas, rolled up, I’ll repaint it. Initially I’d wanted to have it lined because I didn’t think I’d be able to do it again. However, as my mind has grown calmer since, I can indeed redo it now.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">The thing is, among the number of things that one makes there are always some that one has felt or wanted more and which one wants to keep all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">When I see a painting that intrigues me, I can never help asking myself, ‘in what house, room, corner of the room, in whose home would it do well, would it be in its rightful place’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Thus the paintings of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Hals</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1421">Vermeer</rs> are only at home in the old Dutch house.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Now the Impressionists – once again, if an interior isn’t complete without a work of art, neither is a painting if it isn’t at one with original surroundings, resulting from the era in which it was produced. And I don’t know if the Impressionists are worth more than their time, or rather aren’t yet worth as much.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">In a word, are there souls and interiors of houses that are more important than what has been expressed by painting, I’m inclined to believe so. 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I’ve seen an advertisement for a forthcoming exhibition of Impressionists called <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_328">Anquetin</rs> and other names.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Am therefore inclined to believe that another new sect has been formed, no less infallible than the others that already exist. Was this the exhibition you were talking to me about? What storms in teacups.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">I’m in good health – so-so, I feel happier with my work here than I could outside. By staying here a fairly long time, I’ll have acquired controlled behaviour, and in the long run the result will be more order in my life and less impressionability. And that would be something gained. Besides, I wouldn’t have the courage to begin again outside. I once went into the village — accompanied, at that. The mere sight of the people and things had an effect on me as if I was going to faint, and I felt very ill. In the face of nature it’s the feeling for work that keeps me going. But anyway, that’s to tell you that there must have been some over-strong emotion inside me that brought that about, and I have no idea what could have caused it.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">I’m bored to death at times after work, and yet I have no desire to begin again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">The doctor who has just come by says that he won’t be going to Paris for a few weeks yet, so don’t expect his visit for the time being.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I hope that you’ll write to me soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">This month I’ll again really be in need of</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">8 tubes silver white</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">6 ,,  Veronese Green</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">2 ,,  Ultramarine</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">2 ,,  Cobalt</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">2   yellow Ochre</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">1  red ,,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">1  raw sienna</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">1  ivory black<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">It’s funny that every time I try to reason with myself in order to get a clear picture of things – why I came here, and that after all it’s only an accident like any other – a terrible terror and horror seizes me and prevents me from thinking. It’s true that it tends vaguely to diminish, but it also seems to me to prove that there is indeed something, I don’t know what, disturbed in my brain. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/> But it’s astounding to be afraid of nothing like this, and not to be able to remember.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">Only you can count on the fact that I’m doing everything I can to become active and perhaps useful again, in this sense at least, that I want to do better paintings than before.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">Many things in the landscape here often recall <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs>, but the figure of the ploughman is lacking. In our country one sees men, women, children, animals at work everywhere and at all times of the year, and here not a third of that, and in addition they’re not the honest workers of the north. They seem to work the land in an awkward, lax way, without energy. Perhaps I’ve got hold of the wrong idea here, I hope so at least, since I’m not from round here. But it makes things colder than one would dare think from reading Tartarin,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> who had perhaps been expelled many years ago with his entire family.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Above all write to me soon, for your letter is very slow in coming, I hope that you’re well. It’s a great consolation for me to know that you’re no longer living alone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">If one month or another it should be too difficult for you to send me colours, canvas &amp;c., then don’t send them, for believe me it’s better to live than to do art in an absent-minded way. 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/> And before everything else, your house must be neither sad nor dismal. That first and painting next.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Then I feel tempted to begin again with the simpler colours, the ochres for example.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.39" n="39">Is a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1056">Van Goyen</rs> ugly because it’s painted all in oils with very little neutral colour, or a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1228">Michel</rs>?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.40" n="40">My undergrowth with ivy is completely finished,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I want very much to send it to you immediately, as soon as it’s dry enough to be rolled up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.41" n="41">With a really strong handshake to you and your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.42" n="42">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.43" n="43">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On 9 June 1889, Peyron thanked Theo for paying Vincent’s expenses (100 francs); he also confirmed receipt of the shipment of canvas, brushes and paint (FR b1060). Furthermore, he said about Vincent that ‘for several days now he has been leaving the house to take some viewpoints in the countryside’. Given that Van Gogh writes this himself in the present letter and that in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 Jo van Gogh-Bonger dated it ‘9 June 1889’ (possibly relying on a postmark), we have dated it to Sunday, 9 June 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml">letter 776</ref> Van Gogh had ordered canvas and paint, and in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let777.xml">letter 777</ref> he had asked for brushes and more canvas. Theo’s account book records under ‘Account Vincent’ on 6 June 1889 a payment of 197 francs to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_784">Tasset &amp; Lhote</rs>, probably for the order mentioned here. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 44.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml">letter 774</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Theo had written to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Peyron</rs> on 23 May; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let777.xml#n-1">see letter 777, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The 1889 World Exhibition was held in Paris from 5 May to 5 November. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Dr Peyron</rs> visited Theo in the second half of September 1889 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let806.xml">see letter 806</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh describes one of these canvases immediately after this (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-6">n. 6</ref>); he says it depicts the view from his room, so the ‘view taken in the hills’ must refer to the other landscape. This was the underlying depiction of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ravine</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2853">F 662 / JH 1804</rs>), which he copied in late June or early July in the drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wild vegetation</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2805">F 1542 / JH 1742</rs>). See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml#n-16">letter 784, n. 16.</ref> In this landscape he did what he had recently resolved to do: paint the colour effects of the flowers in the fields (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let777.xml">letter 777</ref>). At the beginning of October he painted over it (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let810.xml#n-15">see letter 810, n. 15</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield after a storm </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2796">F 611 / JH 1723</rs>). It measures 70.5 x 88.5 cm and is therefore slightly smaller than a no. 30 canvas.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>) had suffered slight damage; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml#n-29">see letter 776, n. 29.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_939">Chardin</rs> often depicted loaves of bread in his still lifes and genre pieces. Van Gogh probably knew <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_844">The purveyor</rs></hi>, 1739, and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_845">The brioche</rs></hi>, 1763 from the Louvre. See Pierre Rosenberg, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Chardin</hi>. Paris 1983, pp. 97, 108-109, cat. nos. 115 B, 167.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>At the 1889 World Exhibition <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1037">Charles Garnier</rs> built a street with 39 dwellings running from Champ de Mars to Trocadéro. Each house or hut represented a culture and a stage in the history of habitation from prehistory to modern times. The dwellings, which were nearly lifesize, were built with authentic materials. This part of the exhibition (‘Dessins et modèles d’architecture’) was titled ‘Histoire de l’habitation’. See exhib. cat. Paris<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi>1889, p. 104, and Paul Greenhalgh, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ephemeral Vistas. The Expositions Universelles, great Exhibitions and World’s Fairs, 1851-1939</hi>. Manchester 1988, p. 20. Garnier's first name was Charles, not Jules. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let809.xml">Letter 809</ref> reveals that Van Gogh had obtained the information about the Egyptian house from an illustrated journal, though it is not known which one.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>On <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs>’s etchings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_624">The servant</rs></hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2163">The table</rs></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2164">The servant at the table</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let542.xml#n-2">see letter 542, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1118">Jacquemart</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_249">The reader</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-7">see letter 686, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>The paint and canvas that Vincent asked Theo to order were usually sent directly to Vincent by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_784">Tasset &amp; Lhote</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>On the occasion of the World Exhibition, the ‘Groupe Impressionniste et Synthétiste’, with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> as its leader, held an exhibition from 8 June through October 1889 in the Café Volpini, situated next to the Palais du Champs de Mars, where the official exhibition took place. A total of 94 works were on display: 17 by Gauguin, 20 by Schuffenecker, 23 by Bernard, 10 by Laval, 7 by Anquetin, 7 by Louis Roy, 5 by Léon Fauché, 3 by Georges-Daniel de Monfreid and 2 by Ludovic Nemo (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s pseudonym). See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-5 and Merlhès 1995, pp. 26-32. Theo had been approached to exhibit work by Vincent, but declined because he disapproved of the way the exhibition was organized. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let781.xml#n-3">See letter 781, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh later added ‘2 yellow ochre ... ivory black’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s novels <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_459">Tartarin de Tarascon</ref> </hi>and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">see letter 583, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Trees with ivy in the garden of the asylum </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2789">F 609 / JH 1693</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    