<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Tuesday, 2 July 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let785"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b713 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>785</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W13</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>788</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-07-02">Tuesday, 2 July 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0713" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0713" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000968_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">de ces jours ci j’ai déjà commencé une autre lettre en reponse à la tienne mais je me suis aperçu que je n’avais guère la tête assez à moi pour écrire. Je te remercie toi et Lies du livre de Rod<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> que j’ai fini et que je te renverrai bientôt. Le titre terrible<c type="kk">/</c> le sens de la vie<c type="kk">/</c> m’effrayait un peu mais comme il n’en est guere parlé dans ce volume heureusement<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai été assez content de lire quelque chôse ayant des traits de famille avec le philosophe sous les toits de Souvestre<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> ou avec Monsieur<c type="kk">/</c> madame et bébé de Droz.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> La morale en est qu’un monsieur finit par préférer dans des cas à vivre avec une gentille femme bien dévouée et son enfant<c type="kk">/</c> à la vie de restaurant<c type="kk">/</c> boulevard et café qu’il avait sans trop d’excès préalablement menée. C’est très gentil sans doute<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">En effet c’est à remarquer que la maladie de la bonne madame Duquesne ait prit une fin encore inattendue<c type="kp">_</c> Cela doit avoir eté quand meme un jour de bien grande delivrance pour elle.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Si tu dis dans ta lettre que lorsque tu en vois tant d’autres dans la vie qui<c type="kk">/</c> cherchant leur propre chemin te paraissant peutêtre faire plus de chemin que toi – vont et viennent – que te dirai-je – que moi aussi parfois ai un sentiment de stupefaction devant ma propre vie et d’ailleurs vis à vis de plusieurs autres vies d’ouvriers dans mon métier<c type="kp">_</c> Je viens d’envoyer à Theo une douzaine de dessins d’après des toiles que j’ai en train<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> alors que tout le reste de ma vie est absolument aussi inepte qu’elle l’etait du temps qu’à 12 ans j’étais dans une pension où je n’apprenais absolument rien.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Enormement de peintres qui certes ne feraient pas mes 12 toiles ni en 2 mois ni en 12 sont en ville ou à la campagne etant consideré comme des artistes et comme des gens intelligents. Mais crois moi je dis cela pour être explicatif et non pas parceque je verrais urgence ou possibilité ou désir de changer les chôses<c type="kp">_</c> Nous ne connaissons guère la vie<c type="kk">/</c> nous ignorons à tel point ses dessous<c type="kk">/</c> nous vivons enfin à une époque où tout parait radoter et à l’état vaccillant et ce n’est pas être malheureux que de trouver un devoir qui nous force à rester tranquille dans notre coin<c type="kk">/</c> occupé d’un peu de besogne plus simple de certains devoirs qui gardent quelque raison d’être.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">De ces jours où nous vivons on risque de revenir d’une bataille honteux d’avoir bataillé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Ainsi mon ami qui était avec moi à Arles<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> et quelques autres ont organisé ainsi une exposition où j’aurais participé en bonne santé<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Et qu’est ce qu’ils ont pu faire – presque rien – et que dans leurs toiles cependant il y avait du neuf<c type="kk">/</c> du bon<c type="kk">/</c> de quoi me faire plaisir et de m’enthousiasmer par exemple moi<c type="kk">/</c> cela je te l’assure. Entre artistes nous ne savons plus que nous dire<c type="kk">/</c> nous ne savons s’il faut en rire ou en pleurer et ne faisant ma foi ni l’un ni l’autre nous sommes encore le plus content lorsque nous nous trouvons en possession d’un peu de couleur et de toile<c type="kk">/</c> ce dont nous manquons aussi quelquefois et qu’au moins nous puissions travailler. Mais toute idée de vie reguliere<c type="kk">/</c> toute idée de reveiller en nous mêmes ou en d’autres des idees ou des sensations douces<c type="kk">/</c> tout cela doit nécessairement nous paraître pure utopies.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ainsi quoique hier on ait payé plus d’un demi million de francs l’angelus de Millet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ne vas pas croire que davantage d’âmes ressentiront ce qu’il y avait dans l’âme de Millet. ou que des bourgeois ou des ouvriers commenceront à mettre dans leurs maisons par exemple la lithographie de l’Angelus de Millet en question<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ne vas pas croire que pour cela les peintres qui travaillent encore en Bretagne dans les paysans ayent davantage d’encouragement<c type="kk">/</c> moins de la meme disette noire qui a toujours entouré Millet<c type="kk">/</c> davantage de courage surtout.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Hélas souvent le souffle et la foi nous font défaut<c type="kk">/</c> à tort certes mais – et voila où nous revenons à nos moutons – si cependant nous voulons travailler il faut nous soumettre et à la dureté opiniâtre du temps et à notre isolement quelquefois dur à supporter comme l’exil. Or devant nous<c type="kk">/</c> après nos années ainsi relativement perdues<c type="kk">/</c> la pauvreté<c type="kk">/</c> la maladie<c type="kk">/</c> la vieillesse<c type="kk">/</c> la folie et toujours l’exil. C’est bien le moment de dire “bénie soit Thébé<c type="kk">/</c> fille de Telhui<c type="kk">/</c> prêtresse d’Osiris<c type="kk">/</c> qui ne s’est jamais plainte de personne”.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Chérir la mémoire des bonnes gens<c type="kk">/</c> est ce qu’en somme cela ne vaudrait pas mieux que d’être dans les ambitieux<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Je suis assez absorbé dans la lecture de Shakespeare que Theo m’a envoyé ici où j’aurai enfin le calme nécessaire pour faire un peu de lecture plus difficile. J’ai pris d’abord la serie des rois dont j’ai deja lu Richard <hi>II</hi><c type="kk">/</c> Henry <hi>IV</hi><c type="kk">/</c> Henry <hi>V</hi> et une partie de Henry <hi>VI</hi> – ces drames-là m’étaient le plus inconnus. As tu jamais lu King Lear<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Mais enfin je crois que je ne t’engagerai pas trop à lire des livres si dramatiques alors que moi-même revenant de cette lecture suis toujours obligé d’aller regarder un brin d’herbe<c type="kk">/</c> une branche de pin<c type="kk">/</c> un épi de blé<c type="kk">/</c> pour me calmer.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Ainsi si tu veux faire comme font les artistes regarde les pavots blancs et rouge avec les feuilles bleuatres<c type="kk">/</c> avec ces boutons s’élevant sur des tiges à courbes gracieuses. Les heures de trouble et de combat viennent bien nous trouver sans qu’on aille les chercher.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">La séparation de Cor sera dure. et elle est bien prochaine<c type="kp">_</c> Que peut on faire autre chose<c type="kk">/</c> en songeant à toute chose dont on ne comprend pas la raison<c type="kk">/</c> que de regarder les champs de blé<c type="kp">_</c> Leur histoire est la nôtre car nous qui vivons de pain<c type="kk">/</c> ne sommes nous pas nous-même du blé en considerable partie<c type="kk">/</c> au moins devons nous pas nous soumettre à croitre impuissant de nous mouvoir<c type="kk">/</c> comme une plante<c type="kk">/</c> relativement à ce que parfois notre imagination désire<c type="kk">/</c> et à etre fauché lorsque nous serons mûrs comme lui.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je te le dis<c type="kk">/</c> pour moi je crois que ce soit le plus sage de ne pas desirer retablir<c type="kk">/</c> de ne pas désirer reprendre des forces plus que maintenant et je m’y habituerai probablement<c type="kk">/</c> à être cassé<c type="kp">_</c> Un peu plus tot un peu plus tard<c type="kk">/</c> qu’est ce que cela peut me faire.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Ce que tu écris de la santé de Theo je le sais tout à fait<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai neamoins l’espérance que la vie de ménage le rétablira tout à fait. Sa femme je la crois sage et aimante assez pour avoir beaucoup de soins de lui et d’y veiller qu’il ne mange pas exclusivement du manger de restaurant mais qu’il retrouve 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>la cuisine Hollandaise. C’est bien cela la cuisine Hollandaise et qu’elle se fasse donc cuisiniere plus ou moins<c type="kk">/</c> qu’elle prenne un exterieur <hi rend="italics">rassurant</hi><c type="kk">/</c> fut ce un peu rude. Theo lui-meme est obligé d’être parisien mais avec cela il a besoin absolument de ce qui lui rappelle sa jeunesse et son passé<c type="kp">_</c> Moi qui n’ai ni femme ni enfant j’ai besoin de voir les champs de blé et difficilement je pourrais exister dans une ville longtemps. Ainsi connaissant son caractère j’ai bon espoir que son mariage lui fera énormément du bien<c type="kp">_</c> Avant qu’on puisse se faire une idee de sa santé il faut un peu leur laisser le temps de prendre racine l’un dans l’autre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Et après elle aura bien<c type="kk">/</c> j’ose encore espérer<c type="kk">/</c> trouvé bien des manieres pour lui rendre la vie un peu plus agreable que cela ne fut le cas auparavant. Car il en a vu de dures.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Enfin je dois conclure cette lettre si je veux qu’elle parte aujourd’hui et je n’ai même pas le temps de la relire<c type="kp">_</c> Ainsi si j’ai dit trop de bêtises tu voudras m’excuser. Porte toi bien<c type="kk">/</c> ne t’embête pas trop et en cultivant ton jardin<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> comme tu le fais et le reste que tu fais<c type="kk">/</c> sois bien assurée que tu abats de la besogne. En pensée je t’embrasse bien<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">In recent days I already began another letter in reply to yours, but I became aware that I didn’t have sufficient mastery of my mind to write. I thank you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> for the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_732">Rod</rs> book<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which I’ve finished and which I’ll return to you soon. The terrible title, Le sens de la vie, terrified me a little, but as it’s happily scarcely spoken of in this volume, I was quite content to read something which has a family resemblance to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Souvestre</rs>’s Le philosophe sous les toits<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> or with Monsieur, madame et bébé by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_586">Droz</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> The moral of it is that in some cases a gentleman ends up preferring to live with a nice, devoted wife and his child, to the life of the restaurant, boulevard and café which he had previously led without too much excess. That’s undoubtedly very pleasant.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It is indeed remarkable that good <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_627">Mrs du Quesne</rs>’s illness came to an unexpected end after all. It must have been a day of great deliverance for her all the same.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">If you say in your letter that when you see so many others in life who come and go, seeking their own path, appearing to you perhaps to be making more headway than you, what can I tell you, that I too sometimes have a feeling of stupefaction in the face of my own life, and as regards several other lives of workers in my profession besides. I’ve just sent Theo a dozen drawings after canvases which I have on the go,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> while all the rest of my life is absolutely as inept as it was at the time when, at the age of 12, I was at a boarding school where I learned absolutely nothing.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">An enormous number of painters who certainly couldn’t do my 12 canvases either in 2 months or in 12 are regarded as artists and as intelligent people in town or in the countryside. But believe me, I say this in order to be explanatory and not because I would see any urgency or possibility or desire to change things. We scarcely know life, we’re so unaware of its hidden aspects, anyway we’re living in an age when everything appears to be in its dotage and tottering, and it isn’t unfortunate to find a duty which forces us to stay calmly in our corner, occupied with a little simpler toil, with certain duties that retain some <hi rend="italics">raison d’être</hi>.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">In these days in which we live we risk coming back from a battle ashamed of having done battle.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">So my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">friend</rs> who was with me in Arles<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and a few others have thus organized an exhibition in which, in good health, I would have taken part.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And what have they been able to do – almost nothing – and yet in their canvases there was something brand new, good, something to give me pleasure and make me enthusiastic for example, me, I can assure you of that. Among artists, we no longer know what to say to each other, we don’t know if we ought to laugh or cry about it, and doing, my word, neither one thing or the other, we are happiest when we find ourselves in possession of a little paint and canvas, the thing we also lack sometimes and which at least we can work on. But any idea of a regular life, any idea of awakening in ourselves or in others gentle ideas or sensations, all of this must necessarily appear pure utopia to us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">So although yesterday more than half a million francs were paid for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s Angelus,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> don’t go believing that more souls will feel what was in Millet’s soul. Or that middle-class people or workers will begin to put in their houses the lithograph of that Millet Angelus, for example.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Don’t go believing that the painters who are still working in Brittany among the peasants will have more encouragement for that matter, less of the same black famine that always surrounded Millet, above all more courage.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Alas, we often lack breath and faith, wrongly certainly but – and here we come back to the point – if, however, we want to work we must submit both to the stubborn harshness of the time and to our isolation, which is sometimes as hard to bear as exile. Now before us, after our years which have thus been lost, relatively speaking, poverty, illness, old age, madness and always exile. It is indeed the moment to say ‘blessed be Thebe, daughter of Telhui, priestess of Osiris, who never complained about anyone’.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Cherishing the memory of good people, wouldn’t that be worth more than being among the ambitious ones on the whole?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’m quite absorbed in reading the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs> that Theo sent me here, where at last I’ll have the calm necessary to do a little more difficult reading. I’ve first taken the kings series, of which I’ve already read Richard <hi>II</hi>, Henry <hi>IV</hi>, Henry <hi>V</hi> and a part of Henry <hi>VI</hi> – as these dramas were the most unfamiliar to me. Have you ever read King Lear?<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> But anyway, I think I shan’t urge you too much to read such dramatic books when I myself, returning from this reading, am always obliged to go and gaze at a blade of grass, a pine-tree branch, an ear of wheat, to calm myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">So if you want to do as artists do, gaze upon the white and red poppies with the bluish leaves, with those buds raising themselves up on stems with gracious curves. The hours of trouble and battle will assuredly come and find us without our going to look for them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">The separation from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> will be hard. And it’s going to happen really soon. What else can one do, thinking of all the things whose reason one doesn’t understand, but gaze upon the wheatfields. Their story is ours, for we who live on bread, are we not ourselves wheat to a considerable extent, at least ought we not to submit to growing, powerless to move, like a plant, relative to what our imagination sometimes desires, and to be reaped when we are ripe, as it is?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I tell you, as for myself I think it would be wisest not to wish to get better, not to wish to regain more strength than now, and I’ll probably grow accustomed to it, to being cracked. A little sooner, a little later, what can that matter to me?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">What you write about Theo’s health I know completely, nevertheless it is my hope that married life will completely restore him. I believe his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> to be wise and loving enough to take lots of care of him and to see that he doesn’t just eat restaurant food, but that he gets back to 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> Dutch cooking. Dutch cooking is good, and so let her turn herself into something of a cook, let her take on a <hi rend="italics">reassuring</hi> outer appearance, even if it’s a little rough. Theo himself is obliged to be a Parisian, but with that he absolutely needs what reminds him of his youth and his past. I, who have neither wife nor child, I need to see the wheatfields, and it would be difficult for me to exist in a town for long. So, knowing his character, I’m optimistic that his marriage will do him an enormous amount of good. Before we can form an idea of his health we must allow them a little time to take root within each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">And afterwards, I dare also hope, she’ll have found lots of ways to make his life a little more pleasant than was the case before. For he has seen hard times.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Anyway I must close this letter if I want it to go off today, and I don’t even have time to re-read it. So, if I’ve said too many silly things you will kindly excuse me. Look after yourself, don’t get too bored, and by cultivating your garden<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> as you do, and the rest that you do, be well assured that you’re getting through a lot of work. I kiss you affectionately in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On the basis of the remark that Millet’s painting had been sold ‘yesterday’ – this sale took place on 1 July 1889 (<ref target="#n-8">see n. 8</ref>) – we have dated the letter to Tuesday, 2 July 1889. Van Gogh’s reading of Shakespeare reveals that Theo’s letter of the same date was actually written earlier; <ref target="let781.xml">see letter 781</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The Volpini exhibition <ref target="let779.xml">(779)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Cor’s departure for South Africa <ref target="let784.xml">(784)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_732">Rod</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_318">Le sens de la vie</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let783.xml#n-5">see letter 783, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Souvestre</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_92">Un philosophe sous les toits</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let093.xml#n-2">see letter 93, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_70">Monsieur, madame et bébé</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_586">Antoine Gustave Droz</rs> (1866) stresses the benefits of viewing marriage as a blessing and not as a grind.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_627">Catharina du Quesne van Bruchem-Van Willis</rs>, a cancer patient nursed by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Elisabeth</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>, had died in Soesterberg on 17 May 1889 (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let426.xml#n-1">letter 426, n. 1</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Regarding this consignment of eleven drawings, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml#n-16">see letter 784, n. 16.</ref> Vincent wrote twice to Theo that it was ‘ten or so’ (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml">letters 784</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let790.xml">790</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>From 1864 to 1866, Van Gogh had attended a boarding school in the North-Brabant town of Zevenbergen.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The large <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Vente Secrétan</hi>, at which 350 lots were sold, took place from 1 to 4 July 1889 at Galerie Charles Sedelmeyer, located at 4bis rue de Rochefoucauld in Paris. See auct. cat. Paris 1889 (Lugt 1938-1987, no. 48407). Pierre-Etienne Secrétan was the owner of a copper foundry in Sérifonfaine, 85 km west of Paris. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1697">The angelus</rs></hi> was sold for 553,000 francs on 1 July 1889, the first day of the sale. The auction had attracted a lot of attention. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> wrote about it to her family in Amsterdam: ‘The whole street full of vehicles – unbearably hot inside and naturally a sea of people ... I shall be glad for Theo when it’s all over, for he is extremely busy’ (FR b4290, 27 June 1889). With regard to the painting, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let017.xml#n-3">see letter 17, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
    
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1716">Emile Louis Vernier</rs>, lithograph after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> The Angelus</hi>, 1881, published by Lemercier &amp; Cie in Paris (Paris, Bibliothèque Nationale, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2291">Ill. 2291</rs>. Theo sent this lithograph soon after this to the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Rev. Salles</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let792.xml">see letter 792</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>For this epitaph on the Carpentras Stele, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let753.xml#n-8">see letter 753, n. 8.</ref> Van Gogh also quoted the inscription in his previous letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let764.xml">letter 764</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            


<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_735">Shakespeare</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_295">Richard <hi>ii</hi></ref></hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_200">Henry <hi>iv</hi></ref></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_298">Henry <hi>v</hi></ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml#n-6">see letter 784, n. 6.</ref> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Henry <hi>vi</hi> </hi>(1590-1591) revolves around the battle between Lord Talbot and the advancing French army. The English lose ground, despite Talbot’s heroic command. Defeated in the end by domestic power conflicts, he is the innocent victim of the curse resting on the crimes committed by Richard <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">ii</hi>.</p>

 


<p rend="indent">The power of passion and the disastrous consequences of uncontrolled rage lead in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_201">King Lear</ref></hi> (1606-1607) to the old king’s ruin. King Lear, determined to free himself of the burden of the throne, is in the end driven mad by bitter rage.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>An allusion to the end of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_445">Candide</ref></hi>. Regarding this novel, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let568.xml#n-3">see letter 568, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    