<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Tuesday, 16 July 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let792"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b739 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>792</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T12</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>793</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-07-16">Tuesday, 16 July 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0739 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0739 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001000_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0739 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001001_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001001_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0739 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001001_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001001_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">le 16 Juillet 1889.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’ai été absolument incapable de t’écrire plus tôt, la chaleur était accablante et je me sentais si faible, que tout me fatiguait extrêmement. Maintenant je suis remis à peu près, pour de bon j’espère. Je te remercie bien de tes lettres et des beaux dessins que tu as envoyé.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> L’hospice à Arles<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> est très remarquable, le papillon<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> et 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>les branches d’églantiers<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> sont biens beaux aussi: simple comme couleur et d’un bien beau dessin. Les derniers dessins ont l’air d’être faits en furie et s’éloignent un peu plus de la nature<c type="kp">_</c> Quand j’aurai vu un de ces motifs en peinture je les comprendrai plus.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> J’ai eu plusieurs personnes pour voir tes tableaux<c type="kp">_</c> Les Pissarro,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> le père Tangui, Werenskiold<c type="kk">/</c> un Norvégien qui a beaucoup de talent et qui a eu la médaille d’honneur dans la section de son pays à l’Exposition Universelle<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> &amp; Maus. Ce dernier est le secretaire des XX à Bruxelles. Il venait demander si tu voulais exposer à leur exposition prochaine.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Il y a encore le temps, mais il ne savait pas s’il viendrait à Paris avant. Je lui ai dit que je croyais que tu 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>n’y verrais pas un inconvenient. Il doit inviter aussi Bernard. Généralement on aime l’effet de nuit<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> et les tournesols<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Un des tournesols je l’ai mis dans nôtre salle à manger contre la cheminée. Il fait l’effet d’un morceau d’étoffe brodé de satin et d’or, c’est magnifique.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Comme à partir du 15 de ce mois je n’ai plus l’appartement Rue Lepic &amp; que chez nous il était absolument impossible de caser toutes les toiles<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai loué dans la maison du père Tangui une petite pièce où j’en ai mis pas mal.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> J’ai fait un choix de ceux qui sont à enlever des chassis &amp; alors on en remettra d’autres. Le père Tangui m’a déjà donné une bon coup de main et il va être très facile de lui renouveler continuellement ce qu’il peut montrer. Tu penses comme lui est enthousiaste des choses de couleur comme les vignes,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> l’effet de nuit etc. Je voudrais bien que tu pouvais une fois l’entendre. J’oubli aussi de dire que de Haan a été içi, il a envoyé à Jo un bouquet monstre de coquelicots de toutes les couleurs, jamais 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>j’avais vu un si beau bouquet, et la pluie de feuilles multicolores quand elles commencaient à défleurir. Il aime beaucoup ce que tu fais<c type="kp">_</c> Il est maintenant avec Gauguin.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Isaacson est tout dépaysé depuis que de Haan n’y est plus<c type="kp">_</c> Je ne sais pas ce qu’il faudrait qu’il fasse, mais ce qu’il peint est d’un maigre! Il parle mieux sur l’art qu’il en fait.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Gauguin écrit dans un journal, que je t’envoi<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> il m’a écrit la semaine dernière &amp; demandait de lui donner ton adresse, qu’il avait perdu. de Haan racontait que Gauguin a fait de très belles choses. Tu n’as pas eu de chance quand tu es allé à Arles de ne pas trouver M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Salles ni Rey. J’ai eu une lettre du premier<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Il est à un petit endroit au bord de la mer. Avant d’avoir reçu ta lettre où tu disais de lui envoyer les Pelerins d’Emmaus<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> je lui avais envoyé l’Angelus<c type="kk">/</c> lith<c type="kp">_</c> par Vernier.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Je regrette de ne pas avoir songé à l’autre sujet car il aurait été plûtot à son gout.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Tu penses comment la nouvelle que Jo est enceinte a donné de l’émotion à ses parents.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Le père &amp; la mère vont venir içi la semaine prochaine. Moe aussi est très contente. C’est très juste que tu 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>dis que sa lettre est remarquable pour son age.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Oui, certainement c’est bien que je me suis marié, car si cela ne s’était pas fait je crois que je serais bien malade maintenant, tandis que je crois que maintenant je vais reprendre des forces &amp; que je pourrai travailler un peu mieux que je l’ai fait. Jo est bien bonne pour moi et elle a eu cependant des jours bien mauvaises par des vomissements etc.<c type="kk">/</c> maintenant cela parait se calmer et elle a bonne mine. Si l’enfant est seulement viable. Je crois que généralement les enfants 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>héritent plutot le genre de constitution des parents que bien<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> l’état de santé de ceux çi au moment quand ils l’ont fait.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">André Bonger aimerait beaucoup avoir un enfant mais il n’en vient pas. Sa femme est d’un caractère très difficile<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> et ils ont beaucoup de mal pour arriver avec l’argent qu’il gagne. Leur ménage est loin d’être gai. Sa femme n’est cependant pas la première venue, mais ils ne savent pas s’accorder. Comme ils restent très loin de chez nous, nous ne les voyons pas souvent.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> Je finis ma lettre à la hate<c type="kp">_</c> çi inclus un bon de poste, car n’ayant pas trouvé M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Salles tu as peut être besoin de quelque chose.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Bien bonjour aussi de Jo &amp; encore bien merci de tes bonnes lettres &amp; les dessins<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">à toi</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">16 July 1889.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I was absolutely incapable of writing to you earlier, the heat was overwhelming, and I felt so weak that everything tired me out extremely. Now I’m more or less recovered, for good I hope. I thank you very much for your letters and for the beautiful drawings you sent.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> The Hospital at Arles<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> is very remarkable, the Butterfly<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> the Eglantine branches<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> are really beautiful too: simple in terms of colour and really beautifully drawn. The latest drawings look like they’ve been done in a fury and are a little more distanced from nature. When I see one of these subjects in a painting I’ll understand them more.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I’ve had several people to see your paintings. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267 bio.xml#_1268">The Pissarros</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1441">Werenskiold</rs>, a Norwegian who has a lot of talent and who got the medal of honour in his country’s section at the World Exhibition,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Maus</rs>. The latter is the secretary of the Vingt in Brussels. He came to ask if you would exhibit at their next exhibition.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> There’s still time, but he didn’t know if he’d be coming to Paris beforehand. I told him that I thought you 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> wouldn’t have anything against it. He’ll probably invite <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> as well. People generally like the Night effect<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> and the Sunflowers.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I’ve put one of the Sunflowers on the mantelpiece in our dining room. It has the effect of a piece of fabric embroidered with satin and gold, it’s magnificent.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">As from the 15th of this month I no longer have the rue Lepic apartment, and as it was absolutely impossible to store all the canvases at our place, I’ve rented a small room in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy</rs>’s house where I’ve put quite a few of them.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I’ve made a choice of those which are to be taken off the stretching frames and then we’ll put others on them. <hi rend="italics">Père</hi> Tanguy has already given me a lot of help, and it’s going to be very easy to let him continually have new things to show. You can imagine how enthusiastic he is about coloured things like the Vineyards,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> the Night effect, etc. I’d very much like you to be able to hear him sometime. I also forgot to say that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> has been here, he sent <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> a monster bouquet of poppies of all colours, never 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> had I seen such a beautiful bouquet, and the rain of multicoloured leaves when they were beginning to drop their petals. He very much likes what you’re doing. He’s now with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> is all at sea now that De Haan is no longer there. I don’t know what he ought to do, but what he’s painting is poor! He talks about art better than he does it.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is writing in a newspaper, which I’m sending you.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> He wrote to me last week and asked me to give him your address, which he’d lost. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> was saying that Gauguin has done some very fine things. You were unlucky when you went to Arles not to find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs>, or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_637">Rey</rs> either. I’ve had a letter from the former.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> He’s at a little seaside place. Before receiving your letter in which you say to send him the Pilgrims at Emmaus<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> I’d sent him the Angelus, lithograph by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1716">Vernier</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> I regret not having thought of the other subject, for it would have been rather more to his taste. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">You can imagine how the news that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> is pregnant excited her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Her father and mother are going to come here next week. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> is also very pleased. It’s very true what you 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> say, that her letter’s remarkable for her age.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Yes, certainly it’s good that I’ve got married, for if it hadn’t been done I think I would be really ill now, while I think that now I’m going to regain strength and that I’ll be able to work a little better than I have done. Jo is really good to me, and yet she’s had some really bad days with vomiting etc., now it seems to be calming down and she looks well. If only the child is viable. I think that children generally inherit 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> their parents’ kind of constitution rather than the latter’s state of health at the moment when they made it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> would very much like to have a child, but it doesn’t come. His <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">wife</rs> has a very difficult nature,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> and they have a lot of trouble getting by on the money he earns. Their household is far from cheerful. Yet his wife isn’t just anybody, but they can’t manage to see eye to eye. We don’t see them often, as they live very far from our place.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> I’ll finish my letter in haste. Enclosed is a postal order, for as you didn’t find <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs> you may need something.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Warm regards, from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> as well, and thank you very much again for your kind letters and the drawings.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘le 16 Juillet 1889.’</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent had sent six drawings around 18 June (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let782.xml">see letter 782</ref>), and on 2 July another eleven (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml">see letter 784</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The courtyard of the hospital</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2784">F 1467 / JH 1688</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Giant peacock moth</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2793">F 1523 / JH 1700</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Theo must mean the drawing of periwinkle: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2935">F 1614 / JH 2060</rs>. See cat. Amsterdam 2007, p. 191.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Theo is referring to the second consignment, which consisted of drawings after paintings Vincent was working on. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml#n-16">See letter 784, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Camille Pissarro</rs> and his son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267">Lucien</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>At the 1889 World Exhibition in Paris, the Norwegian painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1441">Erik Theodor Werenskiold</rs> was represented by the works <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_855">Deux frères</rs> </hi>(Two brothers), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_856">Grande mère</rs> </hi>(Grandmother), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_857">Paysage</rs></hi> (Landscape) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_858">Enterrement à la campagne</rs></hi> (Burial in the country). He received the ‘Grand Prix’ for the last painting, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Peasant burial</hi>, 1885 (Oslo, Nasjonalgalleriet). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1421">Ill. 1421</rs>. See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-3, cat. nos. 120-123, and Marit Werenskiold, ‘Erik Werenskiold in Munich 1875-1881’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Konsthistorisk Tidskrift </hi>68-2, 1999, pp. 81-95, esp. p. 81.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Regarding the artists’ society Les Vingt, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let580.xml#n-6">see letter 580, n. 6.</ref> The seventh exhibition of Les Vingt was held in Brussels from 18 January to 23 February 1890. Works by the 19 members of the society were augmented by the work of 18 other ‘invited artists’: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Eugène Boch</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_932">Paul Cézanne</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1847">Alexandre-Louis-Marie Charpentier</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_994">Albert Dubois-Pillet</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1074">Louis Hayet</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1211">Xavier Mellery</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1848">George Minne</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267">Lucien Pissarro</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1303">Odilon Redon</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1293">Auguste Renoir</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1849">Louis Oscar Roty</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1850">Giovanni Segantini</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Paul Signac</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1349">Alfred Sisley</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1851">Charles Storm van 's Gravesande</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1776">William Thornley</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec</rs> and Vincent van Gogh. See Delevoy 1981, pp. 197 ff.</p>

<p rend="indent">Van Gogh exhibited six works: ‘Tournesols’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>)), ‘le lierre’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Trees with ivy in the garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2789">F 609 / JH 1693</rs>)), ‘verger en fleurs (Arles)’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard in blossom with a view of Arles</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2781">F 516 / JH 1685</rs>)), ‘champ de blé; soleil levant (Saint-Rémy)’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>)) and ‘la vigne rouge (Mont-Major)’ (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The red vineyard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>)). See Delevoy 1981, p. 216 and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let820.xml">letter 820</ref> (Van Gogh’s list of the works to be exhibited).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Starry night over the Rhône </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2723">F 474 / JH 1592</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Theo probably means <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>), which Vincent found suitable to exhibit (see, for example, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let741.xml">letter 741</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The version of the sunflowers that hung above the fireplace at Theo and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s (and later on, in Jo’s house), was probably <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>. Jo did not lend this version out to exhibitions until 1901. See Van Tilborgh and Hendriks 2001, pp. 26-27.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>To rent this little room, Theo paid <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> 30 francs on 15 October 1889, 4 February 1890 and 27 April 1890 (<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, pp. 63, 69).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The green vineyard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2726">F 475 / JH 1595</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            
      
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s stay in Brittany, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-15">see letter 774, nn. 15</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-16">16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> published art reviews in the Dutch journal <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">De Portefeuille</hi>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let807.xml#n-2">See letter 807, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, ‘Notes sur l’art à L’Exposition Universelle’, appeared in two parts in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Moderniste Illustré</hi>: on 4 July 1889 (no. 11), pp. 84, 86 and on 13 July 1889 (no. 12), pp. 90-91. In the first part, Gauguin voiced fierce criticism of the organization of the World Exhibition, which allowed only established academic artists to display their work and refused to give independent, innovative artists their own exhibition space. In the second part of his article he discusses the statues and ceramics on display; in a footnote the editor (or Gauguin himself?) expresses his surprise at the fact that Gauguin’s ceramics, which were earlier exhibited at Theo van Gogh’s, were not to be seen at the exhibition.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>This letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Salles</rs> to Theo is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Vincent wrote this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let783.xml">letter 783</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>For the lithograph by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1716">Vernier</rs> after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2291">Angelus</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let785.xml#n-9">see letter 785, n. 9.</ref> Theo paid 36.15 francs for this lithograph on 29 June 1889. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 56.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Jo’s parents were <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22">Hendrik Christiaan Bonger</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_23">Hermine Louise Bonger-Weissman</rs>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Vincent said this about the letter he received from their <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>, who was nearly 70; Vincent had forwarded this letter to Theo (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let784.xml">see letter 784</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>The word ‘bien’ (here ‘que bien’ is rendered as ‘rather than’) is unusual in this place; it is possible that its use was prompted by the Dutch ‘dan wel’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> was married to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Annie van der Linden</rs>. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and the rest of the Bonger family did not get along very well with her, and even Andries did not seem very happy with her. As early as 12 September 1888, he wrote to Jo in a bitter tone: ‘She is hopelessly apathetic. Sometimes I think she spent years lying on top of a marble tomb. Sadly, we do not seem to cheer each other up’ (See FR b1033; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness </hi>1999, pp. 21, 23).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_283">Annie</rs> lived at 127 rue du Ranelagh in Passy, on the west side of Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let787.xml">letter 787</ref> Vincent had written that he would be receiving money from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Salles</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    