<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Monday, 2 September 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let798"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b650 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>798</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>602 / 602a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>799</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-09-02">on or about Monday, 2 September 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0650 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0650 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000886_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0650 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000887_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000887_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0650 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000887_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000887_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000887_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">depuis que je t’ai écrit je vais mieux et tout en ne sachant pas si cela durera je ne veux pas attendre plus longtemps pour t’écrire de nouveau<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Merci encore une fois de cette belle eau-forte d’après Rembrandt. je voudrais bien connaitre le tableau et savoir à quelle epoque de sa vie il l’a peint<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Tout cela rentre avec le portrait de Fabritius de Rotterdam<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> le voyageur de la galerie Lacaze<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> dans une cathégorie speciale où le portrait d’un être humain se transforme en je ne sais quoi de lumineux et de consolant<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Et comme cela est très différant de Michel Ange ou de Giotto quoique ce dernier s’en rapproche pourtant et qu’ainsi Giotto forme comme le trait d’union possible entre l’école de Rembrandt &amp; les italiens.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’ai hier recommencé à travailler un peu – une chôse que je vois de ma fenêtre – un champ de chaume jaune qu’on laboure<c type="kk">/</c> l’opposition de la terre labourée violacée avec les bandes de chaume jaune<c type="kk">/</c> fond de collines.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Le travail me distrait infiniment mieux qu’autre chôse et si je pouvais une fois bien me lancer là-dedans de toute mon énergie ce serait possible<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> le meilleur remède<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">L’impossibilité d’avoir des modèles<c type="kk">/</c> un tas d’autres chôses<c type="kk">/</c> empêchent de parvenir cependant<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin il faut bien que j’essaie de prendre les chôses un peu passivement et patienter<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Je pense bien souvent aux copains en Bretagne.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> qui certes sont en train de faire du meilleur travail que moi. Si avec l’expérience que j’en ai à présent il m’était possible de recommencer je n’irais pas voir dans le Midi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Etais-je indépendant et libre<c type="kk">/</c> j’aurais néanmoins conservé mon enthousiasme car il y a de bien belles choses à faire<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Ainsi les vignes<c type="kk">/</c> les champs d’oliviers<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="italics">Si</hi> j’avais confiance dans l’administration d’ici<c type="kk">/</c> rien ne serait mieux et plus simple que de mettre tous mes meubles ici à l’hospice et de continuer tranquillement<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> En cas de guérison ou dans les intervalles je pourrais tôt ou tard revenir à Paris ou en Bretagne pour un temps. Mais d’abord ils sont ici <hi rend="italics">très chers</hi> et puis à présent j’ai peur des autres malades<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Enfin un tas de raisons font que je ne crois pas que j’ai eu de la chance pas ici non plus.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’exagère peut-être dans le chagrin que j’ai d’être encore foutu en bas par la maladie – mais j’ai comme peur<c type="kp">_</c>– Tu me diras ce que je me dis aussi<c type="kk">/</c> que la faute doit être en dedans de moi et non aux circonstances ou à d’autres personnes. Enfin c’est pas gai.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">M. Peyron a été bon pour moi et il a une longue expérience<c type="kk">/</c> je ne mépriserai pas ce qu’il dit ou juge bon.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Mais aura-t-il une opinion arrêtee<c type="kk">/</c> t’-a-t il écrit quelque chôse de clair?? et de possible.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Tu vois que je suis encore de bien mauvaise humeur<c type="kk">/</c> c’est que ça ne va pas<c type="kp">_</c>– Puis je me trouve imbécile d’aller demander la permission de faire des tableaux à des médecins. Il est d’ailleurs à espérer que si tôt ou tard je guérisse<c type="kk">/</c> jusqu’à un certain point ce sera parceque je me serai guéri en travaillant<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui fortifie la volonté et conséquemment laisse moins de prise à ces faiblesses mentales.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Mon cher frère je voulais t’écrire mieux que ça mais cela ne va pas fort. J’ai grand desir d’aller dans les montagnes peindre des journées entières<c type="kk">/</c> j’espère qu’ils me laisseront de ces jours ci<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Tu verras bientôt une toile d’une cabane dans les montagnes<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> que j’avais faite impressioné par ce livre de Rod.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ce serait bon pour moi de rester dans une ferme pour un temps<c type="kk">/</c> au moins y ferais je peutêtre du bon travail<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Je dois écrire à la mere et à Wil de ces jours ci<c type="kp">_</c> Wil a demandé de lui envoyer un tableau et je voudrais bien par même occasion en donner un à Lies aussi qui n’en a pas encore à ce que je sache.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Qu’en dis tu que la mère va habiter Leyden<c type="kp">_</c> je lui donne raison dans ce sens que je comprends qu’elle languisse d’après ses petits enfants.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Et puis il n’y aura plus guère personne de nous autres en Brabande<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Parlant de cela – il n’y a pas très long<c type="shy">-</c>temps à Arles je lisais je ne sais plus quel livre de Henri Conscience. Si tu veux c’est excessivement sentimental<c type="kk">/</c> ses paysans<c type="kk">/</c> mais parlant d’<hi rend="italics">impressionisme</hi> sais tu qu’il 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>y a là-dedans des descriptions de paysage avec des notes de couleur d’un juste<c type="kk">/</c> d’un senti<c type="kk">/</c> d’un primitif de <hi rend="italics">premier</hi> ordre. Et c’est toujours comme cela. Ah mon cher frère ces bruyeres-là de la Campine<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> c’etait pourtant quelque chose. Mais enfin cela ne reviendra pas<c type="kk">/</c> et en avant<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Il – Conscience – avait decrit une maisonette toute neuve avec toit de tuile tout rouge en plein soleil<c type="kk">/</c> un jardin avec de l’oseille et oignons<c type="kk">/</c> les pommes de terre à verdure sombre<c type="kk">/</c> une haie de hêtre<c type="kk">/</c> une vigne et plus loin les sapins<c type="kk">/</c> les genets tout jaunes<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> N’aie pas peur<c type="kk">/</c> c’etait pas du Cazin<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> mais du Claude Monet<c type="kp">_</c>– Puis dans l’exces même de sentimentalité il y a de l’originalité<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Et moi qui sens cela et ne peux rien foutre nom d’un chien<c type="kk">/</c> n’est ce pas emmerdant<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Si tu rencontres des occasions pour les lithographies Delacroix<c type="kk">/</c> Rousseau<c type="kk">/</c> Diaz &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><c type="kk">/</c> des artistes anc. &amp; modernes<c type="kk">/</c> Galeries modernes &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> je ne saurais trop te recommander d’en garder car tu verras que cela deviendra rare<c type="kp">_</c> C’etait pourtant bien le moyen de populariser les belles choses que ces feuilles à 1 franc de dans le temps<c type="kk">/</c> ces eauxfortes &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> d’alors. Tres intéressant la brochure Rodin – Claude Monet. que j’aurais voulu voir cela<c type="kp">_</c> Inutile de dire que neamoins je suis pas d’accord lorsqu’il dit que Meissonnier n’est rien et que Th<c type="kp">_</c> Rousseau n’est pas grand chôse<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Les Meissonnier et les Rousseau sont quelque chôse de fort intéressant pour ceux qui les aiment et cherchent à savoir ce que sentait l’artiste<c type="kp">_</c> Que tous soient de cet avis n’est pas possible parcequ’il faut en avoir vu et regardé et c’est plus rare que des pavés. Or un Meissonnier si on le regarde un an durant<c type="kk">/</c> il y a encore pour l’année prochaine à regarder<c type="kk">/</c> soyez tranquille. Sans compter que c’est un homme qui a eu ses jours de bonheur<c type="kk">/</c> de trouvailles parfaites. Certes je le sais<c type="kk">/</c> Daumier<c type="kk">/</c> Millet<c type="kk">/</c> Delacroix ont <hi rend="italics">un</hi> <hi rend="italics">autre</hi> dessin – mais cette facture de Meissonnier<c type="kk">/</c> 
      <pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>ce quelque chose d’essentiellement Français surtout<c type="kk">/</c> alors que les vieux Hollandais n’y trouveraient rien à redire et pourtant c’est autre chose qu’eux et c’est moderne<c type="kk">/</c> faut-il être aveugle pour croire que Meissonnier ne soit pas un artiste et – de premier ordre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">A-t-on fait beaucoup de chôses donnant mieux la note du XIX siecle que le portrait d’Hetzel?<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Lorsque Besnard faisait ces deux très beaux panneaux<c type="kk">/</c> l’homme primitif et l’homme moderne<c type="kk">/</c> que nous avons vus chez Petit<c type="kk">/</c> en faisant de l’homme moderne un liseur il avait la même idée.–<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Et toujours je regretterai que de nos jours on croie à l’incompatibilité de la generation de mettons 48 et l’actuelle. Je crois moi que les deux se tiennent quand même tout en ne pouvant le prouver.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Tiens prends le bon Bodmer. Est ce qu’il n’a pu etudier la nature en chasseur<c type="kk">/</c> en sauvage<c type="kk">/</c> ne l’a-t-il pas aimée et connue avec experience d’une longue vie mâle entiere – et crois tu que le premier parisien venu qui s’en aille à la banlieue en sache autant ou plus parcequ’il fera un paysage avec des tons plus crus. Non pas que ce soit mal d’employer des tons purs et heurtés<c type="kk">/</c> non pas qu’<hi rend="italics">au point de vue du coloris</hi> je sois <hi rend="italics">toujours</hi> admirateur de Bodmer mais j’admire et j’aime l’homme qui connaissait toute la forêt de Fontainebleau à partir de l’insecte jusqu’au sanglier et du cerf jusqu’à l’alouette<c type="kp">_</c> Du grand chène et du bloc de rocher jusqu’à la fougère et du brin d’herbe.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Or une chose comme çà<c type="kk">/</c> ne la sent<c type="kk">/</c> ne la trouve pas qui veut<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Et Brion – oh un faiseur de tableaux de genre alsaciens me dira-t-on<c type="kp">_</c>– C’est bien il a en effet fait le repas des fiancailles<c type="kk">/</c> le mariage protestant &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> qui en effet sont alsaciens<c type="kp">_</c> Lorsque personne ne se trouve à meme d’illustrer les miserables<c type="kk">/</c> lui pourtant le fait d’une façon jusqu’à présent pas surpassée et il ne se trompe pas dans ses types.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> C’est il peu de chôse que de tellement bien connaitre les gens<c type="kk">/</c> l’humanité de cette periode-là<c type="kk">/</c> tellement bien qu’on ne se trompe guère d’expression et de type<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Ah – à nous autres il nous faudrait vieillir en travaillant dur et c’est pourquoi qu’alors nous nous morfondons lorsque cela ne va pas<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Je crois que si un jour tu verras le musée Brias de Montpellier je crois qu’alors rien ne t’émotionnera plus que Brias lui-même alors qu’on se rend compte d’après ses achats de ce qu’il a cherché à être pour les artistes<c type="kp">_</c> C’est un peu désespérant lorsqu’on voit de certains portraits de lui tellement le visage est navré et evidemment contrarié<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Si l’on ne reussit pas dans le midi c’est que reste toujours celui là qui a souffert toute sa vie pour cette cause-là.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Les seuls portraits sereins sont le Delacroix<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> et le Ricard<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">Par exemple par un grand hasard celui par Cabanel est juste et comme observation fort interessant. au moins cela donne une idée de l’être<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Cela me fait plaisir que la mere de Jo soit venu à Paris. L’année prochaine ce sera peut-être un peu différent et tu auras un enfant et cela apporte pas mal de petites misères de la vie humaine<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> – mais de certaines grandes misères de spleen etc<c type="kp">_</c> disparaissant à tout jamais c’est certes ainsi que cela doit aller.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.33" n="33">Bientôt je t’écris de nouveau<c type="kk">/</c> je ne t’ecris pas comme j’aurais voulu<c type="kk">/</c> j’espère que tout va bien chez toi &amp; continuera à aller bien. Suis fort fort content de ce que Rivet t’aie débarassé de la toux qui m’inquiétait bien un peu aussi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.34" n="34">Ce que j’avais dans la gorge tend à disparaitre<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-25"/> je mange encore avec quelque difficulté mais enfin ça a repris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.35" n="35">Bonne poignée de main à toi &amp; à Jo.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.36" n="36">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.37" n="37">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Since I wrote to you I’m feeling better, and whilst I don’t know if it’ll last I don’t want to wait any longer to write to you again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Thanks once again for that beautiful etching after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>. I’d very much like to get to know the painting and know in which period of his life he painted it.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> All this goes with the Rotterdam portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1012">Fabritius</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> the traveller in the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_480">La Caze</rs> gallery,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> into a special category in which the portrait of a human being is transformed into something luminous and consoling.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">And how very different this is from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1229">Michelangelo</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, although the latter however comes close to it, and Giotto thus forms a sort of possible hyphen between the school of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> and the Italians.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Yesterday I started working again a little – a thing I see from my window – a field of yellow stubble which is being ploughed, the opposition of the purplish ploughed earth with the strips of yellow stubble, background of hills.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Work distracts me infinitely better than anything else, and if I could once really throw myself into it with all my energy that might possibly be the best remedy.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">The impossibility of having models, a heap of other things, prevent me from managing it however. Anyway, I really must try to take things a little passively and be patient.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I often think of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039 bio.xml#_1075">pals</rs> in Brittany,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> who are certainly doing better work than I am. If, with the experience I’m having at present, it was possible for me to begin again, I wouldn’t go and look around the south.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Were I independent and free, I would nevertheless have retained my enthusiasm, for there are some really beautiful things to do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Such as the vineyards, the fields of olive trees. <hi rend="italics">If</hi> I had confidence in the management here, nothing would be better and simpler than to put all my furniture here at the hospital and quietly continue.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> If I were to recover, or in the intervals, I could sooner or later come back to Paris or Brittany for a time. But first they’re <hi rend="italics">very expensive</hi> here, and then I’m afraid of the other patients at the moment.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Anyway, a heap of reasons mean that I don’t think I’ve been lucky here either.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’m perhaps exaggerating in the sadness I feel at being knocked down by illness again – but I feel a kind of fear. You’ll tell me what I tell myself too, that the fault must be inside me and not in the circumstances or other people. Anyway, it isn’t fun.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> has been kind to me and he has long experience, I shan’t scorn what he says or considers good.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But will he have a firm opinion, has he written anything definite to you?? And possible?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">You can see that I’m still in a very bad mood, it’s because things aren’t going well. Then I consider myself imbecilic to go and ask doctors for permission to make paintings. Besides, it’s to be hoped that if I recover sooner or later, up to a certain point it’ll be because I’ve cured myself by working, which fortifies the will and consequently allows these mental weaknesses less hold.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">My dear brother, I wanted to write to you better than this, but things aren’t going very well. I have a great desire to go into the mountains to paint for whole days, I hope they’ll allow me to in the coming days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">You’ll soon see a canvas of a hut in the mountains<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> which I did under the influence of that book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_732">Rod</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> It would be good for me to stay on a farm for a while, at least I might do some good work there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I must write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> in the next few days. Wil asked to be sent a painting, and I’d very much like to give one to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs> as well on the same occasion, who doesn’t have any yet as far as I know.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">What do you say about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> going to live in Leiden? I think she’s right in this sense, that I can understand that she’s pining for her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_414 bio.xml#_415">grandchildren</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And then there’ll be none of us left in Brabant.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Speaking of that – not very long ago in Arles I was reading a book, I can’t remember which one, by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Henri Conscience</rs>. It’s excessively sentimental if you like, what with his peasants, but speaking of <hi rend="italics">Impressionism</hi> do you know that it 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> contains descriptions of landscape with colour notes of accuracy, feeling and primitiveness of the <hi rend="italics">first</hi> order. And it’s always like that. Ah my dear brother, those heaths in the Kempen<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> were something though. But anyway, that won’t come back, and onward we go.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">He – <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Conscience</rs> – described a brand-new little house with a bright red slate roof in the full sunshine, a garden with dock and onions, potatoes with dark foliage, a beech hedge, a vineyard, and further on the pine trees, the broom all yellow.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Don’t be afraid, it wasn’t like a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_916">Cazin</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> it was like a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs>. Then there’s originality even in the excess of sentimentality.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">And as for me, who feels it and can’t damned well do anything, isn’t that sickening.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">If you get opportunities for lithographs of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1332">Rousseau</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_992">Diaz</rs> &amp;c., ancient and modern artists, Galeries modernes &amp;c., I can’t advise you too strongly to hold onto them, for you’ll see that they’ll become rare. Yet it was really the way to popularize beautiful things, those 1-franc sheets of those days, those etchings &amp;c. back then. Very interesting the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1319">Rodin</rs> – <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs> brochure. How I’d have liked to see that. Pointless to say that nevertheless I don’t agree when he says that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs> is nothing and that T. Rousseau isn’t much.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Meissoniers and Rousseaus are something highly interesting for those who like them and try to discover what the artist was feeling. It isn’t possible for everyone to be of that opinion, because one has to have seen and looked at them, and you don’t find that on every corner. Now a Meissonier, if you look at it for a year there’s still enough in it to look at the next year, never fear. Not to mention that he’s a man who had his days of happiness, of perfect finds. Certainly I know, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_977">Daumier</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> have <hi rend="italics">another</hi> way of drawing – but Meissonier’s execution, 
      <pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> that something essentially French above all, although  the old Dutchmen would find nothing  to fault in it, and yet it’s something other than them and it’s modern; one has to be blind to believe that Meissonier isn’t an artist and – one of the first rank.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Have many things been done that give the note of the 19th century better than the portrait of Hetzel?<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> When <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_858">Besnard</rs> did those two very beautiful panels, primitive man and modern man, which we saw at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_552">Petit</rs>’s, in making the modern man a reader he had the same idea.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">And I’ll always regret that in our times people believe in the incompatibility of the generation of, say, 48 and the present one. I myself believe that the two hold their own all the same, though I can’t prove it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">Let’s take good <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_867">Bodmer</rs> for example. Was he not able to study nature as a hunter, a savage, did he not love it and know it with experience of an entire long manly life – and do you think that the first Parisian to come along who goes to the suburbs knows as much or more about it because he’ll do a landscape with harsher tones? Not that it’s bad to use pure and clashing tones, not that <hi rend="italics">from the point of view of colour</hi> I’m <hi rend="italics">always</hi> an admirer of Bodmer, but I admire and I like the man who knew all the forest of Fontainebleau, from the insect to the wild boar and from the stag to the lark. From the tall oak and the lump of rock to the fern and the blade of grass.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Now a thing like that, not anyone who wants to can feel it or find it.
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs> – oh a maker of Alsatian genre paintings people will tell me. That’s fine, he has indeed done the Engagement meal, the Protestant wedding &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> which are indeed Alsatian. When no one is up to illustrating Les Misérables, he however does it in a manner unsurpassed up to now, and he isn’t mistaken in his types.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Is it a small thing to know people so well, the humanity of that period, so well that one scarcely makes a mistake in expression and type?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Ah – the rest of us would have to get old working hard, and that’s why we then get despondent when things don’t go right.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I think that if you see the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_312">Bruyas</rs> museum in Montpellier one day, I think that then nothing will move you more than Bruyas himself, when one realizes from his purchases what he sought to be for artists. It’s a little disheartening when one sees from certain portraits of him how heartbroken and obviously frustrated his face is.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> If one doesn’t succeed in the south there still remains he who suffered all his life for that cause.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">The only serene portraits are the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs><ptr target="#note-t-21"/> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1315">Ricard</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">For example, by a great chance the one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_917">Cabanel</rs> is accurate and most interesting as an observation, at least it gives an idea of the man.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.33" n="33">I’m pleased that Jo’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_23">mother</rs> has come to Paris. Next year it will perhaps be a little different and you’ll have a child, and that brings a fair few petty vexations of human life<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> – but as certain great miseries of spleen etc. will disappear for ever, that’s certainly how it should go.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.34" n="34">I’ll write to you again soon, I’m not writing to you as I would have wished, I hope that all is well at your place and will continue to go well. Am very, very pleased that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Rivet</rs> has rid you of the cough, which really worried me a bit too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.35" n="35">What I had in my throat is starting to disappear,<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> I’m still eating with some difficulty, but anyway it has got better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.36" n="36">Good handshake to you and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.37" n="37">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.38" n="38">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The previous letter to Theo dated from 22 August <ref target="let797.xml">(797)</ref>. Vincent says here that he is slightly better since he last wrote and that he does not want to wait any longer to write (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-4</ref>), which means that several days must have elapsed since his last letter. Theo responded on Thursday, 5 September (<ref target="let799.xml">letter 799</ref>) to the present letter. It is not clear how long he waited before writing back, but given the circumstances he would not have waited long. We have therefore dated the letter to about Monday, 2 September 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
      <p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Dr Peyron added several lines for Theo at the bottom of Vincent’s letter. <ref target="documentation.xml#id2September1889">See <hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, On or about 2 September 1889</ref>. </p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">First attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let793.xml">(793)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo had sent the etching by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_965">Courtry</rs> after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_344">The archangel Raphael</rs></hi> (then attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let781.xml#n-4">see letter 781, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1012">Carel Fabritius</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1885">Self-portrait</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let155.xml#n-18">see letter 155, n. 18</ref>, first paragraph.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For the portrait <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2159">Young man with a walking stick</rs></hi> (no longer attributed to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let536.xml#n-9">see letter 536, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Field with a ploughman</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_212">F - / JH 1769</rs>) was made after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2825">F 625 / JH 1768</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘possiblement’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">Gauguin</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> were staying in Brittany; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-15">see letter 774, nn. 15</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-16">16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s lack of faith in the asylum was undoubtedly connected with his disappointment at the recurrence of his illness. In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let787.xml">letter 787</ref> he wrote very optimistically about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Peyron</rs>’s offer to store his furniture in the asylum.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
      
<p>Theo paid 100 francs a month for board and lodging for Vincent (FR b1059). With regard to the other patients in the asylum, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml#n-21">see letter 776, nn. 21</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml#n-22">22</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let777.xml#n-2">letter 777, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alpilles with a hut </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2823">F 622 / JH 1766</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_732">Rod</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_318">Le sens de la vie</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let797.xml#n-13">see letter 797, n. 13.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh intended seven canvases for his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let803.xml#n-4">see letter 803, n. 4.</ref> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies van Gogh</rs> had long had in her possession the small Nuenen painting <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old tower in the snow </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_364">F 87 / JH 600</rs>), and after Vincent’s death received a number of Paris works as well (FR b2002). As far as we know, she received no works from Saint-Rémy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> moved on 2 November 1889 from Breda to Herengracht 100 in Leiden. Van Gogh’s sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs>, her husband <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Joan van Houten</rs> and their daughters, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_415">Sara</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_414">Annie</rs>, also lived in Leiden.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p> ‘La Campine’ (de Kempen) is a region in the north of Belgium.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s description of the little house does not come from <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_77">Le conscrit</ref></hi>, which he refers to in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let800.xml">letter 800</ref>, but was probably inspired by the little blue house in Borgerhout (Antwerp), as described in the novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_210">La maison bleue</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Henri Conscience</rs>: ‘From either side of its door climbed a vine whose intertwined branches surrounded the windows with festoons, and covered the blue-painted façade and the red roof tiles so completely that one would think one was looking at a cradle of greenery.</p>

<p rend="indent">When, in late autumn, the two vines showed their white and blue grapes through the bright green foliage, we would stop, every child, on the road to school, in front of the pretty little house’ (De chaque côté de sa porte grimpait une vigne dont les rameaux entrelacés entouraient les fenêtres de festons, et couvraient si complétement la façade peinte en bleu et les tuiles rouges du toit, qu’on eût cru voir un berceau de verdure.</p>

<p rend="indent">Lorsque, dans l’arrière-saison, les deux vignes montraient leurs raisins blancs et bleus à travers le feuillage d’un vert éclatant, nous nous arrêtions, tout enfant, sur le chemin de l’école, devant la jolie maisonnette) (ed. Paris 1882, pp. 1-2). The description of the surroundings is something that Van Gogh himself might have penned.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The French landscape painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_916">Jean-Charles Cazin</rs> began his career as a realistic painter, but later came under the influence of Impressionism. In the 1880s and ’90s, he was seen as <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Monet</rs>’s rival. See Thomson, ‘Theo van Gogh’ 1999, p. 203, n. 144.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            
      
<p>Theo had sent Vincent the catalogue of the exhibition of works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Monet</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1319">Rodin</rs> held at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_552">Georges Petit</rs>’s (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let797.xml#n-10">see letter 797, n. 10</ref>). Vincent discusses the following passage in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_706">Octave Mirbeau</rs>’s article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_586">Claude Monet</ref>’: ‘M. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Meissonier</rs>, in his garden at Poissy, scattering flour in order to represent the snow in which the French soliders died during the retreat from Russia, and painting this flour with the conscientiousness we know, plies a trade of some sort, inferior to that of the cabinet-maker who fits a drawer precisely onto its runners ... <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1332">Théodore Rousseau</rs>, to mention but him, does not stand up to even superficial study. The air that he paints is unbreathable, his sweet chestnuts and oaks may well have solid forks, his depictions of the ground a weighty and robust structure, but they are devoid of life; his foliage shines, but the air does not circulate through this crude, coarse masonry; no sap runs beneath this inert and desiccated vegetation, with its concistency of metal’ (M. Meissonier, semant, dans son jardin de Poissy, de la farine pour figurer la neige où moururent les soldats français, pendant la retraite de Russie, et peignant cette farine avec la conscience que l’on sait, fait un métier quelconque, inférieur à celui du menuisier qui emboîte exactement un tiroir sur ses coulisses ... Théodore Rousseau, pour ne parler que de lui, ne résiste pas à une analyse, même superficielle. L’atmosphère qu’il peint est irrespirable; ses châtaigniers et ses chênes ont beau avoir de solides embranchements, ses terrains une lourde et robuste ossature, ils ne vivent point; ses feuillages luisent, mais l’air ne circule pas à travers ce maçonnage grossier et canaille; aucune sève ne court sous ces végétations inertes et desséchées, aux consistences de métal’. See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-6, p. 13.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1208">Ernest Meissonier</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pierre-Jules Hetzel</hi>, 1879 (Meudon, Musée d’Art et d’Histoire de la Ville de Meudon). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1136">Ill. 1136</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_858">Albert Besnard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Modern man</hi>, c. 1884-1886 (Beauvais, Musée départemental de l’Oise) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Prehistoric man</hi>, c. 1887 (private collection). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_578">Ill. 578</rs>- <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_471">471</rs>. The works are on canvas, not on panel; they are preparatory studies for decorative paintings in the Ecole de Pharmacie in Paris. Van Gogh saw them in 1887 at the exhibition held at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_552">Georges Petit</rs>’s. Cf. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Exposition internationale de peinture et de sculpture. Sixième année</hi>. Paris (Galerie Georges Petit), 8 May - 8 June 1887, p. 3, cat. nos. 1-2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was possibly mistaken about the title <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The engagement meal</hi> and actually meant <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The wedding dinner</hi> (engraving by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1511">Joel Ballin</rs>), at which the wedding guests arrive in an upstairs room to be seated at table (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_650">Ill. 650</rs>. Cf. René Ménard, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’art en Alsace-Lorraine</hi>. Paris 1876, pp. 126, 132. Ménard speaks of the intimate emotions of the ‘fiançailles’ (betrothal), portrayed so well by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs>. The print was also available as a ‘Carte-Album’. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Cat. Goupil</hi> 1877, pp. 11, 75, no. 774.</p>

<p rend="indent">
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Protestant marriage</hi> (1869) by Brion was shown at the 1869 Salon. It was known through its reproduction in the following publications: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Album Boetzel. Le Salon 1869</hi>; at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_700">Paul Mantz</rs>, ‘Salon de 1869 (2me et dernier article)’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 11 (1869), 2nd series, vol. 2, pp. 5-23, ill. between pp. 6-7, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1589">Paul Adolphe Rajon</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_648">Ill. 648</rs>; in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Musée Universel</hi> 6 (17 November 1877), 1e semestre, vol. 11, no. 268, p. 100; and in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Graphic</hi> 6 (10 October 1872), p. 361. The painting was sold on 13 October 1994 at Christie’s in New York.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs>’s illustrations to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_310">Les misérables</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let333.xml#n-14">see letter 333, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>For the Maecenas <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_312">Bruyas</rs> and his collection in the Musée Fabre at Montpellier, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let726.xml#n-1">see letter 726, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_76">Alfred Bruyas</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let726.xml#n-2">see letter 726, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1315">Ricard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1272">Alfred Bruyas</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let726.xml#n-3">see letter 726, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_917">Cabanel</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_666">Alfred Bruyas</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let726.xml#n-5">see letter 726, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            
      
<p>Regarding the origin of this expression deriving from the book <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_222"><hi rend="italics">Petites misères de la vie humaine</hi></ref> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_745 bio.xml#_748">Old Nick and Grandville</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let178.xml#n-6">see letter 178, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh had written in his previous letter that he had a sore throat. It had probably been caused by the filth he had eaten during his attack, as well as by the paint and turpentine with which he had attempted to poison himself (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let797.xml#n-6">see letter 797, n. 6</ref>). This behaviour was no doubt connected with the ‘ideas of suicide’ mentioned by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Dr Peyron</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="documentation.xml#id2September1889">see <hi rend="italics">Documentation</hi>, On or about 2 September 1889</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    