<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Thursday, 19 September 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let803"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b654 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>803</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>606</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>804</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-09-19">Thursday, 19 September 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0654" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000896_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000896_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0654" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000896_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000896_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000896_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste Moeder,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Vooreerst wil ik U<c type="kk">/</c> al is het laat<c type="kk">/</c> nog gelukwenschen met Uw verjaardag<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Reeds twee maal begon ik een brief die ik weer liet liggen<c type="kk">/</c> daar mijn hoofd niet naar schrijven stond.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wat geef ik U en Wil groot gelijk na Cor’s vertrek maar eens beiden voor een tijd een andere om<c type="shy">-</c>geving gezocht te hebben.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Er stond heel wat nieuws in uwe laatste brieven<c type="kk">/</c> vooreerst de bijzonderheden van Cors vertrek en dan dat U met November verhuizen gaat; ik kan ’t me wel begrijpen dat U gaarne meer in de buurt van uw kleinkinderen zijn wilt. Maar het zal toch een vreemd gevoel zijn te denken er niemand van ons in Brabant gebleven is<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Het is mijn plan U binnen kort een schilderij te sturen en aan Wil ook<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb ze onderhanden en tegen ’t eind van de maand zeker klaar<c type="kp">_</c> Doch eer ze droog genoeg zijn om te verzenden kan een 14 dagen langer duren.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Deze laatste weken gaat het me wat de gezondheid betreft volkomen goed en ik werk van s’morgens tot s’avonds haast aan een stuk door<c type="kk">/</c> den eenen dag voor<c type="kk">/</c> den anderen dag na<c type="kk">/</c> en ik sluit me in ’t atelier op om geen afleiding te hebben. Zoo blijft het me een groote troost dat het werk eer vóór- dan achteruit gaat en ik het met volkomen kalmte doe en mijn gedachten in dat opzigt geheel helder en zelfbewust zijn<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En zoo bij anderen vergeleken hier, die niets uitvoeren kunnen, heb ik bepaald geen reden tot klagen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">dezer dagen schreef ik aan Theo dat ik wel lust zou hebben voor een tijd minder ver van Parijs te zijn en denkelijk zal daar wel van komen. Niet dat ik er mijn vrijheid niet voor over heb om anderen <hi rend="italics">als</hi> het te erg wordt minder tot last te zijn, maar momenteel komt het nog tamelijk op ’t zelfde neer. En onder de artisten zijn er zoo velen die ondanks zenuwziekte – of toevallen van tijd tot tijd – toch hun gang gaan en in ’t schildersleven is het<c type="kk">/</c> naar ’t schijnt<c type="kk">/</c> niet genoeg schilderijen te maken maar moet men zijn relaties met andere schilders ook niet in ’t riet laten loopen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Mijn gezondheid is in de tusschentijden zóó goed en mijn maag zooveel beter dan vroeger dat ik geloof er nog jaren tusschen liggen kunnen eer ik geheel ongeschikt worde<c type="kk">/</c> ’t geen ik aanvankelijk vreesde direkt het geval zou zijn.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Dat alle uitstel geen afstel is als men met ziekte te doen heeft daar vrees ik nog wel meer van te merken in vervolg van tijd. Maar er schijnt geen regel op te zijn en de dokter<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> herhaalde mij al menigmaal dat men er niets vooruit van zeggen kan.– Maar als men weet dat het een kwaal is die blijft duren zult U U kunnen begrijpen dat men<c type="kk">/</c> al is men in ’t begin absoluut verbijstert<c type="kk">/</c> gaat wennen aan de gedachte en dan nadenkt aan wat men toch nog doen kan<c type="kp">_</c> En zulks zou nog kunnen meevallen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">In ’t begin was ik zoo mismoedig dat de lust me verging zelfs om vrienden weer te zien en te werken – nu tegenwoordig begint de behoefte aan die twee dingen te werken en daarbij komt dat in de tusschentijden eetlust en gezondheid volkomen goed zijn. En dus verlang ik erg naar Theo en zijn vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> die ik nog niet eens gezien heb<c type="kk">/</c> en stel belang in alles. En als ik er aan denk dat nieuwe vrienden zoeken nu niet noodig is dan denk ik te meer aan tegenwoordige en vroegere vrienden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">Toch begrijp ik dat ik hierin mij niet teveel mag verdiepen<c type="kk">/</c> daar het zoo heel anders kan blijken geschikt te moeten worden dan ik wel eens verzin en trouwens het een of ander <hi rend="italics">bepaald</hi> verlangen voel ik me niet gestemd toe<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">Alleen<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben zoo alles behalve dapper in het verdriet en alles behalve geduldig als ik niet wel ben ofschoon ik een tamelijk solide dosis geduld heb om aan mijn werk te blijven. Maar dat is ook letterlijk alles.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Zoodikwijls ik er gelegenheid toe heb werk ik op portretten waarvan ik zelf soms denk dat zij serieuser en beter zijn dan de rest van mijn werk<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> En <hi rend="italics">als</hi> het zijn mogt dat mijn toestand toelaat om weer naar Parijs of in de buurt terug te gaan zal dat wel hoofdzaak voor mij worden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">En nu zeg ik U goeden dag voor heden<c type="kk">/</c> neem het mij niet kwalijk ik niet eer schreef en binnen kort hoop ik U de schilderijen te sturen die ik voor U onderhanden heb. In gedachten omhelsd<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">First of all, even though it’s late, I want to wish you a happy birthday.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Twice I started a letter that I abandoned again because my mind wasn’t on writing.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> How very right of you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> simply both to have looked for other surroundings for a while after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>’s departure.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> There was a lot of news in your last letters, first of all the particulars about Cor’s departure, and then that you’re going to move in November; I can well understand that you’d really like to be closer to your grandchildren. But all the same it will be a strange feeling to think that none of us is left in Brabant.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’m planning to send you a painting before long, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> too, I’m working on them, and certainly finished by the end of the month. Although it may take another fortnight before they’re dry enough to send.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">These last few weeks I’ve been perfectly well as far as my health goes, and I work almost without stopping from morning till night, day after day, and I lock myself up in the studio to have no distractions. So it continues to be a great comfort to me that the work is progressing rather than going backwards, and I do it with perfect calm, and my thoughts in this respect are entirely clear and self-assured.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And so compared with others here, who can’t do anything, I certainly have no reason to complain. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The other day I wrote to Theo that I’d like to be not so far from Paris for a while, and probably something will come of it. Not that I’m unwilling to sacrifice my freedom so as to be less of a burden to others <hi rend="italics">if</hi> it gets too bad, but at the moment it comes down to much the same thing. And among artists there are so many who, despite nervous diseases — or seizures from time to time — nevertheless go their own way, and in the life of the painter it is, it seems, not enough to make paintings but one must also not let one’s relations with other painters be harmed.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">My health is so good between times and my stomach so much better than before that I believe it could still be years before I become completely unfit, which I initially feared would be the case immediately.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I’m afraid that I’ll again notice in time that tomorrow always comes when one is dealing with illness. But there doesn’t appear to be any rule to it, and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">doctor</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> repeated to me many times that one can say nothing about it in advance. But when one knows that it’s a malady that persists you’ll be able to understand that although one is completely overcome at first, one starts to get used to the idea and then considers what one can still do anyway. And that could still turn out better than expected.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">At first I was so despondent that I even lost the desire to see friends again and to work — now at the moment the need for those two things is beginning to act and, added to that, appetite and health are perfectly good between times. And so I really hanker for Theo and his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs>, whom I haven’t even seen yet, and am interested in everything. And when I think that now there’s no need to seek new friends, then I think all the more about present and former friends.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">All the same, I understand that I may not go into this too deeply, since it might have to be arranged so very differently from what I sometimes imagine, and besides I’m not disposed towards any <hi rend="italics">particular</hi> desire.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Only I’m anything but courageous in distress and anything but patient when I’m not well, although I do have a fairly solid measure of patience to keep at my work. But that’s literally all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">As often as I get the opportunity, I work on portraits that I sometimes think myself are more serious and better than the rest of my work.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> And <hi rend="italics">if</hi> it might be that my condition permits me to go back to Paris again, or in the vicinity, that will become the main thing for me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">And now I bid you goodbye for today, I beg your pardon for not writing before, and I hope to send you the paintings I’m making for you before long. Embraced in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Your loving</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In his letter to Willemien of 19 September, Vincent says that he has also written to their mother, by which he must be referring to this letter (<ref target="let804.xml">see letter 804</ref>). Because the two letters were most likely sent together, we have also dated the present letter to Thursday, 19 September 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Enclosed with <ref target="let804.xml">letter 804</ref> to Willemien.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Cor’s departure for South Africa <ref target="let784.xml">(784)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> celebrated her 70th birthday on 10 September.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had started a letter to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> on 9 September; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let801.xml">see letter 801</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> had been staying in Middelharnis, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> in Princenhage (FR b2902, b2931).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>By the end of September, Van Gogh had finished five canvases for his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield and cypresses </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2842">F 743 / JH 1790</rs>), an unknown painting of an olive grove, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Reaper </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2844">F 619 / JH 1792</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2845">F 483 / JH 1793</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait with clean-shaven face</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2769">F 525 / JH 1665</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let806.xml">See letter 806</ref>. Around 21 October he added two more – <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Field with a ploughman </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2825">F 625 / JH 1768</rs>) and a painting of an orchard in blossom – and sent the whole consignment to Theo in December (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let824.xml">see letter 824</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Théophile Peyron</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Shortly before this, Van Gogh had painted two self-portraits, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2827">F 627 / JH 1772</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2826">F 626 / JH 1770</rs>), and the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Charles-Elzéard Trabuc</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2829">F 629 / JH 1774</rs>)). At the time of writing, he was working on <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Jeanne Trabuc</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2832">F 631 / JH 1777</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let800.xml">See letters 800</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let801.xml">801</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">805</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    