<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Thursday, 19 September 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let804"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b714 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>804</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W14</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>805</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-09-19">Thursday, 19 September 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0714" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0714" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000969_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">déjà plus d’une fois j’ai essayé – dans l’intervalle depuis ma dernière lettre<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – de t’écrire à toi et à la mère. Je te remercie donc de m’avoir encore ecrit une si bonne lettre.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Que je vous donne raison à toutes les deux la mère et toi d’avoir quitté Breda pour quelque temps<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> après le départ de Cor.– Certes il ne faut pas que le chagrin s’amasse dans notre coeur comme l’eau d’une mare trouble<c type="kp">_</c>– Parfois je me sens interieurement ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> comme ayant l’ame bien troublée mais cela c’est une maladie et pour des personnes se portant bien et agissantes certes il faut faire comme vous avez faites.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Ainsi que je l’ecris à la mère<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> je lui enverrai 
mettons dans à peu près un mois un tableau et il y en aura un pour toi aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">J’en ai peint quelques uns pour moi-même aussi dans ces dernieres semaines – je n’aime pas trop à voir dans ma chambre à coucher mes propres tableaux donc j’en ai copié un de Delacroix<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> et quelques uns de Millet<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Le Delacroix est une piéta c.à.d. un Christ mort avec la Mater dolorosa. A l’entrée d’une grotte git incliné<c type="kk">/</c> les mains en avant sur le côté gauche<c type="kk">/</c> le cadavre épuisé et la femme se tient derrière<c type="kp">_</c> C’est une soirée après l’orages et cette figure desolée vêtue de bleu se détache – ses vêtements flottants agités par le vent – contre un ciel où flottent des nuages violets bordés d’or<c type="kp">_</c> Elle aussi par un grand geste désesperé etend les bras vides en avant et on voit ses mains<c type="kk">/</c> des bonnes mains solides d’ouvrière<c type="kp">_</c> Avec ses vetements flottants cette figure est presqu’aussi large d’envergure que haute<c type="kp">_</c> Et le visage du mort étant dans l’ombre<c type="kk">/</c> la tete pâle de la femme se detache en clair contre un nuage – opposition qui fait que ces deux têtes paraitraient une fleur sombre avec une fleur pâle<c type="kk">/</c> arrangées exprès pour se faire valoir. Je ne savais pas ce qu’était devenu ce tableau mais précisément pendant que j’étais en train d’y travailler je tombe sur un article de Pierre Loti<c type="kk">/</c> l’auteur de mon frère Yves et des Pêcheurs d’Islande et de M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Chrysanthème<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Un article de lui sur Carmen Sylva.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Si j’ai bonne mémoire tu as lu ses poesies<c type="kp">_</c> C’est une reine – est elle reine de la Hongrie ou d’un autre pays (je l’ignore) et Loti en decrivant son boudoir<c type="kk">/</c> ou plutot son atelier où elle écrit et où elle fait de la peinture<c type="kk">/</c> en parle qu’il y a vu cette toile de Delacroix en question<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui le frappa beaucoup.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Il parle de Carmen Sylva en faisant sentir qu’elle est personellement encore plus intéressante que ses paroles quoi qu’elle dise des chôses comme ceci: Une femme sans enfant c’est une cloche sans battant – le son de l’airain serait peut être bien beau – mais – ...<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Cependant cela fait du bien de songer qu’une telle toile soit dans de telle mains et cela console un peu les peintres de pouvoir s’imaginer que reellement il y a des ames qui sentent les tableaux.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Mais il y en a relativement peu<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’y ai pensé de t’envoyer à toi une esquisse de cela pour te donner une idée de ce qu’est Delacroix. Cette petite copie n’a bien entendu aucune valeur sous aucun point de vue<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Tu pourras pourtant y voir que Delacroix ne dessine pas les traits d’une mater Dolorosa à la façon des statues romaines –</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">et que l’aspect blafard<c type="kk">/</c> le regard eperdu et vague d’une personne fatiguée d’être en angoisse et en pleurs et en veilles y est à la Germinie Lacerteux plutôt.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Je trouve fort bien et fort heureux que tu ne sois pas absolument enthousiaste du livre magistral de de Goncourt<c type="kp">_</c> Tant mieux que tu préfères Tolstoi<c type="kk">/</c> toi qui lis surtout les livres pour y puiser des energies pour agir. Je te donne mille fois raison<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Mais moi qui lis les livres pour y chercher l’artiste qui l’a fait<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> aurais je tort de tant aimer les romanciers francais.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Je viens de terminer le portrait d’une femme d’une bonne quarantaine d’années<c type="kk">/</c> insignifiante. le visage fané et fatigué<c type="kk">/</c> marqué de la petite vérole<c type="kk">/</c> un teint olivâtre et hâlé<c type="kk">/</c> cheveux noirs<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Une robe noire fanée ornee d’un geranium rose tendre et le fond d’un ton neutre entre le rose et le vert<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Parceque je peins quelquefois des chôses comme cela – aussi peu et autant dramatiques qu’un brin d’herbe poudreux au bord de la route – il est juste à ce qu’il me semble que j’aie moi une admiration sans bornes pour de Goncourt<c type="kk">/</c> Zola<c type="kk">/</c> Flaubert<c type="kk">/</c> Maupassant<c type="kk">/</c> Huysmans. Mais pour toi ne te presse pas et continue hardiment les Russes. As tu déjà lu ma religion de Tolstoi<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> – cela doit être très pratique et reellement utile<c type="kp">_</c> Va donc bien à fond là-dedans puisque tu aimes cela<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">J’ai dernierement fait deux portraits de moi dont l’un est je crois assez dans le caractère<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> mais en Hollande ils s’en moqueraient probablement des idees qui germent ici quant aux portraits<c type="kp">_</c> As tu vu chez Theo le portrait du peintre Guillaumin et le portrait de jeune femme par le même<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Cela donne bien une idee de ce que l’on cherche<c type="kp">_</c> Lorsque Guillaumin exposait son portrait<c type="kk">/</c> public et artistes en ont beaucoup ri,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> et cependant c’est une des chôses rares qui se tiendraient à côté des vieux Hollandais Rembrandt et Hals mêmes<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Je trouve toujours les photographies affreuses moi et je n’aime pas à en avoir<c type="kk">/</c> surtout pas des gens que je connais et que j’aime<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Ces portraits-là d’abord sont fanés plus vite que nous mêmes tandis que durant bien des générations le portrait peint reste<c type="kp">_</c> Un portrait peint d’ailleurs est une chôse sentie faite avec amour ou respect de l’être représenté<c type="kp">_</c> Que nous reste-t-il des vieux Hollandais? les portraits<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Ainsi dans la famille de Mauve les enfants le verront encore toujours dans le portrait que Mesker a très bien fait de lui<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Je viens au moment même de recevoir une lettre de Théo dans laquelle il me répond au sujet de ce que je lui avais dit de mon desir de retourner pour un temps dans le nord<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Il est assez probable que cela se fera<c type="kk">/</c> dire au juste quand<c type="kk">/</c> cela dépend encore 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>des occasions qu’il y aurait d’aller vivre avec un artiste ou un autre<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Mais comme nous en connaissons plusieurs et que souvent il est avantageux de vivre à deux<c type="kk">/</c> cela ne tardera pas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Enfin je te dis à bientôt en te remerciant encore beaucoup de tes lettres<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">Je ne sais encore quels toiles je t’enverrai à toi et à la mère<c type="kk">/</c> probablement un champ de blé et un verger d’oliviers avec cette copie d’après Delacroix.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">Il fait un temps splendide dehors depuis bien longtemps<c type="kk">/</c> pourtant<c type="kk">/</c> je ne sais pourquoi<c type="kk">/</c> je ne suis sorti de ma chambre de deux mois<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Il me faudrait du courage et j’en manque souvent<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">Et c’est aussi que depuis ma maladie le sentiment de solitude s’empare de moi dans les champs d’une façon si redoutable que j’hésite à sortir<c type="kp">_</c> Avec le temps cela changera cependant encore<c type="kp">_</c> Ce n’est que devant le chevalet en peignant que je sens un peu de vie<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Enfin cela changera encore car ma santé va tellement bien que le physique gagnera encore la partie<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.30" n="30">Je t’embrasse bien en pensée et à bientôt<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.31" n="31">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">More than once already I’ve tried – in the interval since my last letter<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – to write to you and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>. So I thank you for having again written me such a kind letter.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> How right I think both of you were, Mother and you, to have left Breda for a while<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>’s departure. Certainly grief mustn’t build up in our hearts like the water of a turbid pool. From time to time I feel like that inside, as if I have a very turbid soul, but that’s an illness, and for people who are well and active, certainly they must do as you have done.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">As I write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I’ll send her a painting in let’s say around a month, and there’ll be one for you too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I’ve painted a few for myself, too, these past few weeks – I don’t much like seeing my own paintings in my bedroom, so I’ve copied one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and a few by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> is a Pietà, i.e. a dead Christ with the Mater Dolorosa. The exhausted corpse lies bent forward on its left side at the entrance to a cave, its hands outstretched, and the woman stands behind. It’s an evening after the storm, and this desolate, blue-clad figure stands out – its flowing clothes blown about by the wind – against a sky in which violet clouds fringed with gold are floating. In a great gesture of despair she too is stretching out her empty arms, and one can see her hands, a working woman’s good, solid hands. With its flowing clothes this figure is almost as wide in extent as it’s tall. And as the dead man’s face is in shadow, the woman’s pale head stands out brightly against a cloud – an opposition which makes these two heads appear to be a dark flower with a pale flower, arranged expressly to bring them out better. I didn’t know what had become of this painting, but while I was in the very process of working on it I came across an article by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Pierre Loti</rs>, the author of Mon frère Yves and Pêcheur d’Islande and Madame Chrysanthème.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">An article by him on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_835">Carmen Sylva</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">If I remember rightly, you’ve read her poems. She’s a queen – she’s queen of Hungary or another country (I don’t know which), and in describing her boudoir, or rather her studio where she writes and where she makes paintings, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs> says that he saw this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> canvas there, which struck him greatly.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">He speaks of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_835">Carmen Sylva</rs>, making one feel that she’s personally even more interesting than her words, although she says things like this: A woman without a child is a bell without a clapper – the sound of the bronze would perhaps be very beautiful – but — ...<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">However, it does one good to think that a canvas like that is in such hands, and it consoles painters a little to be able to imagine that really there are souls who have a feeling for paintings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But there are relatively few of them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I thought of sending you yourself a sketch of it to give you an idea of what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> is. This little copy of course has no value from any point of view.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> However, you’ll be able to see in it that Delacroix doesn’t draw the features of a Mater Dolorosa in the manner of Roman statues –</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">And that the pallid aspect, the lost, vague gaze of a person tired of being in anguish and in tears and keeping vigil is present in it rather in the manner of Germinie Lacerteux.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I consider it very good and very fortunate that you’re not absolutely enthusiastic about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>’s masterly book. So much the better that you prefer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_829">Tolstoy</rs>, you who read books above all to derive energies from them in order to act. I think you’re right a thousand times over.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But I, who read books to seek in them the artist who made them,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> could I be wrong to like French novelists so much?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’ve just finished the portrait of a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_792">woman</rs> of forty or more, insignificant. The face faded and tired, pockmarked, an olive-tinged, suntanned complexion, black hair.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">A faded black dress adorned with a soft pink geranium, and the background in a neutral tone between pink and green.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Because I sometimes paint things like that – with as little and as much drama as a dusty blade of grass by the side of the road – it’s right, as it seems to me, that I should have an unbounded admiration for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_596">Flaubert</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_708">Maupassant</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_672">Huysmans</rs>. But as regards yourself, don’t hurry, and continue boldly with the Russians. Have you read Ma religion by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_829">Tolstoy</rs><ptr target="#note-t-15"/> yet – it must be very practical and really useful. So go right to the very depths of that, since you like it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Lately I’ve done two portraits of myself, one of which is quite in character, I think,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> but in Holland they’d probably scoff at the ideas about portraits that are germinating here. Did you see at Theo’s the portrait of the painter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> and the portrait of a young woman by the same?<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> That really gives an idea of what one is searching for. When Guillaumin exhibited his portrait, public and artists laughed at it a great deal,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and yet it’s one of the rare things that would hold up alongside even the old Dutchmen <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Hals</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">I myself still find photographs frightful and don’t like to have any, especially not of people whom I know and love.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">These portraits, first, are faded more quickly than we ourselves, while the painted portrait remains for many generations. Besides, a painted portrait is a thing of feeling made with love or respect for the being represented. What remains to us of the old Dutchmen? The portraits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Thus in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs>’s family the children will always continue to see him in the portrait that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1216">Mesker</rs> did so very well of him.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">At this very moment I’ve just received a letter from Theo in which he answers me on the subject of what I’d said of my desire to return to the north for a while.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> It’s quite likely that this will happen, to say exactly when, that still depends 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> on the opportunities there may be to go and live with some artist or another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">But as we know several of them and it’s often advantageous to live in pairs, it won’t take long.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24">Finally, I say ‘à bientôt’ to you, thanking you again very much for your letters.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25">I don’t know yet which canvases I’ll send to you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>, probably a wheatfield and an olive grove with that copy after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.26" n="26">The weather outside has been splendid for a very long time, but I haven’t left my room for two months, I don’t know why.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">I would need courage, and I often lack it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.28" n="28">And it’s also that since my illness the feeling of loneliness takes hold of me in the fields in such a fearsome way that I hesitate to go out. With time, though, that will change again. It’s only in front of the easel while painting that I feel a little of life.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.29" n="29">Anyway, that will change again, for my health is so good that the physique will win the day again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.30" n="30">I kiss you affectionately in thought, and more soon.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.31" n="31">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">On the basis of Vincent’s remark that he has ‘just’ received a letter from Theo <ref target="#l-124">(ll. 124-125)</ref> – this was <ref target="let802.xml">letter 802</ref> of 18 September – we have dated the present letter to Thursday, 19 September 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Enclosed with <ref target="let803.xml">letter 803</ref> to Mrs van Gogh.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Cor’s departure for South Africa <ref target="let784.xml">(784)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent has paintings intended for his mother and Willemien <ref target="let803.xml">(803)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent’s suggestion that he live with Pissarro <ref target="let801.xml">(801)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The last letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let785.xml">letter 785</ref> of 2 July 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> had written to Vincent between 8 and 12 September (FR b2931).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> had been staying in Middelharnis, and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> in Princenhage (FR b2902, b2931).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The letter to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let803.xml">letter 803</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh painted two versions of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pietà (after Delacroix)</hi>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2830">F 630 / JH 1775</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2831">F 757 / JH 1776</rs>, after the lithograph by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1251">Nanteuil-Leboeuf</rs> after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_75">Pietà</rs></hi> (for the lithograph, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-3">see letter 686, n. 3</ref>). The canvas he describes here, which he made for his bedroom, is F 630.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">Letter 805</ref> to Theo reveals that these paintings are copies after the series <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1887">The labours of the field</rs></hi>, consisting of ten prints on one sheet, engraved by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1155">Adrien Lavieille</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml#n-1">see letter 156, n. 1</ref>). Here Van Gogh mentions ‘a few’ copies (in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">letter 805</ref> he meanwhile has seven). Because he most likely kept to the order of the prints, the ‘few’ mentioned here were probably the first of the series (for the prints and Van Gogh’s paintings after them, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml#n-6">see letter 805, n. 6</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Pierre Loti</rs>’s novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_359">Mon frère Yves</ref></hi> (1883) is the story of the friendship between the first-person narrator, Pierre, and his friend Yves, both sailors. Pierre is an officer and can therefore protect Yves, who has inherited his father’s tendency to drink too much. This weakness causes problems on board ship and in Yves’s young family. Pierre’s support is crucial, and eventually Yves mends his ways. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> probably read this book because Vincent mentioned it here; on 19 October 1889, she wrote to J<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">o van Gogh-Bonger</rs> that she had enjoyed it very much (FR b2404).</p>

<p rend="indent">For Loti’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_502">Pêcheur d’Islande</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let714.xml#n-3">see letter 714, n. 3,</ref> and for <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_481">Madame Chrysanthème</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let628.xml#n-20">see letter 628, n. 20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_71">Carmen Sylva</ref>’ by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Pierre Loti</rs> was published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Figaro, Supplément Littéraire</hi> of 28 April 1888; the second part appeared on 5 May. Van Gogh took his information from the first part.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs> gives a detailed description of the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">boudoir</hi> of the Romanian queen. Commenting on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>’s painting, Loti said: ‘When she was seated at her work, I could see, from the spot she had indicated to me on the first day, and which it was my habit to resume, her face and her veil standing out in front of a large, superb canvas by Delacroix: the entombment of Christ.’ (Lorsqu’elle était assise à travailler, de la place qu’elle m’avait indiquée le premier jour et que j’avais coutume de reprendre, je voyais son visage et son voile se détacher en avant d’une grande et superbe toile de Delacroix: la mise au tombeau du Christ.) This was in fact a copy of Delacroix’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_992">The lamentation</rs></hi>, 1844 (Saint-Denis du Saint-Sacrement, Paris). Van Gogh must have misidentified this painting as the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pietà</hi> he was interested in. See Johnson 1981-1989, vol. 5, p. 80, n. 1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_704">Loti</rs> quotes the saying that a house without a child is like a bell without a clapper. The passage comes from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_835">Carmen Sylva</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_83">Les pensées d’une reine</ref></hi> (The thoughts of a queen): ‘A house without children is like a bell without a clapper. The dormant sound would surely be very beautiful, if there were something to awaken it!’ (Une maison sans enfants est comme une cloche sans battant. Le son qui dort serait bien beau, s’il y avait quelque chose pour le réveiller!) See Sylva 1888, p. 45 (‘L’amour’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The ‘little copy’ is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pietà (after Delacroix) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2831">F 757 / JH 1776</rs>); the canvas measures 42 x 34 cm. Van Gogh painted this ‘sketch’ first, as emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let801.xml">letter 801</ref>. It did eventually come into <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>’s possession (see also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-21">n. 21</ref> below).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>For the novel <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_449">Germinie Lacerteux</ref></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">Jules and Edmond de Goncourt</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let574.xml#n-5">see letter 574, n. 5.</ref> Germinie’s sad appearance, which Van Gogh compares with that of his model, is expressed in the following passage, among others: ‘the whiteness of her back, contrasting with the brown of her face. It was the whiteness of lethargy, the whiteness, both sickly and angelic, of flesh that is not alive.’ (la blancheur de son dos, contrastant avec le hâle de son visage. C’était une blancheur de lymphatique, la blancheur à la fois malade et angélique d’une chair qui ne vit pas.) Ed. Paris 1887, chapter 5, p. 52. Cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let685.xml#n-10">letter 685, n. 10</ref> and Sund 1992, p. 292 (n. 91).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
  
<p>This idea is based on <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_311">Mon Salon</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let515.xml#n-11">see letter 515, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the first version of the portrait of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_792">Jeanne Trabuc</rs>, the 55-year-old wife of the chief orderly. He made a repetition of it and let Madame Trabuc choose between them (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">see letter 805</ref>). Only the portrait that was sent to Theo is known: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Jeanne Trabuc</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2832">F 631 / JH 1777</rs>). Because we do not know if Theo received the first or the second version, we cannot tell whether the portrait he had is the one referred to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            
  
<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_829">Tolstoy</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_293">Ma religion</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-10">see letter 686, nn. 10</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-20">20.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2826">F 626 / JH 1770</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2827">F 627 / JH 1772</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2292">Self-portrait with palette</rs></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_146">Portrait of a young woman</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let800.xml#n-21">see letter 800, n. 21.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> exhibited his <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2292">Self-portrait with palette</rs></hi> in 1880 at the fifth exhibition of the Impressionists (no. 72, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Portrait de M.G.</hi>). <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_146">Portrait of a young woman</rs></hi> was shown at the eighth and last exhibition, in 1886 (no. 65, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Portrait</hi>). See Ruth Berson, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The New Painting. Impressionism 1874-1886. Documentation. Volume II. Exhibited Works</hi>, San Francisco 1996, pp. 150, 244.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1216">Theo Mesker</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Anton Mauve</hi>, 1871 (present whereabouts unknown). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1143">Ill. 1143</rs>. See Engel 1967, no. B1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>The letter to Theo was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let802.xml">letter 802</ref>. This remark prompted <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> to ask Theo on 2 October 1889: ‘Is Vincent perhaps coming to Paris again, he wrote that to me’ (FR b2401).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>The consignment of paintings intended for his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>, which Vincent sent to Theo in December, did contain canvases of a wheatfield and an olive grove, but not the copy after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let824.xml">See letter 824</ref>. F 757 did eventually come into Willemien’s possession; see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book </hi>2002, p. 20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had not been out of doors since his attack on 16 or 17 July 1889 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let793.xml#n-1">see letter 793, n. 1</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    