<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Tuesday, 8 October 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let810"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b658 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>810</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>610</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>810</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-10-08">on or about Tuesday, 8 October 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0658" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000901_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000901_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0658" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000901_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000901_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000901_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">je viens de rentrer une toile à laquelle je travaille depuis quelque temps representant encore le même champ du faucheur. À present c’est des mottes de terre et le fonds les terrains arides puis les rochers des Alpines<c type="kp">_</c> Un bout de ciel bleu vert avec petit nuage blanc &amp; violet<c type="kp">_</c> Sur l’avant plan: Un chardon et des herbes sèches<c type="kp">_</c> Un paysan trainant une botte de paille au milieu<c type="kp">_</c> C’est encore une etude rude et au lieu d’être jaune presqu’en<c type="shy">-</c>tierement cela fait une toile violette presque tout à fait. Des violets rompus et neutres.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Mais je t’ecris cela parceque je crois que cela complètera le faucheur et fera mieux voir ce que c’est. Car le faucheur parait fait au hasard et ceci avec le mettra d’aplomb. Aussitôt seche je te l’envoie avec la repetition de la chambre à coucher.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Je te prie beaucoup de les montrer<c type="kk">/</c> si l’un ou l’autre verra les etudes<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="italics">ensemble</hi> à cause de l’opposition des complémentaires<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Puis j’ai fait cette semaine l’entrée d’une carrière qui est comme une chôse japonaise<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> tu te rappelles bien qu’il y a des dessins japonais de rochers où croissent cà et là des herbes et de petits arbres. Il y a des moments entre temps où la nature est superbe<c type="kk">/</c> des effets d’automne d’un glorieux comme couleur<c type="kk">/</c> des ciels verts contrastant avec des végétations jaunes<c type="kk">/</c> orangées<c type="kk">/</c> vertes<c type="kk">/</c> des terrains de tous les violets<c type="kk">/</c> l’herbe brûlée où les pluies ont néamoins rendu une derniere vigueur à certaines plantes qui se reprennent à produire des petites fleurs violettes<c type="kk">/</c> roses<c type="kk">/</c> bleues<c type="kk">/</c> jaunes. Des chôses qu’on est tout mélancolique de ne pouvoir rendre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Et des ciels – comme nos ciels du nord mais les couleurs des couchers et des levers de soleil sont plus variées et plus franches. Comme dans les Jules Dupré et les Ziem.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">J’ai aussi deux vues du parc et de la maison de santé où ce lieu parait fort agréable<c type="kp">_</c> J’ai cherché à reconstruire la chôse comme cela a pu être en simplifiant et en accentuant le caractère fier et inalterable des pins et des buissons de cèdre contre le bleu<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Enfin – si serait qu’ils se souviendraient de moi – ce à quoi je ne tiens pas – il y aura de quoi envoyer quelque chôse de coloré aux vingtistes. Mais cela m’est indifferent<c type="kp">_</c> Ce qui ne m’est pas indifférent c’est qu’un homme qui m’est très supérieur<c type="kk">/</c> Meunier<c type="kk">/</c> ait peint les scloneuses du Borinage et le trait allant à fosse et les usines<c type="kk">/</c> leurs toits rouges et leurs cheminées noires contre un ciel gris fin<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – toutes chôses que j’ai rêvées de faire<c type="kk">/</c> sentant que ce n’était pas fait et que cela devait être peint. Et encore il y a pour les artistes des sujets à l’infini par là et il faudrait descendre dans le fond et peindre les effets de lumière<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Si tu n’as pas encore expedié la toile et les couleurs<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> saches que je suis absolument sans toile à présent<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Et j’allais te demander si serait le cas que tu trouverais difficulté à envoyer le montant de ce que je lui dois à m. Peyron tout de suite<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> s’il t’etait possible de m’envoyer alors par bon de poste une quinzaine de francs j’irais un de ces jours à Arles<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Souvent il me semble que si Gauguin etait resté ici il n’y aurait rien perdu car je vois bien aussi dans la lettre qu’il m’a écrite qu’il n’est pas en plein dans son fort.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Et je sais bien à quoi cela tient – ils sont trop gênés pour trouver les modèles<c type="kk">/</c> et vivre à si bon compte qu’il croyait possible dans le commencement n’aura pas duré. Cependant avec sa patience l’année prochaine sera peut être épatante. mais alors il n’aura pas Bernard avec lui si celui là fait son service.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Est ce que tu sens combien les figures de Jules Breton et Billet<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> et autres <hi rend="italics">resteront</hi><c type="kp">_</c> Ces gens-là ont vaincu la difficulté des modèles et c’est beaucoup cela<c type="kp">_</c> Et un tableau d’Otto Weber du bon temps (pas des anglais)<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> comme cela doit se maintenir<c type="kp">_</c> Une hirondelle n’amène pas le printemps et une idée nouvelle n’abat point des oeuvres faites et parfaites<c type="kp">_</c> C’est là le terrible des impressionistes que le développement de la chôse cloche et qu’ils restent des années devant des obstacles dont la génération précédente avait triomphé<c type="kk">/</c> la difficulté d’argent et de modèles. Et ainsi Breton<c type="kk">/</c> Billet et autres doivent bien s’en moquer et s’etonner et dire: “mais voyons à quand vos paysans et vos paysannes”.– Moi je me sens pour un honteux et défait.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">j’ai copié cette femme avec un enfant assise auprès d’un foyer de M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Dumont Breton<c type="kk">/</c> presque tout violet<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> je vais certainement continuer à copier<c type="kk">/</c> cela me fera une collection à moi et lorsque ce sera 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>important et complet assez je donne le tout à une école<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Je peux t’annoncer aussi que prochain envoi tu feras plus amplement connaissance avec les Alpines du bon Tartarin<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> que jusqu’à présent – sauf la toile des montagnes<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> – tu n’as encore vu se defiler que tout au fond des toiles<c type="kp">_</c> J’en ai une étude plus rude que la précédente des montagnes<c type="kp">_</c> Un ravin très sauvage où se faufile un mince ruisseau dans son lit de rochers<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">C’est tout violet. De ces Alpines je pourrais certes faire toute une série car les ayant vus à présent longtemps je me suis un peu fait à cela. Tu te rappelles ce beau paysage de Monticelli que nous avons vu chez Delarebeyrette d’un arbre sur des rochers contre un couchant.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> Des effets comme cela il y en a beaucoup à présent<c type="kk">/</c> seulement je ne peux jamais être dehors à l’heure du coucher de soleil sans quoi j’en aurais essayé.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Est ce que la santé de Jo continue à aller bien. je crois qu’en somme cette année est plus heureuse pour toi que les précédentes. Pour moi la santé va bien de ces jours ci – je crois bien que M. Peyron a raison lorsqu’il dit que je ne suis pas fou proprement dit car ma pensée est absolument normale et claire entre temps et même davantage qu’auparavant. mais dans les crises c’est pourtant terrible et alors je perds connaissance de tout. Mais cela me pousse au travail et au serieux comme un charbonnier toujours en danger se dépêche dans ce qu’il fait. La mère et la soeur feront leurs préparatifs de déménagement<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Je t’envoie ci inclus un mot pour Isaacson<c type="kk">/</c> Bernard et Gauguin<c type="kp">_</c> C’est naturellement pas pressé du tout de le leur remettre. la première fois qu’ils viendront te voir suffit. Le soir je m’embête à mourir<c type="kk">/</c> mon dieu la perspective de l’hiver n’est pas gaie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">J’espère que tu auras reçu en bon ordre les toiles expediées il y a une dizaine de jours.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Je m’en vais faire une longue course dans les montagnes pour chercher des sites<c type="kp">_</c> à bientôt – surtout envoie la couleur et la toile si c’est pas expédié car je n’ai plus de toile du tout ni de blanc de zinc.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Bien des chôses à Jo.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve just brought back a canvas I’ve been working on for some time, once again of the same field as the one of the reaper. Now it’s mounds of earth and the background parched lands, then the rocks of the Alpilles. A bit of blue-green sky with small white and violet cloud. In the foreground: A thistle and some dry grass. A peasant dragging a bundle of straw in the middle. It’s another harsh study, and instead of being almost entirely yellow it makes an almost completely violet canvas. Broken and neutral violets.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">But I’m writing you this because I think that this will complement the reaper and will make it easier to see what it is. For the reaper appears done at random, and this with it will balance it. As soon as it’s dry I’ll send it to you with the repetition of the bedroom.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I seriously ask you to show them <hi rend="italics">together</hi>, if someone or other comes to see the studies, because of the opposition of the complementaries.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then this week I’ve done the entrance to a quarry, which is like a Japanese thing,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> you’ll well remember that there are Japanese drawings of rocks where grasses and little trees grow here and there. There are moments between times when nature is superb, autumnal effects glorious in colour, green skies contrasting with yellow, orange, green vegetation, earth in all shades of violet, burnt grass where the rains have nevertheless given a last vigour to certain plants, which again start to produce little violet, pink, blue, yellow flowers. Things that make you quite melancholy not to be able to render them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And the skies – like our northern skies, but the colours of the sunsets and sunrises are more varied and more pure. As in works by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Jules Dupré</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1449">Ziem</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I also have two views of the park and the asylum in which this place appears most agreeable. I tried to reconstruct the thing as it may have been by simplifying and accentuating the proud, unchanging nature of the pines and the cedar bushes against the blue.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Anyway – if they should happen to remember me – which I’m not keen on – there’ll be enough to send something coloured to the Vingtistes. But I’m indifferent to that. What I’m not indifferent to is that a man who is far superior to me, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1209">Meunier</rs>, has painted the female thrutchers of the Borinage and the shift going to the pit and the factories, their red roofs and their black chimneys against a delicate grey sky<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – all things I’ve dreamed of doing, feeling that it hadn’t been done and that it ought to be painted. And still, there’s an infinite number of subjects there for artists, and one should go down into the depths and paint the light effects.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">If you haven’t yet sent the canvas and the colours,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> you should know that I now have absolutely no canvas.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">And I was going to ask you if you would find it difficult to send the amount of what I owe to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> immediately,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> if it was possible for you then to send me about fifteen francs by postal order, I would go to Arles one of these days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">It often seems to me that if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had remained here he wouldn’t have lost anything, for I clearly see, also in the letter he wrote me, that he isn’t entirely at the top of his form.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> And I know well the cause of that – they’re too hard up to find models, and living as cheaply as he thought possible at the beginning won’t have lasted. However, with his patience, next year will perhaps be dazzling. But then he won’t have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> with him if the latter does his military service.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Do you sense how much the figures of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules Breton</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_876">Billet</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and others <hi rend="italics">will remain</hi>? Those people overcame the difficulty of models, and that’s a lot. And a painting like that by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1423">Otto Weber</rs> from the good period (not the English)<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> is bound to hold its own. One swallow doesn’t make a summer, and one new idea doesn’t in any way destroy works that have been done and perfected. That’s the terrible thing about the Impressionists, that the development of the thing gets stuck, and that for years they’re left facing obstacles that the preceding generation had overcome, the difficulty of money and models. And so Breton, Billet and others really are certain to mock it and be astonished and say: ‘come on, when are we going to see your peasants and your peasant women?’ As for me, I feel ashamed and defeated.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">I’ve copied that woman with a child sitting beside a hearth by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_901">Mrs Demont-Breton</rs>, almost all violet,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> I’m certainly going to continue copying, it will give me a collection of my own, and when it’s 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> sufficiently large and complete I’ll give the whole lot to a school.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I can also tell you that next consignment you’ll become better acquainted with good Tartarin’s Alpilles,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> which up to now – apart from the canvas of the mountains<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> – you haven’t yet seen unfold, except in the distant background of the canvases. I have a study, rougher than the previous one of the mountains. A very wild ravine where a slender stream weaves its way along its bed of rocks.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">It’s all violet. I could certainly do an entire series of these Alpilles, for having seen them for a long time now I’ve got used to it a little. You remember that fine landscape by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> that we saw at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_344">Delarebeyrette</rs>’s, of a tree on some rocks against a sunset.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> There are a lot of effects like that at the moment, only I can’t ever be outside at the time the sun sets, otherwise I would have tried it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Does <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> continue in good health? I think that all in all this year is happier for you than the preceding ones. As for me, my health has been good lately – I really think that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> is right when he says that strictly speaking I’m not mad, for my thoughts are absolutely normal and clear between times, and even more than before, but during the crises it’s terrible however, and then I lose consciousness of everything. But it drives me to work and to seriousness, as a coal-miner who is always in danger makes haste in what he does. Our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> will be making their preparations to move house.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’m enclosing a note for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>. Naturally there’s no urgency at all to get it to them. The first time they come to see you will suffice. In the evenings I’m bored to death, my God the prospect of winter isn’t a cheery one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">I hope that you’ll have received the canvases sent about ten days ago in good order.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">I’m going off for a long hike in the mountains to look for sites. More soon – above all send the paint and the canvas if it hasn’t been sent, for I’ve no canvas left at all, nor any zinc white.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Kind regards to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh is referring to the consignment of paintings which he sent ‘about ten days ago’ <ref target="#l-125">(l. 125)</ref>. Considering that he sent the consignment on Saturday, 28 September (<ref target="let806.xml">see letter 806</ref>), we have dated the present letter to about Tuesday, 8 October 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh enclosed letters for Isaäcson and Gauguin (both no longer extant), as well as one for Bernard (<ref target="let809.xml">letter 809</ref>), and asked Theo to deliver them.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Third consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let806.xml">(806)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had depicted this field in his three versions of the <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Reaper</hi>: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2813">F 617 / JH 1753</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2828">F 618 / JH 1773</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2844">F 619 / JH 1792</rs>. The new study is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ploughed field with a man carrying a bundle of straw </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2846">F 641 / JH 1795</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3007">F 484 / JH 1771</rs>) is the repetition of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Entrance to a quarry </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2824">F 635 / JH 1767</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The description ‘the pines and the cedar bushes against the blue’ refers to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pine trees in the garden of the asylum </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2850">F 643 / JH 1799</rs>). The second work is probably <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Trees in the garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2849">F 642 / JH 1798</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
      
<p>For the paintings <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1150">Black region, Borinage</rs></hi>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_892">Female coal-pit drawers (the coupling point)</rs></hi> and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_893">Return from the pit (black)</rs></hi> by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1209">Meunier</rs>, which Theo had written about, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let802.xml#n-5">see letter 802, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let808.xml">letter 808</ref> Van Gogh had said that he urgently needed zinc white and canvas.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Vincent owed <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Dr Peyron</rs> 125 francs; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let808.xml">see letter 808</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is probably referring here to the letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, receipt of which he confirmed in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let797.xml">letter 797</ref> of 22 August. From <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let808.xml">letter 808</ref> it emerges that he had not yet answered it.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s military service, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let575.xml#n-8">see letter 575, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_876">Pierre Billet</rs> was a pupil of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules Breton</rs>. He belonged to the second generation of realists and specialized in portraying the life of peasants and fishermen.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1423">Otto Weber</rs>, a pupil of Steffeck in Berlin and Couture in Paris, had specialized in landscape painting. In 1854 his work was exhibited at the Berlin Salon, and he received prizes at the Paris Salon of 1864 and 1869. He later settled in London, where he worked for Queen Victoria. From 1874 until his death he exhibited regularly at the Royal Academy, specializing in watercolours. Van Gogh’s remark therefore refers to work Weber had made before 1874.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The husband is at sea (after Demont-Breton) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2854">F 644 / JH 1805</rs>). For the print by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_901">Virginie Demont-Breton</rs> after which Van Gogh made the painting, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let800.xml#n-26">see letter 800, n. 26.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let583.xml#n-9">see letter 583, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Theo had received <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alpilles with a hut </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2823">F 622 / JH 1766</rs>) in the second consignment from Saint-Rémy; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let807.xml">see letter 807</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ravine </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2853">F 662 / JH 1804</rs>). Owing to a lack of canvas (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#l-55">see ll. 55-56</ref>), Van Gogh painted this over a landscape from June 1889. See Chavannes and Van Tilborgh 2007.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>It is not known which work by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> is referred to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    