<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Le Pouldu, between about Sunday, 10 and Wednesday, 13 November 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let817"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b866 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>817</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>GAC 37</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>819</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-10">between about Sunday, 10 and Wednesday, 13 November 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Le Pouldu</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0866" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0866" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001156_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Vincent</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">J’ai reçu votre lettre l’autre jour<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> et je vois avec plaisir que vous voilà remis (si ce n’est sans retour) au moins pour longtemps: temps pendant lequel vous allez pouvoir travailler. Non je n’ai pu voir vos dernières toiles, étant depuis longtemps en Bretagne,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> mais de Haan le hollandais qui est avec moi a reçu une lettre d’un ami lui disant que vos nouvelles toiles étaient réellement quelque chose de bien artiste et plus imaginatif que les autres.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Je suis content que vous vous souveniez de nos conversations en tant que dessin, et de Haan qui m’a écouté là-dessus a fait de réels progrès ici sur ce rapport. J’ai peu de nouvelles à vous donner des amis étant moi-même un peu isolé de tout – Laval est à Paris – Bernard à S<hi rend="super">t </hi>Briac<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Son père lui a totalement défendu d’être à Pont aven<hi rend="italics"> avec moi</hi>. Vous vous rappelez sans doute la lettre bourgeoise du bonhomme courroucé<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Bernard m’écrit quelquefois; il a beaucoup changé à son avantage et comme artiste il continue à faire des choses curieuses et belles<c type="kp">_</c>– Il n’en n’est pas de même pour moi<c type="kp">_</c>– J’ai une malheureuse nature qui a soif de nouveau et je ne peux m’empêcher de faire de nouvelles recherches. J’ai cette année fait un travail tout autre que l’année dernière, travail préparatoire à une chose que j’<hi rend="italics">entrevois </hi>importante. J’ai fait chez vous à Arles un tableau un peu dans ce sens – Les vendanges (un tableau dont vous avez fait le dessin.) Une femme assise, des vignes en triangle rouge<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Degas ne comprend pas celui-là<c type="kp">_</c>– Dans cet ordre d’idées abstraites je suis amené à chercher la forme et la couleur synthétiques<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Le moins de métier possible et par ci par là des accessoires très-peu executés pour laisser à l’impression d’une figure toute sa puissance et ne pas tomber dans la babiole<c type="kk">/</c> enfantillage<c type="kp">_</c>– J’ai devant moi plusieurs eaux fortes, reproductions de tableaux etc. de Rembrandt et j’y trouve beaucoup de ces choses-là<c type="kp">_</c>– Dans celui que vous avez (la tête d’ange executée et le reste inachevé).<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Dans le Tobie<c type="kk">/</c> si toutefois c’est un Tobie<c type="kk">/</c> le lion est imposant<c type="kk">/</c> puissant, le paysage aussi et tout le coin d’avant plan inachevé, le bonhomme aussi<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Il m’a semblé à moi que c’était un <hi rend="italics">parti pris</hi> et j’ai recherché le pourquoi parceque<c type="kp">_</c>– Et ce n’est pas une raison parceque je ne suis pas un maître pour que je n’entre pas dans l’ordre d’idées d’un maître comme celui-là (avec des applications différentes). Tout celà (mon cher Vincent) me fait crier dessus à Paris (et je sens qu’ils ont tort)<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> j’ai fait cette année des efforts inouis de travail et de réflexion et j’ai l’air de m’être reposé<c type="kp">_</c>– J’ai à la maison une chose que je n’ai pas envoyée et qui vous irait je crois<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">C’est le Christ dans le jardin des Oliviers – Ciel bleu vert<c type="kk">/</c> crépuscule, des arbres tous penchés en masse pourpre, terrain violet et le Christ enveloppé d’un vêtement ocre sombre a les cheveux vermillon<c type="kp">_</c>– Cette toile n’étant pas destinée à être comprise je la garde pour longtemps<c type="kp">_</c>– Ci inclus ce dessin qui vous donnera vaguement l’idée de celà<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Nous sommes<c type="kk">/</c> de Haan et moi<c type="kk">/</c> installés pour le <hi rend="italics">travail et le calme</hi><c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">J’ai trouvé sur le bord de la mer une <hi rend="italics">grande maison</hi><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> qui est louée seulement 2 mois pour les bains de mer – à raison de celà je l’ai eue pour très bon marché l’hiver.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Le haut est une immense terrasse<c type="kk">/</c> 15 mètres sur 12 et 5 mètres de haut – vitrée sur 2 côtés<c type="kp">_</c>– D’un côté nous plongeons 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>sur un immense horizon de mer. Les orages sont magnifiques et nous les peignons directement de l’atelier, en pleine <hi rend="italics">sensation</hi> du terrible des vagues frappant des rochers noirs<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">De l’autre côté des sables rouges, des champs et quelques fermes entourées de leurs arbres. Des modèles tous les jours de femmes<c type="kk">/</c> hommes venant garder des vaches, ou ramasser le goëmon à la mer<c type="kp">_</c>– On les fait poser comme on veut pour un franc<c type="kp">_</c>– Vous voyez qu’il y a tout ce qu’il faut pour travailler<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">À côté de nous nous avons une petite auberge où nous mangeons très bien<c type="kk">/</c> pas cher<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Voilà pour le côté matériel<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">de Haam<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> s’est mis tout à fait au travail dans notre sens et marche très-bien sans perdre sa personalité et je vous promets que maintenant il comprend mieux Rembrandt qu’autrefois, ainsi que les maîtres hollandais<c type="kp">_</c>– Il y a chez les maîtres anciens une relation intellectuelle qui les relie tous entre eux et en <hi rend="italics">faisant comme eux</hi> on arrive à faire autre chose<c type="kp">_</c>– Voilà un paradoxe (mais je me comprends)<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Depuis 2 mois j’ai travaillé à une grande sculpture (de bois peint) et j’ose croire que c’est jusqu’ici ce que j’ai fait de mieux en tant que puissance et harmonie – mais le côté littéraire de celà est insensé pour beaucoup<c type="kp">_</c>– Un monstre qui me ressemble prend la main d’une femme nue – voilà le sujet principal. Dans les intervalles des figures (plus petites). Le haut une ville<c type="kk">/</c> une Babylonne quelconque, le bas la campagne avec quelques fleurs imaginées (une vieille désolée) et un renard, l’animal fatidique de la perversité chez les Indiens<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Il est difficile de vous donner la sensation de celà avec un dessin, il faut voir la couleur du bois se mariant avec le fond peint vert, ocre jaune, et fleurs jaunes<c type="kk">/</c> des cheveux or, quelques figures 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>verdâtres<c type="kp">_</c>– Car malgré l’inscription les personnes ont l’air triste<c type="kk">/</c> en contradiction avec le titre. Sur ce bois ciré il y a des reflets que donne la lumière sur les parties bosses qui donne de la richesse<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Je vais l’envoyer à Paris dans quelques jours. Peut être celà plaira plus que ma peinture.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">de Haann<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> vous dit bien des choses.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Cordialement à vous</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">P. Gauguin</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">P.S. Je sais que vous fatiguez quand vous ecrivez<c type="kk">/</c> aussi je ne demande pas de lettre (malgré tout le plaisir que j’ai à vous lire)<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Le service militaire de Bernard a été remis à un an (pour santé)<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/> 
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">au Pouldu près Quimper (Finistère)<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Vincent</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I received your letter the other day<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and I’m pleased to see that you’re recovered (if it’s not forever) at least for a long time: a time during which you’re going to be able to work. No, I wasn’t able to see your latest canvases, having been in Brittany for a long time,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>, the Dutchman who is with me, received a letter from a friend telling him that your new canvases were really something very artistic and more imaginative than the others.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I’m pleased that you remember our conversations about drawing, and De Haan, who has listened to me on that score, has made real progress here in this regard. I have little news to give you about our friends, as I myself am a little isolated from everything – <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1148">Laval</rs> is in Paris – <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> in St-Briac.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> His <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_15">father</rs> has totally forbidden him to be in Pont-Aven <hi rend="italics">with me</hi>. You will doubtless remember the bourgeois letter from the angry fellow.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> writes to me sometimes; he has greatly changed for the better, and as an artist he continues to do curious and beautiful things. It isn’t the same for me. I have an unfortunate nature which is thirsty for new things, and I can’t stop myself carrying out new researches. This year I’ve done work completely different from last year, preparatory work for a thing that I <hi rend="italics">glimpse</hi> as important. At your place in Arles I did a painting a little in that direction – The grape harvests (a painting you did the drawing of). A woman seated, vines in a red triangle.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_981">Degas</rs> doesn’t understand, that man. In this order of abstract ideas I am led to seek synthetic form and colour.
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">As little craft as possible, and here and there secondary motifs, very lightly executed, to allow the impression of a figure all its power and not to fall into trifles, childishness. In front of me I have several etchings, reproductions of paintings etc. by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, and I find a lot of these things in there. In the one you have (the detailed angel’s head and the rest unfinished).<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> In the Tobias, if, however, it is a Tobias, the lion is imposing, powerful, the landscape too, and the whole foreground area unfinished, the fellow too.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> It seemed to me that it was a <hi rend="italics">standpoint,</hi> and I researched the reason why. And there’s no reason why, because I’m not a master, I shouldn’t enter into the order of ideas of a master like that one (with different applications). All this (my dear Vincent) leads to me being shouted at in Paris (and I feel that they’re wrong).<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> This year I’ve made incredible efforts in work and reflection, and still it’s as if I’ve rested. At home I have a thing I haven’t sent and which would suit you, I think.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">It’s Christ in the Garden of Olives – blue-green sky, dusk, trees all bent into a purple mass, ground violet and Christ wrapped in a dark ochre garment has vermilion hair. As this canvas isn’t destined to be understood I’m keeping it for a long time. Included is this drawing, which will give you a vague idea of it.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">We, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and I, have settled ourselves in for <hi rend="italics">work and calm</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Beside the sea I’ve found a <hi rend="italics">large house</hi><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> which is rented out for only 2 months for sea bathing – because of that I got it very cheaply for the winter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">The upper part is an immense terrace, 15 metres by 12 and 5 metres high – glazed on 2 sides. On one side we plunge 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> over an immense sea horizon. The storms are magnificent, and we paint them directly from the studio, right in the midst of the <hi rend="italics">sensation</hi> of the terribleness of the waves striking black rocks.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">On the other side, red sands, fields, and a few farms surrounded by their trees. Models every day of women, men coming to herd the cows, or gather the seaweed from the sea. You can pose them as you wish for a franc. You can see that there’s everything one needs here to work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Beside us we have a little inn where we eat very well, not expensively.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> That deals with the material side.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> has completely set himself to work in our direction, and is getting along very well without losing his personality, and I promise you that now he understands <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> better than before, as well as the Dutch masters. With the old masters there’s an intellectual bond that links them all together, and by <hi rend="italics">doing as they do</hi> one succeeds in doing something else. There’s a paradox (but I understand myself).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">For 2 months I’ve been working on a large sculpture (of painted wood), and I dare believe that it’s the best thing I’ve done up to now as regards power and harmony – but the literary side of it is insane to many. A monster who looks like me is taking the hand of a naked woman – that’s the main subject. Figures (smaller) in the gaps. The top part a town, some sort of Babylon, the bottom the countryside with a few imagined flowers (an old and desolate woman) and a fox, the fateful animal of perversity for the Indians.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">It’s difficult to give you the feel of it with a drawing, you have to see the colour of the wood marrying with the background painted green, yellow ochre, and yellow flowers, golden hair, a few 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/> greenish figures. For despite the inscription the people look sad, in contradiction to the title. On this waxed wood there are reflections where the light hits the parts in relief, imparting richness.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">I’m going to send it to Paris in a few days. Perhaps it will please people more than my painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> sends you his kind regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Yours cordially,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">P. Gauguin</rs></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">P.S. I know that you become tired when you write, so I don’t ask you for a letter (despite all the pleasure I have in reading you).</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s military service has been put back a year (for health).<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">At Le Pouldu near Quimper (Finistère).</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo sent Vincent this letter from Gauguin, together with a letter of his own, dated 16 November (<ref target="let819.xml">letter 819</ref>), so the present letter must have been written several days earlier. It is not likely that Theo left Gauguin’s letter lying around for a long time. Gauguin says in the present letter that he is going to send Theo <hi rend="italics">Be in love</hi>; on 16 November Theo had meanwhile received the sculpture (<ref target="let819.xml">see letter 819</ref>). It is impossible to give a precise dating on the basis of this information; we have therefore dated the letter to between about Sunday, 10 and Wednesday, 13 November 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was enclosed with <ref target="let819.xml">letter 819</ref> to Theo.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Second consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let805.xml">(805)</ref> </p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This letter from Van Gogh to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is not known. It was enclosed with <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let810.xml">letter 810</ref> to Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had been in Brittany since the end of May 1889. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-16">See letter 774, n. 16.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This friend of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>, who had seen Vincent’s second consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy at Theo’s. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let807.xml">See letter 807</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Apparently <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> did not know that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> had returned to Paris. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let807.xml#n-9">See letter 807, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For this letter from Bernard’s <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_15">father</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let737.xml#n-4">see letter 737, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2242">Human miseries</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let717.xml#n-2">see letter 717, n. 2.</ref> A drawing by Van Gogh after this painting is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For this etching after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_374">Angel Raphael</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let781.xml#n-4">see letter 781, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>,<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Saint Jerome reading in an Italian landscape</hi> (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet; B104). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1597">Ill. 1597</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Here <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is referring to, among other things, Theo’s reaction to his paintings. On this subject, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let813.xml#n-11">see letter 813, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>The sketch is after <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> Christ in the Garden of Olives</hi>, 1889 (W326) (West Palm Beach, Norton Gallery and School of Fine Art). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_101">Ill. 101</rs>. Gauguin wrote about it to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>: ‘I’m keeping this canvas, pointless to show it to Van Gogh [i.e. Theo]; it would be understood even less than the rest. I’ve sent the drawing of it in a letter to Vincent, who had written me an equally sad letter.’ (Je garde cette toile inutile de la montrer à Van Gogh; elle serait encore moins compris que le reste. J’en ai envoyé le dessin dans une lettre à Vincent, qui m’avait écrit une lettre aussi triste.) See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gauguin lettres </hi>1946, p. 178.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> rented this house from Mr Mauduit, the owner of a stationer’s shop in Quimperlé. It looked out over the beach of Les Grands Sables. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1983, p. 283.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>This was Marie Henry’s inn at Le Pouldu. See also <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let828.xml#n-2">letter 828, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Haan’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Be in love, you will be happy</hi>, 1889 (Boston, Museum of Fine Arts). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_112">Ill. 112</rs>. Gauguin included a sketch of it in his letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Haan’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>With regard to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s military service, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let575.xml#n-8">see letter 575, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    