<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 16 November 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let819"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b747 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>819</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T20</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>821</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-16">Saturday, 16 November 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0747 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0747 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001011_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0747 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001012_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001012_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0747 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001012_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001012_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Paris le 16 Nov: 1889</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je t’envois sous ce pli une lettre que Gauguin m’a envoyé pour toi.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Le bois dont il te parle est également arrivé içi.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Quel excellent <hi rend="italics">ouvrier</hi> il est<c type="kk">/</c> ceci est travaillé avec un soin qui doit lui avoir demandé énormément de travail. Surtout la figure de femme est très belle, en bois ciré, tandis que les figures environnantes sont en bois rude &amp; 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>coloriées. C’est évidemment bizarre &amp; n’exprime pas une idée bien nette mais c’est beau comme un travail japonais, où également il est difficile<c type="kk">/</c> au moins pour un européen<c type="kk">/</c> de saisir la signification, mais où il faut admirer les combinaisons de lignes &amp; les beaux morceaux. L’ensemble est d’un ton tres sonore. Je voudrais bien que tu pouvais le voir. Tu l’aimerais certainement. J’ai été cette semaine chez Bernard qui m’a montré ce qu’il a fait dans le dernier temps<c type="kp">_</c> Je trouve qu’il a fait beaucoup de progrès. Son dessin est moins déterminé mais n’existe pas moins. Il y a plus de souplesse dans sa touche. Chez lui 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>il y a une influence plus directe des primitifs<c type="kk">/</c> ainsi il a fait une figure agenouillé entouré d’anges. Le terrain est à grands carraux et les figures sont posées comme sur un échiquier mais il y a une figure d’ange qui a vraiment de la noblesse.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Lui aussi a fait un Christ au jardin des oliviers. Un Christ violet à cheveux rouges avec un ange jaune.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> C’est bien difficile à comprendre et la recherche du style donne souvent quelque chose de ridicule à ses figures mais il en sortira peut être quelque chose de bien. Quand on voit beaucoup de tableaux, tellement que l’on voudrait quelquefois ne pas en voir pour quelque temps, ce qui satisfait alors le plus c’est les choses saines, vraies, sans-préoccupations d’école ou d’idées abstraites. Tu me 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>diras peut être que toute oeuvre d’art doit être le résultat de quantité de combinaisons compliquées, c’est juste, mais chez le peintre aussi il doit y arriver des moments qu’il est tellement inspiré par son motif ou son sujet qu’il le rend tel qu’on pourrait le saisir, ou au moins le sentir comme une chose devant lequel on se trouve. Je sens cela devant plusieurs de tes toiles. Il y en a un chez Tangui en ce moment à l’étalage<c type="kk">/</c> une vue sur la campagne au printemps avec des peupliers gris traversant la toile de façon qu’on ne voit ni le bas de l’arbre ni le sommet<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Je l’aime énormément. C’est vraiment nature cela. Ce matin il y avait une lettre pour toi venant des XX à Bruxelles<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai mis ton adresse dessus.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Un mot de Maus que je reçois en même 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>temps me dit qu’ils seront heureux si tu exposes, tableaux &amp; dessins. Lui quand il est venu aimait beaucoup les pommiers en fleurs,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> mais van Rijsselberghe saisit mieux ce que tu cherches dans les choses plus récentes.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Le portrait de Roulin,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> les tournesols<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> etc. Il faut que tu me dises un peu ce que tu penses de l’exposition &amp; ce que tu veux y envoyer. Je crois qu’il y à 5 à 7 mètres de cimèse.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> Cette année ils ont invité Puvis de Chavanne, Bartholomé<c type="kk">/</c> Cézanne, Dubois Pillet, Forain<c type="kk">/</c> Signac<c type="kk">/</c> L<c type="kp">_</c> Pissarro, Hayet, Renoir<c type="kk">/</c> Sisley &amp; de Lautrec &amp; toi.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Si mauvais qu’était l’exposition des Indépendants, Les Iris<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> ont été vu par beaucoup de personnes qui m’en parlent. Si on pouvait avoir à Paris une exposition régulière des 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>artistes peu connus par le public cela serait une bonne chose, mais il faudrait presque que cela fût une exposition permanente. Les locaux sont si chers içi<c type="kk">/</c> cela sera toujours un inconvenient.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Pissarro m’a écrit, que sa femme &amp; lui ont déjà regardé un peu dans le pays d’après une pension pour toi, mais il dit qu’il croit que tu seras mieux chez ce D<hi rend="super">r</hi> à Auvers; il dit devoir le voir sous peu.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Je suis content que tu te sens mieux portant; plus que tu aies de forces phisiques mieux cela vaut. Ecris moi une fois comment sont tes vêtements<c type="kk">/</c> est ce que tu n’as pas besoin de quelque chose de chaud? Jo se porte heureusement bien &amp; te dit bien bonjour, il commence déjà à faire hiver içi. Est ce que le mistral souffle à S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy comme à Arles?</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Bonne poignée de mains &amp;</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">tout à toi</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Paris, 16 Nov. 1889</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I enclose a letter which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> sent me for you.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> The wood he speaks of has also arrived here.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> What an excellent <hi rend="italics">workman</hi> he is, this is worked with a care that must have demanded an enormous amount of work from him. Above all the woman’s figure is very beautiful, in waxed wood, while the surrounding figures are in rough wood and coloured. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> It’s obviously bizarre and doesn’t express a very clear idea, but it’s beautiful like a piece of Japanese work, the significance of which is also hard to grasp, at least for a European, but in which one must admire the combinations of lines and the beautiful pieces. The whole has a very sonorous tone. I’d very much like you to be able to see it. You would certainly like it. I’ve been to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s this week, and he showed me what he has done lately. I think he’s made a lot of progress. His drawing is less determined, but it’s there all the same. There’s more flexibility in his touch. With him 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> there’s a more direct influence from the primitives, thus he has done a kneeling figure surrounded by angels. The ground is in large squares, and the figures are posed as if on a chessboard, but there’s one angel figure which really has nobility.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> He’s also done a Christ in the Garden of Olives. A red-headed, violet Christ with a yellow angel.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> It’s very difficult to understand, and the search for style often lends something ridiculous to his figures, but perhaps something good will come of it. When one sees a lot of paintings, so many that sometimes one would like not to see any for a while, what then satisfies one the most are the healthy, real things, without preoccupations about schools or abstract ideas. You’ll 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> perhaps tell me that any work of art must be the result of a quantity of complicated combinations, that’s right, but with the painter also there must be moments when he’s so inspired by his motif or his subject that he renders it as one might grasp it, or at least feel it like a thing one finds oneself in front of. I feel that in front of several of your canvases. There’s one at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s at the moment, in the shop window, a view over the countryside in springtime with grey poplars crossing the canvas in such a way that you can’t see either the bottom or the top of the tree.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> I like it enormously. That truly is nature. This morning there was a letter for you from Les Vingt in Brussels, I put your address on it.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> A line from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Maus</rs> that I received at the same 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> time tells me that they’d be happy if you would exhibit, paintings and drawings. When he came, he very much liked the apple trees in blossom,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1313">Van Rijsselberghe</rs> grasps better what you’re seeking in the more recent things.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> The portrait of Roulin,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> The sunflowers<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> etc. You must tell me what you think of the exhibition and what you want to send there. I believe there’s 5 to 7 metres of wall space. This year they’ve invited <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_470">Bartholomé</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_932">Cézanne</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_994">Dubois-Pillet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1028">Forain</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1267">L. Pissarro</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1074">Hayet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1293">Renoir</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Sisley</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">De Lautrec</rs> and you.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> However bad the Independents’ exhibition was, The Irises<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> were seen by a lot of people who talk to me about them. If we could have a regular exhibition in Paris of 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> artists little known by the public, that would be a good thing, but it would have to be almost a permanent exhibition. The premises are so expensive here, that will always be a drawback.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> wrote to me that his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_181">wife</rs> and he have already had a little look round the country for a place for you to lodge, but he says that he thinks you’ll be better off with this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr</rs> at Auvers; he says he’s to see him shortly.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> I’m pleased that you feel better; the more physical strength you have, the better. Write to me sometime about how your clothes are, don’t you need something warm? Fortunately <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> is well and sends her warm regards. Winter’s already starting here. Does the mistral blow in St-Rémy as it does in Arles?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Good handshake and</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Paris le 16 Nov: 1889’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <ref target="let817.xml">Letter 817</ref> from Gauguin was enclosed.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent considers settling in Auvers and putting himself in the care of Dr Gachet <ref target="let808.xml">(808)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The enclosed letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml">letter 817</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_112">Be in love, you will be happy</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml#n-13">see letter 817, n. 13.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Emile Bernard</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The annunciation</hi>, 1889 (private collection). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2309">Ill. 2309</rs>. See Luthi 1982, pp. 36-37, cat. no. 216; exhib. cat. Mannheim 1990, pp. 209-213, cat. no. 62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Emile Bernard, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Christ in the Garden of Olives</hi>, 1889 (present whereabouts unknown). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2">Ill. 2</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard in blossom with a view of Arles </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2781">F 516 / JH 1685</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let818.xml">letter 818</ref> from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Octave Maus</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Theo had written in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let792.xml">letter 792</ref> that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Maus</rs> had come to see Vincent’s paintings. Theo must be referring to the orchard paintings from the spring of 1888, because those from 1889 had not yet arrived in Paris when Maus visited.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Theo had written in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let813.xml">letter 813</ref> that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1313">Theo van Rijsselberghe</rs> had seen Vincent’s canvases at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Joseph Roulin </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2777">F 436 / JH 1675</rs>). <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let774.xml#n-3">See letter 774, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Theo must be referring to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>), which Vincent thought suitable to be exhibited (see, for example, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let741.xml">letter 741</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘cimaise’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For the artists invited to participate, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let792.xml#n-8">see letter 792, n. 8.</ref> In the end, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Pierre Puvis de Chavannes</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_470">Albert Bartholomé</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1028">Louis Forain</rs> did not exhibit any work.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irises </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2787">F 608 / JH 1691</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>On 14 November 1889, Theo thanked <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> and his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_181">wife</rs> for their efforts: ‘Thank you for being so willing to take the trouble to see if there isn’t a boarding-house to be found where my brother would be comfortable, and Mrs Pissarro is most kind to take an interest in it too. It seems to me that if he could stay at Auvers, near this doctor of whom you’ve spoken, that would be excellent’. (Je vous remercie de ce que vous voulez bien vous donner la peine de voir s’il n’y a pas une pension à trouver où mon frère serait bien et madame Pissarro est bien aimable de s’en occuper aussi. Il me semble que s’il pouvait rester à Auvers, près de ce médecin dont vous m’avez parlé, cela serait excellent). Pissarro must have been reluctant to confront his children with the unstable Van Gogh. See Jampoller 1986, p. 57 and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Correspondance Pissarro</hi> 1980-1991, vol. 2, p. 299 (n. 2).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    