<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Tuesday, 19 November 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let820"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b662 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>820</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>614</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>822</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-19">on or about Tuesday, 19 November 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0662" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0662" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000905_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci de ta lettre<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> et suis bien aise que tu écris que Jo continue à aller bien<c type="kp">_</c>– C’est maintenant là le grand événement<c type="kk">/</c> je pense bien souvent à vous autres. Pour toi<c type="kk">/</c> lorsque tu écris voir tant de tableaux que tu désirerais pour un temps ne pas en voir<c type="kk">/</c> cela prouve bien que tu as des tracas d’affaires de trop<c type="kp">_</c>– Et puis – oui il y a dans l’existence autre chôse que les tableaux et ce reste on le néglige et la nature parait alors se venger et le sort s’acharne d’ailleurs à nous contrarier. Je crois qu’il faut dans ces circonstances tenir aux tableaux autant que le devoir l’exige mais pas davantage. Pour les Vingtistes voici ce que j’aimerais à exposer:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">1 &amp; 2   les deux pendants de tournesols<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">   3       le lierre en hauteur<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">   4       Verger en fleur (celui que Tanguy expose dans </p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">            ce moment<c type="kk">/</c> avec des peupliers traversant la toile)<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">   5       La vigne rouge<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">   6       Champ de blé<c type="kk">/</c> soleil levant<c type="kk">/</c> auquel je </p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">            travaille dans ce moment.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Gauguin m’a écrit une très bonne lettre et parle avec animation de de Haan et de leur vie rude au bord de la mer<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Bernard aussi m’a écrit<c type="kk">/</c> se plaignant d’un tas de chôses tout en se résignant en bon garçon qu’il est mais pas heureux du tout; avec tout son talent<c type="kk">/</c> tout son travail<c type="kk">/</c> toute sa sobriété<c type="kk">/</c> il parait que la maison est souvent un enfer pour lui<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">La lettre d’Isaacson me fait bien du plaisir<c type="kk">/</c> ci-inclus ma réponse que tu liras – les idées commencent à s’enchainer avec un peu plus de calme mais comme tu l’y verras je ne sais s’il faut continuer à peindre ou laisser là la peinture<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Si je continue certes je suis d’accord avec toi que peutêtre il vaut mieux attaquer les chôses avec simplicité que de chercher les abstractions<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Et je ne suis pas admirateur du Christ au jardin des oliviers de Gauguin par exemple dont il m’envoie croquis<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Puis celui de Bernard<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> il m’en promet une photographie<c type="kk">/</c> je ne sais mais je crains que ses compositions bibliques me feront désirer autre chôse. Ces jours ci j’ai vu les femmes cueillir et ramasser les olives<c type="kk">/</c> pas moyen pour moi d’avoir modèle<c type="kk">/</c> je n’en ai rien fait<c type="kp">_</c> Cependant faudrait pas dans ce moment me demander de trouver bien la composition de l’ami G. – puis l’ami Bernard n’a probablement jamais vu un olivier<c type="kp">_</c>– Or il évite donc de se faire la moindre idee du possible et de la realité des chôses et ce n’est pas là le moyen de synthetiser<c type="kp">_</c>– Non de leurs interprétations bibliques jamais je ne m’en suis mêlé<c type="kp">_</c>– J’ai dit que Rembrandt<c type="kk">/</c> que Delacroix avaient fait cela admirablement<c type="kk">/</c> que j’aimais cela même mieux que les primitifs<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> mais puis halte-là<c type="kp">_</c>– Je ne veux pas recommencer sur ce chapitre<c type="kp">_</c>– Si je reste ici je ne chercherais pas à peindre un Christ au jardin des oliviers mais enfin le grapillage des olives tel que l’on le voit encore et alors quand meme<c type="kk">/</c> donnant la proportion juste de la figure humaine là-dedans<c type="kk">/</c> ça y ferait peutêtre songer. Avant d’en avoir fait des études plus serieuses que jusqu’à présent je n’ai pas le droit de m’en mêler<c type="kp">_</c> Et puis les préraphaelites<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> ont été fort loin dans cet ordre d’idées là<c type="kp">_</c> Lorsque Millais a peint son Light of the world c’était autrement sérieux.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Vraiment il n’y a pas de comparaison. Sans compter Holman Hunt et autres<c type="kk">/</c> Pinwell et Rossetti.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Et puis ici il y a Puvis de Chavannes.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">A present je te dirai que j’ai été à Arles et que j’ai vu M. Salles qui m’a remis le reste de l’argent que tu lui avais envoyé et le reste de ce que je lui avais remis<c type="kk">/</c> soit 72 francs<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Cependant il ne reste en caisse à M. Peyron qu’une vingtaine de francs actuellement puisque je me suis là-bas approvisionné de couleurs et que j’ai payé la chambre où sont les meubles &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Suis resté 2 jours là-bas<c type="kk">/</c> ne sachant pas encore que faire dans la suite<c type="kk">/</c> il est bon de s’y montrer de temps en temps pour que la meme histoire ne se renouvelle pas avec les gens.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> à présent personne là-bas ne m’en veut à ce que je m’aperçoive<c type="kk">/</c> au contraire ils etaient très aimables et m’ont fait la fête même<c type="kp">_</c> Et si je restais dans le pays peu à peu j’aurais chance de m’y acclimater ce qui n’est guere commode pour les étrangers et aurait son interêt pour y peindre<c type="kp">_</c>– Mais nous verrons un peu d’abord si ce voyage provoquerait une autre crise<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> j’ose espérer presque que non<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Il fait froid souvent ici aussi<c type="kk">/</c> cependant on est par les montagnes un peu davantage abrité contre le mistral. Et entre temps je travaille toujours<c type="kp">_</c>– J’ai plusieurs chôses à t’envoyer avec la toile pour les Vingtistes – j’attends que celle là soit sèche<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Si j’avais su à temps qu’il y a eu des trains d’ici à Paris à 25 franc seulement je serais certes venu<c type="kp">_</c> C’est allant à Arles seulement que j’ai su cela et c’est pour les frais que je ne l’ai pas fait – à présent il me semblerait qu’au printemps il serait pourtant bon de venir en tous les cas pour revoir un peu les gens &amp; chôses du nord. Car c’est terriblement abrutissant cette vie d’ici et j’y perdrais à la longue mon énergie. Je n’avais guere osé esperer que je me porterais encore si bien qu’est le cas<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.19" n="19">Cependant tout dépend de ce que cela te convienne ou pas et je crois qu’il est sage de ne pas presser<c type="kp">_</c>– Peut-être en attendant un peu n’aurons nous même pas besoin du médecin à Auvers ni des Pissarro.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.20" n="20">Si la santé demeure stable<c type="kk">/</c> alors si tout en travaillant je me remets à chercher à vendre<c type="kk">/</c> à exposer<c type="kk">/</c> à faire des échanges<c type="kk">/</c> peutêtre y aura-t-il quelque progrès pour t’être moins à charge d’un côté et de l’autre pour retrouver un peu plus d’entrain<c type="kp">_</c> Car je ne te cache pas que le séjour ici est bien fatiguant par sa monotonie et parceque la société de tous ces malheureux qui ne font absolument rien<c type="kk">/</c> énerve.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.21" n="21">Mais que veux tu<c type="kk">/</c> il ne faut pas avoir des prétentions dans mon cas<c type="kk">/</c> j’en ai encore trop tel que c’est.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.22" n="22">Gauguin dit qu’ils ont des modèles facilement<c type="kp">_</c> C’est cela qui me manque le plus ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.23" n="23">Bernard me parle d’un échange<c type="kk">/</c> tu es bien libre de traiter cela avec lui s’il le désirerait et t’en parlerait<c type="kp">_</c> Je voudrais bien qu’en dehors du portrait de sa grand mère<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> tu eusses une bonne chôse de lui<c type="kp">_</c> Parait qu’il a envie de la berceuse<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.24" n="24">Je crois que les 6 tableaux pour les Vingtistes feront comme cela un ensemble<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> le champ de blé fera fort bien pendant au verger.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.25" n="25">J’ecris un mot à M. Maus pour lui donner titres ainsi que dans sa lettre il les reclame<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.26" n="26">à present bien le bonjour à Jo et bonne poignée de main<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.27" n="27">Tu liras la lettre à Isaacson<c type="kk">/</c> cela complète celle ci. à bientôt<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.28" n="28">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.29" n="29">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and am very glad that you write that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> is staying well. The great event is nearing now, I think of you both very often. For you, when you write about seeing so many paintings that you would wish not to see any for a while, this clearly proves that you’ve had too many business worries. And then – yes there’s something in life other than paintings, and this something else one neglects and nature seems to avenge itself then, and besides, fate is bent on thwarting us. I think that in these circumstances one must keep to the paintings as much as duty demands but no more. As for the Vingtistes, here’s what I’d like to exhibit:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">1 and 2 the two pendants of sunflowers<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">3  The ivy, upright<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">4  Orchard in blossom (the one Tanguy’s exhibiting at the moment, with poplars crossing the canvas)<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">5  The red vineyard<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">6  Wheatfield, rising sun, which I’m working on at the moment.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote me a very kind letter and speaks animatedly of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and of their rough-and-ready life at the seaside.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9"> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> also wrote to me, complaining about a heap of things while resigning himself like the good boy he is, but not happy at all; with all his talent, all his work, all his sobriety, it appears that home is often a hell for him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>’s letter gives me great pleasure, I enclose my reply which you will read – the ideas are beginning to link together a little more calmly, but as you’ll see from it I don’t know if I should continue to paint or leave painting alone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"> If I continue, certainly I’m in agreement with you that perhaps it’s better to attack things with simplicity than to seek abstractions. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12"> And I’m not an admirer of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s Christ in the Garden of Olives for example, a croquis of which he sent me.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Then as for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> he promises me a photograph of it, I don’t know, but I fear that his biblical compositions will make me wish for something else. Lately I’ve seen women picking and gathering olives, no way for me to get a model, so I didn’t do anything about it. However now isn’t the moment to ask me to approve of friend G’s composition – and friend Bernard has probably never seen an olive tree. Now he therefore avoids conceiving the least idea of the possible and of the reality of things, and that isn’t the way to synthesize. No, never have I got involved in their Biblical interpretations. I said that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Delacroix</rs> had done this admirably, that I liked that even better than the primitives,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> but then stop. I don’t want to begin on that chapter again. If I remain here I wouldn’t try to paint a Christ in the Garden of Olives, but in fact the olive picking as it’s still seen today, and then giving the correct proportions of the human figure in it, that would perhaps make people think of it all the same. Before I’ve done more serious studies than I have up to now I don’t have the right to get involved in this. And then the Pre-Raphaelites<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> went a long way in that category of ideas. When <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs> painted his Light of the World it was serious in another way.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Really, there’s no comparison. Not to mention <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1100">Holman Hunt</rs> and others, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1269">Pinwell</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1321">Rossetti</rs>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"> And then here there’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>.</p><pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14"> Now I’ll tell you that I’ve been to Arles and I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs>, who handed me the rest of the money you sent him and the rest of what I’d handed over to him, that is, 72 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> However, only around twenty francs remain in the cash-box with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> at the moment, since down there I stocked myself up with colours and paid for the room where the furniture &amp;c. is.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Stayed there for 2 days, not yet knowing what to do next, it’s good to show oneself there from time to time so that the same story doesn’t start again with the people.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> At present no one there is hostile to me as far as I can tell, on the contrary, they were very friendly, and even gave me a warm welcome. And if I stayed in the area, little by little I’d have a chance to acclimatize myself, which isn’t easy for strangers and would have its uses for painting there. But first we’ll see a little if this journey might provoke another crisis.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I almost dare hope not.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15"> It’s often cold here too, however we’re a little more sheltered from the mistral by the mountains. And between times I keep working. I have several things to send you with the canvas for the Vingtistes. I’m waiting for that one to be dry.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16"> If I’d known in time that there were trains from here to Paris at only 25 francs I would certainly have come. It’s only on going to Arles that I found this out, and it’s because of the expense that I haven’t done it – at the moment it would seem to me that in springtime it would however be good to come in any event to see the people and things of the north again. For this life here is terribly numbing, and in the long run I’d lose my energy. I had hardly dared hope that I would still be as well as is the case.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17"> However, everything depends on whether this suits you or not, and I think it’s wise not to rush things. Perhaps by waiting a little we won’t even have need of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">doctor</rs> at Auvers or the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268 bio.xml#_181">Pissarros</rs>. 
      <pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18"> If my health remains stable, then if while I’m working I again start to try to sell, exhibit, make exchanges, perhaps there’ll be some progress so as to be less of a burden to you on the one hand and to regain a little more zest on the other. For I don’t hide from you the fact that my stay here is very tiring on account of its monotony, and because the society of all these unfortunates, who do absolutely nothing, gets on one’s nerves.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19"> But what can one do, one can’t have pretensions in my case, I already have too many as it is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20"> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> says that they get models easily. That’s what I lack most here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.21" n="21"> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> speaks to me of an exchange, you’re quite free to deal with this with him if he wishes and speaks to you about it. I’d really like that, besides the portrait of his grandmother,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> you should have a good thing of his. It appears he fancies the Berceuse.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.22" n="22"> I think that the 6 paintings for the Vingtistes will make an ensemble like this,<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> the wheatfield will make a very good pendant to the orchard.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.23" n="23"> I’m dropping a line to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Mr Maus</rs> to give him titles, as he asks in his letter.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.24" n="24"> Now, warm regards to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, and good handshake.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.25" n="25"> You must read the letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>, it complements this one. More soon. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.26" n="26"> Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.27" n="27">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent responds to Theo’s letter of 16 November <ref target="let819.xml">(819)</ref>. Because the note to Maus – which he says he is going to write in this letter <ref target="#l-152">(l. 152)</ref> – is dated 20 November (<ref target="let821.xml">letter 821</ref>), we have dated the present letter to about Tuesday, 19 November 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh enclosed a letter for Isaäcson, which is no longer extant, as well as <ref target="let818.xml">letter 818</ref> from Maus, with a sketch on the back showing the hanging of his canvases.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent considers settling in Auvers and putting himself in the care of Dr Gachet <ref target="let808.xml">(808)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let819.xml">letter 819</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>). Van Gogh considered these two versions suitable to be exhibited; the two repetitions (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2772">F 455</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2771">F 458</rs>) were intended for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let741.xml">See letter 741</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Trees with ivy in the garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2789">F 609 / JH 1693</rs>). Theo had expressed his appreciation of this painting in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let813.xml">letter 813</ref>, and this must have influenced Vincent in his choice.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Orchard in blossom with a view of Arles</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2781">F 516 / JH 1685</rs>). Theo had written in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let819.xml">letter 819</ref> that the work was hanging in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s shop window and that he thought it splendid.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The red vineyard</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml">letter 817</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_101">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml#n-10">see letter 817, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let819.xml#n-4">see letter 819, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written this to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> in June 1888; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let632.xml">see letter 632</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let625.xml#n-10">see letter 625, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is mistaken: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1800">The Light of the World</rs></hi> is not by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1227">Millais</rs>, but by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1100">William Holman Hunt</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let108.xml#n-10">See letter 108, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Salles</rs> had written to Theo on 5 June 1889 that this amount was left after paying the hospital bill and the trip to Saint-Rémy (FR b1053).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s furniture from the Yellow House was in storage at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382">Ginoux</rs>’s Café de la Gare; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let760.xml#n-4">see letter 760, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            
      
<p>A reference to the petition to have Van Gogh placed under restraint, which had been signed by the residents of his neighbourhood in Arles in February 1889. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let750.xml#n-2">See letter 750, n. 2</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let750.xml#n-3">3</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s first attack in Saint-Rémy had occurred shortly after his visit to Arles (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let793.xml">see letter 793</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The canvas for Les Vingt which still had to dry was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>). The other works for the exhibition were already at Theo’s.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">portrait <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2212">Bernard’s grandmother</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let655.xml#n-3">see letter 655, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>Vincent had previously suggested to Theo that he give one of the Berceuse paintings to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>. The latter is in fact known to have had one in his possession: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>). It is not known whether he got it from Theo, possibly in exchange for work of his own, or only acquired it later. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let776.xml#n-4">See letter 776, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>Van Gogh sketched the way he wanted his paintings to be hung on the back of <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let818.xml">letter 818</ref>, which he enclosed in the present letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>This is <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let821.xml">letter 821</ref> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_505">Maus</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    