<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Sunday, 22 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let830"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b749 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>830</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T22</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>833</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-22">Sunday, 22 December 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0749 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0749 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001015_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0749 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-8">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0749 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-7">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001016_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Paris 22 Dec<c type="kp">_</c> 1889</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">J’ai bien reçu ton envoi du champ de blé<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> &amp; des deux chambres à coucher.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Surtout j’aime le dernier,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> qui comme couleur est comme un bouquet de fleurs. C’est d’une intensité de couleur bien grande. Le champ de blé a peut être plus de poesie; c’est comme un souvenir de quelque chose qu’on a vu. Tangui le monte en ce moment &amp; le 3 Janvier tout part pour Bruxelles. Maintenant j’ai quelque chose 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>qui m’a fait bien plaisir. J’ai eu à la maison la visite de <hi rend="italics">M</hi><hi rend="super"><hi rend="italics">r </hi></hi><hi rend="italics">Lauzet</hi><c type="kk">/</c> le lithographe de Monticelli.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Il venait pour voir les nôtres<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> et les trouve très beaux. Pour les fleurs,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> il ne croit pas pouvoir le rendre car les planches sont monochromes et il ne croit pas pouvoir rendre la sensation de ce tableau dans une couleur. Il commence par l’Italienne<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Mais ce qui lui plaisait surtout c’était tes toiles &amp; tes dessins, oh mais, il les comprend. Il en avait vu depuis longtemps chez Tangui et il était vraiment content de voir tout ce que j’avais ici, en parcourant les dessins il y avait une ramasseuse de pommes<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> qui lui plaisait &amp; je lui en ai fait cadeau car je crois que tu aurais fait de même. Il 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>est revenu le lendemain au magasin pour me demander s’il n’y aurait pas moyen d’avoir un autre dessin que tu as fait tout au commencement quand tu étais à S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy<c type="kp">_</c> À gauche un petit bosquet d’arbres sombres contre un ciel avec un croissant de lune<c type="kk">/</c> à droite une barrière.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Il me disait que ce dessin ne lui sortait pas de la tête<c type="kk">/</c> qu’il était plus beaux que les dessins de V. Hugo qu’il aime beaucoup etc. Je lui ai proposé de l’échanger contre un ex<c type="kp">_</c> de son album de Monticelli, ce qu’il a accepté toute suite.<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> L’album est encore loin d’être prêt mais il le terminera<c type="kk">/</c> Cottier &amp; Reid ont souscrit à plusieurs exemplaires de sorte qu’il est couvert pour les frais d’impression. Il y a 16 lit<c type="kp">_</c> de prêt sur 25 qu’il veut faire<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Ce que je trouve de mieux réussi c’est la tete d’enfant que nous avons vu dans le temps chez la Roquette.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> L’artiste me semble bien sympathique. Il est du midi &amp; a quelque chose d’Espagnol<c type="kk">/</c> visage pâle &amp; barbe noire, mais en même temps quelque chose de doux comme un poete anglais. C’est bien dommage qu’il n’ait pas fait des planches à plusieurs couleurs car on ne se rend pas compte de la force de la couleur que Monticelli était un des premiers à employer en se servant d’une opposition pour obtenir de la puissance tout en restant harmonieux. Les planches que j’ai vues ressemblent à des eaux fortes sur pierre comme faisait Marvy<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Tu dis que tu penses quelquefois que tu aurais mieux fait en restant marchand, mais ne le dis pas. Voilà Gauguin par exemple<c type="kk">/</c> j’aime bien son talent &amp; je sais<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> bien ce qu’il veut, mais je ne suis pas fichu de lui vendre quoi que 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>ce soit &amp; cependant j’ai des choses de toutes sortes de lui<c type="kp">_</c> Le public est le plus rebel au choses qui ne sont pas faites dans un ordre parfait<c type="kp">_</c> Et il est évident que Goguin qui est moitié Inca moitié Européen<c type="kk">/</c> superstitieux comme les premiers &amp; avancé d’idées comme certains de ces derniers<c type="kk">/</c> ne peut pas travailler tous les jours de même<c type="kp">_</c> Il est bien malheureux qu’on ne peut pas lui trouver quelque chose avec quoi il puisse vivre. Ces derniers tableaux sont moins vendables que ceux de l’année dernière.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> Il m’a écrit la semaine dernière qu’un de ses enfants est tombé d’une fenêtre &amp; a été relevé presque mort<c type="kp">_</c> On espère cependant le sauver.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Il ferait tout pour obtenir un peu d’argent mais je ne peux pas lui en procurer.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Pissarro aussi est aux abois. Il travaille comme un nègre. Il a fait pour Jo un bien joli eventail. Des bonnes femmes qui causent dans les champs avec dans le fond un arc en ciel,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> il n’a jusqu’à présent pas vu ce M<hi rend="super">r</hi> d’Auvers,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> au moins il n’écrit rien à ce sujet, ce qu’il y aura de mieux sera que tu viennes chez nous au printemps &amp; que tu ailles toi-même voir si à la campagne tu puisses trouver une pension qui te convient. Nous devons toujours être content que depuis l’année dernière à cette époque tu ailles beaucoup mieux. Je craignais alors que tu ne guérirait pas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Nous attendons Wil pour le 2 Janv.<c type="kk">/</c> elle restera un mois chez nous. Je suis de ton avis que je serais ravi si elle trouvait à se marier &amp; celui qui l’aurait trouverait en elle une charmante femme.</p>
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Cor écrit assez souvent du Transvaal<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> La vie là-bas ne doit pas être bien amusant. Des plantes ou des fleurs il n’y en a pas. S’il n’y fait pas une chaleur torride il y pleut de façon que tout est blanc.<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> Les jours se ressemblent absolument, pourquoi il dit qu’il déteste les Dimanches &amp; les autres heurres de repos. Tu sais que Isaacson devait y aller aussi mais comme ses amis à Amsterdam sont très bons pour lui &amp; je pense que tant qu’ils le soutiendront il y restera &amp; saura s’occuper là-bas<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> Le Transvaal n’est pas recommandable à ce que l’on en entend.– Il fait içi un temps abominable<c type="kk">/</c> froid &amp; gris; presque tout le monde est malade. Comment vas tu? est-ce que 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/>là-bas il fait aussi froid qu’à Arles? Je suis curieux de voir tes oliviers.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> Cela peut être beau. Les tournesols<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> étaient en montre chez Tangui cette semaine &amp; faisaient très bien. Tes tableaux égaient le magasin de Tangui et le père Tangui les aime beaucoup, mais il ne vend pas plus autre chose que les tiens. J’aime beaucoup les deux dessins que tu as envoyés.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Veux-tu que j’en envoie quelques uns à Bruxelles? Réponds moi de suite à ce sujet car il n’y aura pas de temps à perdre pour l’encadrement. Jo te dit bien des choses, elle va relativement très bien.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> J’espère que tu feras le portrait du petit ce printemps. Je te serre bien la main et j’espère que tu aura une bonne fin d’année<c type="kp">_</c> </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">à toi</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Je reçois ta carte postale, les tableaux seront prêts à temps.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Paris 22 Dec. 1889</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I’ve safely received your consignment of the Wheatfield<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and the two Bedrooms.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Above all I like the last one,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> which in terms of colour is like a bouquet of flowers. It has a very great intensity of colour. The Wheatfield perhaps has more poetry; it’s like a memory of something one has seen. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> is mounting it at the moment, and on 3 January everything is leaving for Brussels. Now I have something 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> that gave me great pleasure. I was visited at home by <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Mr Lauzet</rs></hi>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s lithographer.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> He came to see ours,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and considers them very fine. As regards the flowers,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> he doesn’t think he can render them, as the prints are monochrome and he doesn’t think he can render the feeling of this painting in one colour. He’s starting with the Italian woman.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> But what pleased him above all was your canvases and your drawings, oh but he understands them. He’s been seeing them for a long time at Tanguy’s, and he was really pleased to see all that I had here, while going through the drawings there was a woman picking up apples<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> that he liked, and I made him a present of it, for I think you’d have done the same. He 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> came back to the shop the next day to ask me if there wouldn’t be some way of having another drawing you did right at the beginning when you were at St-Rémy. On the left a little thicket of dark trees against a sky with a crescent moon, on the right a gate.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> He told me that he couldn’t get this drawing out of his mind, that it was finer than the drawings of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">V. Hugo</rs>, which he likes a great deal etc. I suggested that he exchange it for a copy of his Monticelli album, which he accepted immediately. The album is still far from being ready but he will finish it, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_331">Cottier</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_623">Reid</rs> have put their names down for several copies so he’s covered for the printing costs. There are 16 lithographs ready out of 25 he wants to do. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">What I consider the most successful thing is the head of a child we saw once at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343 bio.xml#_344">La Roquette</rs>’s.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> The artist seems very sympathetic to me. He’s from the south and has something of the Spaniard about him, pale face and black beard, but at the same time something gentle like an English poet. It’s a great pity he hasn’t done any prints in several colours, for one doesn’t realize the strength of the colour that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> was one of the first to employ by using an opposition to obtain power while remaining harmonious. The prints that I’ve seen resemble etchings on stone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1198">Marvy</rs> did.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You say that you sometimes think that you would have done better by remaining a dealer, but don’t say that. Look at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> for example, I do like his talent and I’m well aware<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> of what he wants, but I haven’t managed to sell anything 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> whatsoever of his, and yet I have all kinds of things by him. The public is most rebellious towards things that aren’t done in perfect order. And it’s evident that Gauguin, who is half Inca, half European, superstitious like the former and advanced in ideas like certain of the latter, can’t work every day in the same way. It’s most unfortunate that we can’t find something he can live from. These latest paintings are less saleable than last year’s.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> He wrote to me last week that one of his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">children</rs> fell out of a window and was picked up almost dead. There is hope, though, of saving it.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> He’d do anything to obtain a little money, but I can’t procure any for him. 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs>, too, is at bay. He works like a negro. He made a very pretty fan for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>. Women chatting in the fields with a rainbow in the background,<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> up to now he hasn’t yet seen this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">gentleman</rs> from Auvers,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> at least he writes nothing about the subject, the best thing will be for you to come to us in the spring and go yourself to see if you can find lodgings that suit you in the country. We must in any case be pleased that you’re much better than you were this time last year. Then I feared that you might not recover.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">We’re expecting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> on 2 Jan., she’ll stay a month with us. I share your opinion that I’d be delighted if she could see her way to marrying, and the man who had her would find a charming wife in her. 
<pb f="2v" n="7" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-7" facs="#zone-pb-2v-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> writes quite often from the Transvaal.<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> Life down there can’t be much fun. There are no plants or flowers. If the heat isn’t torrid, it rains so much that everything is flooded. The days are all absolutely alike, which is why he says he detests Sundays and other time off. You know that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> was to go there too, but as his friends in Amsterdam are very kind to him, and I think that as long as they support him he’ll stay there and will be able to occupy himself over there.<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> The Transvaal isn’t to be recommended, from what one can gather. Here the weather is abominable, cold and grey; almost everybody is ill. How are you? Is it 
<pb f="2r" n="8" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-8" facs="#zone-pb-2r-8"/> as cold down there as in Arles? I’m curious to see your Olive trees.<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> They can be beautiful. The Sunflowers<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> were on show at Tanguy’s this week and made a very good effect. Your paintings cheer up <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs>’s shop, and <hi rend="italics">père</hi> Tanguy likes them a lot, but he sells as few by others as by you. I very much like the two drawings you sent.<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> Do you want me to send some to Brussels? Reply immediately on this subject, for there’s no time to lose for the framing. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> sends her warm regards, she’s very well, relatively speaking.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> I hope that you’ll do the little one’s portrait this spring. I shake your hand firmly, and hope that you’ll have a good end to the year.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Theo</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I received your postcard, the paintings will be ready in time.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Paris 22 Dec_ 1889’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Fifth consignment (paintings and drawings) from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let829.xml">(829)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent considers settling in Auvers and putting himself in the care of Dr Gachet <ref target="let808.xml">(808)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield at sunrise </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3007">F 484 / JH 1771</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In mentioning ‘the last one’, Theo is referring to the repetition of the bedroom: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The bedroom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3007">F 484 / JH 1771</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Lauzet</rs> was working on the edition of lithographs <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_517">Adolphe Monticelli</ref></hi>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let825.xml#n-7">see letter 825, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Vincent and Theo owned five works by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-5">see letter 578, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_306">Vase of flowers</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let578.xml#n-4">see letter 578, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Adolphe Monticelli</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Italian girl</hi>, c. 1879 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2302">Ill. 2302</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>There is no known drawing depicting a woman picking up apples. Theo is presumably referring to ‘ramasseuse de pommes de terre’, in which case this might refer to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Woman lifting potatoes</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_911">F 1272 / JH 910</rs>). However, the early provenance of this work is unknown.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>There is no known drawing that fits this description.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘tout de suite’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            
      
<p>Theo means <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Auguste Marie Lauzet</rs>’s lithograph <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Head of a child</hi>, no. 17 in the publication <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_517">Adolphe Monticelli</ref></hi>. The painting which served as the model for the print has not been traced; the caption says that at the time the print after it was made, the painting was in the possession of Mr Bagnard.<hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"> </hi><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2303">Ill. 2303</rs>.</p>

<p rend="indent"> ‘La Roquette’ refers to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_343">Evelina Delarebeyrette</rs> or her son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_344">Gabriel Delarebeyrette</rs>. The gallery they ran together sold many <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>s. For the nickname ‘La Roquette’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let600.xml#n-14">see letter 600, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Regarding <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1198">Marvy</rs>’s technique, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let825.xml#n-8">see letter 825, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>It is possible that Theo wrote ‘sens’ instead of ‘sais’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Theo had recently received two consignments of paintings from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> in Brittany; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let799.xml#n-10">see letter 799, n. 10</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let813.xml#n-11">letter 813, n. 11.</ref> Theo was less enthusiastic about these recent paintings than he had been about the paintings sent from Brittany the year before, several of which he had managed to sell. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let704.xml#n-1">See letter 704, n. 1</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let722.xml#n-1">letter 722, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>On about 16 December <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote to Theo about the accident that his eight-year-old son <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">Jean-René</rs> had had in Copenhagen: ‘One of my boys fell from the 3rd floor. He was picked up in a terrible state and at the moment he’s in the hospital, more or less out of danger.’ (Un de mes garçons est tombée du 3em étage. On l’a relevé en capilotade et il est à l’hôpital a peu près sauvé en ce moment.) See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1983, p. 177 (GAC 23).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Figures in a meadow</hi>, 1889 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_312">Ill. 312</rs>. The fan was a present from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs> to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>. See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Correspondance Pissarro</hi> 1980-1991, vol. 2, pp. 312-313 (letter 557) and Jampoller 1986, p. 52.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Paul Gachet</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>Only one letter from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> in South Africa has been preserved from this period (FR b838, 20 October 1889).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘inondé’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>’s plans to go to the Transvaal, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let811.xml#n-2">see letter 811, n. 2.</ref> It could not be ascertained which Amsterdam friends of Isaäcson Theo is referring to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>In <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let829.xml">letter 829</ref> Vincent had written that he had a ‘half-dozen’ studies of olive groves.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>). Van Gogh intended to submit these two canvases to the exhibition of Les Vingt (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let820.xml#n-2">see letter 820, n. 2</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            
      
<p>For these two drawings, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_909">F 1552 / JH 1863</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_910">F 1545 / JH 1851</rs>), <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let829.xml#n-9">see letter 829, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries</rs> wrote several days later to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs>: ‘Later Net [<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>] and Theo are coming to have lunch with us. Net seems in fine fettle and Theo has regained his strength’ (FR b1850, 25 December 1889).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>This postcard is not known. Vincent must have asked Theo how the framing of the paintings for Brussels was coming along.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    