<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Monday, 23 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let831"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b668 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>831</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>619</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>831</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-23">on or about Monday, 23 December 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0668" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0668" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000911_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste Moeder,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">Tegen het einde van het jaar kom ik U nog eens goeden dag zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>– U zult zeggen dat ik dat menig keer vergeten heb. t’Is een jaar geleden ik ziek werd en ’t is voor mij moeielijk me uit te drukken in hoever ik hersteld ben al dan niet. Dikwijls heb ik geducht zelfverwijt over dingen in ’t verleden als zijnde mijn ziekte me zoo tamelijk door mijn eigen schuld overkomen en in elk geval is ’t me twijfelachtig of ik op eeniger wijze fouten kan goedmaken<c type="kp">_</c> Maar redeneeren of denken hierover is soms zoo moeielijk en meer dan vroeger overweldigt mijn gevoel mij soms<c type="kp">_</c> En dan kan ik zoo aan U denken en aan het verleden<c type="kp">_</c> U en Pa zijn voor mij zoo mogelijk nog meer dan voor de anderen zoo veel<c type="kk">/</c> zoo heel veel geweest en ik blijk geen gelukkig karakter gehad te hebben. Ik ben dat te Parijs gaan inzien<c type="kk">/</c> hoeveel meer dan ik Theo zijn best heeft gedaan om Pa praktisch te helpen<c type="kk">/</c> zóó dat zijn eigen belangen er dikwijls bij inschoten<c type="kp">_</c> Daarom ben ik er nu tegen<c type="shy">-</c>woordig zoo dankbaar voor Theo eindelijk eene vrouw heeft gevonden en zijn kindje wacht. Enfin Theo had meer zelfverloochening dan ik en dat zit diep in zijn karakter<c type="kp">_</c> En toen Pa er niet meer was en ik bij hem te Parijs kwam toen hechtte de arme zich zóó aan mij dat ik er van leerde begrijpen hoeveel hij van Pa had gehouden<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">En nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik zeg dat aan U en aan Wil en niet aan hem<c type="kk">/</c> het is maar goed ik niet in Parijs ben gebleven want wij zouden<c type="kk">/</c> hij en ik<c type="kk">/</c> al te zeer ons in elkaar verdiept hebben<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>En daar is het leven niet voor<c type="kp">_</c> ik kan het U niet zeggen hoe veel beter ik het zóó voor hem vind als het nu is dan voorheen, hij had te veel vermoeiende zaken aan t’hoofd en daar leed zijn gezondheid onder<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">In t’begin dat ik ziek werd kon ik niet berusten in ’t idee in een gesticht te moeten gaan<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">En nu tegenwoordig geef ik het gewonnen dat ik reeds vroeger had moeten behandeld worden maar het is menschelijk zich daarin te vergissen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Een fransch schrijver zegt dat alle schilders zoo wat krankzinnig zijn<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en al is daartegen heel wat in te brengen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is zeker dat men er te zeer afgetrokken door wordt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Wat hier ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> hier waar ik voor niets te zorgen heb enz<c type="kp">_</c> verbeeld ik me ik vooruitga in gehalte van mijn werk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">En dus ga ik met betrekkelijke kalmte voort en doe mijn best op mijn werk en reken me niet onder de ongelukkigen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.9" n="9">Op ’t oogenblik werk ik aan een schilderij van een pad tusschen de bergen en een kleine beek die zich tusschen de steenen voortwerkt. De rotsen zijn effen lilas grijs of rose met hier en daar struiken: palm en een soort brem die door de herfst allerlei kleuren hebben<c type="kk">/</c> groen<c type="kk">/</c> geel<c type="kk">/</c> rood<c type="kk">/</c> bruin<c type="kp">_</c> En de beek op den voorgrond wit en schuimend als zeepsop en verderop weerspiegelend het blaauw van de lucht.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.10" n="10">En nu is zeker het werk dat men tegenwoordig hier maakt heel anders – kleuriger en meer vierkant geteekend dan wat men vroeger in Holland deed in den tijd van b.v. Schelfhout.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.11" n="11">En toch<c type="kk">/</c> het een is zoozeer een gevolg van t’andere<c type="kp">_</c> zoo b.v. U heeft nog gekend de oude van der Sande Bakhuyzen en Jules Bakhuyzen<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ik dacht aan hun werk onlangs nog dat bij alle schijnbaar verschil er toch zoo weinig verandering in de gedachten der menschen is<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.12" n="12">Enfin ik geloof dat b.v. Jules Bakhuyzen heel best zou begrijpen wat ik dezer dagen schilder<c type="kk">/</c> die ravijn met de beek en een ander schilderij<c type="kk">/</c> van het park van het gesticht – groote mastboomen tegen een avondlucht.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.13" n="13">Ik hoop Theo U mijn studies heeft gestuurd<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> maar ik heb opnieuw een nog al groot schilderij voor U onder handen van vrouwen die aan het oogsten van olijven zijn. De boomen grijs groen met een rose lucht en paarschachtigen grond.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Al de kleuren zachter dan gewoonlijk.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.14" n="14">Ik had gehoopt het dezer dagen te kunnen verzenden maar het droogt langzaam.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.15" n="15">Zooals ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik betreur het wel eens dat ik zoo afgetrokken soms ben<c type="kk">/</c> ik verzet er me tegen maar het maakt mij zoo ongeschikt om veel dingen te doen die eigentlijk mijn pligt waren<c type="kp">_</c> Mijn gezondheid mankeert letterlijk niets maar de schok van verleden jaar maakt ik er toch tegen op zou zien buiten een gesticht te gaan. Ik heb me soms verbeeld dat als ik het schilderen daarliet en een of ander hard leven had<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. als soldaat naar de oost<c type="kk">/</c> mij dat beter zou maken<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar het is daar al wat laat voor en ik vrees men zou me afkeuren<c type="kp">_</c> Ik denk dit half in scherts<c type="kk">/</c> half in ernst<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.16" n="16">Voorloopig gaat het werk goed maar natuurlijk blijven mijn gedachten<c type="kk">/</c> steeds op de kleuren &amp; teekenen gevestigd<c type="kk">/</c> in een nog al klein kringetje ronddraaien<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Ik wil dus maar bij den dag leven – van den een op den ander zoeken te komen<c type="kp">_</c>– En trouwens mijn kameraads schilders klagen ook dikwijls er over dat het vak zoo magteloos maakt. of dat het magteloozen zijn die het uitoefenen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.17" n="17">Wat zult U veel om Theo en Jo en de aanstaande gebeurtenis denken<c type="kk">/</c> moge het goed afloopen hoop ik zoo van harte. Ik ben er blij om me te kunnen verbeelden hoe uw woning is naar de beschrijving van Wil.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.18" n="18">Zijn er weer berigten van Cor. Erg best is het U in de buurt van Anna zijt en Uw kleinkinderen om U heen zult zien<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Groet hen bij Anna regt hartelijk voor me bij t’eindigen van t’jaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.19" n="19">Het weer is hier nog al zacht dezer dagen<c type="kk">/</c> toch ook veel dagen van vorst en wind maar dan schijnt de zon krachtiger dan in Holland<c type="kp">_</c> Weet U nog dat Rappard eens zeide “het frischt wel eens op” toen hij typheuse koorts gehad had en later bij ons logeerde<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> ik denk daar wel eens aan als ik me veel sterker en bij tijden helderder voel dan verl. jaar.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.20" n="20">Nu ik wensch U prettige Kerstdagen toe en een goed oud &amp; nieuwe jaar. In gedachten omhelsd door</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.21" n="21">Uw liefh.</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.22" n="22">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.23" n="23">ik schrijf aan Wil volgende keer<c type="kk">/</c> daar het posttijd is.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Towards the end of the year I come to bid you good-day once more. You’ll say that I’ve forgotten it many times. It’s a year since I became ill, and it’s difficult for me to express the extent to which I have or haven’t recovered. I often have terrible self-reproach about things in the past, my illness being pretty much my own fault, and in any event it’s doubtful whether I can make amends for faults in any way. But reasoning or thinking about this is sometimes so difficult, and sometimes my feelings overwhelm me more than in the past. And then I can think so much of you and of the past. You and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> have been so much, so very much to me, possibly more even than to the others, and I don’t seem to have had a happy nature. I started to realize that in Paris, how much more than I Theo did his best to help Pa practically, so much so that his own interests often went by the board because of it. That’s why I’m so thankful now at present that Theo finally found a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs> and is waiting for his baby. Anyway, Theo had more self-denial than I, and that’s deep in his character. And when Pa was no longer with us and I went to him in Paris, then the poor chap attached himself so much to me that I came to understand how much he had loved Pa.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">And now, I say this to you and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> and not to him, it’s a good thing I didn’t stay in Paris because we should, he and I, have become all too much bound up in each other. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And that’s not what life’s for. I can’t tell you how much better I think it is for him as it is now than before; he had too many tiring things on his mind, and his health suffered for it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">When I was first ill I couldn’t accept the idea that I had to go into an asylum.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">And now at present I admit that I should have been treated earlier, but it’s human to err in that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">A French writer says that all painters are mad to some degree,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and although there’s a great deal to be said against that, it’s certain that one is too easily alienated by it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Be this as it may, here, where I don’t have to concern myself with anything etc. — I imagine that the standard of my work is getting better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">And so I go on with relative calm and do my best at my work and don’t count myself among the unfortunates.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">At the moment I’m working on a painting of a path between the mountains and a small stream that works its way between the stones. The rocks are solid lilac grey or pink, with bushes here and there: box and a sort of broom, that have all sorts of colours, green, yellow, red, brown, because of the autumn. And the stream in the foreground white and foaming like soapsuds, and further up reflecting the blue of the sky.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">And now it’s certain that the work they’re making here at present is very different — more colourful and more forthrightly drawn than what people used to do in Holland in the time of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1338">Schelfhout</rs>, say. 
      <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">And yet the one is so much a consequence of the other. For example, you knew the old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1344">Van de Sande Bakhuyzen</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1342">Jules Bakhuyzen</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I thought of their work only recently, that with all the apparent difference there’s still so little change in people’s ideas.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Anyway I believe that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1342">Jules Bakhuyzen</rs>, say, would understand perfectly what I paint these days, that ravine with the stream, and another painting — of the park at the asylum — large pine trees against an evening sky.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I hope Theo sent you my studies,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> but I’m already working on another rather large painting for you of women harvesting olives. The trees grey-green with a pink sky and purplish soil.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> All the colours more subdued than usual.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">I had hoped to send it before long, but it’s drying slowly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">As I told you, I often regret that I’m sometimes so alienated; I resist it, but it makes me so unfit to do many things that were actually my duty. There’s literally nothing wrong with my health, but last year’s shock means I would still dread going outside an asylum. I’ve sometimes imagined that if I abandoned painting and had some hard life or other, as a soldier going to the east, say, that would make me better. But it’s already rather too late for that, and I’m afraid they’d turn me down. I think this half in jest, half in earnest.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">For the moment the work’s going well, but of course my thoughts, always fixed on colours and drawing, continue to go round in a rather small circle. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> So I want to live by the day — trying to get from one to the next. And for that matter my fellow painters also often complain that the profession makes one so powerless. Or that it’s the powerless who practise it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">How much you must be thinking about Theo and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and the forthcoming event; I hope with all my heart that it goes well. I’m glad to be able to imagine what your house is like after Wil’s description.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Is there any more news from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>? It’s very good that you’re close to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and will see your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_414 bio.xml#_415">grandchildren</rs> around you.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Give everyone at Anna’s my very best wishes at the ending of the year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">The weather here has been quite mild the last few days. Although many days of frost and wind, too, but then the sun shines more strongly than in Holland. Do you remember that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> once said ‘it’s sometimes refreshing’ when he’d had typhoid fever and later stayed with us.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I sometimes think about that when I feel much stronger and at times more clear-headed than last year.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.20" n="20">Now I wish you a happy Christmas and a good New Year. Embraced in thought by</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.21" n="21">Your loving</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.23" n="23">I’ll write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> next time, because it’s time for the post. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">In this letter to his mother, Vincent says that he will write later to Willemien. That letter is <ref target="let832.xml">letter 832</ref>, but its beginning reveals that it was in fact enclosed with the present letter, which means that these two letters were most likely written on the same day.</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">In <ref target="let832.xml">letter 832</ref> Van Gogh writes: ‘it’s exactly a year since I had that attack’, meaning his first attack, which he suffered on 23 December 1888. In the present letter Vincent also wished his mother a happy Christmas <ref target="#l-126">(l. 126)</ref>, which makes it likely the letter was written shortly before 25 December. We have therefore dated it, like <ref target="let832.xml">letter 832</ref>, to about Monday, 23 December 1889.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter was enclosed with <ref target="let832.xml">letter 832</ref> to Willemien (see <ref target="let832.xml#l-1*">ll. 1*-3</ref> in that letter).</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>It is impossible to say which writer Van Gogh is referring to. Artists battling madness feature in many French novels, by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Zola</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>, among others. See Max Milner, ‘Le peintre fou’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Romantisme</hi> 19, no. 66 (1989), pp. 5-21. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ravine </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2881">F 661 / JH 1871</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>The Van Gogh family was related to the Van de Sande Bakhuyzen family; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let022.xml#n-9">see letter 22, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pine trees with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2863">F 652 / JH 1843</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>On 6 December Vincent had sent Theo seven paintings intended for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let824.xml">See letter 824</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Women picking olives</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2879">F 655 / JH 1869</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Vincent’s sister <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and her husband, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Joan van Houten</rs>, had two daughters, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_415">Sara</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_414">Annie</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs> had stayed with the Van Goghs in Etten in June and October 1881; in May 1884 he stayed with them in Nuenen (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let168.xml">see letters 168</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let176.xml">176</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let446.xml">446</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    