<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Saturday, 4 January 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let836"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b671 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>836</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>622</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>838</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-01-04">Saturday, 4 January 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0671" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0671" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000915_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci de ta lettre.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> bien que je viens de t’écrire hier je te réponds aussitôt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Il y a que je n’ai jamais travaillé avec plus de calme que dans mes dernières toiles – tu vas en recevoir quelques unes en même temps j’espère que ma présente. Momentanément un grand découragement m’a surpris. Mais puisqu’en une semaine cette attaque a été terminée à quoi bon se dire qu’elle peut en effet encore revenir<c type="kp">_</c>– D’abord on ne sait pas ni ne peut prevoir comment &amp; sous quelle forme.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Continuons donc le travail tant que cela se peut comme si rien n’était<c type="kp">_</c> J’aurai bientôt occasion de sortir dehors quand il fera un temps pas trop froid et alors j’y tiendrais un peu de chercher à terminer le travail entrepris ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Pour donner une idée de la Provence il est indispensable de faire encore quelques toiles des cyprès et des montagnes.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Le ravin<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> et une autre toile des montagnes avec chemin sur l’avant plan<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> en sont des types. Et surtout le ravin que j’ai encore ici parcequ’il n’est pas sec.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Ainsi que la vue du parc aussi avec les pins.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Cela m’a pris tout le temps d’observer le caractère des pins<c type="kk">/</c> cyprès &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> dans l’air pur d’ici<c type="kk">/</c> les lignes qui ne changent pas et qu’on retrouve à chaque pas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Il est parfaitement juste que l’année passée la crise est revenue à diverses epoques – mais alors aussi c’etait precisément en travaillant que l’état normal revenait peu à peu. Ainsi en sera-t-il probablement aussi à cette occasion<c type="kp">_</c> Fais donc comme si rien n’était car nous n’y pouvons absolument rien. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Et ce qui serait infiniment pire c’est de se laisser aller à l’etat de mes compagnons d’infortune qui ne font rien de toute la journée<c type="kk">/</c> semaine<c type="kk">/</c> mois<c type="kk">/</c> année<c type="kk">/</c> ainsi que mainte fois je te l’ai dit et l’ai encore répété à m. Salles<c type="kk">/</c> l’engageant bien à ne jamais recommander cet asile ci. Le travail me fait encore garder un peu de présence d’esprit et rend possible que j’en sorte un jour.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">A présent j’ai les tableaux mûrs dans ma tête<c type="kk">/</c> je vois d’avance les endroits que je veux encore faire de ces mois ci<c type="kp">_</c> pourquoi changerais je de moyen d’expression<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">de retour d’ici<c type="kk">/</c> supposons<c type="kk">/</c> il faudra un peu voir si reellement il n’y a rien à faire de mes toiles<c type="kk">/</c> j’en aurais un certain nombre des miennes<c type="kk">/</c> un certain nombre des autres et peut-être chercherais je à faire un peu de commerce<c type="kp">_</c> Je ne le sais pas d’avance mais je ne vois aucune raison de ne pas faire ici encore des toiles qu’il me faudra alors que je sortirais d’ici. Encore une fois je ne peux absolument rien prévoir<c type="kk">/</c> je ne vois pas d’issue mais je vois aussi qu’indéfiniment le séjour ici ne pourra pas se prolonger. Alors pour ne rien hâter<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>brusquer<c type="kk">/</c> je désirerais continuer comme d’habitude tant que je suis ici<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">J’ai hier envoyé 2 toiles à Marseille<c type="kk">/</c> c. à d<c type="kp">_</c> j’en ai fait cadeau à l’ami Roullin<c type="kk">/</c> un mas blanc dans les oliviers<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> et un champ de blé avec fond de montagnes lilas et un arbre noir<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> comme dans la grande toile que je t’ai envoyé<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Et à M. Salles j’ai donné une petite toile avec des géraniums roses et rouges sur un fond tout noir<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> comme dans le temps j’en ai fait à Paris.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Pour l’argent que tu as envoyé il en revenait 10 francs à m. Peyron qu’il m’avait avancé le mois dernier, j’ai donné 20 francs d’étrennes et j’en ai pris 10 pour l’affranchissement des toiles et autres dépenses donc il reste en caisse encore 10 francs.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">A présent je viens de faire un petit portrait d’un des garçons d’ici qu’il voulait envoyer à sa mère<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> c’est pour dire que j’ai déjà repris le travail et s’il y voyait obstacle M. Peyron probablement ne m’aurait pas laissé faire. Ce qu’il m’a dit c’est “espérons que cela ne se renouvelle pas” – donc absolument la même chôse que toujours. il m’a causé avec beaucoup de bonté et pour lui ces chôses-là ne l’étonnent guère mais puisqu’il n’y a pas de remède 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>tout prêt c’est le temps et les circonstances qui seules peuvent influencer peutêtre<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">J’aurais bien envie d’aller encore une fois à Arles<c type="kk">/</c> pas immediatement mais vers la fin de Fevrier par exemple<c type="kk">/</c> d’abord pour revoir des amis<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui me ranime toujours et puis pour essayer si je suis capable de risquer le voyage à Paris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Suis fort content que la soeur soit venue<c type="kp">_</c> Bien le bonjour à elle et à Jo<c type="kk">/</c> et pour toi et pour moi ne nous faisons pas d’inquietudes<c type="kp">_</c> Quoi qu’il en soit cela n’a pas duré si longtemps que l’autre année et donc pouvons encore espérer que peu à peu le temps fera passer tout cela. Allons<c type="kk">/</c> bon courage et bonne poignée de main.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for your letter.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Although I just wrote to you yesterday I’m replying immediately.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">The fact is that I’ve never worked more calmly than in my latest canvases – you’re going to receive a few at the same time as this letter, I hope. For the moment I’ve been caught unawares by a great discouragement. But since this attack ended in a week, what’s the good of telling oneself that it can in fact recur? First we don’t know, nor can we foresee how and in what form.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">So let’s continue the work as much as possible as if nothing were amiss. I’ll soon have the opportunity to go outside when the weather isn’t too cold, and then I’d rather like to try to finish the work undertaken here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">To give an idea of Provence it’s vital to do a few more canvases of cypresses and mountains.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">The ravine<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and another canvas of mountains with a path in the foreground<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> are types of this. And especially the Ravine that I still have here because it isn’t dry.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> As well as the view of the park too, with the pines.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> It took me all the time to observe the character of the pines, cypresses &amp;c. in the pure air here, the lines that don’t change and which one finds again at every step.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">It’s perfectly true that last year the crisis recurred at various times – but then, too, it was precisely by working that the normal state returned little by little. It will probably be the same on this occasion too. So act as if nothing were amiss, for we can do absolutely nothing about it. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And what would be infinitely worse is to let myself slide into the state of my companions in misfortune who do nothing all day, week, month, year, as I’ve told you many times and repeated again to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs>, making him promise never to recommend this asylum. The work makes me retain a little presence of mind still, and makes it possible that I can get out one day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">At the moment I have the paintings ripe in my mind, I see in advance the places that I still want to do in the coming months. Why would I change means of expression.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Once I’m back from here, let’s suppose, we’ll have to see a little if there’s really nothing to be done with my canvases, I would have a certain number of mine, a certain number of other people’s, and perhaps I’d try to do a little dealing. I don’t know in advance, but I see no reason not to do more of the canvases here that I’ll need were I to get out of here. Once again, I can foresee absolutely nothing, I see no way out, but I also see that my stay here cannot be prolonged indefinitely. Then, in order not to hurry anything 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> or break it off suddenly, I’d wish to continue as usual as long as I’m here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Yesterday I sent 2 canvases to Marseille, i.e. I made a present of them to my friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs>, a white farmhouse among the olive trees<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and a wheatfield with a background of lilac mountains and a dark tree,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> as in the large canvas I sent you.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> And I’ve given <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_663">Mr Salles</rs> a little canvas with pink and red geraniums on a completely black background,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> like I used to do in Paris.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">As regards the money you sent, 10 francs of it were owing to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs>, which he’d advanced me last month, I gave 20 francs in New Year’s gifts, and I took 10 for the postage on the canvases and other expenses, so 10 francs still remain in the cash-box.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">At the moment I’ve just done a little portrait of one of the lads from here which he wanted to send to his mother,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> that’s to say I’ve already started work again, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> would probably not have allowed me to if he saw any obstacles there. What he said to me was ‘let’s hope that this doesn’t happen again’ – so absolutely the same thing as always. He talked to me with great kindness and these things scarcely surprise him, but since there’s no ready remedy 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> it’s time and circumstances alone that can perhaps have influence.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I’d very much like to go to Arles one more time, not immediately, but towards the end of February for example, first to see friends, which always cheers me up, and then to test whether I’m capable of risking the journey to Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Am very pleased that our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs> has come. Warm regards to her and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, and as for you and me, let’s not worry ourselves. In any event, it didn’t last as long as the other year, and so we can still hope that little by little time will make all of this pass. Well, be of good heart, and good handshake</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent says that he is replying immediately to Theo’s letter of 3 January <ref target="let835.xml">(835)</ref>. We have therefore dated the letter to Saturday, 4 January 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <ref target="let837.xml">Letter 837</ref> to Willemien was probably enclosed; see the <hi rend="italics">Additional details</hi> to that letter.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Sixth consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let834.xml">(834)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Second attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let833.xml">(833)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Willemien is staying with Theo and Jo <ref target="let835.xml">(835)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let835.xml">letter 835</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ravine </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2853">F 662 / JH 1804</rs>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Alpilles with a hut </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2823">F 622 / JH 1766</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ravine </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2881">F 661 / JH 1871</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pine trees with setting sun </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2863">F 652 / JH 1843</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This is probably a reaction to Theo’s suggestion in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let835.xml">letter 835</ref> that Vincent should temporarily confine himself to drawing.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Farmhouse among olive trees </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2876">F 664 / JH 1865</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfields with a tree and mountains </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2877">F 663 / JH 1866</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Wheatfields with a tree and mountains </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2875">F 721 / JH 1864</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This painting is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had painted a great many still lifes against a dark background in Paris in the summer of 1886. See cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>This portrait is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    