<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Joseph Ginoux and Marie Ginoux-Julien. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Monday, 20 January 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let842"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement/>
                                        <institution/>
                                        
                                        <idno/>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>842</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>622a</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>834</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-01-20">Monday, 20 January 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Joseph Ginoux and Marie Ginoux-Julien</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1r/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1r/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1r/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1v/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1v/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/842_1v/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="brief van elders" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/unknown/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mes chers amis Monsieur &amp; Madame Ginoux,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Je ne sais si vous vous en rappelez, je le trouve assez étrange, qu’il y a un an à peu près M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Ginoux a été malade en même temps que moi;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> et à présent cela a encore été comme cela puisque – juste vers Noël – pendant quelques jours j’ai été cette année encore assez mal pris<c type="kk">/</c> cependant cela a été très vite fini; je n’en ai pas eu pour une semaine. Puisque donc, mes chers amis, nous souffrons quelque fois ensemble cela me fait penser à ce que dit Madame Ginoux – “quand on est amis on l’est pour longtemps”.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je crois moi que les contrariétés qu’on éprouve dans le train train ordinaire de la vie nous font au moins autant de bien que de mal<c type="kp">_</c> Ce dont on tombe malade<c type="kk">/</c> accablé de découragement aujourd’hui<c type="kk">/</c> cela même nous rend l’énergie, la maladie accomplie, de nous lever et de vouloir guérir le lendemain<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Je vous l’assure que l’autre année cela m’a presque contrarié de guérir – d’aller mieux pour un temps plus ou moins long – continuant à redouter toujours les rechûtes – presque contrarié – vous dis-je – tellement j’avais peu envie de recommencer. Je me suis bien souvent dit que je préférais qu’il n’y eût plus rien et que cela fût fini. Mais oui – nous n’en sommes pas le maitre – de notre existence et il s’agit parait-il d’apprendre à vouloir vivre encore, même en souffrant.– Eh, je me sens si lâche là-<c type="shy">-</c>dedans<c type="kk">/</c> la santé revenant même. Je redoute encore. Alors qui suis-je pour encourager les autres<c type="kk">/</c> me direz-vous comme de juste<c type="kk">/</c> cela ne me sied guère.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Enfin c’est seulement pour vous dire, mes chers amis, que 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>j’espère si ardemment<c type="kk">/</c> et d’ailleurs que j’ose croire<c type="kk">/</c> que la maladie de m<hi rend="super">m </hi>Ginoux soit très passagère et qu’elle en remontera tout à fait ragaillardie<c type="kp">_</c> Mais elle n’ignore pas combien nous tenons tous à elle et désirons la voir bien portante<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Pour moi, la maladie m’a fait du bien – ce serait ingrat de ne pas en convenir; cela m’a calmé et très différent<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> de ce que je m’étais figuré cette année j’ai eu plus de chance que je n’avais osé espérer.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Mais si je n’avais pas été si bien soigné, si les gens n’avaient pas été pour moi aussi bons qu’ils l’ont été, je crois que j’aurais claqué ou que j’aurais perdu complètement la raison.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Les affaires sont les affaires puis aussi le devoir est le devoir<c type="kk">/</c> ce n’est donc que comme de juste que je retourne bientôt un peu voir mon frère<c type="kp">_</c> Mais il me sera penible de quitter le midi<c type="kk">/</c> je 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>vous l’assure à vous tous qui êtes devenus des amis pour moi – des amis pour longtemps.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">J’ai encore oublié de vous remercier des olives que vous m’avez envoyé l’autre fois et qui étaient excellentes<c type="kk">/</c> prochainement je vous rapporte les boîtes.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Je vous écris donc, chers amis, pour essayer de distraire pour un moment notre chère malade pour qu’elle reprenne son sourire habituel<c type="kk">/</c> pour nous faire plaisir à tous qui la connaissons<c type="kp">_</c> Ainsi que je vous l’ai dit, dans une quinzaine j’espère venir vous revoir bien guérie<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Les maladies sont là pour nous en faire ressouvenir que nous ne sommes pas en bois<c type="kp">_</c> Voila ce qui me parait le bon côté de tout cela. Puis après on s’en reva<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> à son travail de tous les jours redoutant moins les contrariétés<c type="kk">/</c> avec une nouvelle provision de sérénité<c type="kp">_</c> Et même en se séparant ce sera en se disant pourtant encore: “et lorsqu’on est amis on l’est pour longtemps” – car voila le moyen pour pouvoir se quitter.–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Allons, à bientôt, et mes meilleurs souhaits pour la prompte guérison de M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Ginoux. croyez moi</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">bien à vous</p>
    
<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Vincent.</p><pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friends <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">Mr and Mrs Ginoux</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I don’t know if you’ll remember, I find it quite strange, that about a year ago Mrs Ginoux was ill at the same time as I was;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and now it has been so again since – just around Christmas – for a few days I was again taken quite badly this year, however it was over very quickly; I had it less than a week. Since, therefore, my dear friends, we sometimes suffer together, it makes me think of what Mrs Ginoux said – ‘when people are friends they’re that way for a long time’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I myself believe that the annoyances one experiences in the ordinary routine of life do us at least as much good as bad. The thing that makes one fall ill, overcome by discouragement, today, that same thing gives us the energy, once the illness is over, to get up and want to recover the next day.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I can assure you that the other year it almost vexed me to recover my health – to be better for a longer or shorter time – continuing always to fear relapses – almost vexed – I tell you – so little desire did I have to begin again. I’ve very often told myself that I’d prefer that there be nothing more and that it was over. Well yes – we’re not the master of that – of our existence, and it’s a matter, seemingly, of learning to want to live on, even when suffering. Ah, I feel so cowardly in that respect, even as my health returns. I still fear. So who am I to encourage others, you’ll rightly say to me, it hardly suits me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Anyway, it’s only to say to you, my dear friends, that 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I hope so ardently, and that moreover I dare hope, that Mrs Ginoux’s illness will be very fleeting and that she’ll recover from it entirely enlivened. But she isn’t unaware how fond we all are of her and wish to see her well.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">As for me, illness has done me good – it would be ungrateful not to acknowledge that; it has calmed me, and I’ve had more luck this year than I had dared hope for, quite unlike what I had imagined.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">But if I hadn’t been so well cared for, if people hadn’t been as kind to me as they have been, I think I would have pegged out or that I would have completely lost my reason.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Business is business, then duty too is duty, so it’s only right that I soon return for a while to see my brother. But it will be hard for me to leave the south, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I can assure all of you who have become friends to me – friends for a long time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I’ve forgotten again to thank you for the olives you sent me the other time and which were excellent, I’ll bring you back the boxes soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">I’m therefore writing to you, dear friends, to try to distract for a moment our dear patient so that she can resume her habitual smile, to please all of us who know her. As I’ve told you, in a fortnight I hope to come and see you again, quite cured.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">Illnesses are there to make us remember again that we aren’t made of wood. That’s what seems the good side of all this to me. Then afterwards one goes back to one’s everyday work less fearful of the annoyances, with a new store of serenity. And even if we part, it will be while yet saying to oneself again: ‘and when people are friends they’re that way for a long time’ – for that is the means to be able to leave one another.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Well, more soon, and my best wishes for Mrs Ginoux’s speedy recovery. Believe me</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Vincent.</p><pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Date of the postmark: Monday, 20 January 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The envelope of this letter has been preserved. The front is postmarked ‘ST REMY DE PROV / BES D / 3E 20 / 90’, and the back ‘JANV / 90’. Stamp: 15 centimes. The address reads: ‘Monsieur Ginoux / Café de la gare / Place Lamartine / <hi rend="italics">Arles</hi>’.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Second attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let833.xml">(833)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Madame Ginoux</rs> had had the flu, and was also suffering from nervousness and menopausal complaints. Van Gogh had visited her on 18 or 19 January (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let841.xml">see letter 841</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read : ‘différemment’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It emerges from <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let850.xml">letter 850</ref> that Van Gogh had said this during his visit to the <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">Ginouxs</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘retourne’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    