<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Wednesday, 19 February 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let855"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b676 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>855</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>627</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>856</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-02-19">Wednesday, 19 February 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0676" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000922_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000922_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0676" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000922_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000922_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Beste Moeder,</p>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2">reeds dagen lang was ik van plan uw brief te beantwoorden maar van schrijven kwam niet door dat ik van s’morgens tot s’avonds zat te schilderen &amp; zoo de tijd verliep. Naar ik mij voorstel zult U even als ik ook veel in gedachten bij Jo en Theo zijn<c type="kk">/</c> wat was ik blijde toen de tijding kwam het goed was afgeloopen, erg best Wil gebleven was. Veel liever had ik gehad dat hij zijn jongen naar Pa had genoemd<c type="kk">/</c> aan wien ik dezer dagen zoo dikwijls dacht<c type="kk">/</c> dan naar mij, maar enfin nu het eenmaal zoo is heb ik dadelijk begonnen een schilderij voor hem te maken om in hun slaapkamer te hangen. Groote takken witte amandelbloessem tegen een blaauwe lucht.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3">Ik dank U wel voor de berigten aangaande Cor<c type="kp">_</c> U zult wel niet vergeten hem voor mij te groeten als U schrijft. Wat U van Tante Mina schrijft trof mij<c type="kk">/</c> dat zij met zooveel geduld haar pijn verdraagt.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Nu zult U wel weer in Leiden terug zijn. Deze laatste dagen hadden wij hier nog al triest weer maar vandaag was het een ware lentedag en de velden jong koren met de lilas heuvels in ’t verschiet zoo mooi en de amandel boomen beginnen overal te bloeïen. Ik heb nog al erg verwonderd opgekeken van dat artikel dat zij over me geschreven hebben<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – Isaäcson wou het in der tijd doen<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en ik verzocht hem het liever maar in de pen te laten, ik was er bedroefd door toen ik het las omdat het zoo zeer overdreven is; het zit anders in elkaar – wat mij draagt bij het werk is juist het gevoel dat er verscheiden zijn die net ’t zelfde doen als ik en waarom dan een artikel over mij en niet over die 6 of 7 anderen enz.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">Nu moet ik bekennen dat later toen mijn verwondering wat geweken was ik er bij wijlen erg door opgemonterd me gevoel, gisteren bovendien melde Theo me dat zij een van mijn schilderijen te Brussel verkochten voor 400 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> In vergelijking van andere prijzen, ook de Hollandsche<c type="kk">/</c> is dit weinig maar ik tracht daarom <hi rend="italics">productief</hi> te zijn om in de <hi rend="italics">redelijke</hi> prijzen te kunnen <hi rend="italics">blijven</hi> werken. En als we met onze handen ons brood moeten zoeken te verdienen heb ik heel wat kosten in te halen.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Zooeven komt de brief van Wil en U, erg dank er voor<c type="kp">_</c> ik had u al eerder moeten schrijven doch zooals gezegd door nog al druk werk stond mijn hoofd zoo weinig naar schrijven.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.6" n="6">Nu denk ik er sterk over van het buitenkansje van t’verkoopen van dat sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> maar te profiteeren om eens naar Parijs te gaan – om Theo eens te bezoeken. En dank zij de dokter hier ga ik in mijn gevoel kalmer &amp; gezonder weg dan ik er kwam<c type="kp">_</c>– Eens te probeeren hoe ’t gaat buiten een gesticht is misschien nog al vanzelf sprekend<c type="kp">_</c> Het werk zal me mogelijk echter moeielijker vallen als ik weer op vrije voeten me zal bevinden.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.nl.7" n="7">Enfin we willen ’t beste hopen. Het is wel zonderling dat mijn vriend met wien ik te Arles een tijd zamen werkte lust zou hebben naar Antwerpen te gaan<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en zoodoende ware ik weer wat digter bij U allen. Maar ik vrees dit is niet geheel uitvoerbaar<c type="kk">/</c> ook al omdat ’t meen ik kostbarer ware en als men hier gewend is aan ’t klimaat misschien de gezondheid ook tegen kon vallen<c type="kk">/</c> meer in ’t noorden terug. Enfin ik begin met eens een week of wat te Parijs te probeeren<c type="kp">_</c>– In gedachten omhelsd door Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.8" n="8">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I’ve been meaning to answer your letter for days, but didn’t get round to writing because I was painting from morning till night, and so the time passed. I imagine that your thoughts, like mine, are with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and Theo. How glad I was when the news came that it had gone well; very good thing <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> stayed. I’d much rather that he’d called his boy after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>, whom I’ve thought about so often these days, than after me, but anyway, as it’s been done now I started right away to make a painting for him, to hang in their bedroom. Large branches of white almond blossom against a blue sky.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">I thank you for the news about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs>. You won’t forget to send him my regards when you write, will you? What you write about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317">Aunt Mina</rs>, that she bears her pain with so much patience,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> touched me. You must be back in Leiden again by now. The last few days we’ve had rather miserable weather here, but today it was a real spring day, and the fields of young wheat and the lilac hills in the distance so beautiful, and the almond trees are beginning to blossom everywhere. I was really rather surprised at that article they wrote about me<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> wanted to do it some time ago<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and I asked him not to put pen to paper; I was saddened by it when I read it because it’s so exaggerated; it’s not like that — precisely what sustains me in my work is the feeling that there are several people who are doing exactly the same as I, and so why an article about me and not about those 6 or 7 others etc.?
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Now I must confess that later, when my surprise had abated somewhat, I felt very heartened by it at times; yesterday, what’s more, Theo informed me that they’d sold one of my paintings in Brussels for 400 francs.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> In comparison with other prices, including the Dutch ones, this isn’t much, but that’s why I try to be <hi rend="italics">productive</hi> in order to be able to <hi rend="italics">keep</hi> working at <hi rend="italics">reasonable</hi> prices. And if we have to try to earn our living with our hands, I have an awful lot of expenses to make up for.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">The letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> and you just arrived, thank you very much for it. I should have written to you before but, as I said, my mind wasn’t on writing because I was so busy working.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Now I’m seriously thinking of profiting from that windfall of selling that painting to go to Paris — to visit Theo. And thanks to the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">doctor</rs> here I feel I’ll leave calmer and healthier than I came here. Just to see how it goes outside an asylum is perhaps only a matter of course. The work may possibly be more difficult for me, though, when I’m at liberty again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Anyway, we’ll hope for the best. It’s odd that my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">friend</rs> with whom I worked for a time in Arles should want to go to Antwerp,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and that way I’d be a little closer to you all again. But I’m afraid this isn’t entirely practicable, partly because I think it would be more expensive, and if one’s accustomed to the climate here it might also be bad for one’s health to return further north. Anyway, I’ll start by trying a week or so in Paris. Embraced in thought by your loving</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter dates from after 10 February, because Van Gogh refers in the enclosed letter to Willemien <ref target="let856.xml">(856)</ref> to the letter he had written to Aurier <ref target="let853.xml">(853)</ref>. Moreover, it must have been written before 22 February, since that is when Van Gogh went to Arles, where he suffered another attack (<ref target="let858.xml">letter 858</ref>).</p>
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="indent">The remark ‘The last few days we’ve had rather miserable weather here, but today it was a real spring day’ <ref target="#l-19">(ll. 19-21)</ref> means that the letter was most likely written on 19 February, when the nearest weather station (at Arles) registered a temperature of 18 degrees Celsius, whereas the three preceding days had had highs of 7.2, 10 and 14 degrees, with precipitation (<hi rend="italics">Météo-France</hi>). On the basis of this information we have dated the letter to Wednesday, 19 February 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Most likely enclosed with <ref target="let856.xml">letter 856</ref> to Willemien.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Almond blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2890">F 671 / JH 1891</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_317">Aunt Mina</rs>’s health complaints, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let811.xml#n-8">see letter 811, n. 8.</ref> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> had visited her in Amsterdam (cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let850.xml#n-23">letter 850, n. 23</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_521">Aurier</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_524">Les isolés: Vincent van Gogh</ref>’, and for <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs>’s reaction to the article, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let845.xml#n-2">see letter 845, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>At the beginning of October 1889, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> had planned to write an article on Van Gogh (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let808.xml">see letter 808</ref>). </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The painter <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_870">Anna Boch</rs>, a sister of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_869">Eugène Boch</rs>, had bought Van Gogh’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>) at the exhibition of Les Vingt in Brussels. The letter in which Theo reported this to Vincent is not known. On 6 March 1890, Theo recorded in his account book under ‘Rekening Vincent’ (Account Vincent) the sum of 400 francs, received from ‘Mlle Bock pour tab Vigne rouge’ (Miss Boch for the painting Red vineyard). He also recorded that he had paid 21.60 francs for the packing of the paintings shown at the exhibition of Les Vingt (29 March 1890). See <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 45. The works sold are listed in the anonymous article ‘Acquisition d’objets d’art’, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">L’Art Moderne. Revue Critique des Arts et de la Littérature</hi> 10 (23 February 1890), no. 8, pp. 57-59; the sale of Van Gogh’s painting is recorded on p. 59.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had written this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let844.xml">letter 844</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    