<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Wednesday, 19 February 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let856"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b720 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>856</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W20</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>857</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-02-19">Wednesday, 19 February 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0720" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000975_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000975_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0720" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000975_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000975_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000975_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Merci beaucoup de tes deux dernières lettres<c type="kk">/</c> celle datée de Paris &amp; celle d’aujourd’hui<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Ce que tu m’écris encore de l’accouchement de Jo me touche, oui tu as été bien brave &amp; bien bonne de rester auprès. Je serais<c type="kk">/</c> dans des circonstances où l’effroi nous prend<c type="kk">/</c> probablement davantage que toi comme une poule mouillée<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Mais enfin le résultat c’est que l’enfant y est – et ainsi que je l’écris à sa grandmère je me suis mis à peindre de ces jours ci pour lui – une grande toile bleu de ciel sur lequel se détachent des branches fleuries<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Possible que je le voie bientôt – je l’espère du moins – vers la fin de mars<c type="kp">_</c>– Je vais essayer demain ou après demain d’aller encore une fois à Arles pour voir si je supporte le voyage et la vie ordinaire sans que les attaques reviennent.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Il faut peutêtre se fortifier la resolution de ne pas vouloir avoir la tête faible dans mon cas<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Naturellement par un travail de tête continuel la pensee d’un artiste prend parfois quelque chôse d’exagéré et d’excentrique. J’ai trouvé l’article de M<c type="kp">_</c> Aurier<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – abstraction faite si je merite ce qu’il dit de moi – en soi très artistique<c type="kk">/</c> très curieux – mais c’est plutot comme cela qu’il <hi rend="italics">faudrait</hi> être que la triste realite de ce que je me sens<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Je lui ai écrit que dans tous les cas il me semblait que Monticelli et Gauguin etaient plûtot ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> qu’il me semblait donc que la part qui m’en reviendrait ne serait que secondaire<c type="kk">/</c> tres secondaire<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Ces idées dont il parle ne sont pas à moi car en général les artistes impressionistes sont tous ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> sous une même influence et tous nous sommes un peu des névrosés. Cela nous rend très sensible à la couleur et à son langage particulier<c type="kk">/</c> ses effets de complémentaires<c type="kk">/</c> de contrastes<c type="kk">/</c> d’harmonie<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>Mais quand j’ai lu l’article j’en devenais presque triste juste en pensant: faudrait être comme cela et je me sens si inférieur<c type="kp">_</c> Et l’orgueil grise comme la boisson<c type="kk">/</c> quand on est loué et qu’on a bu on devient triste ou enfin je ne sais pas dire comment je le sens mais il me semble que le meilleur travail que l’on ferait serait celui qu’on executerait en famille sans se louer<c type="kp">_</c> Et alors dans les artistes on n’est pas toujours dans des dispositions d’amitié <hi rend="italics">suffisantes</hi>. Ou bien on exagère les qualités de quelqu’un ou bien on le neglige par trop. Je veux cependant volontiers croire qu’au fond la <hi rend="italics">Justice</hi> se porte mieux que cela puisse paraître<c type="kp">_</c> Il faut bien pouvoir rire quelquefois et s’egayer un peu ou même beaucoup. Je trouve que tu as eu de la chance de voir Degas chez lui<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">J’ai en train un portrait d’arlésienne où je cherche une expression autre que celles des parisiennes<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Ah Millet! Millet! celui là comme il a peint l’humanité et le “quelque chôse là-haut”<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> familier et pourtant solennel<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Se dire de nos jours que celui là s’est mis à peindre en pleurant<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> que Giotto<c type="kk">/</c> qu’Angelico peignaient à genoux<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Delacroix si navré<c type="kk">/</c> si emu.... <hi rend="italics">presqu</hi>’en souriant<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Qui sommes nous impressionistes pour faire déjà comme eux. Salis dans la lutte pour la vie... “qui rendra à l’âme ce qu’en ont enlevée le souffle des revolutions” – voila le cri d’un poète de l’autre génération qui sembla pressentir nos faiblesses<c type="kk">/</c> nos maladies<c type="kk">/</c> nos egarements actuels.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Et je le dis souvent<c type="kk">/</c> sommes nous aussi neufs que le vieux Belge Henri Conscience. Ah c’est pourquoi j’etais content du succès de Bruxelles<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> à cause de cette Campine d’Anvers<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> que je cherche parfois encore à rappeler dans les sillons calmes des champs 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>tout en m’en sentant devenir un enfant bien dégénéré. Songeant ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> mais bien lointain<c type="kk">/</c> me vient le désir de me refaire et de chercher à me faire excuser de ce que mes tableaux sont pourtant presqu’un cri d’angoisse tout en symbolisant dans le rustique tournesol la gratitude. Tu vois que je raisonne pas encore bien – il vaut mieux savoir calculer ce que vaut une livre de pain et un quart de café comme le savent les paysans<c type="kp">_</c>– Et nous y revoilà<c type="kp">_</c> Millet donnait l’exemple en vivant dans une chaumière<c type="kk">/</c> en restant bien avec les gens sans nos écarts d’orgueil<c type="kk">/</c> d’excentricité<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Donc plutot un peu de sagesse que beaucoup d’entrain<c type="kp">_</c>– Alors comme alors<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’espère t’écrire de nouveau sous peu – porte toi bien et la mère aussi.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">A Paris j’espère faire quelques portraits<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai toujours eu la croyance que par les portraits on apprend à réfléchir. Ce n’est pas qui plaît le plus aux amateurs mais un portrait est quelquechose de presqu’utile et parfois agreable<c type="kk">/</c> comme les meubles qu’on connait cela rappelle des souvenirs longtemps.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">En pensée je t’embrasse bien<c type="kp">_</c> Si les autres soeurs desireraient avoir des toiles aussi<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> tu peux en demander d’autres à Theo et tu les choisirais à ton goût. Encore une fois bien des chôses et bonne poignée de main.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">b. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Je ne déteste pas du tout que quelques toiles encore aillent en Hollande<c type="kk">/</c> comme tu le sais<c type="kk">/</c> à l’occasion.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks very much for your last two letters, the one dated from Paris and today’s.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">What you write further about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s confinement touches me, yes you were very brave and very kind to stay by her side. In circumstances where fright seizes us, I’d probably be more of a milksop than you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">But anyway, the result is that the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">child</rs>’s here – and as I wrote to his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">grandmother</rs>, I’ve started painting for him these last few days – a large sky-blue canvas against which branches covered in blossoms stand out.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Possible that I may see him soon – I hope so at least – towards the end of March. I’m going to try to go to Arles once more tomorrow or the day after tomorrow to see if I can bear the journey and ordinary life without the attacks recurring.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Perhaps in my case I must strengthen my resolve not to want to have a feeble mind.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Naturally, through continual brain-work, the thoughts of an artist sometimes take on something of the exaggerated and eccentric. I found <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_521">Mr Aurier</rs>’s article<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – leaving aside whether I deserve what he says of me – in itself very artistic, very curious – but it’s rather like this that I <hi rend="italics">ought</hi> to be than the sad reality of what I feel myself to be.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">I wrote to him that in any event it seemed to me that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> were rather like that, that it therefore seemed to me that the share which was owing to me would be only secondary, very secondary.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> These ideas of which he speaks aren’t mine, for in general the Impressionist artists are all like this, under the same influence, and we’re all of us somewhat neurotic. This makes us very sensitive to colour and its particular language, its effects of complementaries, contrasts, harmony.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> But when I read the article it made me almost sad as I thought: should be like this and I feel so inferior. And pride intoxicates like drink, when one is praised and has drunk one becomes sad, or anyway I don’t know how to say how I feel it, but it seems to me that the best work one could do would be that carried out in the family home without self-praise. And then among artists, people’s friendly dispositions aren’t always <hi rend="italics">enough</hi>. Either someone’s qualities are exaggerated or he’s over-neglected. However, I very much want to believe that basically <hi rend="italics">Justice</hi> is in better health than it appears to be. One really must be able to laugh sometimes, and make merry a little or even a lot. I think you were lucky to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_981">Degas</rs> at his home.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I have a portrait of an <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs> on the go in which I’m seeking an expression different from that of Parisian women.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">Ah <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>! Millet! How that fellow painted humanity and the ‘something on high’,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> familiar and yet solemn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">These days, to think that  that fellow wept as he started painting,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1048">Giotto</rs>, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_295">Angelico</rs> painted on their knees,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> so utterly sad and moved... <hi rend="italics">almost</hi> smiling.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Who are we Impressionists to act like them already? Soiled in the struggle for life... ‘who will give back to the soul that which the breath of revolutions has taken away’ – that’s the cry of a poet of the other generation who seemed to have a premonition of our present weaknesses, our sicknesses, our confusions.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> And I say it often, are we as brand new as the old Belgian, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Henri Conscience</rs>? Ah, that’s why I was pleased with the success in Brussels,<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> because of that Kempen of Antwerp<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> that I still try to recall from time to time in the calm furrows of the fields 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> while feeling myself become a most degenerate child. Thinking like this, but very far off, the desire comes over me to remake myself and try to have myself forgiven for the fact that my paintings are, however, almost a cry of anguish while symbolizing gratitude in the rustic sunflower. You can see that I’m not yet reasoning well – it’s better to know how to calculate what a pound of bread and a quarter of coffee are worth, the way the peasants know. And here we are again. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> set the example by living in a cottage, keeping in well with people without our lapses of pride and eccentricity.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> So rather a little wisdom than a lot of gusto. So, just like then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">I hope to write to you again soon – look after yourself, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">In Paris I hope to do a few portraits, I’ve always had the belief that through portraits one learns to reflect. It isn’t what pleases art lovers the most, but a portrait is something almost useful and sometimes pleasant, like pieces of furniture one knows, they recall memories for a long time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I kiss you affectionately in thought. If our other <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401 bio.xml#_412">sisters</rs> would also like to have canvases<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> you can ask Theo for others, and you could choose them according to your taste. Once again warm regards, and good handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I don’t hate it at all that a few more canvases should go to Holland, as you know, if the opportunity arises.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">For the date assigned to this letter, <ref target="let855.xml">see letter 855</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Almond blossom </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2890">F 671 / JH 1891</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_521">Aurier</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_524">Les isolés: Vincent van Gogh</ref>’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let845.xml#n-2">see letter 845, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh said this to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_521">Aurier</rs> in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let853.xml">letter 853</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
      
<p>In Saint-Rémy Van Gogh painted a total of five portraits of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Madame Ginoux</rs>, based on the drawing <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> had made in Arles: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_97">Madame Ginoux (study for ‘Night café, Arles’)</rs></hi>, 1888 (Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco). Four versions are now known of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi>: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2891">F 540 / JH 1892</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2892">F 541 / JH 1893</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2893">F 542 / JH 1894</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2894">F 543 / JH 1895</rs>. The fifth portrait, intended for Madame Ginoux, is lost (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let857.xml#n-1">see letter 857, n. 1</ref>). We do not know which of the versions is referred to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>For ‘something on high’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let288.xml#n-15">see letter 288, n. 15.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The remark ‘that fellow wept as he started painting’ refers to something <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> recounted about his arrival as a young artist in Paris in January 1837: ‘I was only able to stop weeping by dashing in my face fistfuls of water that I took from a fountain in the street’. (Je ne parvins à arrêter mes pleurs qu’en me jetant au visage des poignées d’eau que je pris à une fontaine de la rue). See Sensier 1881, p. 44.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This remark probably refers to something Van Gogh had read in 1885 in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Jean Gigoux</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi> about <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, who drew figures after Raphael every day: ‘It was his way of saying his prayers, in the manner of the old masters, who would kneel before starting a work’ (C’était sa manière de faire sa prière, à l’imitation des vieux maîtres, qui, eux, se mettaient à genoux avant de commencer une oeuvre). Gigoux 1885, p. 70.</p>

<p rend="indent">The legend of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_295">Fra Angelico</rs> weeping before painting a crucifix originates in <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1814">Giorgio Vasari</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_526">Vite</ref></hi> (1550) and is elaborated and embroidered upon in every subsequent publication. Cf. Sir Martin Conway, M.P., <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Van Eycks and their followers</hi>. London 1921, p. 103.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The words ‘almost smiling’ were taken from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_742">Silvestre</rs>’s book <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_415">Eugène Delacroix. Documents nouveaux</ref></hi>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let526.xml#n-2">See letter 526, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This quotation, possibly from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, has not been traced.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>‘The success in Brussels’ refers to the praise given Van Gogh’s work at the exhibition of Les Vingt in that city, and the sale of one of the paintings exhibited, which he wrote about in the enclosed letter to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let855.xml">letter 855</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>‘La Campine’ (de Kempen) is a region in northern Belgium.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh derived his knowledge of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s way of life primarily from <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>, who told of Millet’s humble origins and his life as a peasant among the peasants. See Sensier 1881 and cf. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let493.xml#n-6">letter 493, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Vincent had already sent Theo seven studies intended for their <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let824.xml">See letter 824</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    