<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Friday, 2 May 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let866"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b681 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>866</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>632</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>867</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-05-02">on or about Friday, 2 May 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0681 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000927_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000927_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0681 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000927_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000927_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0681 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000928_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000928_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0681 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000928_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000928_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">encore une fois je t’ecris pour dire que la santé continue à aller bien, pourtant je me sens un peu éreinté par cette longue crise et j’ose croire que le changement projeté me rafraichira davantage les idées<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Je crois que le mieux sera que j’aille moi-même voir ce médecin à la campagne le plus tôt possible; alors on pourra bientôt décider si c’est chez lui ou provisoirement à l’auberge que j’irai loger; et ainsi on évitera un séjour trop prolongé à Paris, chôse que je redouterais<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Tu te rappelles qu’il y a 6 mois je te disais après une crise que si cela se répétait je te demanderais de changer<c type="kp">_</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Nous en sommes là – quoique je ne me sens pas capable de porter un jugement sur la façon qu’ils ont ici de traiter les malades – il suffit que je sens ce qui me reste de raison et de puissance de travailler absolument en danger. tandis qu’au contraire je me fais fort de prouver à ce médecin duquel tu parles que je sais encore travailler logiquement et lui me traitera en conséquence, et puisqu’il aime la peinture il y a assez de chance qu’il en résulte une amitié solide.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Je ne crois pas que M. Peyron s’opposera à un très prompt départ. je me persuade d’ailleurs que le plaisir de passer quelques jours avec toi me remettra beaucoup.– Et dès lors nous pouvons bien compter sur une période de santé relative<c type="kp">_</c> Ne tarde donc pas à prendre les mesures nécessaires pour que cela ne traîne pas<c type="kp">_</c>–</p>
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Une fois là-bas je pourrai faire venir mon lit qui est à Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">D’ailleurs je changerais quand même<c type="kk">/</c> préférant être dans un asile où les malades travailleraient<c type="kk">/</c> à cette affreuse oisiveté d’ici qui reellement me parait simplement comme un crime. Enfin tu me diras qu’on voit cela un peu partout et que même à Paris cela abonde. Quoi qu’il en soit j’espère que nous nous reverrons sous peu.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Les eaux fortes que tu m’as envoyé<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> sont bien belles. Ci contre j’ai griffonné un croquis d’après une peinture que j’ai faite de trois figures qui sont dans le fond de l’eau forte du Lazare.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Le mort et ses deux soeurs<c type="kp">_</c>– La grotte et le cadavre sont violet<c type="kk">/</c> jaune<c type="kk">/</c> blanc<c type="kp">_</c> La femme qui ôte le mouchoir de la face du ressucité a une robe verte et des cheveux orangés<c type="kk">/</c> l’autre a une chevelure noire et un vetement rayé. Vert &amp; rose. Derriere une campagne<c type="kk">/</c> des collines bleues<c type="kk">/</c> un soleil levant jaune. La combinaison de couleurs ainsi parlerait par elle-même de la même chose qu’exprime le clair obscur de l’eau forte<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">J’aurais encore à ma disposition le modèle qui a posé la berceuse<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> et l’autre dont tu viens de recevoir le portrait d’après le dessin de Gauguin<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> alors certes j’essayerais à exécuter en grand cette toile<c type="kk">/</c> les personalités étant ce que j’aurais rêvé comme caractères. Mais laissant de côté des motifs de ce genre<c type="kk">/</c> il restera là-bas l’étude d’après nature de paysans et paysages quand je serai de retour dans le nord.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Pour ce qui est de la commande de couleurs.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> si c’est que je reste ici encore quelques jours<c type="kk">/</c> expédies en je te prie une partie <hi rend="italics">de suite</hi><c type="kp">_</c>– si toutefois je pars de ces jours ci – ce que j’espère – tu peux bien la garder à Paris.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Ecris moi de ces jours ci dans tous les cas; j’espère que tu auras reçu les toiles en bon ordre. j’en ai fait encore une d’un coin de verdure qui me parait avoir quelque fraîcheur.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> J’ai aussi essayé une copie du bon Samaritain de Delacroix.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Je crois d’après une note dans le Figaro que le père Quost doit avoir un tableau rudement bien au salon.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Bien des chôses à ta femme, je me fais une fête de faire enfin sa connaissance et bonne poignée de main en pensee<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">t. à t<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">Once again I’m writing to you to say that I’m staying well, yet I feel a little worn out by this long crisis, and I dare believe that the planned move will refresh my ideas more.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">I think that it’ll be best for me to go myself to see this <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">doctor</rs> in the country as soon as possible; then we can soon decide if I’m going to lodge with him or temporarily at the inn; and thus we’ll avoid an over-long stay in Paris, a thing that I would fear. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">You remember that 6 months ago I told you after a crisis that if it happened again I would ask you to let me move?<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> We’re at that point – although I don’t feel capable of passing judgement on the way they have of dealing with the patients here – it’s enough that I feel that what remains to me of reason and capacity for work is absolutely in danger. While, on the contrary, I’m confident that I can prove to this doctor you speak of that I still know how to work logically, and he’ll treat me accordingly, and since he likes painting there’s sufficient chance that a solid friendship will result from it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I don’t think <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> will oppose a very prompt departure. Besides, I tell myself that the pleasure of spending a few days with you will do me a lot of good. And from that moment on we can really count on a period of relative health. So don’t delay in taking the necessary steps so that this doesn’t drag on. 
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">Once I’m there I can send for my bed, which is in Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">Besides, I would move anyway, preferring to be in an asylum where the patients worked to this awful idleness here, which really seems to me quite simply a crime. Anyway, you’ll tell me that this is seen more or less everywhere, and that there’s even plenty of it in Paris. Whatever the case, I hope that we’ll see each other again very soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">The etchings you sent me<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> are really beautiful. Opposite this I’ve scribbled a croquis after a painting I’ve done of three figures which are in the background of the Lazarus etching.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">The dead man and his two sisters. The cave and the corpse are violet, yellow, white. The woman who is taking the handkerchief from the resurrected man’s face has a green dress and orange hair, the other has black hair and a striped garment. Green and pink. Behind a countryside, blue hills, a yellow rising sun. The combination of colours would thus itself speak of the same thing expressed by the chiaroscuro of the etching. 
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">If I were still to have at my disposal the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">model</rs> who posed for the Berceuse<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">other</rs> whose portrait you’ve just received after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> then certainly I’d try to execute it in a large size, this canvas, the personalities being what I would have dreamed of as characters. But leaving aside subjects of this kind, there will still remain the study from life of peasants and landscapes when I’m back in the north.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">As regards the order for colours.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Should I remain here for another few days, please send off part of it <hi rend="italics">at once</hi>. If, however, I leave in the next few days – which I hope – you can keep it in Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">In any event, write to me in the next few days; I hope that you’ll have received the canvases in good order. I’ve done another one of a nook of greenery which seems to me to have some freshness.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> I’ve also attempted a copy of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>’s Good Samaritan.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I think from a note in Le Figaro that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1282"><hi rend="italics">père</hi> Quost</rs> must have a darned good painting in the Salon.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Warm regards to your <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">wife</rs>, I’m very much looking forward to making her acquaintance at last, and good handshake in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent wrote to Theo on 29 April and on or about 1 May (<ref target="let863.xml">863</ref> and <ref target="let865.xml">865</ref>). In the present letter he says: ‘Once again I’m writing to you’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>), and asks Theo: ‘In any event, write to me in the next few days’ <ref target="#l-79">(ll. 79-80)</ref>. This suggests that Theo’s letter of 3 May (<ref target="let867.xml">letter 867</ref>) had not yet arrived in Saint-Rémy – their letters probably crossed. Because Vincent again mentions the Rembrandt etchings he received, the present letter follows upon <ref target="let865.xml">letter 865</ref>, in which he thanks Theo for sending them. We have therefore dated this letter to about Friday, 2 May 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Fourth attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let857.xml">(857)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Vincent considers settling in Auvers and putting himself in the care of Dr Gachet <ref target="let808.xml">(808)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Seventh consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let863.xml">(863)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written this in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">letter 805</ref> of about 20 September 1889, some two months after his first attack in Saint-Rémy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>When he left Arles in May 1889, Van Gogh had stored his furniture at <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">Joseph and Marie Ginoux</rs>’s Café de la Gare.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>For these etchings by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let865.xml">see letter 865</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The raising of Lazarus</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">(after Rembrandt) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_225">F - / JH 1973</rs>) was made after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2900">F 677 / JH 1972</rs>. For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s etching, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let865.xml#n-3">see letter 865, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            


<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">Augustine Roulin</rs> was the model for the five versions of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi>: <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2762">F 504 / JH 1655</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2773">F 505 / JH 1669</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2774">F 506 / JH 1670</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2776">F 507 / JH 1672</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

      
<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Marie Ginoux</rs> was portrayed by <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> in his drawing <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Madame Ginoux (study for ‘Night café, Arles’)</hi>, 1888 (Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco. Memorial gift from Dr T. Edward and Tullah Hanley, Bradford Pennsylvania). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_97">Ill. 97</rs>. Gauguin’s drawing came into the possession of Theo and was sold in 1910 (see <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 150). Van Gogh had made five paintings after it, four of which are still known: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2891">F 540 / JH 1892</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2892">F 541 / JH 1893</rs>, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2893">F 542 / JH 1894</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2894">F 543 / JH 1895</rs>. Regarding this consignment, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let863.xml#n-8">see letter 863, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let863.xml">Letter 863</ref> contained an order for paint, brushes and canvas.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Meadow in the garden of the asylum </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2902">F 672 / JH 1975</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The Good Samaritan (after Delacroix) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2901">F 633 / JH 1974</rs>). Van Gogh had planned to paint this canvas as early as September 1889, and mentioned his intention again in February (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">see letters 805</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let854.xml">854</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            


<p>Albert Wolff wrote in his article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_582">Le Salon</ref>’, published in <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Le Figaro</hi> 36 (30 April 1890), 3rd series, pp. 1-3, about the work of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1282">Quost</rs>: ‘Mr Quost paints flowers with virtuosity, in the open air, in bright daylight, all in green and all in yellow’ (M. Quost peint avec virtuosité des fleurs en plein air, en pleine lumière, en plein vert et en plein jaune) (p. 2). The painting in question is <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Easter flowers</hi> (Roubaix, Musée d’Art et d’Industrie). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_324">Ill. 324</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    