<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Auvers-sur-Oise, Tuesday, 3 June 1890. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let877"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b687 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>877</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>638</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>881</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-06-03">Tuesday, 3 June 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0687" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0687" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000935_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher Theo,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">déjà depuis plusieurs jours j’aurais désiré t’écrire à tête reposée mais ai été absorbé par le travail. Ce matin arrive ta lettre de laquelle je te remercie et du billet de 50 fr. qu’elle contenait<c type="kp">_</c> Oui je crois que pour bien des chôses il serait bien que nous fussions encore ensemble tous ici pour une huitaine de tes vacances<c type="kk">/</c> si plus longtemps n’est pas possible. Je pense souvent à toi<c type="kk">/</c> à Jo et au petit, et je vois que les enfants ici au grand air sain ont l’air de bien se porter<c type="kp">_</c> Et pourtant c’est dejà ici aussi difficile assez de les élever<c type="kk">/</c> à plus forte raison est ce plus ou moins terrible à de certains moments de les garder sains &amp; saufs à Paris dans un quatrième étage. Mais enfin il faut prendre les chôses comme elles sont. M. Gachet dit qu’il faut que père et mère se nourrissent bien naturellement<c type="kk">/</c> il parle de prendre 2 litres de biere par jour &amp;c.<c type="kk">/</c> dans ces mesures-là. Mais tu feras certes avec plaisir plus ample connaissance avec lui et il y compte déjà<c type="kk">/</c> en parle toutes les fois que je le vois<c type="kk">/</c> que vous tous viendrez. Il me parait certes aussi malade et ahuri que toi ou moi et il est plus agé et il a perdu il y a quelques années sa femme<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> mais il est très médecin et son métier et sa foi le tiennent pourtant. Nous sommes déjà très amis et par hasard il a connu encore Brias de Montpellier<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> et a les mêmes idées sur lui que j’ai<c type="kk">/</c> que c’est quelqu’un d’important dans l’histoire de l’art moderne. Je travaille à son portrait </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">la tête avec une casquette blanche<c type="kk">/</c> très blonde<c type="kk">/</c> très claire<c type="kk">/</c> les mains aussi à carnation claire<c type="kk">/</c> un frac bleu et un fond bleu cobalt<c type="kk">/</c> appuyé sur une table rouge sur laquelle un livre jaune et une plante de digitale à fleurs pourpres.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Cela est dans le même sentiment que le portrait de moi que j’ai pris lorsque je suis parti pour ici.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">M. Gachet est absolument <hi rend="italics">fanatique</hi> pour ce portrait et veut que j’en fasse un de lui si je peux<c type="kk">/</c> absolument comme cela<c type="kk">/</c> ce que je désire faire aussi. Il est maintenant aussi arrivé à comprendre le dernier portrait d’Arlésienne dont tu en as un en rose<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – il revient<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’il vient voir les etudes<c type="kk">/</c> tout le temps sur ces deux portraits et il les admet en plein<c type="kk">/</c> mais en plein tels qu’ils sont. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>J’espère t’envoyer un portrait de lui bientôt<c type="kp">_</c> Puis j’ai peint chez lui deux études que je lui ai données semaine passee<c type="kp">_</c> Un aloes avec des soucis et des cyprès<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> puis Dimanche dernier des roses blanches<c type="kk">/</c> de la vigne et une figure blanche là-dedans<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">Je ferai très probablement aussi le portrait de sa fille qui a 19 ans<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> et avec laquelle je me figure aisément que Jo sera vite amies.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Alors je m’en fais une fête de faire les portraits de vous tous en plein air<c type="kk">/</c> le tien<c type="kk">/</c> celui de Jo et celui du petit.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">J’ai encore rien trouvé d’intéressant en fait d’atelier possible et il faudra pourtant prendre une chambre pour y mettre les toiles qui sont de trop chez toi et qui sont chez Tanguy<c type="kp">_</c> Car il faut encore beaucoup y retoucher. Mais enfin je vis au jour le jour – il fait si beau. Et la santé va bien<c type="kk">/</c> je me couche à 9 heures mais me lève à 5 h<c type="kp">_</c> la pluspart du temps.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">J’ai esperance qu’il ne sera pas desagréable de se retrouver après une longue absence<c type="kp">_</c> Et j’espère aussi que cela continuera que je me sens bien plus sûr de mon pinceau qu’avant d’aller à Arles. Et M. Gachet dit qu’il trouverait fort improbable que cela revienne et que cela va tout à fait bien. Mais lui aussi se plaint amèrement de l’etat de choses partout dans les villages où il est venu le moindre etranger<c type="kk">/</c> que la vie y devient si horriblement chère. Il dit qu’il s’étonne que les gens où je suis me logent et nourrissent pour cela et que j’ai encore<c type="kk">/</c> relativement à d’autres qui sont venus et qu’il a connus<c type="kk">/</c> de la chance. Que si tu viens et Jo et le petit vous ne pourrez faire mieux que de loger à cette même auberge. Maintenant rien<c type="kk">/</c> absolument rien ne nous retient ici que Gachet – mais celui là restera un ami à ce que je presumerais<c type="kp">_</c> Je sens que chez lui je peux faire un tableau pas trop mal toutes les fois que j’y vais et il continuera bien de m’inviter à diner tous les dimanches ou lundis<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Mais jusqu’à present<c type="kk">/</c> si c’est agréable d’y faire un tableau c’est une corvée pour moi d’y diner et déjeûner car l’excellent homme se donne du mal pour faire des diners où il y a 4 ou 5 plats<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui est abominable 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>pour lui comme pour moi car il n’a certes pas l’estomac fort<c type="kp">_</c> Ce qui m’a un peu retenu d’y trouver à redire c’est que je vois que lui cela lui rappelle les jours d’autrefois où l’on faisait des diners de famille qu’enfin nous connaissons bien aussi<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Mais l’idée moderne de manger un, tout au plus deux plats est pourtant certes un progrès et un sain retour à l’antiquité vraie.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">Enfin le père Gachet est beaucoup mais beaucoup comme toi et moi. J’ai lu avec plaisir dans ta lettre que M. Peyron a demandé de mes nouvelles en t’ecrivant<c type="kp">_</c> Je vais lui écrire que cela va bien ce soir même car il était très bon pour moi et je ne l’oublierai certes pas. Desmoulins<c type="kk">/</c> celui qui a des tableaux japonais au Champ de Mars<c type="kk">/</c> est revenu ici et j’espère bien le rencontrer<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Qu’est ce qu’a dit Gauguin du dernier portrait d’arlésienne qui est fait sur son dessin.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Tu finiras par voir je croirais<c type="kk">/</c> que cela est une des choses les moins mauvaises que j’ai faites. Gachet a un Guillaumin<c type="kk">/</c> femme nue sur un lit<c type="kk">/</c> que je trouve fort belle<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> il a aussi un très ancien portrait de Guillaumin par lui<c type="kk">/</c> très different du nôtre, noir mais intéressant<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">Mais sa maison tu verras c’est plein<c type="kk">/</c> plein comme un marchand d’antiquités<c type="kk">/</c> de chôses pas toujours intéressantes<c type="kk">/</c> c’est même terrible.– Mais dans tout cela il y a ceci de bon que pour arranger des fleurs ou des natures mortes il y aurait toujours de quoi. J’ai fait ces études pour lui<c type="kk">/</c> pour lui montrer que si ce n’est pas un cas où on lui payerait en argent nous le dédomagerons pourtant toujours de ce qu’il ferait pour nous.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Connais tu une eauforte de Bracquemond<c type="kk">/</c> le portrait de Comte<c type="kk">/</c> c’est un chef d’oeuvre.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.15" n="15">Il me faudrait aussitôt que possible 12 tubes blanc de zinc de Tasset et 2 tubes moyen laque geranium.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.16" n="16">Puis aussitôt que tu pourrais me les envoyer je tiendrais absolument à copier encore une fois toutes les Etudes au fusain de Bargue<c type="kk">/</c> tu sais les figures nues. Je peux les dessiner relativement vite<c type="kk">/</c> mettons dans un mois les 60 feuilles qu’il y a<c type="kk">/</c> donc tu enverrais un exemplaire en commission<c type="kk">/</c> je ferais en sorte de ne pas les tacher ou salir.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Si je négligeais d’étudier encore les proportions et le nu je me trouverais mal pris plus tard. Que cela ne te paraisse pas absurde ou inutile<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.17" n="17">Gachet m’a dit aussi que si je voulais lui faire un grand plaisir il désirerait que je refasse pour lui la copie de la pieta de Delacroix qu’il a regardé très longtemps.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Dans la suite probablement il me donnera un coup de main pour les modèles, je sens qu’il nous comprendra tout à fait et qu’il travaillera avec toi et moi sans arriere pensée<c type="kk">/</c> pour l’amour de l’art pour l’art<c type="kk">/</c> de toute son intelligence. Et il me fera peutêtre bien avoir des portraits<c type="kp">_</c> Or pour avoir des clients pour les portraits il faut pouvoir en montrer differents que l’on a fait. Voilà tout ce que je vois de possibilité de placer quelque chôse. Mais pourtant<c type="kk">/</c> pourtant de certaines toiles un jour trouveront des amateurs. Je trouve seulement que tout le bruit qu’ont fait les grands prix payés dans les derniers temps pour des Millets &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> ont encore empiré l’etat de chôses quant à la chance qu’on a rien que de rentrer dans ses frais de peinture. C’est à avoir le vertige. Donc qu’y penserons nous, cela abrutirait. Mieux vaut encore peutêtre chercher un peu d’amitié et vivre au jour le jour. J’espère que le petit continuera à aller bien et vous deux également jusqu’au revoir<c type="kk">/</c> à bientot<c type="kk">/</c> je vous serre bien la main<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">For several days now I’d have liked to write to you with a rested mind, but have been absorbed in work. This morning your letter arrives, for which I thank you and for the 50-franc note it contained. Yes, I think that it would be good for many reasons that we were all together again here for a week of your holidays, if longer isn’t possible. I often think of you, Jo and the little one, and I see that the children here look well in the healthy fresh air. And yet it’s difficult enough to raise them, even here, all the more is it rather terrible sometimes to keep them safe and sound in Paris on a fourth floor. But anyway, one must take things as they are. Mr Gachet says that father and mother must feed themselves quite naturally, he talks of taking 2 litres of beer a day &amp;c., in those amounts. But you’ll certainly enjoy furthering your acquaintance with him, and he’s already counting on it, speaks of it every time I see him, that you’ll all come. He certainly appears to me as ill and confused as you or I, and he’s older and a few years ago he lost his wife,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but he’s very much a doctor, and his profession and his faith keep him going however. We’re already firm friends, and by chance he also knew Bruyas of Montpellier<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and has the same ideas on him as I have, that he’s someone important in the history of modern art. I’m working on his portrait</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">the head with a white cap, very fair, very light, the hands also in light carnation, a blue frock coat and a cobalt blue background, leaning on a red table on which are a yellow book and a foxglove plant with purple flowers.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> It’s in the same sentiment as the portrait of myself that I took when I left for here.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Mr Gachet is absolutely <hi rend="italics">fanatical</hi> about this portrait, and wants me to do one of him if I can, absolutely like that, which I also wish to do. He has now also come to understand the last portrait of the Arlésienne, one of which you have in pink<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> – he comes back all the time, when he comes to see the studies, to these two portraits and he accepts them fully, but fully as they are. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I hope to send you a portrait of him soon. Then I painted two studies at his house which I gave him last week. One aloes with marigolds and cypresses,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> then last Sunday white roses, vines and a white figure in it.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">I’ll very probably also do the portrait of his daughter, who is 19,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and with whom I can easily imagine Jo will quickly make friends.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">So I’m looking forward to doing the portraits of all of you in the open air, yours, Jo’s and the little one’s.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I still haven’t found anything interesting in the way of a possible studio, and yet I’ll have to take a room to put in the canvases which are surplus at your apartment and which are at Tanguy’s. For they still need a great deal of retouching. But anyway, I live from day to day – the weather is so fine. And my health is good, I go to bed at 9 o’clock but I get up at 5 o’clock most of the time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">I have hopes that it won’t be disagreeable to be together again after a long absence. And I also hope that I’ll continue to feel much surer of my brush than before I went to Arles. And Mr Gachet says that he would consider it highly improbable that it should recur, and that it’s going completely well. But he, too, complains bitterly of the state of things everywhere in the villages where the least foreigner has come, that life there becomes so horribly expensive. He says that he’s astonished that the people where I am lodge and feed me for that, and that I’m still fortunate, compared to others who have come and whom he’s known. That if you come, and Jo and the little one, you can’t do better than stay at this same inn. Now nothing, absolutely nothing keeps us here but Gachet – but the latter will remain a friend, I’d assume. I feel that at his place I can do not too bad a painting every time I go there, and he’ll certainly continue to invite me to dinner each Sunday or Monday.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">But up to now, however agreeable it is to do a painting there, it’s a chore for me to dine and lunch there for, the excellent man goes to the trouble of making dinners in which there are 4 or 5 courses, which is as abominable 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> for him as it is for me, for he certainly doesn’t have a strong stomach. What has held me back a little from saying something about it is that I see that, for him, it reminds him of the days of yore when people had family dinners, which anyway we too well know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">But the modern idea of eating one, at most two courses is, however, certainly progress, and a healthy return to true antiquity.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">Anyway <hi rend="italics">père</hi> Gachet is a lot, yes a lot like you and I. I was pleased to read in your letter that Mr Peyron asked for news of me when he wrote to you. I’m going to write to him this very evening that things are going well, for he was very kind to me and I’ll certainly not forget him. Dumoulin, the one who has Japanese paintings at the Champ de Mars, has come back here, and I very much hope to meet him.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">What did Gauguin say about the last portrait of the Arlésienne that’s done after his drawing?<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> You’ll end up seeing, I would think, that it’s one of the least bad things I’ve done. Gachet has a Guillaumin, naked woman on a bed, which I consider very beautiful,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> he also has a very old Guillaumin portrait by him, very different from ours, dark but interesting.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">But his house, you will see, is full, full like an antique dealer’s, of things that aren’t always interesting, it’s terrible, even. But in all of this there’s this good aspect, that there would always be what I need there for arranging flowers or still lifes. I’ve done studies for him, to show him that should he not be paid in money we’ll nevertheless still compensate him for what he does for us.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Do you know an etching by Bracquemond, the portrait of Comte, it’s a masterpiece.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">I’d also need as soon as possible 12 tubes zinc white from Tasset and 2 medium tubes geranium lake. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.17" n="17">Then as soon as you could send them I’d be absolutely set upon copying all of Bargue’s Etudes au fusain again, you know the nude figures. I can draw them quite quickly, let’s say the 60 sheets that there are in a month, so you might send a copy on loan, I’d make sure not to stain or dirty it.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> If I neglected to keep on studying proportions and the nude I’d find myself in a bad position later on. Don’t think this absurd or futile.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.18" n="18">Gachet also told me that if I wanted to give him great pleasure he would like me to redo for him the copy of Delacroix’s Pietà, which he gazed at for a long time.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Later he’ll probably give me a hand with the models, I feel that he’ll understand us completely, and that he’ll work with you and me without reservation, with all his intelligence, for the love of art for art’s sake. And he’ll perhaps have me do some portraits. Now to have clients for portraits one must be able to show different ones that one has done. That’s the only possibility I can see of placing something. But however, however, certain canvases will one day find collectors. Only I think that all the fuss created by the large prices paid lately for Millets &amp;c.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> has further worsened the state of things as regards the chance one has of merely recouping one’s painting expenses. It’s enough to make one dizzy. So why are we thinking about it, it would stupefy us. Better still, perhaps, to seek a little friendship and live from day to day. I hope that the little one will continue to be well, and you two also until we see each other again, more soon, I shake your hand firmly.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Van Gogh says that he received Theo’s letter ‘this morning’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>. That was <ref target="let876.xml">letter 876</ref> of 2 June. We have therefore dated the present letter to Tuesday, 3 June 1890. In <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914 Jo van Gogh-Bonger dated this letter to 4 June 1890; she possibly had a postmark to rely on, in which case the letter was sent a day after it was written.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Gachet was 62 years old. In 1868 he had married Blanche Elisa Castets, who had died on 25 May 1875 in Paris. See exhib. cat. Paris 1999, p. 19 (n. 15).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>In 1857-1858 Gachet had met the art collector Alfred Bruyas of Montpellier; in December 1888 Van Gogh had seen the Bruyas Collection. See exhib. cat. Paris 1999, p. 4, and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let726.xml">letter 726</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Doctor Gachet</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_227">F - / JH 2008</rs>) was made after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2916">F 753 / JH 2007</rs>. The sketch shows one book; Van Gogh would add another one in the painting.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2827">F 627 / JH 1772</rs>). That Van Gogh is referring to this portrait is apparent from the description in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let879.xml">letter 879</ref>. The portrait had been at Theo’s since September 1889 (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let805.xml">see letter 805</ref>), so Vincent must have taken it from there.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>There were four versions of this <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi>, made after a drawing by Gauguin (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-10">see n. 10</ref> below). The portrait ‘in pink’ which Theo had was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2894">F 543 / JH 1895</rs>. Of the other three, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2893">F 542 / JH 1894</rs> was intended for Gauguin (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let884.xml">see letter 884</ref>) and so still at Theo’s, so that the version Vincent took along to Auvers must have been <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2891">F 540 / JH 1892</rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2892">F 541 / JH 1893</rs>. Van Gogh speaks of ‘the last portrait of the Arlésienne’ to distinguish it from an earlier portrait, which was also at Theo’s: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’) </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2744">F 489 / JH 1625</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Doctor Gachet’s garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2913">F 755 / JH 1999</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marguerite Gachet in the garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2914">F 756 / JH 2005</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Marguerite Gachet was 20 years old. Van Gogh painted her portrait (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2932">F 772 / JH 2048</rs>) at the end of June (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let893.xml">see letter 893</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For Louis Dumoulin, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let874.xml#n-3">see letter 874, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            
      
<p>For Gauguin’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_97">Madame Ginoux (study for ‘Night café, Arles’)</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let866.xml#n-6">see letter 866, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Armand Guillaumin, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Nude woman on a bed</hi>, c. 1877 (Paris, Musée d’Orsay). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_145">Ill. 145</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Armand Guillaumin, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi>, c. 1870-1875 (Paris, Musée d’Orsay). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_147">Ill. 147</rs>. For the self-portrait of Guillaumin in Theo’s possession, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let800.xml#n-21">see letter 800, n. 21.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Félix Bracquemond, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Auguste Comte (after Joseph Guichard)</hi>, 1851 (Paris, BNF, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_626">Ill. 626</rs>. This etching came from Gachet’s collection. See exhib. cat. Paris 1999, p. 179.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>For Bargue’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_202">Exercices au fusain</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let156.xml#n-12">see letter 156, n. 12.</ref> Vincent had already asked Theo to send it in <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let874.xml">letter 874</ref>. For the copies Van Gogh drew after Bargue’s sheets in Auvers, see cat. Amsterdam 2007, pp. 479-487, cat. nos. 483-485.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Pietà (after Delacroix)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2830">F 630 / JH 1775</rs>). For Nanteuil’s lithograph after Delacroix, on which Van Gogh based his painting, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let686.xml#n-3">see letter 686, n. 3.</ref> As far as we know, Van Gogh did not make a copy for Gachet.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>This remark probably refers to the fact that Millet’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1697">The angelus</rs></hi> had been sold in January 1890 for the huge sum of 800,000 francs to the department store magnate Alfred Chauchard. He bought the painting from the American Arts Association, which had acquired it in September 1889 at the Secrétan sale. See exhib. cat. Boston 1984, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">ix</hi> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let785.xml#n-8">letter 785, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    