<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Willemien van Gogh. Auvers-sur-Oise, Thursday, 5 June 1890. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let879"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b722 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>879</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>W22</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>883</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-06-05">Thursday, 5 June 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Willemien van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0722" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0722" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000977_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Ma chère soeur,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">depuis longtemps j’aurais dû répondre à tes deux lettres que j’ai encore reçu à S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy mais le voyage<c type="kk">/</c> le travail et un tas d’emotions nouvelles jusqu’aujourd’hui me le faisaient remettre du jour au lendemain. Cela m’a beaucoup intéressé que tu aies soigné des malades à l’hôpital Wallon<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> certes c’est ainsi que l’on apprend un tas de chôses<c type="kk">/</c> des meilleures &amp; des plus nécessaires que l’on puisse apprendre et moi je le regrette que je sache rien<c type="kk">/</c> en tout cas pas assez<c type="kk">/</c> de tout cela.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">C’était pour moi un grand bonheur de revoir Theo<c type="kk">/</c> de faire connaissance avec Jo et le petit. Theo toussait davantage que lorsque je l’ai quitté il y a plus de 2 ans mais en causant et lorsqu’on le voyait de près pourtant je le trouvais certes<c type="kk">/</c> tout bien compté<c type="kk">/</c> plutot changé à son avantage, et Jo est pleine et de bon sens et de bonne volonté. Le petit n’est pas malingre mais pas fort aussi<c type="kp">_</c>– C’est un bon systeme que la femme accouche à la campagne et y passe avec le petit les premiers mois si l’on reste<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> dans une grande ville<c type="kp">_</c> Mais voilà<c type="kk">/</c> pour la première fois surtout l’accouchement étant redoutable ils n’ont certes pas pu faire mieux ou autrement qu’ils n’aient fait. J’espère qu’ils viendront ici à Auvers pour quelques jours bientôt.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Pour moi le voyage &amp; le reste jusqu’ici se sont bien passés et de revenir dans le nord me distrait beaucoup. Puis j’ai trouvé dans le D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gachet un ami tout fait et quelque chôse comme un nouveau frère serait – tellement nous nous ressemblons physiquement et 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>moralement aussi. Il est très nerveux et beaucoup bizarre luimême et a rendu aux artistes de la nouvelle école beaucoup d’amitiés &amp; services<c type="kk">/</c> tant que c’était dans son pouvoir. J’ai fait son portrait l’autre jour<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> et vais peindre aussi celui de sa fille qui a 19 ans<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Il a perdu sa femme il y a quelques années ce qui a contribué à beaucoup le casser.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Nous avons été amis pour ainsi dire tout de suite et j’irai passer toutes les semaines une ou deux journées chez lui à travailler dans son jardin dont j’ai déjà peint deux études<c type="kk">/</c> l’une avec des plantes du midi<c type="kk">/</c> aloès<c type="kk">/</c> cyprès<c type="kk">/</c> soucis<c type="kk">/</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> l’autre des roses blanches, de la vigne et une figure.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> puis un bouquet de renoncules.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Avec cela j’ai un plus grand tableau de l’église du village<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – un effet où le bâtiment parait violacé contre un ciel d’un bleu profond &amp; simple de cobalt pur<c type="kk">/</c> les fenêtres à vitraux paraissent comme des taches bleu d’outremer<c type="kk">/</c> le toit est violet et en partie orangé. Sur l’avant plan un peu de verdure fleurie et du sable ensoleillé rose<c type="kp">_</c> C’est encore presque la même chôse que les études que je fis à Nunen de la vieille tour et du cimetière<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Seulement à présent la couleur est probablement plus expressive<c type="kk">/</c> plus somptueuse<c type="kp">_</c> Mais dans les derniers temps à S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Remy j’ai encore travaillé comme un enragé<c type="kk">/</c> surtout à des bouquets de fleurs<c type="kp">_</c> Roses et Iris violets<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’ai rapporté pour le petit de Theo et Jo un tableau assez grand – qu’ils ont accroché au-dessus du piano – de fleurs d’amandiers blanches – de grandes branches sur un fond bleu céleste<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> et ils ont dans leur appartement aussi un nouveau portrait d’Arlésienne<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Mon ami le D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gachet est <hi rend="italics">décidemment</hi> <hi rend="italics">enthousiaste</hi> de ce dernier portrait d’arlésienne dont moi aussi j’ai un exemplaire pour moi<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> et d’un portrait de moi<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> et cela m’a fait plaisir puisqu’il me poussera à faire de la figure et j’espère me trouvera quelques modèles intéressants à faire. Ce qui me passionne le plus<c type="kk">/</c> beaucoup beaucoup davantage que tout le reste dans mon métier – c’est le portrait<c type="kk">/</c> le portrait moderne. Je le cherche par la couleur et ne suis certes pas seul à le chercher dans cette voie. Je <hi>voudrais</hi><c type="kk">/</c> tu vois je suis loin de dire que je puisse faire tout cela mais enfin j’y tends, je <hi rend="italics">voudrais</hi> faire des portraits qui un siecle plus tard aux gens d’alors aparussent comme des apparitions. Donc je ne nous cherche pas à faire par la ressemblance photographique mais par nos expressions passionnées<c type="kk">/</c> employant comme moyen d’expression et d’exaltation du caractère notre science et goût moderne de la couleur. Ainsi le portrait du D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gachet vous montre un visage couleur d’une brique surchauffé et hâlé de soleil<c type="kk">/</c> avec la chevelure rousse<c type="kk">/</c> une casquette blanche<c type="kk">/</c> dans un entourage de paysage<c type="kk">/</c> fond de collines bleu<c type="kk">/</c> son vêtement est bleu d’outremer<c type="kk">/</c> cela fait ressortir le visage et le palit malgré qu’il soit couleur brique. les mains<c type="kk">/</c> des mains d’accoucheur<c type="kk">/</c> sont plus pâles que le visage.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">devant lui sur une table de jardin rouge des romans jaunes et une fleur de digitale pourpre sombre. Mon portrait à moi est presqu’aussi ainsi mais le bleu est un bleu fin du midi et le vêtement est lilas clair. le portrait d’arlésienne est d’un ton de chair incolore et mate<c type="kk">/</c> les yeux calmes et fort simples<c type="kk">/</c> le vetement noir<c type="kk">/</c> le fond rose et elle est accoudée à une table verte avec des livres verts. Mais dans l’exemplaire qu’en a Theo, le vetement est rose<c type="kk">/</c> le fond blanc jaune et le devant du corsage ouvert de la mouseline d’un blanc qui tourne sur le vert. Dans toute ces couleurs claires<c type="kk">/</c> les cheveux seuls<c type="kk">/</c> les cils et les yeux font des taches noires.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Je ne reussis pas à en faire un bon croquis.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Il y a de Puvis de Chavannes à l’expo<c type="shy">-</c>sition un tableau superbe.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">les personnages sont vêtus de couleurs claires et on ne sait pas si c’est des costumes de maintenant ou bien des vêtements de l’antiquité; deux femmes causent (toujours en longues robes simples) d’un côté<c type="kk">/</c> des hommes artistes de l’autre<c type="kk">/</c> au centre une femme<c type="kk">/</c> son enfant dans les bras<c type="kk">/</c> cueille une fleur sur un pommier en fleur<c type="kp">_</c> une figure sera bleu myosotys<c type="kk">/</c> une autre citron clair<c type="kk">/</c> une autre rose tendre<c type="kk">/</c> une autre blanche<c type="kk">/</c> une autre violette<c type="kk">/</c> le terrain une prairie piquée de fleurettes blanches et jaunes<c type="kp">_</c> Des lointains bleus avec une ville blanche et un fleuve. Toute l’humanité<c type="kk">/</c> toute la nature simplifiée mais comme elle pourrait être si elle ne l’est pas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">Cette description ne dit rien – mais en voyant le tableau<c type="kk">/</c> en le regardant longtemps on croirait assister à une renaissance fatale mais bienveillante de toutes chôses auquelles on aurait crues<c type="kk">/</c> qu’on aurait désirées<c type="kk">/</c> une rencontre étrange et heureuse des antiquités fort lointaines avec la crue modernité<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.11" n="11">J’ai revu aussi avec plaisir André Bonger qui avait l’air fort et calme et raisonnait ma foi avec une grande justesse sur des choses artistiques<c type="kk">/</c> cela me faisait grand plaisir qu’il etait venu les jours que j’etais à Paris<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.12" n="12">Merci encore de tes lettres<c type="kk">/</c> à bientot<c type="kk">/</c> je t’embrasse en pensée<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.13" n="13">t. à t.</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.14" n="14">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">I ought to have replied to your two letters long since, which I received while still in St-Rémy, but the journey, work and a host of new emotions up to today made me put it off from one day to the next. It interested me very much that you’ve cared for patients at the Walloon hospital,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> that’s certainly how one learns heaps of things, the best and most necessary that one can learn, and I myself regret that I know nothing, in any event not enough, about all that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It was a great happiness for me to see Theo again, to meet <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">little one</rs>. Theo was coughing more than when I left him more than 2 years ago, but while talking and when I saw him at close hand, however, I considered him certainly rather changed for the better, all things considered, and Jo is full of both good sense and good will. The little one is not sickly, but not strong either. It’s a good system that if one lives in a large town the woman gives birth in the country and spends the first months there with the little one. But there you are, for the first time especially, as the birth is frightening, they certainly couldn’t have done better or otherwise than they did. I hope that they’ll come here to Auvers for a few days soon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">For me the journey and the rest up to now have gone well, and coming back to the north distracts me a lot. Then I’ve found in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs> a ready-made friend and something like a new brother would be – so much do we resemble each other physically, and 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> morally too. He’s very nervous and very bizarre himself, and has rendered much friendship and many services to the artists of the new school, as much as was in his power. I did his portrait the other day<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and am also going to paint that of his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_391">daughter</rs>, who is 19.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> He lost his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_390">wife</rs> a few years ago, which has greatly contributed to breaking him.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> We were friends, so to speak, immediately, and I’ll go and spend one or two days a week at his house working in his garden, of which I’ve already painted two studies, one with plants from the south, aloes, cypresses, marigolds,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> the other with white roses, vines and a figure.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Then a bouquet of buttercups.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> With that I have a larger painting of the village church<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> – an effect in which the building appears purplish against a sky of a deep and simple blue of pure cobalt, the stained-glass windows look like ultramarine blue patches, the roof is violet and in part orange. In the foreground a little flowery greenery and some sunny pink sand. It’s again almost the same thing as the studies I did in Nuenen of the old tower and the cemetery.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Only now the colour is probably more expressive, more sumptuous. But in the last few days at St-Rémy I worked like a man in a frenzy, especially on bouquets of flowers. Roses and violet Irises.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">For Theo and Jo’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">little one</rs> I brought back a rather large painting — which they’ve hung above the piano – white almond blossoms – big branches on a sky-blue background,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> and in their apartment they also have a new portrait of an <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> My friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs> is <hi rend="italics">decidedly enthusiastic</hi> about this latest portrait of the Arlésienne, one of which I also have myself,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and about a portrait of myself,<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> and that gave me pleasure, since he’ll drive me to do figure work and I hope he’ll find me a few interesting models to do. What I’m most passionate about, much much more than all the rest in my profession – is the portrait, the modern portrait. I seek it by way of colour, and am certainly not alone in seeking it in this way. I <hi>would like</hi>, you see I’m far from saying that I can do all this, but anyway I’m aiming at it, I <hi rend="italics">would like</hi> to do portraits which would look like apparitions to people a century later. So I don’t try to do us by photographic resemblance but by our passionate expressions, using as a means of expression and intensification of the character our science and modern taste for colour. Thus the portrait of Dr Gachet shows you a face the colour of an overheated and sun-scorched brick, with a reddish head of hair, a white cap, in surroundings of landscape, blue background of hills, his suit is ultramarine blue, this brings out the face and makes it paler, despite the fact that it’s brick-coloured. The hands, hands of an obstetrician, are paler than the face.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Before him on a red garden table yellow novels and a dark purple foxglove flower. My portrait of myself is almost like this too, but the blue is a fine southern blue and the suit is light lilac. The portrait of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs> is of a colourless and matt flesh tone, the eyes calm and very simple, the clothing black, the background pink, and she’s leaning her elbow on a green table with green books. But in the one Theo has, the clothing is pink, the background yellow-white, and the front of the open bodice is of white muslin, verging on the green. In all these bright colours, only the hair, the eyelashes and the eyes form dark patches.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">I can’t manage to do a good croquis of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">At the exhibition there’s a superb painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.10" n="10"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11">The figures are dressed in bright colours and one doesn’t know if they’re costumes from now or clothes from antiquity; two women are talking (also in long, simple dresses). On one side, artistic-looking men on the other, in the centre a woman, her child in her arms, is picking a flower from an apple tree in blossom. One figure will be forget-me-not blue, another bright lemon, another soft pink, another white, another violet, the ground a meadow dotted with little white and yellow flowers. Blue distance with a white town and a river. All humanity, all nature simplified, but how it could be, if it isn’t already.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">This description doesn’t say anything – but by seeing the painting, by looking at it for a long time one would think one was present at an inevitable but benevolent rebirth of all things that one might have believed in, that one might have desired, a strange and happy meeting of the very distant days of antiquity with raw modernity.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.13" n="13">I was also pleased to see<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282"> André Bonger</rs> again; he looked strong and calm, and my word reasoned with great accuracy on artistic things, it pleased me very much that he’d come during the days when I was in Paris.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.14" n="14">Thank you again for your letters, more soon, I kiss you in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.15" n="15">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">For the date assigned to this letter, <ref target="let878.xml">see letter 878</ref>, <hi rend="italics">Date</hi>. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Enclosed with <ref target="let878.xml">letter 878</ref> to Mrs van Gogh; see the <hi rend="italics">Additional details</hi> to that letter. An earlier version of this letter is RM19, which was never sent.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
      
<p>Regarding the ‘Hôpital Wallon’, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let878.xml#n-2">see letter 878, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘habite’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Doctor Gachet </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2916">F 753 / JH 2007</rs>). Van Gogh describes this portrait later on in the letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_391">Marguerite Gachet</rs> was 20 years old.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Paul Gachet’s wife, <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_390">Blanche Elisa Castets</rs>, had died in 1875.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Doctor Gachet’s garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2913">F 755 / JH 1999</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marguerite Gachet in the garden</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2914">F 756 / JH 2005</rs>). Van Gogh was to paint <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_391">her</rs> portrait at the end of June: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marguerite Gachet at the piano</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2932">F 772 / JH 2048</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This flower painting is possibly <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Roses and anemones in a vase </hi>(<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2931">F 764 / JH 2045</rs>), which probably displays turban buttercups and not anemones. See exhib. cat. Paris 1999, p. 82.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Church at Auvers</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2915">F 789 / JH 2006</rs>). It measures 94 x 74 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>Van Gogh made several paintings of this subject, but the comparison must refer primarily to <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Roses</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2903">F 681 / JH 1976</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Roses</hi> <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2906">F 682 / JH 1979</rs>), <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irises in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2904">F 678 / JH 1977</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Irises in a vase</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2905">F 680 / JH 1978</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Almond blossom</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2890">F 671 / JH 1891</rs>). It measures 73.5 x 92 cm. Vincent had sent the painting to Theo on 29 April; see letters <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let863.xml">863</ref> and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let867.xml">867</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>From the description and the letter sketch occurring later in the letter, it emerges that Theo had <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2894">F 543 / JH 1895</rs>), after which Van Gogh made the letter sketch (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_228">F - / JH 1896</rs>) from memory.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>The version of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> that Vincent took with him to Auvers and that <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Gachet</rs> therefore knew was <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2891">F 540 / JH 1892</rs> or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2892">F 541 / JH 1893</rs>. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let877.xml#n-5">See letter 877, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>It emerges later on in the letter that this was <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2827">F 627 / JH 1772</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Pierre Puvis de Chavannes</rs>, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Inter Artes et Naturam </hi>(Between art and nature), 1890 (Musée des Beaux-Arts de Rouen). <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_316">Ill. 316.</rs> A smaller version is now in the Metropolitan Museum in New York. Van Gogh had seen the large painting at the exhibition of the Société Nationale des Beaux-Arts. See exhib. cat. Paris 1890-4, p. <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">xxii</hi>, no. 718, and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="RM21.xml">RM21</ref>. Van Gogh made the letter sketch (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_229">F - / JH -</rs>) from memory.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries Bonger</rs> had met Vincent on the evening of Sunday, 18 May. He wrote about it on 21 May 1890 to his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs>: ‘Vincent the painter has already left. I spoke to him Sunday evening. He looks better than ever, and has become fat. He spoke very normally and cheerfully. I believe it’s good for him to be out of that asylum’ (FR b1852).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    