<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Tuesday, 22 July 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let901"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b770 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>901</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>906</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-07-22">Tuesday, 22 July 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0770" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_01_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0770" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001039_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">le 22 Juillet 1890</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">Jo m’envoit de Hollande ta lettre qui nous avait suivie &amp; je la lis un peu avec surprise. Où as tu vu ces violentes querelles domestiques?<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Que nous étions très fatigués par des préoccupations ininterrompues au sujet de l’avenir de nous tous, oui; qu’avec cette affaire vis à vis de la maison<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> je ne savais pas très bien ce qui était mon intérêt, oui, mais vraiment je ne vois pas les querelles domestiques intenses dont tu parles. Est ce la discussion avec Dries? Certes je lui avais voulu voir un peu plus d’audace à entreprendre 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>quelque chose,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> mais il est comme cela et ce n’est pas une raison de rompre avec lui. Est ce peut être, mais je ne peu pas croire cela, que tu considère comme querelle domestique intense que Jo te demandait de ne pas mettre le Prevost<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> à un endroit où tu voulais l’accrocher. Elle n’a pas pensée te blesser avec cela &amp; certes aurait préféré que tu l’y laisses que de te fâcher pour cela. Son enfant la préoccupe de trop pour qu’elle aie beaucoup le temps de penser à la peinture &amp; quoiqu’elle voit déjà bien mieux que dans le temps elle ne voit pas toujours de suite ce qu’il y a dedans. Non si c’était cette bagatelle-là je te dirais à toi de la cesser car cela n’en vaut pas la peine que l’on s’en occupe. J’espère mon cher Vincent que ta santé va bien &amp; comme tu disais que tu écris difficilement &amp; ne me parle pas de ton travail<c type="kk">/</c> j’ai un peu crainte qu’il y a quelque chose qui te gène ou qui ne 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>marche pas. Dans ce cas va un peu voir le D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gachet<c type="kk">/</c> il te donnera peut être quelque chose qui te remette bien. Donne moi de tes nouvelles aussitôt que possible.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Mardi dernier j’ai conduit Jo &amp; l’enfant jusqu’à Leiden et j’y suis rester jusqu’à Jeudi. La mère est bien un peu vieillie, mais elle était si content de voir son petit fils &amp; c’était amusant de voir comme elle le prenait &amp; le rendait content<c type="kp">_</c> Wil aussi allait bien &amp; était très gentile pour nous. Jo est rester chez eux encore un jour après mon départ &amp; alors est parti à Amsterdam où elle est encore<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’espère que tout ce monde s’efforce un peu à ne pas la fatiguer mais qu’on lui laisse un peu de repos, elle en avait tant besoin car c’est une corvée je t’assure. Malheureusement, comme içi le temps n’y est pas stabile<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> de sorte qu’elle ne peut pas être beaucoup en plein air &amp; l’enfant 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>non plus. Je pense qu’il se pourrait bien qu’elle désire de revenir plus vite que nous avions fait le projet, mais c’est bon d’un autre côté que sa maison içi lui plaise plus que celle de ses parents. Je serai très content quand elle sera de retour car la maison est si déserte! et le petit me manque aussi. Notre vie, justement par cet enfant est si étroitement liée que tu ne dois pas avoir peur qu’une petite différance, si tu en a vue une<c type="kk">/</c> puisse occasionner un écartement qui rendra difficile une conciliation. Ne penses donc plus à cela. Moi le voyage en Hollande m’a fait beaucoup de bien &amp; m’a fait beaucoup me reposer, dont j’avais bien besoin.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Espérons que la santé à nous tous puisse s’améliorer, car la santé c’est beaucoup. Çi inclus je t’envois f<hi rend="super">r</hi> 50 – écris moi vite &amp; crois moi ton frère qui t’aime<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">22 July 1890</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">From Holland <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> sent me your letter, which had followed us, and I read it with some surprise. Where did you see these violent domestic quarrels?<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> That we were very tired by uninterrupted preoccupations on the subject of all our futures, yes; that I didn’t really know where my interest lay with this affair as regards the company,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> yes, but really I don’t see the intense domestic quarrels you speak of. Is it the discussion with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Dries</rs>? Certainly I’d wanted to see him a little bolder in undertaking 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> something,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> but that’s how it is, and it’s no reason to break with him. Is it perhaps, but I can’t believe it, that you consider it an intense domestic quarrel that Jo asked you not to put the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1275">Prévost</rs><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> in the place where you wanted to hang it? She hadn’t thought to hurt you with that, and certainly would have preferred you to leave it there than to get angry about it. Her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">child</rs> preoccupies her too much for her to have much time to think about painting, and although she already sees much better than she used to, she doesn’t always see immediately what’s in it. No, if it was that trifle I would tell you to stop it, for it’s not worth the trouble of bothering with it. I hope, my dear Vincent, that your health is good, and as you said that you’re writing with difficulty and don’t speak to me about your work, I’m a little afraid that there’s something that’s bothering you or that isn’t 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> going right. In that case, do go and see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs>, he’ll perhaps give you something that will buck you up again. Give me news of you as soon as possible.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Last Tuesday I took <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">child</rs> to Leiden and stayed there until Thursday. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> has indeed aged a little, but she was so pleased to see her grandson, and it was amusing to see how she took him and made him happy. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> was also well and was very kind to us. Jo stayed with them for another day after I left, and then left for Amsterdam where she still is.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I hope that everyone is making efforts not to tire her but is allowing her a little rest, she had such need of it, for it’s hard labour, I assure you. Unfortunately, like here, the weather isn’t settled there, so that she can’t be out in the open air much and nor can 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">child</rs>. I think that it might well be that she wishes to come back sooner than we’d planned, but it’s good on the other hand that her house here pleases her more than that of her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_22 bio.xml#_23">parents</rs>. I’ll be very pleased when she’s back, for the house is so deserted! And I miss the little one too. Our life, precisely through this child, is so closely bound together that you mustn’t be afraid that one small disagreement, if you saw one, might occasion a divergence that will make conciliation difficult. So don’t think about that any more. As for me, the journey to Holland has done me a lot of good and made me take a lot of rest, which I very much needed.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Let’s hope that the health of all of us may improve, for health is a great deal. Enclosed I’m sending you 50 francs – write to me quickly, and believe me your brother who loves you.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Letter headed: ‘Paris le 22 Juillet 1890’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo and Jo’s visit to the Netherlands <ref target="let898.xml">(898)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Theo considers leaving the firm of Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie <ref target="let894.xml">(894)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>On 20 July 1890, Theo wrote to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> about Vincent’s letter, which is not known, but which must have been written about 16 July (it was apparently forwarded to the Netherlands, and finally arrived, via Jo, on 19 July at Theo’s in Paris): ‘I understand from Vincent’s letter that what he means by domestic quarrels are my attempts to achieve my own ends in the matters I discussed with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Dries</rs>. That’s the only explanation I can think of, it’s certainly not clear. If only he’s not melancholy and heading for another crisis, it was all going so well’ (See FR b2058; <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 249-250, with a small change in the translation).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This refers to the firm of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_282">Andries</rs> had withdrawn his offer to be Theo’s business associate. <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let900.xml#n-6">See letter 900, n. 6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1275">Prévost</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2216">Lady with a dog</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let658.xml#n-9">see letter 658, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘stable’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The journey had also brought Theo to the decision to stay for the time being with <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs>. On 22 July, Theo informed his <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> and <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> about his interview with his employers the day before (about which he says nothing at all to Vincent): ‘I haven’t written to you since I’ve been back, because I was waiting for a resolution on the part of the Gentlemen. On the way and coming back here, I realized so clearly that recklessly giving up my position to plunge into uncertainty was a very dangerous matter, for I did have hope of finding the money to start my own business, but was not sure of it by any means. I thought about it so much that I was nearly desperate about having let things come so far and perhaps being very soon without one penny of income. So yesterday morning I had another talk with the Gentlemen and found that they are not really ill-disposed towards me. I said that when I had first spoken I had had rather a lot of faith in my lucky stars, and had not thought enough about the power of the firm, but that on second thoughts I had come to the conclusion that it was wiser for me to stay and that even if they thought I didn’t deserve a rise, I would reconcile myself to it and manage to get by. <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_27">Etienne B</rs> was then very friendly and said that nothing had been decided yet about my salary and that they would see if they could make things easier for me. I only hope that now I can do some business, that would surely be the best thing to help them make up their minds, but it is a quiet time [for business]’ (FR b933).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    