<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Ramsgate, Monday, 17 April 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let076"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b73 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>076</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>60</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>074</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-04-17">Monday, 17 April 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Ramsgate</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0073" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0073" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000076_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Ramsgate 17 April <supplied>1876.</supplied></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Beste Vader &amp; Moeder,</p><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">De telegram heeft U zeker reeds ontvangen,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> maar <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>zult nog wel wat meer bijzonderheden willen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>weten. In de spoor schreef ik nog een &amp; ander &amp; stuur <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>U dat<c type="kk">,</c> dan kunt U zien hoe ik het op reis had.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Vrijdag</p><lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Wij willen vandaag bij elkander blijven<c type="kp">.</c>─ Wat zou <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>beter zijn<c type="kk">,</c> de vreugde van het wederzien of den <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>weemoed van het afscheid.</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Reeds dikwijls namen wij afscheid van elkander; <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>wel was er ditmaal meer wee in dan vroeger, van <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>beide kanten, maar moed ook, door het vaster <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>vertrouwen op, bij de grooter behoefte aan zegen. <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>En was het niet of de natuur met ons medevoelde<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>’t was zoo grijs en min of meer bar een paar uur <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>geleden.</p><lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Nu zie ik over de uitgestrekte weiden heen, en alles <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>is zoo stil en de zon gaat onder achter de grijze <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>wolken en werpt een gouden gloed over het land. <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Die eerste uren na het afscheid, die U doorbrengt in <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>de kerk en ik in het station en in den trein, wat <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>verlangen wij naar elkaar, en wat denken wij aan <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>de anderen, aan Theo, en aan Anna en aan de andere 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>zusjes en aan het broerken.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Daar juist kwamen wij Zevenbergen voorbij en ik <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>dacht aan den dag toen U mij daar bracht en ik op <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>de stoep bij den H<hi rend="super">r</hi> Provily<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> stond en uw rijtuig nakeek op <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>den natten weg. En dan dien avond toen mijn Vader <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>mij voor de eerste keer kwam opzoeken. En dat eerste t’huis <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>komen met Kersmis.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Zaturdag en Zondag.</p><lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Wat heb ik op de boot gedacht aan Anna, alles daar herrinnerde <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>mij aan onze reis zamen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Het weer was helder en vooral op de Maas<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> was het mooi <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>en ook het gezicht op de duinen, die wit in de zon blonken, <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>van uit zee gezien. Het laatste wat men van Holland zag <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>was een grijs torentje.</p><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Tot zonsondergang bleef ik op het dek maar toen werd het <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>wat koud en bar.</p><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Den volgenden morgen in de spoor van Harwich naar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Londen was het mooi om in de morgenschemering de zwarte <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>akkers en groene weilanden met schapen en lammeren <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>en hier en daar een dorenheg en enkele groote eikeboomen <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>met donkere takken en grijs bemoste stammen te zien. De <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>schemerende blauwe lucht met nog enkele sterren, en <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>een bank<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> grijze wolken aan den horizon er boven. Reeds <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>voor de zon op ging hoorde ik een leeuwrik.</p><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Toen wij bij het laatste station vóór Londen kwamen ging <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de zon op. De bank grijze wolken was verdwenen en daar <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>was de zon, zoo eenvoudig en groot als maar mogelijk is, <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>een echte Paaschzon.</p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Het gras schitterde van dauw en nachtvorst.─</p><lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Maar toch heb ik dat grijze uur toen wij afscheid <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>namen liever.─</p><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Zaturdag middag bleef ik op het dek tot de zon onder <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>was. Zoover men zien kon was het water vrij donker blauw <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>met nog al hooge golven met witte toppen. De kust was <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>reeds uit het gezigt. De lucht was licht blauw, strak en <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>zonder één wolkje.─</p><lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">En de zon ging onder en wierp een streep schitterend licht <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>op het water.─</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Het was wel een grootsch en majestueus gezicht, maar <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>toch, eenvoudiger<c type="kk">,</c> stiller dingen treffen zooveel dieper, <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>want nu rilde ik onwillekeurig en dacht aan den nacht <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>in de benauwde kajuit met rookende en zingende <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>passagiers<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Te Londen gekomen ging er 2 uur later een trein naar <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Ramsgate. Dat is nog ongeveer 4 1/2 uur sporen.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Het is een <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>mooie weg, onder anderen kwamen wij voorbij een gedeelte <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>dat heuvelachtig is. De heuvels zijn beneden begroeid <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>met schraal gras en boven met eikebosschen. Het heeft veel <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>van onze duinen. Tusschen die heuvels in lag een dorp <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>met grijze kerk<c type="kk">,</c> begroeid met klimop even als de meeste <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>huizen. De boomgaarden stonden in bloei en de lucht <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>was licht blaauw met grijze en witte wolken.</p><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Ook kwamen wij langs Canterbury<c type="kk">,</c> eene stad waar nog veel <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>middeneeuwsche gebouwen zijn, vooral is er een prachtige kerk <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>met oude olmboomen er omheen. Reeds dikwijls had ik <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>op schilderijen iets aangaande die stad gezien.</p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">U kunt wel denken ik reeds een tijd van te voren uit <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>het raampje naar Ramsgate zat uit te kijken.</p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Tegen 1 uur kwam ik bij M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Stokes. Deze was van huis <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>maar komt heden avond terug. Gedurende zijne afwezigheid <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>werd hij vervangen door zijn zoon (23 jaar denk ik)<c type="kk">,</c> schoolmeeste<supplied>r</supplied> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>te Londen.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Stokes<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> zag ik s’middags aan tafel<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Er zijn 24 jongens van 10-14 jaar<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="92a" xml:id="l-92a"/>(Het was een prettig <lb n="92b" xml:id="l-92b"/>gezigt die 24 jongens <lb n="92c" xml:id="l-92c"/>te zien eten<c type="kp">.</c>)</p><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.25" n="25">De school is dus niet groot. Het raam ziet uit op de zee.</p><lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.26" n="26">Na het eten zijn wij gaan wandelen aan den zeekant<c type="kk">,</c> het is <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>daar mooi. De huizen aan zee zijn meest in eenvoudigen <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>gothieken stijl gebouwd, van gelen steen en hebben tuinen <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>vol ceders en andere donkere groenblijvende heesters.─</p><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.27" n="27">Er is eene haven vol schepen<c type="kk">,</c> besloten in steenen dijken waarop <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>men wandelen kan. En verder ziet men de zee in haar natuur<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>lijken staat en dat is mooi.─</p><lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.28" n="28">Gisteren was alles grijs.─</p><lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.29" n="29">s’Avonds gingen wij met de jongens naar de kerk. Op den <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>muur van de kerk stond “zie Ik ben met U tot aan de vol<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>einding der wereld.”<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.30" n="30">Om 8 uur gaan de jongens naar bed en zij staan om 6 uur <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>op.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.31" n="31">Er is nog een ondermeester van 17 jaar.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Deze, 4 jongens <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>en ik slapen in een ander huis dicht bij<c type="kk">,</c> waar ik een <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>klein kamertje heb,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> dat verlangt naar wat prenten <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>aan de muren.</p><lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.32" n="32">En nu genoeg voor heden<c type="kk">,</c> wat hebben wij goede dagen <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>gehad, dank<c type="kk">,</c> dank voor alles. Veel groeten aan Lies<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>Albertine<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> en het broêrken en in gedachten een <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>handdruk van</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.33" n="33">Uw liefh<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.34" n="34">Vincent. </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.35" n="35">Dank voor uwe brieven die daarjuist kwamen en spoedig <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>meer, zoodra ik een paar dagen hier zal geweest zijn <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>en M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Stokes zal gezien hebben.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">[Letterhead: Goupil The Hague (crossed out)]</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Ramsgate, 17 April 1876.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Dear <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Father and Mother</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">By now you’ve no doubt received the telegram,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but will be wanting to know more particulars. I wrote down a few things in the train and am sending you that, so you can see how my trip went.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Friday</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">We want to stay together today. Which would be better, the joy of seeing each other again or the sadness of parting?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">We’ve often parted from each other already, though this time there was more sorrow than before, on both sides, but courage as well, from the firmer faith in, and greater need for, blessing. And wasn’t it as though nature sympathized with us? It was so grey and rather dismal a couple of hours ago.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">Now I look out over rolling pastures, and everything is so quiet and the sun is setting behind the grey clouds and throws a golden glow across the land. How much we long for each other, those first hours after parting, which you’re spending in church and I in the station and the train, and how much we think of the others, of Theo, and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and the other 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407 bio.xml#_401">sisters</rs> and of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">little brother</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">We just passed Zevenbergen, and I thought of the day you took me there and I stood on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_576">Mr Provily</rs>’s<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> steps and watched your carriage driving away down the wet street. And then the evening when my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Father</rs> came to visit me for the first time. And that first homecoming at Christmas.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Saturday and Sunday.</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">How much I thought of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> on the boat; everything there reminded me of our journey together.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">The weather was clear, and on the Maas<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> especially it was beautiful, also the view from the sea of the dunes, gleaming white in the sun. The last thing one saw of Holland was a small grey tower.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">I stayed on deck until sunset, but then it grew cold and dismal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">The next morning in the train from Harwich to London it was beautiful to see in the morning twilight the black fields and green pastures with sheep and lambs, and here and there a hedge of thorn-bushes and a few large oak trees with dark branches and grey, moss-covered trunks. The blue twilit sky, still with a few stars, and a bank of grey clouds above the horizon. Even before the sun rose I heard a lark.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">When we arrived at the last station before London the sun rose. The bank of grey clouds had disappeared and there was the sun, so simple and as big as possible, a real Easter sun.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">The grass was sparkling with dew and night frost.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">And yet I prefer that grey hour when we parted.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Saturday afternoon I stayed on deck until the sun was down. The water was quite dark blue as far as one could see, with rather high waves with white crests. The coast had already disappeared from view. The sky was light blue, burnished and without a cloud.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">And the sun went down and cast a streak of dazzling light on the water. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">It was a truly grand and majestic sight, and yet simpler, quieter things move one so much more deeply, for now I couldn’t help shuddering, and thought of the night in the stuffy saloon with smoking and singing passengers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">A train was leaving for Ramsgate 2 hours after my arrival in London. That’s another train ride of around 4 1/2 hours.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> It’s a beautiful ride; we passed, among other things, a hilly region. The hills have a sparse covering of grass at the bottom and oak woods on the top. It’s very similar to our dunes. Between those hills lay a village with a grey church covered with ivy like most of the houses. The orchards were in blossom, and the sky was light blue with grey and white clouds.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">We also came past Canterbury, a town which still has a lot of medieval buildings, in particular a splendid church with old elm trees around it. Often, already, I’ve seen something of this town in paintings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">You can imagine how I sat looking out of the window, watching well ahead of time for Ramsgate.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">I arrived at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s around 1 o’clock. He was away from home but will be coming back this evening. During his absence his place was taken by his son (23 years old, I think), a schoolmaster in London.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.25" n="25">I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_765">Mrs Stokes</rs><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> in the afternoon at table. There are 24 boys between the ages of 10 and 14. (It was a fine sight, seeing those 24 boys eating.)</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.26" n="26">So the school isn’t large. The window looks out onto the sea.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.27" n="27">After eating we went for a walk by the sea, it’s beautiful there. The houses on the sea are mostly built of yellow brick in a simple Gothic style, and have gardens full of cedars and other dark evergreen shrubs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.28" n="28">There’s a harbour full of ships, closed in by stone jetties on which one can walk. And further out one sees the sea in its natural state, and that’s beautiful.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.29" n="29">Yesterday everything was grey.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.30" n="30">In the evening we went to church with the boys. On the wall of the church was written ‘Lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world’.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.31" n="31">The boys go to bed at 8 o’clock and get up at 6. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.32" n="32">There’s another assistant teacher, 17 years old.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> He, 4 boys and I sleep in another house close by, where I have a small room,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> which wants some prints on the wall.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.33" n="33">And now enough for today, what a good time we had together, thank you, thank you for everything. Many regards to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_240">Albertine</rs><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">little brother</rs>, and in thought a handshake from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.34" n="34">Your loving</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.35" n="35">Vincent.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.36" n="36">Thanks for your letters which just arrived; more soon, when I’ve been here a few days and have seen <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>This letter has been preserved in a copy made by Theo on letter paper from Goupil’s in The Hague. Presumably Mr and Mrs van Gogh had sent him the letter to read, at which time he copied it. He crossed out the letterhead, except for the printed date of 1876, noting in the upper left-hand corner of the sheet: ‘copy’. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Ramsgate 17 April <hi rend="italics">[</hi>1876.<hi rend="italics">]</hi>.’ The passage was added to this letter which had been written already on Friday (‘I wrote down a few things in the train and am sending you that’ <ref target="#l-9">(l. 9)</ref>. The fact that this letter has survived in a copy made by Theo (see <hi rend="italics">Source status</hi>) hampers our understanding of how the original letter was written. The events and impressions of Friday <ref target="#l-11">(ll. 11-35)</ref> were probably described on a separate sheet, but Theo will have put this part in the proper chronological order relative to the other things related in the letter.</p>
<p rend="indent">
      <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 dated the letter ‘17 [or 18] April’, but we see no reason to give it that alternative date; Hulsker 1993-1 gave ‘14-17 April’ as the date, because the events of 14-17 April are recounted in the letter.</p>
<p rend="indent">The letter must be read before the other letter of the same date (<ref target="let077.xml">letter 77</ref>), because additional information about how he spent that Monday morning is contained in the latter letter, in which Van Gogh speaks of the walk he took that morning <ref target="#l-13">(ll. 13-15)</ref> and of the prints that have meanwhile arrived, which he intends to hang in his room <ref target="#l-25">(ll. 25-26)</ref>.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Van Gogh enters the service of William Port Stokes <ref target="let074.xml">(74)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Regarding this telegram, <ref target="let075.xml">see letter 75</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh left on Good Friday, 14 April, taking the 16.00 train to Rotterdam, where he was to take the boat on Saturday morning to Harwich. Cf. also <ref target="let078.xml">letter 78</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cornelis (Cor) Vincent van Gogh</rs>, Vincent’s youngest brother.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>From 1 October 1864 to 31 August 1866 Van Gogh was registered as a pupil at the boys’ boarding school for primary and secondary education run by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_576">Jan Provily</rs> at Zandweg A40 (now Stationstraat 16) in Zevenbergen, a village c. 20 km north of Zundert. Cf. Meyers 1989, pp. 64-70, and Stokvis 1926, p. 14. Van Gogh repeats this recollection of taking leave of his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs> in <ref target="let090.xml">letter 90</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The trip in July 1874; cf. <ref target="let025.xml">letter 25</ref> and <ref target="let026.xml">26</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The River Maas (Meuse) flows past Rotterdam to the sea.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Meaning: ‘een streep’ (a strip).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>This should be 3½ hours. Brown assumes that Van Gogh left London at 9.00, taking the train from Victoria Station and arriving in Ramsgate at 12.30. Meyers thinks that he took the alternative connection (which Brown thinks less likely), leaving London from Charing Cross Station at 7.50 and arriving at Ramsgate at 11.35. See Ruth Brown, <hi rend="italics">Happy days here in Ramsgate for Vincent van Gogh</hi>. Unpublished undergraduate thesis. Ramsgate 1982, and Meyers 1989, pp. 195, 244 (n. 5).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">William Stokes</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_765">Lydia Ann Stokes-Blyth</rs> had a son named <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1650">William Port Stokes</rs>, born in October 1855, and baptized 15 November 1855. He was aged 21 rather than 23, as Van Gogh assumed.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_765">Lydia Ann Stokes-Blyth</rs> had married <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">William Port Stokes</rs> on 25 January 1855 in Isleworth (<hi rend="italics">International Genealogical Index</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 28:20, in English of course; the King James version reads: ‘and, lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world.’</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>The identity of this assistant teacher is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s address was 11 Spencer Square in Ramsgate; he had an attic room. For photographs of the school and the house where Van Gogh lived, see exhib. cat. London<hi rend="italics"> </hi>1992, p. 12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_240">Albertina Ludovica Brugsma</rs>, a friend of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_401">Lies</rs>, who was staying with the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Van Goghs</rs> in Etten.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    