<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Isleworth, Saturday, 7 and Sunday, 8 October 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let093"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b90 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>093</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>76</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>092</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1876-10-07">Saturday, 7 and Sunday, 8 October 1876</date>
                            <placeName>Isleworth</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0090" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-5" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0090" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-6" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000094_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Isleworth 7 Oct. 1876.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Beste Theo,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Het is weer Zaturdag en ik schrijf maar weer <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>eens een woordje<c type="kp">.</c> Zoo verlangend ben ik om <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>U weer eens te zien, o ik kan er soms zoo naar <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>verlangen. Schrijf toch eens spoedig een woordje <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>hoe het er mee gaat.─</p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Verleden Woensdag middag deden wij eene mooie <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>wandeling naar een dorp een uur hier van <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>daan, de weg daarheen gaat door de weilanden en <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>velden langs de heggen van meidoorn vol bramen <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>en clematis en hier en daar een hoogen iepenboom<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Het was zoo mooi toen de zon onderging achter <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>de grijze wolken en toen de schaduws lang waren <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>en toevallig kwamen wij de school van Mr Stokes <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>tegen<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> waar nog verscheidene van de jongens zijn <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>die ik ken.</p><lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">De wolken bleven hun rooden gloed houden nog <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>lang nadat de zon reeds was ondergegaan en <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>toen het reeds schemerde op de velden en wij in <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>de verte de lantaarns zagen aansteken in het dorp. <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Dezen morgen ging de zon ook weer mooi op. Ik <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>zie dat iederen morgen als ik de jongens wakker <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>maak.</p><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Gisteren avond deed ik dat boek van Souvestre <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>weer eens open (Le philosophe sous les toits)<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en ik <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>vond daar zulk eene vriendelijke beschrijving <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>van Parijs in, eene zachtmoedige beschrijving; ik <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>schreef die voor Pa en Moe over<c type="kk">,</c> gij zult die misschien <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ook wel mooi vinden:</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">9<hi rend="super">0</hi> Mai<c type="kp">.</c> Les belles soirées sont revenues; les arbres com<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>mencent à deplisser leurs bourgeons. les hyacinthes, <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>les jonquilles, les violettes et les lilas parfument les <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>éventaires des bouquetières; le foule a repris ses prome<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>nades sur les quais, sur les boulevards. Après dîner, <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>je suis aussi descendu de ma mansarde pour respirer <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>l’air du soir.─</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">C’est l’heure où Paris se montre dans toute sa beauté. <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Pendant la journée, le plâtre des façades fatigue <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>l’oeil par sa blancheur monotone, les chariots pe<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>samment chargés font trembler les pavés sous leurs <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>roues colossales, la foule empressée se croise et se heurte<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>uniquement occupée de ne point manquer l’instant <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>des affaires; l’aspect de la ville a quelque chose d’âpre<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>d’inquiet et de haletant; mais dès que les étoiles se <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>lèvent, tout change; les blanches maisons s’eteignent <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>dans une ombre vaporeuse; on n’entend plus que le <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>roulement des voitures qui courent à quelque fête; <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>on ne voit que passants flaneurs ou joyeux; le tra<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>vail fait place aux loisirs. Maintenant chacun respire <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de cette course ardente à travers les occupations du <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>jour; ce qui reste de force est donné au plaisir! Voici <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>les bals qui éclairent leurs peristyles, les spectacles qui <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>s’ouvrent, les boutiques de friandises qui se dressent le <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>long des promenades, les crieurs de journaux qui font <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>briller leur lanterne. Paris a décidément déposé sa <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>plume<c type="kk">,</c> le mètre et le tablier, après la journeé livrée <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>au travail, il veut la soirée pour jouir; comme les maîtres <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>de Thèbes, il a remis au lendemain les affaires sérieuses. <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>J’aime à partager cette heure de fête, non pour me mêler à <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>la gaîté commune, mais pour la contempler. Si la joie des <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>autres aigrit les coeurs jaloux, elle fortifie les coeurs soumis; <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>c’est le rayon de soleil qui fait epanouir ces deux belles fleurs <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>qu’on nomme la “confiance” et l’“espoir”.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Habituellement, la perspective qui s’ouvre devant ma fenêtre me ravit. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>C’est un chevauchement de toits dont les cimes s’entrelacent, se croisent, <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>se superposent, et sur lesquels de hautes cheminées dressent leurs pitons<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Hier encore je leur trouvais un aspect Alpestre, et j’attendais la première <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>neige pour y voir des glaciers; aujourd’hui je n’aperçois que des tuiles <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>et des tuyaux de poêle. Les pigeons qui m’aidaient à mes illusions agrestes <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>ne me semblent plus que de miserables volatiles qui ont pris les toits <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>pour bassecour; la fumée qui s’élève en legers flocons, au lieu de me <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>faire songer aux soupiraux du Vesuve, me rappelle les preparations <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>culinaires et l’eau de vaisselle, enfin le telegraphe que j’aperçois de <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>loin sur la vieille tour de Montmartre, me fait l’effet d’une ignoble <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>potence dont le bras se dresse au-dessus de la cité.─<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">In sorrow did I bow my head</p><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">There is no peace on earth I said</p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">The world is strong</p><lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">And mocks the song</p><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Of “peace on earth, Goodwill to men”!</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Then pealed the bells more loud and deep:</p><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16"> “God is not dead! nor doth He sleep!</p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">What’s wrong shall fail</p><lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">What’s right prevail</p><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">With peace on earth, goodwill to men<c type="kp">.</c>”<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Er is hier nog veel te doen voor velen wien God <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>Zijn zegen geeft en het leven spaart<c type="kp">.</c>─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Terwijl ik bezig was U te schrijven werd ik bij Mr Jones ge<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>roepen, en die vroeg of ik lust had voor hem naar Londen <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>te wandelen om geld voor hem te ontvangen. En toen ik <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>s’avonds terug kwam, gelukkig daar was een brief van <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>Pa met tijding van U! Wat was ik graag bij U<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>lieden<c type="kk">,</c> bij Pa en bij U,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> jongen. En Goddank het <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>wat beter gaat al zijt Gij nog zwak. En gij zult <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>er naar verlangen om Moe te zien ook en nu ik <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>hoor dat Gij met Moe mede naar huis gaat denk ik <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>aan woorden in Conscience<c type="kk">,</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">J’ai été malade: Mon esprit était fatigué, mon âme désen<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>chantée, mon corps souffrant. Moi, que Dieu a doué au <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>moins d’énergie morale et d’un vaste instinct d’affection, je <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>tombais dans l’abîme du plus amer decouragement et <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>je sentais avec effroi un poison mortel se glisser dans mon <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>coeur rétréci. J’ai passé trois mois dans la Bruyère;─ Vous <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>savez, cette belle contree où l’ame rentre en elle-même <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>et jouit d’un délicieux repos; où tout respire le calme et <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>la paix; où l’âme, en présence de la creation immaculée <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>de Dieu, secoue le joug des convenances, oublie la <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>société et se dégage de ses liens avec la vigueur d’une <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>jeunesse renaissante; où chaque pensée revêt la <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>forme de la prière; où tout ce qui n’est pas en harmonie <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>avec la fraiche et libre nature sort du coeur. Oh! là, l’âme <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>fatiguée rencontre la tranquilité; là l’homme épuisé re<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>trouve une force juvenile. Ainsi se sont passés mes jours <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>de maladie, jours d’indicible jouissance pour mon âme: <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>sourire au soleil quand, dans toute sa majesté, il lance <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>au-dessus de l’horizon ses premiers rayons; epier la <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>nature qui s’éveille et surprendre les premiers accents <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>de l’hymne magnifique qu’elle adresse au ciel; par<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>courir bruyères et forêts; interroger mon âme ─ et <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>penser ─ scruter et admirer la vie des plantes et des <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>animaux, aspirer l’air pur à pleins poumons, s’arrêter, <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>poursuivre sa route, revenir sur ses pas, et parler tout <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>haut dans la solitude; rêver de choses splendides:</p><lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">de Dieu, de l’avenir, de notre Flandre si chère, de paix <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>et d’amour.─ Et le soir donc! Etre assis sous le large <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>manteau de la cheminée, les pieds dans la cendre, <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>l’oeil fixé sur une étoile, qui là-haut m’envoie son <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>rayon par l’embouchure de la cheminée, comme pour m’adresser <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>un appel; ou bien, plongé dans une vague rêverie, regarder <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>le feu, voir les flammes naître, s’élever, haleter, pétiller, se <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>supplanter l’une l’autre comme par envie, pour lêcher la <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>marmite avec leurs langues de feu,─ et songer que c’est là <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>la vie humaine: naître, travailler, aimer, grandir et dis<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>paraître.... Là-haut, la fumée couronne la cheminee <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>de son leger panache; rien de plus ne sort de ce bruit, de <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>ce petillement, de cette ardeur.─<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">Mr Jones heeft mij beloofd dat ik niet zoo veel meer zoude <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>hoeven te onderwijzen maar dat ik in zijne gemeente zou <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>mogen werken voortaan, om de menschen te bezoeken, met hen <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>te spreken enz. God geve er Zijn zegen op. Vader ik bid U dat <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>Gij mij niet uit de wereld wegneemt maar dat Gij mij bewaart voor <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>den booze.─<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.25" n="25">Nu vertel ik U nog van mijne wandeling naar Londen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>s’morgens om 12 uur ging ik van hier en tusschen 5 en 6 <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>uur was ik waar ik zijn moest en deed den brief aan Pa <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>en Moe daar op weg op de post.</p><lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>
  
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.26" n="26">Toen ik in de buurt van de stad kwam waar de meeste <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>schilderijwinkels zijn, in de buurt van het Strand, ont<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>moette ik veel bekenden; het was juist het etensuur <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>en dus waren er veel op straat van de zaken komende <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>of teruggaande. Vooreerst ontmoete ik een jong <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>dominé die hier eens preekte en met wien ik toen <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>kennis maakte, daarna de bediende van Mr Wallis <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>en toen een van de Heeren Wallis zelf, in der tijd <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>kwam ik daar wel een enkelen keer aan huis<c type="kk">,</c> nu <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>heeft hij reeds twee kinderen,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> en toen kwam ik Mr. <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>Reid<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> en Mr. Richardson<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> tegen, dat zijn toch reeds <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>oude vrienden. Verleden jaar om dezen tijd was Mr. <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>Richardson te Parijs en wandelden wij zamen naar <lb n="166" xml:id="l-166"/>Père la Chaise.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Daarna ging ik naar v. Wisselingh <lb n="167" xml:id="l-167"/>waar ik de schetsen voor twee kerkramen zag.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p><lb n="168" xml:id="l-168"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.27" n="27">In het midden van het eene raam het portret van <lb n="169" xml:id="l-169"/>eene bejaarde dame, o zoo’n nobel gezicht met <lb n="170" xml:id="l-170"/>de woorden “Uw wil geschiede”<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> er boven, in het andere <lb n="171" xml:id="l-171"/>raam het portret van hare dochter met de woorden<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="172" xml:id="l-172"/>Het geloof is een vasten grond der dingen die men hoopt <lb n="173" xml:id="l-173"/>en een bewijs voor de dingen die men niet ziet.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> Daar, en <lb n="174" xml:id="l-174"/>in de zaak van Messrs G.&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi><ptr target="#note-t-16"/> zag ik mooie schilderijen en <lb n="175" xml:id="l-175"/>teekeningen, het is zoo’n diep genot om door de kunst zoo <lb n="176" xml:id="l-176"/>telkens aan Holland herinnerd te worden.</p><lb n="177" xml:id="l-177"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.28" n="28">In de City<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> ging ik nog naar Mr Gladwell<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en naar de <lb n="178" xml:id="l-178"/>St Pauls kerk. En van de City naar het andere eindje van <lb n="179" xml:id="l-179"/>Londen<c type="kk">,</c> daar bezocht ik een jongen die in der tijd van de school <lb n="180" xml:id="l-180"/>van Mr. Stokes, wegens ziekte, was vandaan gegaan en vond <lb n="181" xml:id="l-181"/>hem geheel beter, in de straat. Toen naar de plaats waar <lb n="182" xml:id="l-182"/>ik het geld voor Mr. Jones moest ontvangen. Die voorsteden van <lb n="183" xml:id="l-183"/>Londen hebben eene eigenaardige schoonheid; tusschen de <lb n="184" xml:id="l-184"/>kleine huisjes en tuinen zijn open plekken met gras <lb n="185" xml:id="l-185"/>begroeid en meestal met eene kerk of school of armhuis <lb n="186" xml:id="l-186"/>tusschen de boomen en struiken in het midden en het kan <lb n="187" xml:id="l-187"/>daar zoo mooi zijn als de zon rood ondergaat in den <lb n="188" xml:id="l-188"/>fijnen avondmist. Gisteren avond was het zoo en later <lb n="189" xml:id="l-189"/>had ik wel gewild gij die Londensche straten eens gezien <lb n="190" xml:id="l-190"/>hadt toen het begon te schemeren en de lantaarns werden <lb n="191" xml:id="l-191"/>aangestoken en allen en alles naar huis ging, aan alles <lb n="192" xml:id="l-192"/>kon men merken dat het Zaturdag avond was en in al <lb n="193" xml:id="l-193"/>dat gewoel was vrede, men voelde als het ware de behoefte <lb n="194" xml:id="l-194"/>aan en de blijdschap over den naderenden Zondag. O <lb n="195" xml:id="l-195"/>die Zondagen en wat er gedaan en gewerkt wordt op die <lb n="196" xml:id="l-196"/>zondagen<c type="kk">,</c> het is zoo’n verkwikking voor die arme <lb n="197" xml:id="l-197"/>buurten en woelige straten. In de City was het <lb n="198" xml:id="l-198"/>donker maar het was eene mooie wandeling langs <lb n="199" xml:id="l-199"/>die reeks van kerken waar men langs komt. Digt <lb n="200" xml:id="l-200"/>bij het Strand vond ik een omnibus die mij een heel <lb n="201" xml:id="l-201"/>eind verder bragt<c type="kk">,</c> het was reeds vrij laat. Ik kwam voorbij het <lb n="202" xml:id="l-202"/>kerkje van Mr Jones<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> en zag in de verte nog een ander waar zoo <lb n="203" xml:id="l-203"/>laat nog licht brande<c type="kk">,</c> ik ging daarop af en vond dat het <lb n="204" xml:id="l-204"/>een zeer mooi Roomsch kerkje<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> was waar een paar vrouwen <lb n="205" xml:id="l-205"/>baden. Toen kwam ik in dat donkere park waarover <lb n="206" xml:id="l-206"/>ik U reeds schreef<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> en vandaar zag ik in de verte de <lb n="207" xml:id="l-207"/>lichten van Isleworth en de kerk met de klimop en <lb n="208" xml:id="l-208"/>het kerkhof met de treurwilligen aan den kant van de <lb n="209" xml:id="l-209"/>Theems.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-5" facs="#zone-pb-1r-5"/><lb n="213" xml:id="l-213"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.29" n="29">Nu Theo word spoedig <lb n="214" xml:id="l-214"/>beter en lees dezen brief <lb n="215" xml:id="l-215"/>eens als Moe bij U zit <lb n="216" xml:id="l-216"/>omdat ik in gedachten <lb n="217" xml:id="l-217"/>zoo graag bij U beiden <lb n="218" xml:id="l-218"/>zou zijn. Ik ben toch <lb n="219" xml:id="l-219"/>zoo blij dat Mr. Jones <lb n="220" xml:id="l-220"/>beloofd heeft mij in zijne <lb n="221" xml:id="l-221"/>gemeente werk te geven, <lb n="222" xml:id="l-222"/>en ik langzamerhand <lb n="223" xml:id="l-223"/>zal vinden wat goed is<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="224" xml:id="l-224"/>Wij moeten daar naar <lb n="225" xml:id="l-225"/>zoeken maar God moet <lb n="226" xml:id="l-226"/>helpen en doet dat ook<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="227" xml:id="l-227"/>daar is geen leven dat Hij <lb n="228" xml:id="l-228"/>niet heiligen en bezielen <lb n="229" xml:id="l-229"/>kan. Moge ook ik het <lb n="230" xml:id="l-230"/>ondervinden “dat dit <lb n="231" xml:id="l-231"/>is een getrouw woord en <lb n="232" xml:id="l-232"/>aller aanneming waardig <lb n="233" xml:id="l-233"/>dat Christus is in de wereld <lb n="234" xml:id="l-234"/>gekomen om zondaren <lb n="235" xml:id="l-235"/>zalig te maken”<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> en bruik<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="236" xml:id="l-236"/>baar en betrekkelijk goed <lb n="237" xml:id="l-237"/>doende.</p><lb n="238" xml:id="l-238"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.30" n="30">Ik verlang soms zoo naar <lb n="239" xml:id="l-239"/>U. Een hartelijken hand<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="240" xml:id="l-240"/>druk aan U en geef gij <lb n="241" xml:id="l-241"/>Moe een hand voor mij <lb n="242" xml:id="l-242"/>als Zij bij U zit. à Dieu<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="243" xml:id="l-243"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.31" n="31">Uw zoo liefh. broer</p><lb n="244" xml:id="l-244"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.32" n="32">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="245" xml:id="l-245"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.33" n="33">à Dieu<c type="kp">.</c> Moge God mij geven genade te <lb n="246" xml:id="l-246"/>vinden in de oogen van mijn <lb n="247" xml:id="l-247"/>Vader en Moeder en in de <lb n="248" xml:id="l-248"/>oogen van wie zullen na <lb n="249" xml:id="l-249"/>mij komen. En nu, mijn jongen, <lb n="250" xml:id="l-250"/>nog een woord aan U. Zoo wie <lb n="251" xml:id="l-251"/>zich begeeft in Christenomgeving <lb n="252" xml:id="l-252"/>en Christenwerk zoekt en doet zoo <lb n="253" xml:id="l-253"/>goed en zoo kwaad als hij kan<c type="kk">,</c> die <lb n="254" xml:id="l-254"/>zal spoedig zich op een weg voelen <lb n="255" xml:id="l-255"/>die hij gaan <hi rend="italics">moet</hi> of hij wil of niet <lb n="256" xml:id="l-256"/>en zal uitroepen in zielsangst<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="257" xml:id="l-257"/>God helpe mij<c type="kk">,</c> ik kan niet anders<c type="kk">,</c> en God hoort <lb n="258" xml:id="l-258"/>dien roep en God is een machtiger hulp <lb n="259" xml:id="l-259"/>in het leven dan aller menschen en wereld hulp.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-6" facs="#zone-pb-1v-6"/><lb n="260" xml:id="l-260"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.34" n="34">Psalm 107</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="261" xml:id="l-261"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.35" n="35">Looft den Heer want Zijne goeder<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="262" xml:id="l-262"/>tierenheid is in eeuwigheid<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="263" xml:id="l-263"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.36" n="36">Dat zulks de bevrijden des Heeren <lb n="264" xml:id="l-264"/>zeggen, die Hij bevrijd heeft<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="265" xml:id="l-265"/>Die in de woestijn dwaalden <lb n="266" xml:id="l-266"/>in eenen weg der wildernis, die <lb n="267" xml:id="l-267"/>geene stad ter woning vonden: <lb n="268" xml:id="l-268"/>Zij waren hongerig, ook dor<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="269" xml:id="l-269"/>stig, hunne ziel was in hen <lb n="270" xml:id="l-270"/>overstelpt.─</p><lb n="271" xml:id="l-271"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.37" n="37">Doch als zij riepen tot den Heer, <lb n="272" xml:id="l-272"/>in de benaauwdheid die zij <lb n="273" xml:id="l-273"/>hadden, heeft Hij hen gered <lb n="274" xml:id="l-274"/>uit hunne angsten. En Hij <lb n="275" xml:id="l-275"/>leidde hen op eenen regten <lb n="276" xml:id="l-276"/>weg, om te gaan tot eene stad <lb n="277" xml:id="l-277"/>ter woning.</p><lb n="278" xml:id="l-278"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.38" n="38">Hij voerde hen uit de duisternis <lb n="279" xml:id="l-279"/>en Hij brak hunne banden<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="280" xml:id="l-280"/>Want Hij heeft de koperen <lb n="281" xml:id="l-281"/>deuren gebroken en de ijzeren <lb n="282" xml:id="l-282"/>grendelen in stukken gehouwen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="283" xml:id="l-283"/>Hij zond Zijn woord uit en heelde <lb n="284" xml:id="l-284"/>hen en verloste hen uit hunne <lb n="285" xml:id="l-285"/>kuilen.</p><lb n="286" xml:id="l-286"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.39" n="39">Die met schepen de zee bevaren, die <lb n="287" xml:id="l-287"/>zien de groote werken des Heeren <lb n="288" xml:id="l-288"/>en Zijne wonderwerken in de diepe <lb n="289" xml:id="l-289"/>wateren.─</p><lb n="290" xml:id="l-290"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.40" n="40">Als Hij spreekt doet Hij eenen <lb n="291" xml:id="l-291"/>stormwind opstaan, die hare <lb n="292" xml:id="l-292"/>golven omhoog heft. Zij rijzen <lb n="293" xml:id="l-293"/>op naar den Hemel<c type="kk">,</c> zij dalen neder <lb n="294" xml:id="l-294"/>tot in de afgronden; hunne ziel <lb n="295" xml:id="l-295"/>versmelt van angst. Zij dansen <lb n="296" xml:id="l-296"/>en waggelen als een dronken man <lb n="297" xml:id="l-297"/>en al hunne wijsheid wordt ver<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="298" xml:id="l-298"/>slonden. Doch als zij riepen tot <lb n="299" xml:id="l-299"/>den Heer, in de benaauwdheid die <lb n="300" xml:id="l-300"/>zij hadden, zoo voerde Hij hen <lb n="301" xml:id="l-301"/>uit hunne angsten. Hij doet den <lb n="302" xml:id="l-302"/>storm stilstaan, zoodat hunne <lb n="303" xml:id="l-303"/>golven stilzwijgen. Dan zijn <lb n="304" xml:id="l-304"/>zij verblijd, omdat zij gestild zijn, <lb n="305" xml:id="l-305"/>en dat Hij hen tot de have hunner <lb n="306" xml:id="l-306"/>begeerte geleid heeft<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="307" xml:id="l-307"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.41" n="41">Hij brengt de nooddruftige in een <lb n="308" xml:id="l-308"/>hoog vertrek. De opregten zien het <lb n="309" xml:id="l-309"/>en zijn verblijd.─<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="310" xml:id="l-310"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.42" n="42">L’homme s’agite mais Dieu le mène<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="311" xml:id="l-311"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.43" n="43">Protégez-moi mon Dieu car ma bar<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="312" xml:id="l-312"/>que est si petite et Ta mer est si grande.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="313" xml:id="l-313"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.44" n="44">Only they that brave its dangers know <lb n="314" xml:id="l-314"/>the secret of the sea<c type="kk">,</c> understand its mystery<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="38 »" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.45" n="45">Morgen hoop ik voor de tweede maal eenig geld te ontvangen in mijn nieuw werk, en daarvoor een paar <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>nieuwe laarzen te koopen en een nieuwen hoed. En dan als God wil “ons maar <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>weer opmaken”<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="147 »" xml:id="l-147"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.46" n="46">Veel groeten aan allen bij Roos en aan allen die ik ken<c type="kk">,</c> vooral aan allen bij de Hr Tersteeg en v. Stockum en <lb n="147a" xml:id="l-147a"/>Haanebeek.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.47" n="47">Vertel eens aan Moe het zoo heerlijk was een paar door Haar gebreide sokken aan te trekken na dien togt naar Londen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="210 »" xml:id="l-210"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.48" n="48">In de Londensche straten verkoopt men overal ruikende viooltjes<c type="kk">,</c> die bloeijen hier tweemaal s’jaars. ik kocht er van voor <lb n="211" xml:id="l-211"/>Mrs Jones om mijne pijp te vergoeden die ik nu en dan hier rook, vooral s’avonds laat in de speelplaats<c type="kp">.</c> Maar de tabak is nog al <lb n="212" xml:id="l-212"/>zwaarmoedig hier.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Isleworth, 7 Oct. 1876.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">It’s Saturday again, and I’m writing a few words once more. I’m longing so much to see you again, oh, I can long for it so much sometimes. Do write soon and tell me how you are.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Last Wednesday afternoon we took a lovely walk to a village an hour away from here. The road there goes through meadows and fields, along hedgerows of hawthorn full of blackberries and clematis and here and there a tall elm tree. It was so beautiful when the sun went down behind the grey clouds and when the shadows were long, and we chanced to meet <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s school,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> where there are still several boys I know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The clouds kept their red glow long after the sun had set and the twilight was gathering over the fields, and in the distance we saw the street-lamps being lit in the village. This morning there was also a beautiful sunrise. I see it every morning when I wake the boys up.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Last night I opened that book by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Souvestre</rs> again (Le philosophe sous les toits),<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and I found such a friendly description of Paris in it, a kind description; I copied it out for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs>, perhaps you’ll like it too:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">9<hi rend="super"> </hi>May. The beautiful evenings have returned; the trees are beginning to uncurl their buds. Hyacinths, daffodils, violets and lilacs scent the flower-sellers’ stalls; the crowds have begun to stroll along the quays<hi rend="italics"> </hi>and boulevards again. After supper, I too came down from my garret to breathe the evening air. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">It is the hour when Paris shows herself in all her beauty. During the day, the plaster of the facades fatigues the eye with its monotonous whiteness, the heavily laden carts make the cobblestones shudder under their huge wheels, the hurrying crowds cross and collide, intent on not missing a moment of business; there is something harsh, anxious, breathless about the city. But everything changes the moment the stars come out; the white houses fade into misty shadow; nothing is to be heard but the wheels of carriages as they bowl along on their way to some party or other; nothing is to be seen but people strolling idly or gaily by; work gives way to leisure. Now everyone draws breath from that fierce race through the day’s activities; what strength remains is given over to pleasure! See the dance-halls lighting up their colonnades, the theatres opening, the tit-bit stalls lining the avenues, the newsvendors making their lanterns shine. Paris has clearly put aside the pen, the ruler and the apron; after the day dedicated to work it wants to keep the evening for enjoyment; like the masters of Thebes it has put off serious business till the morrow. I love to share this festive time — not to take part in the general gaiety but to observe it. The joy of others may embitter jealous hearts, but it fortifies submissive hearts; it is the ray of sunshine that opens up those two lovely flowers called ‘confidence’ and ‘hope’.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Usually, the view that opens before my window delights me. It is a clutter of roofs whose tops overlap and criss-cross, superimposed on one another, and upon which the tall chimneys raise their peaks. Yesterday I still found something Alpine about them, and waited for the first snow, to see glaciers on them; today I see nothing but tiles and stovepipes. The pigeons that fed my rustic fantasies now seem no more than poor feathered creatures that have taken the roofs for a farmyard; the smoke that rises in faint wisps, instead of giving me dreams of the vent-holes of Vesuvius makes me think of cooking and dish-water; lastly, the telegraph that I can see from afar, on the old tower of Montmartre, looks to me like a revolting gallows whose arm rises above the city.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">In sorrow did I bow my head</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">There is no peace on earth I said</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">The world is strong</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">And mocks the song</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Of ‘peace on earth, Goodwill to men’!</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Then pealed the bells more loud and deep:</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">‘God is not dead! nor doth He sleep!</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">What’s wrong shall fail</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">What’s right prevail</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">With peace on earth, goodwill to men.’<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">There’s still a lot to do here for many to whom God gives His blessing and whose lives He spares.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">While I was writing to you I was summoned to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>, who asked if I felt like walking to London for him to collect some money. And when I returned in the evening, happily there was a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> with news of you! How I’d like to be with you, with Pa and with you,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> old boy. And thank God you’re a little better, even though you’re still weak. And you’ll be longing to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> too, and now that I hear you’re going home with Ma it makes me think of a passage in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Conscience</rs>:</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">I have been ill. My spirit was weary, my soul disenchanted, my body sickly. I, whom God has at least endowed with moral energy and a vast instinct for affection, was falling into the depths of the bitterest discouragement, and I felt with terror a deadly poison creeping into my shrivelled heart. I have spent three months on the heath: you know, that lovely region where the soul returns to itself and enjoys sweet repose; where everything exudes peace and tranquillity; where the soul, in the presence of God’s immaculate creation, shakes off the yoke of convention, forgets society and frees itself from its bonds with the vigour of returning youth; where every thought takes on the form of prayer; where the heart is emptied of everything that is not in harmony with the freshness and freedom of nature. Oh, there the weary soul finds calm; there, the exhausted man regains a youthful strength. Thus were my days of sickness spent, days of ineffable joy for my soul: smiling at the sun when, in all its majesty, it casts its first rays over the horizon; watching the countryside awaken and catching the first notes of the glorious hymn it addresses to heaven; roaming heaths and forests; questioning my soul — and thinking — scrutinizing and admiring the life of plants and animals, taking deep breaths of the pure air, stopping, going on, turning back, and talking out loud in the solitude; dreaming of splendid things: of God, of the future, of our dear Flanders, of peace and love. And in the evening! To sit under the wide chimney-piece, feet in the ashes, eyes fixed upon a star that sends me its light from on high through the chimney-top, as if calling out to me; or, sunk in a vague reverie, to look at the fire, watching the flames come to life, grow, gasp and crackle, pushing each other aside as if vying to lick the cooking-pot with their tongues of fire — and to imagine that this is human life: to be born, to work, to love, to grow up, and to die.... Up above, smoke crowns the chimney with its weightless plume; of all that noise, that crackling, that heat, nothing more comes forth.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs> has promised me that I won’t have to teach so much any more, but that I may work in his parish from now on, visiting people, talking to them, and so on. May God give this His blessing. Father, I pray that Thou dost not take me out of the world, but that Thou shouldest keep me from the evil.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">Now I’ll tell you about my walk to London. I left here at noon and arrived where I had to be between 5 and 6 o’clock and posted the letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">Pa and Ma</rs> along the way.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.25" n="25">When I came to the neighbourhood in the city where most of the galleries are, in the neighbourhood of the Strand, I met a lot of acquaintances; it was right at lunch-time and so there were a lot of people on the street, coming from or going to their offices. First of all, I met a young clergyman who used to preach here and with whom I became acquainted at that time, then <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_818">Mr Wallis</rs>’s clerk and then one of the Messrs Wallis himself, in those days I went to their house once or twice – he already has two children<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> – and then I ran into <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_184">Mr Reid</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_636">Mr Richardson</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> who are old friends by now. Last year at this time Mr Richardson was in Paris, and we walked together to Père Lachaise.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Afterwards I went to see <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Van Wisselingh</rs>, where I saw sketches for two church windows.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.26" n="26">In the middle of one of the windows the portrait of an elderly lady, such a noble face, with the words ‘Thy will be done’<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> inscribed above; in the other window the portrait of her daughter, with the words ‘Faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen’.<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> There, as well as in the gallery of Messrs G.&amp;Cie,<ptr target="#note-t-16"/> I saw beautiful paintings and drawings, it’s such a deep pleasure to be reminded time and again of Holland through art.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.27" n="27">In the City<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> I also went to see<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_396"> Mr Gladwell</rs><ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and to St Paul’s. And from the City to the other end of London, there I visited a boy who had left <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s school because of illness, and I found him completely recovered, outside in the street. Then on to the place where I had to collect the money for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>. The suburbs of London have a peculiar beauty; between the small houses and gardens there are open places covered with grass and usually with a church or school or poorhouse between the trees and shrubbery in the middle, and it can be so beautiful there when the sun goes down red in the light evening mist. It was like that yesterday evening, and later I did so wish that you had seen the streets of London when it began to grow dark and the street-lamps were lit and everyone was going home, it was obvious from everything that it was Saturday evening, and in all that hustle and bustle there was peace, one felt, as it were, the need for and joy at the approach of Sunday. Oh those Sundays and how much is done and striven for on those Sundays, it’s such a relief to those poor neighbourhoods and busy streets. It was dark in the City, but it was a lovely walk past all those churches along the way. Close to the Strand I found an omnibus that brought me a long way, it was already rather late. I rode past <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Mr Jones</rs>’s little church<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> and saw another in the distance where light was still burning so late. I headed for it and found it to be a very beautiful little Roman Catholic church<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> in which a couple of women were praying. Then I came to that dark park I already wrote to you about,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> and from there I saw in the distance the lights of Isleworth and the church with the ivy and the cemetery with the weeping willows on the banks of the Thames. 
<pb f="1r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-5" facs="#zone-pb-1r-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.28" n="28">Now then, Theo, get well soon and read this letter sometime when <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> is sitting with you, because I’d very much like to be with you both in thought. I’m really very glad that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_683">Mr Jones</rs> has promised to let me work in his parish, and that I’ll eventually find the right thing. We must seek that, but God must help and that He does, there is no life that He cannot sanctify and inspire. May I also discover ‘that this is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ came into the world to save sinners’,<ptr target="#note-t-22"/> being useful and of some value.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.29" n="29">I long so much to see you sometimes. A hearty handshake to you, and give <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> your hand for me when she’s sitting with you. Adieu.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.30" n="30">Your most loving brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.31" n="31">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.32" n="32">Adieu. May God grant that I find grace in the eyes of my Father and Mother and in the eyes of those who will come after me. And now, my boy, another word to you. He who puts himself in a Christian sphere, and seeks and does Christian work as best he can, he will soon feel that he is on a path that he <hi rend="italics">must</hi> traverse whether he wants to or not, and will cry out in anguish, God help me, I can do nothing else, and God hears this cry and God is a more powerful help in life than all human and worldly help. 
<pb f="1v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-6" facs="#zone-pb-1v-6"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.33" n="33">Psalm 107</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.34" n="34">O Give thanks unto the Lord, for His mercy endureth forever. Let the redeemed of the Lord say so, whom He hath redeemed. They wandered in the wilderness in a solitary way; they found no city to dwell in. Hungry and thirsty, their soul fainted in them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.35" n="35">Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and He delivered them out of their distresses. And He led them forth by the right way, that they might go to a city of habitation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.36" n="36">He brought them out of darkness, and brake their bands in sunder. For He hath broken the gates of brass, and cut the bars of iron in sunder. He sent His word, and healed them, and delivered them from their destructions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.37" n="37">They that go down to the sea in ships, these see the great works of the Lord, and His wonders in the deep.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.38" n="38">For He commandeth, and raiseth the stormy wind, which lifteth up the waves thereof. They mount up to the Heaven, they go down again to the depths: their soul is melted because of trouble. They reel to and fro, and stagger like a drunken man, and are at their wit’s end. Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and He bringeth them out of their distresses. He maketh the storm a calm, so that the waves thereof are still. Then are they glad because they be quiet; so He bringeth them unto their desired haven.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.39" n="39">He setteth the poor on high. The righteous shall see it, and rejoice.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.40" n="40">Man proposes, but God disposes.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.41" n="41">Protect me O God, for my bark is so small and Thy sea is so great.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.42" n="42">Only they that brave its dangers know the secret of the sea, understand its mystery.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.43" n="43">I hope to receive tomorrow, for the second time, some money for my new work, and to buy a pair of new boots and a new hat with it. And then, God willing, we shall ‘rise up once again’.<ptr target="#note-t-27"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.44" n="44">Many regards to everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_642 bio.xml#_643">the Rooses</rs>’ and to everyone I know, especially everyone at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs>’s and at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_768 bio.xml#_769">the Van Stockums</rs>’ and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_442 bio.xml#_443">the Haanebeeks</rs>’.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.45" n="45"> Tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> that it was such a delight, after that journey to London, to put on a pair of socks that she’d knitted.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.46" n="46">In the streets of London they’re selling sweet violets everywhere; they flower here twice a year. I bought some for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_201">Mrs Jones</rs> to make up for the pipe I smoke here now and then, mostly late in the evening in the playground. The tobacco here is rather strong, though.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Isleworth 7 Oct. 1876.’ After starting the letter on Saturday, Van Gogh was sent by Jones to London on an errand <ref target="#l-92">(l. 92)</ref>. Subsequent events, including those of Saturday evening, were recorded on Sunday.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Theo’s illness <ref target="let092.xml">(92)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Since Van Gogh’s former employer, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_764">Mr Stokes</rs>, had moved his school in June, Stokes’s school was near that of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_682">Slade-Jones</rs>; <ref target="let086.xml#n-1">see letter 86, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Emile Souvestre</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_92"><hi rend="italics">Un philosophe sous les toits. Journal d’un homme heureux</hi></ref>. Paris 1850 (The philosopher in a garret. Diary of a happy man). The book has twelve chapters, each of which relates the events of one day of one month. The protagonist presents the reader with his observations concerning everyday human actions and suggests which virtues are most important in life. In his philosophy, a humble, simple, modest and submissive life ultimately leads to fulfilment.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">E. Souvestre</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_92"><hi rend="italics">Un philosophe sous les toits</hi></ref>. New edition. Paris 1867, pp. 55-57 and pp. 8-9 (chapter 4, ‘Aimons-nous les uns les autres’ (Do we love one another?) and chapter 1, ‘Les étrennes de la mansarde’ (The garret’s Christmas gifts). Cf. Pabst, 1988, p. 66.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Based on the last two stanzas of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">H.W. Longfellow</rs>’s ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_93">Christmas bells</ref>’ from the book <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_94"><hi rend="italics">Flower-de-Luce</hi></ref>. See Longfellow 1886-1891, vol. 3, pp. 132-133. In <ref target="#l-80">l. 80</ref> Van Gogh wrote ‘In sorrow did I bow’ where the source text has ‘And in despair I bowed’, and in <ref target="#l-82">l. 82</ref> he wrote ‘The world is strong’ where the source text has ‘For hate is strong’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Possibly an allusion to Deut. 12:15 or rhy. ps. 34:11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>To lend Theo some support during his illness, first <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs> and later <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> went to visit him (FR b2782 and b2786, dated 7 and 23 October 1876).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Excerpt from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Henri Conscience</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_77"><hi rend="italics">Le conscrit</hi></ref> (The conscript). Van Gogh left out several passages. A comparison with the French version in <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_95"><hi rend="italics">Scènes de la vie flamande</hi></ref> (Scenes of Flemish life) by Henri Conscience, translated by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1663">Léon Wocquier</rs>, first series, new edition, Paris 1864, pp. 187-189 (cf. <ref target="let089.xml">letter 89</ref>) reveals the following changes:</p>

<p><ref target="#l-106">l. 106</ref> mortel [ mortel, – la haine des hommes peut-être, –</p>

<p><ref target="#l-137">l. 137</ref> aimer, grandir [ aimer, haïr, grandir</p>

<p>It is remarkable that in the preceding quotation from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">Longfellow</rs> Van Gogh replaced the word ‘hate’ and in this quotation avoids the words ‘haine’ (hate) and ‘haïr’ (to hate).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  John 17:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>This most likely refers to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_818">Thomas Wallis</rs>, son of the art dealer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1657">William Henry Wallis</rs>. When Van Gogh moved to London in May 1873, he became acquainted with them through his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>: Uncle Vincent and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_853">his wife</rs> were staying with the Wallis family, who invited Vincent to dine with them around 18 May 1873 (FR b2630). Vincent could also have met Thomas Wallis at the end of 1873 when the latter visited a number of studios in The Hague, as emerges from letters written by H.W. Mesdag in December 1873. In the period 1861-1900, Goupil maintained close ties with Wallis &amp; Son. See Stolwijk 1998, p. 216; cf. also Bailey 1990, p. 91.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Presumably <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_184">George R. Reid</rs>; <ref target="let082.xml#n-7">see letter 82, n. 7.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>This person has not been identified, though the reference is probably to one <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_636">J. Richardson</rs>, called in <ref target="let277.xml">letter 277</ref> ‘the traveller of the house of G&amp;Co’. Cf. Bailey 1990, p. 91.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Père Lachaise, a famous cemetery in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            
  
<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Elbert Jan van Wisselingh</rs> had received his training at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_825">Goupil</rs>’s in The Hague (1864-1866) and in Paris (1866-1874). He and the art dealer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_331">Daniel Cottier</rs> were business partners in London in the years 1874-1882. Their gallery was at 8 Pall Mall. See Heijbroek and Wouthuysen 1999. The windows are located in St Andrew's Church in Owslebury, near Winchester. They were commissioned by William Carnegie, 8th Earl of Northesk, as a memorial to his wife and daughter, who both died before him. Both women are depicted as the Virgin Mary. In the family scrapbook of the earl’s descendants, Max Donnelly found photographs of the designs that Van Gogh had described. See Max Donnelly, ‘“Such a noble face”: Vincent van Gogh, Daniel Cottier and the Northesk memorials’, in <hi rend="italics">Burlington Magazine</hi> 153 (2011), pp. 568-571. Ills. 3099-3102<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3099"/><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3100"/><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3101"/><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_3102"/>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 6:10, Matt. 26:42 and Luke 11:2.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>
  Heb. 11:1. The quotation that Van Gogh saw in the original design was replaced with: ‘Fear not, only believe’. See Max Donnelly, ‘“Such a noble face”: Vincent van Gogh, Daniel Cottier and the Northesk memorials’, in <hi rend="italics">Burlington Magazine</hi> 153 (2011), p. 571.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Goupil’s London branch, located at 25 Bedford Street (Strand); <ref target="let029.xml#n-3">see letter 29, n. 3.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p>The ‘corporation of the city of London’, on the north bank of the Thames, comprises what used to be the ancient city.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_396">Henry William Gladwell</rs>’s gallery was located at 20-21 Gracechurch Street.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            
  
<p>The Congregational Church at Turnham Green, which was ‘a prefabricated “tin tabernacle” of a type commonly found’ in Chiswick High Road (c. 5 km from Isleworth), opened its doors in September 1875 (see Taylor 1964, p. 420, and cf. <ref target="let095.xml">letter 95</ref>). Van Gogh sketched this church, which no longer exists, in <ref target="let099.xml">letter 99</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>This must refer to St John’s Church in Boston Park Road (opened in 1866), which was located about 1 km north of Van Gogh’s route along Brentford High Street.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>Syon Park in Isleworth.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>
  1 Tim. 1:15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>Ps. 107; Van Gogh omitted the following verses: 3, 8-13, 15, 17-19, 21-22, 23b, 31-40, 41b and 43.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>Regarding the quotation of ‘L’Homme... mène’, <ref target="let035.xml#n-2">see letter 35, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_744">Emile Souvestre</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_96"><hi rend="italics">Les derniers Bretons</hi></ref> (The last Bretons): ‘On connaît la vieille prière du matelot breton: <hi rend="italics">Mon Dieu, protégez-moi, mon navire est si petit et votre mer si grande!</hi>’. Paris 1858, part 1, chapter 2, paragraph 2, p. 39 (One knows the old prayer of the Breton sailor: Dear God, protect me, my boat is so small and your sea is so great). For an English translation, cf. <ref target="let096.xml">letters 96</ref> and <ref target="let120.xml">120</ref>. Van Gogh also wrote these words in the second poetry album, along with other passages from Souvestre’s book, as well as in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_201">Annie Slade-Jones</rs>’s visitors’ book. See Pabst 1988, pp. 27, 67.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>Taken from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_696">H.W. Longfellow</rs>, ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_97">The secret of the sea</ref>’, from the book <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_98"><hi rend="italics">The seaside and fireside</hi></ref>:</p>
  
<p>‘“Wouldst thou,” – so the helmsman answered,</p>

<p>“Learn the secret of the sea?</p>

<p>Only those who brave its dangers</p>

<p>Comprehend its mystery!”’</p>

<p>See Longfellow 1886-1891, vol. 1, pp. 260-262.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="27" xml:id="note-t-27">
                            

<p>Cf. Gen. 35:3, Gen. 43:8 and Song of Sol. 7:12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    