<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Dordrecht, Monday, 30 April 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let113"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b112 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>113</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>94</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>113</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-04-30">Monday, 30 April 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0112" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0112" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000121_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Dordrecht 30 April 1877</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Wees van harte gelukgewenscht op dezen dag<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> vier dien nog <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>dikwijls, heb morgen een goeden dag en vele goede dagen <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>in het jaar dat Gij begint. De tijd gaat spoedig om <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>en de dagen vliegen voorbij ─ toch kan er iets achterblijven <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>en is het verledene niet geheel verloren ─ wij kunnen rijker <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>worden en vaster van geest<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> van karakter<c type="kk">,</c> van hart<c type="kk">,</c> wij <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>kunnen rijker worden in God,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> wij kunnen rijker worden in <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>het fijne goud<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> van het leven<c type="kk">,</c> de liefde tot elkander en <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>het gevoel “en nogtans ben ik niet alleen want de Vader is <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>met mij”.─<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Zoo ga het met ons allen<c type="kk">,</c> het is een goed <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>gebed dat van onzen Vader: verbind Gij o Heer ons innig aan <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>elkaar, en laat de liefde tot U dien band meer en meer verster<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ken.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Spoedig hoop ik U te zien, want het is mijn plan om als ik naar <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Amsterdam ga nog te s’Hage eenigen tijd stil te blijven,<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> zeg <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>dit echter maar aan niemand want het is mij te doen om met U te <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>zijn vooral.</p><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Woensdag aanst. ga ik naar Etten, om nog eenige dagen daar <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>te blijven en dan de hand aan den ploeg<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Gisteren had ik U wel hier willen hebben, des morgens hoorde <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ik in het Fransche kerkje het afscheid van D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Hooyer,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> de kerk <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>was vol, hij sprak met vuur en gevoel, het gezigt van die 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>deftige eigenaardige Gemeente trof mij, er was veel ernstige <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>stemming. Hij dankte voor de liefde die hij van velen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>had ondervonden in moeielijke dagen vooral, toen in het <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>begin, vier jaar geleden hij had te worstelen met de <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>moeielijkheden van het spreken in de Fransche taal, want <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>hij is een Hollander. Er waren verscheidene van de andere <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>predikanten hier in de kerk<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">s’Middags was ik bij D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Keller van Hoorn in de Groote kerk<c type="kk">,</c> zijn <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>tekst was “Onze Vader”<c type="kk">,</c> s’avonds bij D<hi rend="super">s</hi> Greeff<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> dien ik ook den eersten <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>zondagavond dat ik hier in Dordt was hoorde.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Toevallig sprak hij in <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zijne preek van gisteren over de zelfde woorden waarover hij <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>die eerste keer sprak: Nu zien wij door een spiegel in eene duistere <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>rede, nu ken ik ten deele maar dan zal ik kennen gelijk ook ik <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>gekend ben.─<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Na de kerk wandelde ik dien weg achter het station waar wij <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>ook zamen waren,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> ging dien met de gedachte aan U en wenschende <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>wij te zamen konden zijn ─ en wandelde nog door tot het <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>kerkhof aan het eind van een zwarten kolenweg door de weilanden <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>die er in de schemering zoo mooi uitzagen. Het kerkhof heeft <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>wel iets van die teekening van Apol die in “Eigen haard” staat<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-13"/> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>er is eene gracht om heen en er staat een huis op met mastboomen er om heen waar gisteren avond <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>het licht zoo vriendelijk door de vensters scheen ─ het is een oud <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>huis dat er uitziet als eene pastorie.─<ptr target="#note-t-14"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Er kan voor ons beiden nog veel goeds zijn in de toekomst<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>laat ons het Pa maar leeren nazeggen “ik wanhoop nooit”<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en Oom Jan “de duivel is nooit zoo zwart of men kan <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>hem nog wel onder de oogen zien”.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Schrijf weer eens spoedig, nu Woensdag ben ik dus te <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Etten. Hebt gij de Plancy<c type="kk">,</c> Légendes des artistes met <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>houtsneden naar Rochussen<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-17"/> dat hoop ik U mede te brengen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Zoo tusschen de bedrijven in heb ik dezer dagen <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>uit een catechisatieboekje van Oom Stricker de geheele <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>geschiedenis van Christus nog eens doorgewerkt,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> en de <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>teksten uitgeschreven, zoovele schilderijen van Rembrandt <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>en anderen kwamen mij daarbij in de gedachte.─ het is<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>geloof en vertrouw ik<c type="kk">,</c> eene onberouwelijke keuze<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> die ik <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>heb gedaan om te trachten te worden een christen en een <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>christen werkman<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Ja, alle dingen uit het verleden <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>kunnen medewerken ten goede,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> door de bekendheid met <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>steden als London en Parijs en het leven in huizen als <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>die school te Ramsgate en te Isleworth wordt men sterker <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>aangetrokken en gehecht aan vele dingen en boeken uit den <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>Bijbel als b.v. de Handelingen der Apostelen<c type="kp">.</c> De bekendheid <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>met en liefde voor het werk en leven van mannen als <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Jules Breton<c type="kk">,</c> Millet en Jacque<c type="kk">,</c> Rembrandt<c type="kk">,</c> Bosboom <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>en zooveel anderen kan ook eene bron worden om gedachten <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>te krijgen<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Wat is er veel overeenkomst tusschen het werk en leven <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>van Pa en dat van zulke mannen, dat van Pa schat <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>ik nog hooger.</p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">God helpe ons jongen, Hij kan U en ons allen en mij <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>doen zeggen<c type="kk">,</c> Heer het is genoeg.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">à Dieu<c type="kk">,</c> ontvang een handdruk in gedachten en wees <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>nogmaals hartelijk gelukgewenscht door</p> <space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Uw liefh. broer</p><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">De Heer zegene U en behoede U, de Heer <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>doe zijn aangezigt over U lichten en geve<lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
U vrede.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> De Heer doe U boven bidden en<lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/> boven denken.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> Hij zij Uw bewaarder en Uwe<lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/> schaduw aan Uwe regterhand.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> Hij zij<lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/> met U alle dagen tot aan de voleinding<lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/> der wereld.─<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="88»" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Groet uwe huisgenooten<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dordrecht, 30 April 1877</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">My hearty congratulations on this day,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> many happy returns, have a good day tomorrow, and many good days in the year you’re now beginning. Time passes quickly and the days fly past – yet something can remain and the past isn’t entirely lost – we can become richer and firmer of spirit,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> of character, of heart, we can become richer in God,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> we can become richer in the fine gold<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> of life, the love for one another and the feeling ‘and yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me’.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> May it be so for all of us, it is a good prayer, that one of Father’s: O Lord, join us intimately to one another and let our love for Thee make that bond ever stronger.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I hope to see you soon, because when I go to Amsterdam I’m planning to stop in The Hague for a while. Don’t tell anyone about this, though, because my main purpose in doing so is to see you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’m going to Etten this Wednesday, to stay there for a few days before putting my hand to the plough.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I should have liked you to be here yesterday; in the morning I heard the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_462">Rev. Hooyer</rs>’s farewell sermon in the little French church.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> The church was full, he spoke with fire and feeling, I was moved by the sight of that 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> distinguished, singular congregation, the mood was very earnest. He thanked them for the love that he had received from many of them, especially at difficult times, in the beginning, four years ago, when he was wrestling with the difficulties of speaking in French, because he’s a Dutchman. There were various other clergymen in the congregation.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">In the afternoon I went to the Grote Kerk to hear the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_474">Rev. Keller van Hoorn</rs>, whose text was ‘Our Father’; in the evening I heard the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_434">Rev. Greeff</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> whom I’d heard on my first Sunday evening here in Dordrecht.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> By chance, he took for his sermon yesterday the same text he had taken that first time: Now we see through a glass, darkly; now I know in part, but then shall I know even as also I am known.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">After church I walked along that path behind the station where we walked together,<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> thinking of you and wishing we could be together – and kept on walking until I came to the cemetery at the end of a black cinder road running through the meadows that looked so beautiful in the twilight. The cemetery looks a little like that drawing by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_76">Apol</rs> in ‘Eigen Haard’,<ptr target="#note-t-13"/> there’s a canal around it and there’s a house surrounded by pine trees, yesterday evening the light was shining through the windows in such a friendly way – it’s an old house that looks like a parsonage.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">There can still be much good in store for both of us, let us learn to say after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> ‘I never despair’<ptr target="#note-t-15"/> and after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_410">Uncle Jan</rs> ‘the devil is never so black that one cannot look him in the face’.<ptr target="#note-t-16"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Write again soon, this Wednesday, then, I’ll be in Etten. Do you have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_724">De Plancy</rs>, Légendes des artistes, with woodcuts after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Rochussen</rs>?<ptr target="#note-t-17"/> I hope to bring it for you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">These last few days I’ve managed, in between times, to work my way through the whole story of Christ from a catechism book written by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Uncle Stricker</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-18"/> and I copied out the texts, which brought to mind so many paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> and others. It is, I believe and trust, a choice not to be repented of,<ptr target="#note-t-19"/> which I’ve made in an attempt to become a Christian and a Christian labourer.<ptr target="#note-t-20"/> Yes, all things of the past can work together for good,<ptr target="#note-t-21"/> familiarity with cities like London and Paris and life in such places as that school in Ramsgate and in Isleworth makes one more drawn and attached to many things and such books of the Bible as The Acts of the Apostles. Knowing and loving the work and life of such men as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules Breton</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1117">Jacque</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_884">Bosboom</rs> and so many others, can also be a source of ideas. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">What a similarity there is between the work and life of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> and that of such men; that of Pa I rate even higher.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">God help us, old boy, He can make you and all of us and me say, Lord, it is enough.<ptr target="#note-t-22"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Adieu, accept a handshake in thought and again, hearty congratulations from</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Your loving brother</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">The Lord bless thee, and keep thee: the Lord make his face shine upon thee, and give thee peace.<ptr target="#note-t-23"/> May the Lord do above all that we ask and think.<ptr target="#note-t-24"/> He is your keeper and the shade upon your right hand.<ptr target="#note-t-25"/> May He be with you alway, even unto the end of the world.<ptr target="#note-t-26"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Give my regards to your housemates.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Dordrecht 30 April 1877’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Vincent’s plans to become a clergyman <ref target="let106.xml">(106)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Theo would turn 20 on 1 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  Rhy. ps. 51:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Cf. Luke 12:21 and Jas. 2:5; the <hi rend="italics">KJ</hi> has ‘richer toward God’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Biblical; see, for example, Ps. 19:11 (in <hi rend="italics">KJ</hi> Ps. 19:10) and Isa. 13:12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  John 16:32.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This prayer recurs frequently; <ref target="let042.xml">see letter 42</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Meaning, ‘Halt te houden, de reis te onderbreken’ (To stop, to interrupt the journey).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  Luke 9:62.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_462">Jan Hendrik Hooyer</rs> had been the minister of the Waalse Kerk (French Church) at the corner of Visstraat and Voorstraat since 1873.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_434">Rev. Samuel Essenius Greeff</rs> was the minister of the Nederlands Hervormde (Dutch Reformed) congregation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Sunday, 7 January; <ref target="let101.xml#n-31">see letter 101, n. 31.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>
  1 Cor. 13:12.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Regarding this walk, <ref target="let103.xml">see letter 103</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>A reproduction of the drawing <hi rend="italics">Gevallen grootheid </hi>(Fallen greatness) by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_76">Lodewijk Apol</rs> appeared in <hi rend="italics">Eigen Haard</hi> 1 (1875), no. 30, p. 253. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1803">Ill. 1803</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>The house of the keeper of the cemetery in the Dubbeldamseweg. See  Molendijk 1990, p. 5; a 1914 photograph of this house is to be found in J.J. Beyerman, <hi rend="italics">Dordrecht in oude ansichten</hi>. Zaltbommel 1967, p. 20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="15" xml:id="note-t-15">
                            

<p>This expression of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, which Vincent repeats frequently, could have been derived from hymn 56:1 and hymn 56:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="16" xml:id="note-t-16">
                            

<p>Another version of this proverb is ‘The devil is not so black as he is sometimes painted’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="17" xml:id="note-t-17">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_724">Jacques Albin Simon Collin de Plancy</rs>, <ref target="biblio.xml#lit_130"><hi rend="italics">Légendes des artistes. Dessins-croquis de C. Rochussen</hi></ref>. The Hague (Société neerlandaise pour les Beaux-Arts) 1842. <hi rend="italics">The legends of the artists</hi> contains 14 biographical, anecdotal essays on Dutch and Flemish artists (mostly painters) of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. Each essay is accompanied by several engravings after sketches by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1320">Charles Rochussen</rs>. Theo’s estate included a copy of this edition, which had belonged to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_399">Uncle Hein van Gogh</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="18" xml:id="note-t-18">
                            

<p>A catechism is a question-book used in religious instruction. From the bibliography accompanying the 1887 account of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_318">Stricker</rs>’s life, it appears that Van Gogh’s employer, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_306">Mr Braat</rs>, had published two of his catechisms. See Berlage 1887, p. 36.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="19" xml:id="note-t-19">
                            

<p>Cf. 2 Cor. 7:10.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="20" xml:id="note-t-20">
                            

<p>For the concept of the ‘Christian Workman’, <ref target="let109.xml#n-15">see letter 109, n. 15.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="21" xml:id="note-t-21">
                            

<p>
  Rom. 8:28.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="22" xml:id="note-t-22">
                            

<p>Biblical; Van Gogh was possibly thinking of 1 Kings 19:4, which he quotes at length in <ref target="let118.xml">letter 118</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="23" xml:id="note-t-23">
                            

<p>
  Num. 6:24-26, as well as the closing lines of the liturgical service.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="24" xml:id="note-t-24">
                            

<p>
  Hymn 36:2 and Eph. 3:20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="25" xml:id="note-t-25">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 121:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="26" xml:id="note-t-26">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 28:20.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    