<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Wednesday, 3 January 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let298"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b279 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>298</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>257</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>299</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-01-03">Wednesday, 3 January 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0279" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0279" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000347_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Gisteren schreef ik U doch ik doe het heden op nieuw <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>om U de goede ontvangst van Uw brief te berigten en <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>U daarvoor te bedanken en U te zeggen dat Uw schrijven <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>mij heeft opgemonterd.</p><lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Ik was wat ongerust dat om reden gij maar zoo <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>weinig van mijn werk hadt gezien in den laatsten tijd<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>dit misschien oorzaak zijn mogt ge meendet ik <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>begon slap te worden.</p><lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Ik heb juist in den laatsten tijd zwaar geblokt, <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>en zit nog verdiept in allerlei dingen waarin <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>ik licht begin te zien om ze te doen doch <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>nog niet naar mijn zin onder den duim heb <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>evenwel.</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">In vorig schrijven zeide ik U ik proeven nam <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>in Black &amp; White met het lith. krijt.</p><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Gij zegt te veel goeds van mij in Uw brief <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>doch dat gij goeds van mij denkt is dubbel reden <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>voor mij om te trachten ik het niet geheel onwaardig zij<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>En wat betreft dat ik zeide ik meende iets gevorderd <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>te zijn door die bewuste proeven<c type="kk">,</c> ik weet <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>zelf misschien niet goed mijn eigen werk <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>te zien. Misschien is het een stap vooruit<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>misschien niet – zeg gij er mij Uw <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>opinie eens over naar aanleiding <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>van bijgaande twee studies<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> welke ik dezer <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>dagen met meer anderen maakte.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Terwijl ik zoek naar een krachtiger procedé <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>dan waarmede ik tot hiertoe werkte, tracht ik mij <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>eenigermate te rigten naar de Engelsche reproducties <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>met het bewuste procede dat gij <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>beschreven hebt gemaakt – naar de zwarte <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>krabbels die Buhot op ’t staal papier maakte <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>ook – wat betreft de kracht van zwart.</p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">En zijt ge eens in de gelegenheid<c type="kk">,</c> spreek er <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>eens met een deskundige over of de <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>reproductie van teekeningen als b.v. deze <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>mogelijk zou zijn (afgescheiden van de tweede <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>kwestie<c type="kk">,</c> of deze of dergelijke naar hun specialen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>smaak zouden wezen)<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Wat betreft het sentiment er van<c type="kk">,</c> daarover <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>wil ik wel eens weten wat GIJ vindt<c type="kk">,</c> omdat <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>zooals ik zeide ik zelf niet weet te beoordeelen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>of er meer in is of niet.</p><lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Of liever<c type="kk">,</c> met mij zelf is het zoo gesteld dat <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>ik voor mijzelf studies als deze o.a.<c type="kk">,</c> ook al <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>zijn ze niet af en al is er veel in geheel <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>verwaarloosd<c type="kk">,</c> liever zie dan teekeningen die <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>een sujet hebben<c type="kk">,</c> omdat ik er eene levendige <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>herinnering door krijg van de natuur zelf. <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Gij zult mijne bedoeling begrijpen<c type="kk">,</c> in echte <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/><hi rend="italics">studies</hi> is iets van het leven zelf en de persoon <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>die het maakt zal niet zich zelf doch wel de natuur <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>daarin respecteeren en dus de <hi rend="italics">studie</hi> prefereeren <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>boven wat hij er mogelijk later van maken zal. <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>tenzij er iets geheel anders uit ontsta als eindresultaat <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>van véél studies<c type="kk">,</c> n.l. <hi rend="italics">de type</hi> geconcentreerd <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>uit veel <hi rend="italics">individu's</hi><c type="kp">.</c> Dat is het hoogste van de kunst 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>en <hi rend="italics">daar</hi> is soms de kunst boven de <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>natuur – – – als b.v. in Millets zaaier <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>meer ziel is dan in een gewoon zaaier op ’t veld<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Maar wat ik van U weten wil is <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>of het U voorkomt deze wijze van doen <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>sommige der bezwaren die gij tegen het <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>potlood hadt<c type="kk">,</c> misschien zou wegnemen. <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>Het zijn een paar “heads of the people” <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>en mijn voornemen zou wezen door veel <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>dergelijke dingen te zoeken <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>een soort geheel te vormen dat den titel <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>heads of the people niet geheel onwaardig zou zijn.</p><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Met veel werken<c type="kk">,</c> kerel<c type="kk">,</c> hoop ik <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>nog eens wat goeds te maken. <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>Ik heb het nog niet maar ik jaag <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>er naar en vecht er om<c type="kk">,</c> ik wou iets <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>ernstigs, iets frisch – iets waar ziel <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>in mogt wezen! Vooruit<c type="kk">,</c> vooruit<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Uit wat ik hierboven zei ziet ge duidelijk genoeg <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>dat ik meer begeerig ben om voor <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>reproductie een serieus werk bij elkaar te zoeken <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>dan wel dat ik voldaan zou zijn eens een <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>teekeningetje gedrukt te zien<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Maar alle informatie en wenken omtrent procedés <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>zijn mij hoogst welkom.</p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik zag in de vitrine van G&amp;C<hi rend="super">ie</hi> eene groote ets van <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Fortuny<c type="kk">,</c> Un anachorète<c type="kk">,</c> alsmede zijn twee mooie <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>Kabyle mort en la garde du mort<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> – ik had toen <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>erg spijt dat ik U onlangs gezegd had dat ik Fortuny <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>niet mooi vond<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> vind ik zeer mooi<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>Enfin dat begrijpt ge toch ook zelf wel.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Zoo is ’t met Boldini ook<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Maar dat serieuse dat Fortuny b.v. in <hi rend="italics">die</hi> drie etsen <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>had<c type="kk">,</c> dat juist mankeeren veel van zijn volgelingen die <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>geheel in het vaarwater vervallen eener manier waarvan F<c type="kp">.</c> b.v. in <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>“le choix d'un modèle”<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c. ’t voorbeeld gaf.</p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">En <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> staat lijnregt in oppositie tegenover <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>het sombere<c type="kk">,</c> nobele van Brion<c type="kk">,</c> van de Groux<c type="kk">,</c> Israels &amp;c.</p><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Als ge kunt<c type="kk">,</c> toe stuur mij eens een nommer <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>van de tegenwoordige Vie Moderne<c type="kk">,</c> er een uitzoekende <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>waar zulke reproducties in staan als waarover <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>gij schreeft. Hier ziet men ’t blad nergens (en wat ik <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>heb (een paar nummers) is van jaren her)<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20"><hi rend="italics">Als gij vroeger of later komt zal ik U meer laten</hi> <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/><hi rend="italics">kijken – en we kunnen dan spreken</hi> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/><hi rend="italics">over de toekomst</hi>. Gij weet genoeg hoe weinig ik geschikt ben <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>om ’t zij handelaars ’t zij liefhebbers aan te klampen<c type="kk">,</c> hoe zeer het mij <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>tegenstrijdig is bovendien. Ik wou zoo dol graag wij altijd <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>konden doorgaan als tot nu toe doch ik ben zoo dikwijls <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>er bedroefd over dat ik telkens U tot last moet zijn. <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>Maar wie weet of door den tijd het niet zoo te schikken <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>zou zijn dat gij er nog den een of ander voor kondt <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>opwarmen die U het pak van de schouders nam dat gij in <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>den moeielijksten tijd op U genomen hebt. Dat zou <hi rend="italics">dan</hi> <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>kunnen geschieden wanneer het geheel blijkbaar zal <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>zijn dat mijn werk serieus is, wanneer het duidelijker <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>spreken zal dan dit. <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>Ik heb een zeer eenvoudig leven te <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>lief dan dat ik <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> zou willen veranderen maar later <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>zullen wij om grooter dingen te doen ook grooter <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>uitgaven krijgen<c type="kp">.</c>– Ik zal steeds geloof ik druk met <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>model werken – altijd en altijd. En ik moet het <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>zoo ver brengen dat niet alles op U hoeft te drukken.</p><lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Dit is maar een begin – ge krijgt later mooier dingen <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>van me kerel! Voorloopig<c type="kk">,</c> laat me maar eens hooren <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>of ’t U voorkomt sommige der bezwaren van alleen potlood gebruiken <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>door het krijt er bij eenigermate uit den weg geruimd zouden kunnen <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>worden. Komt het U ook niet voor dat ik door ’t maken van dergelijke <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>teekeningen indirekt misschien dingen voor de eigentlijke lithographie leer.</p><lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">adieu<c type="kk">,</c> nogmaals dank voor Uw brief<c type="kk">,</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="129*" xml:id="l-129s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">t. à. t.</p><lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I wrote to you yesterday, but I’m doing so again today to report the safe arrival of your letter and to thank you for it, and to tell you that what you wrote raised my spirits.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I was a bit concerned that, because you’ve seen so little of my work recently, this might make you think that I’d begun to slacken off.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I have in fact been slogging away lately, and am still wrapped up in various things in which I begin to see light as to how to do them, but which I haven’t yet got the hang of as I would like.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">In my last letter I told you I was experimenting in Black and White with lithographic crayon.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">You speak too highly of me in your letter, but the fact that you think highly of me is an added reason for me to try not to be entirely unworthy of it. And as for my saying I believed I had made some progress through those experiments, it may be that I can’t see my own work properly. Perhaps it’s a step forward, perhaps not. Tell me your opinion about that based on the accompanying two studies,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> which I made in the past few days, together with some others. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">While I search for a more powerful process than the one I’ve worked with up to now, I try to be guided to some extent by the English reproductions made using the process you described — together with the black scratches <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_910">Buhot</rs> made on the sample paper — as to the strength of black.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">And if you get a chance, speak to an expert about whether it would be possible to reproduce drawings like these (as distinct from the second question of whether these or similar ones were to their particular taste).</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">As for their sentiment, I would like to know what YOU think about that, because, as I said, I myself can’t judge whether there’s more in them or not.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Or rather, my position is that for my part I’d rather see studies like these, even though they’re unfinished and even if much is completely neglected, than drawings that have a subject, because through them I get a vivid memory of nature itself. You’ll understand what I mean. True <hi rend="italics">studies</hi> have something of life itself, and the person who makes them will respect not himself but nature in them, and hence prefer the <hi rend="italics">study</hi> to what he may make of it later. Unless something entirely different arises from it as the final outcome of <hi rend="italics">many</hi> studies, namely <hi rend="italics">the type</hi> distilled from many <hi rend="italics">individuals</hi>. That is the highest art, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> and <hi rend="italics">in that</hi> art is sometimes above nature — — — as, for instance, in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s sower, in which there is more soul than in an ordinary sower in the field.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">But what I’d like to know from you is whether you think that this way of working would perhaps remove some of the objections you had to pencil. They’re a few ‘heads of the people’, and my intention would be to find a large number like these to try to form a sort of entity that wouldn’t be entirely unworthy of the title ‘heads of the people’.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Through working hard, old chap, I hope to make something good one day. I haven’t got it yet, but I’m hunting it and fighting for it, I want something serious, something fresh — something with soul in it! Onward, onward.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">You’ll see clearly enough from what I’ve said above that I’m more eager to put together a serious work for reproduction than to have the satisfaction of seeing one drawing printed some day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">But any information and tips as to processes are very welcome.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">In the window at G&amp;Cie I saw a large etching by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Fortuny</rs>, An anchorite, as well as his two beautiful The dead Kabyle and Watching over the dead man<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> — then I deeply regretted saying to you not long ago that I didn’t find Fortuny beautiful<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – <hi rend="italics">this</hi> I found extremely beautiful. Well, you’ll understand that yourself. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">It’s the same with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_887">Boldini</rs> too.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">But that seriousness that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Fortuny</rs> had, for instance, in <hi rend="italics">those</hi> three etchings is just what’s missing with many of his followers, who completely follow in his wake with a manner for which F. set the example in, say, ‘The choice of a model’<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> &amp;c. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">And <hi rend="italics">that</hi> is the direct opposite of the sombre, noble quality of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_891">Brion</rs>, of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">When you can, do send me an issue of the current Vie Moderne, look for one with reproductions like the ones you wrote about. The magazine is nowhere to be found here (and what I have ((a few issues)) is years old).<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20"><hi rend="italics">I’ll show you more when you come, sooner or later — and then we can talk about the future</hi>. You know well enough how little suited I am to approaching either dealers or art lovers, and moreover how it goes against the grain for me. I so dearly wish that we could always carry on as in the past, but I’m often so sad about having to trouble you again and again. But who knows whether in time it mightn’t be possible for you to interest someone or other who could take the load off your shoulders that you’ve borne in the most difficult time. That could be done <hi rend="italics">when</hi> it’s clearly evident that my work is serious, at which time it will have more appeal than this. I’m too fond of my very simple life to want to change <hi rend="italics">it</hi>, but later on we’ll have to incur greater expenses to do greater things. I believe I’ll always work with a model a lot — always and always. And I must get things to the point where not everything rests on your shoulders.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">This is only a beginning — later you’ll get fine things from me, old chap! For the time being, let me know whether you think some of the objections to using pencil alone could be removed somewhat by using crayon as well. Don’t you also agree that by making these drawings I may also indirectly learn things about lithography proper?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Adieu, thanks again for your letter, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Van Gogh says: ‘I wrote to you yesterday’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>. This was <ref target="let297.xml">letter 297</ref>, of Tuesday, 2 January 1883; this means that the present letter dates from Wednesday, 3 January 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Consignment of paper from Buhot <ref target="let280.xml">(280)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>It is not known which studies these are. They are heads in any case, ‘heads of the people’: see <ref target="#l-67">l. 67</ref> and <ref target="let300.xml">letter 300</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>For Millet’s <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1888">Sower</rs>, <ref target="let156.xml#n-3">see letter 156, n. 3</ref>. In ‘Salon de 1861’ <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_554">E.J.T. Thoré</rs> had written about the idea that the <hi rend="italics">type</hi> was the highest that could be attained, and he also linked it to <hi rend="italics">The sower</hi>: ‘<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> does not have <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_962">Courbet</rs>’s brilliance as a colourist; he is more monotonous, but no less precise in his sobriety. He does not seem to be preoccupied with practice, although he achieves a solidity of form that has something statuesque about it; his figures are generous, and in some way fully modelled. What preoccupies him is the essential character of the figure he is trying to create. Doing a <hi rend="italics">sower</hi>, for example, he would have the ambition that it would be <hi rend="italics">the </hi>sower, in general, the very type of the thing, just as in the Bible, or in Homer. And truly, he has grandeur, by dint of sheer simplicity. And yet he also lacks a certain distinction of taste, which holds him back, like Courbet, on a rung of the ladder that the great artists have climbed’. (Millet n’a pas l’éclat de Courbet comme coloriste; il est plus monotone, mais non moins juste dans sa sobriété. La pratique ne semble pas le préoccuper, quoiqu’il arrive à une solidité de formes qui tient de la statuaire; ses figures sont pleines et en quelque sorte modelées jusqu’à au fond. Ce qui le préoccupe, c’est le caractère essentiel du personnage qu’il entend créer. Faisant un <hi rend="italics">semeur</hi>, par exemple, il aurait l’ambition que ce fût <hi rend="italics">le</hi> Semeur en général, le type même de la chose, toujours comme dans la Bible ou dans Homère. Et vraiment, il a de la grandeur, à force de simplicité. A lui aussi cependant manque je ne sais quelle distinction de goût, ce qui l’arrête, comme Courbet, à un certain degré de l’échelle qu’ont escaladée les grands artistes). See <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_545">Salons de W. Bürger, 1861 à 1868</ref></hi>, vol. 1. Paris 1870, pp. 100-101. It is evident from <ref target="let534.xml">letter 534</ref> that Van Gogh had read this review.</p>

<p rend="indent">In a letter of 15 February 1873 to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_688">Camille Lemonnier</rs> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs> said that he wanted to express the true in the type: ‘I assure you, sir, that if it were only a matter of my purpose, I would express very forcefully the type, which is, to my mind, the most potent truth. You are entirely right in attributing to me the intention of doing so’. (Je vous assure, monsieur, que, s’il n’en tenait qu’à ma volonté, j’exprimerais bien fortement le type qui est, à mon sens, la plus puissante vérité. Vous êtes bien dans le vrai en m’attribuant l’intention de le faire). Sensier 1881, p. 354.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Mariano José Maria Bernardo Fortuny y Carbó</rs>, <hi rend="italics">An anchorite</hi>, c. 1867 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_93">Ill. 93</rs>; <hi rend="italics">Kabyle mort</hi> (The dead Kabyle) 1867 (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_94">Ill. 94</rs>. <hi rend="italics">La garde du mort</hi> (Watching over the dead man) refers to <hi rend="italics">Arabe veillant le corps de son ami</hi> (An Arab watching over the body of his dead friend) (1866) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_95">Ill. 95</rs>. From 1878 Goupil published 27 etchings by Fortuny, including the three mentioned. See <hi rend="italics">Cat. Goupil</hi> 1878 (Octobre), p. 2 (without dimensions). Goupil published the fourth state (26.6 x 45 cm). See Vives 1991, pp. 85-92, 133-137, cat. nos. 1, 2, 16.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh wrote this in <ref target="let291.xml">letter 291</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1029">Mariano José Maria Bernardo Fortuny y Carbó</rs>, <hi rend="italics">The choice of a model</hi>, 1866-1874 (Washington, Corcoran Gallery of Art). Also included as a photograph in the series <hi rend="italics">Oeuvres de Fortuny</hi> published by Goupil, Galerie photographique (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2025">Ill. 2025</rs>. See also Eugène Montrosier, <hi rend="italics">Les artistes modernes</hi>, part 1. Paris 1881, p. 36.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>For the issues of <hi rend="italics">La Vie Moderne</hi> that Van Gogh had, cf. <ref target="let283.xml#n-9">letter 283, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    