<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 27 May 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let231"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b224 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>231</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>202</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>230</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-05-27">Saturday, 27 May 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0224" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0224" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000264_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Heden, Zaturdag, heb ik een bezoek gehad van <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Rappard &amp; ik ben er blij om dat hij er eens is <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>geweest. Hij vroeg ook zeer naar U.–</p><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Hij heeft onder anderen de teekeningen gezien <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>waaraan ik voor C.M. werk en die schenen <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>hem te bevallen<c type="kk">,</c> vooral een groote van <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>het hofje of binnenplaatsje waar de moeder van <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Sien woont.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ik wou wel dat gij die ook eens zaagt <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>alsmede een andere van een timmermans<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>loods en werf waar kleine figuurtjes bezig zijn<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Van perspectief is die nog vrij wat gecompliceerder <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>dan de Laan v<c type="kp">.</c> Meerdervoort die ik U zond<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>en er is sjouwerij genoeg aan geweest.</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Gij moet weten dat ik tegenwoordig s’morgens <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>4 uur al buiten zit omdat het op den <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>dag te moeielijk is op straat te zitten wegens de <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>voorbijgangers &amp; straatjongens &amp; ook het mooiste <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>moment om de groote lijnen te zien als <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>de dingen nog toonig zijn.</p><lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Maar kerel<c type="kk">,</c> het is anders een bange 14 <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>daag voor mij geweest. Toen ik U schreef <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>omstreeks half Mei<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> had ik nog maar f<c type="kp">.</c> 3 of <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>f<c type="kp">.</c> 3.<hi rend="super">50</hi> toen ik de bakker betaald had. En <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>heb zoogoed als niets anders gehad dan <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>droog roggebrood met wat koffij &amp; Sien ook. <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Omdat wij goed voor haar kindje hadden gekocht en <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>zij naar Leiden was geweest &amp;c.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Nu is 1 Junij de huishuur en ik heb <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>niets<c type="kk">,</c> letterlijk niets. Ik hoop gij zenden <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>zult.</p><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Ik was een week geleden vreesselijk slap <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>door aanhoudende <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>slapeloosheid<c type="kp">.</c> Nu ik met eenige teekeningen <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>voorspoed had zoodat de bestelling van <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>C.M. zeer ver op weg is en ik <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>daardoor weer wat goeden moed kreeg<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>ben ik weer wat kalmer geworden. <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>Doch kerel, toe, schrijf mij spoedig en <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>verlos mij van den huisheer<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> want gij <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>weet dat die van geen uitstel weten.</p><lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Het bezoek van Rappard heeft mij opgemonterd<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>hij schijnt terdeeg te werken.</p><lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Ik heb f<c type="kp">.</c> 2.<hi rend="super">50</hi> van hem gekregen omdat <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>hij een scheurtje in een teekening zag en <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>zei<c type="kk">,</c> dat moet ge laten maken – <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>ja wel<c type="kk">,</c> zei ik<c type="kk">,</c> maar ik heb het niet <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>en toch moet de teekening weg. Toen <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>zei hij dadelijk dat hij ’t mij graag geven <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>wou en ik had nog meer kunnen krijgen <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>doch wilde niet en gaf hem een <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>heele partij houtsneden en een teekening <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>er voor.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Het was er een voor C.M<c type="kp">.</c> en <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>dus was het mij hoogst welkom dat ik ze <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>in orde kon krijgen omdat het de beste <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>van allen was.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Die zelfde teekening wordt later <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>misschien voor f<c type="kp">.</c> 50 of zoo verkocht <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>en nu – – had ik niet<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> om een scheurtje <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>er in te laten repareeren.</p><lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Enfin<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Ik hoop zoo, broer, dat gij geen kwaad <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>denkt van Sien &amp; mij – die meid heeft <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>door mijn onaangenamen kant heen <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>gebeten en zij begrijpt mij in veel dingen <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>beter dan anderen.</p><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Zij is zóó gewillig om in alles te helpen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>dat ik U niet zeggen kan hoe nuttig <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>zij mij is<c type="kk">,</c> word ik eens driftig <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>’t zij bij ’t poseeren ’t zij over iets anders<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zij weet wat er van te denken en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>heeft gezien dat zulks niet diep bij mij <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>zit. Evenzoo<c type="kk">,</c> als ik tob of zanik over <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>iets dat niet vlot weet zij mij dikwijls weer <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>tot rust te brengen<c type="kk">,</c> wat ik mij zelf niet <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>zou kunnen doen.–</p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">En zij is zuinig en schikt zich naar <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>ons stuk roggebrood als ’t moet<c type="kk">,</c> zonder <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>er mistroostig om te worden. <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>’t Geen ik ook niet doe als wij maar <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>rondkomen.</p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik hoop dat gij de teekeningen ontvangen <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>hebt<c type="kk">,</c> door mij omstreeks 10 Mei geloof ik <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>afgezonden<c type="kk">,</c> een 25tal in portefeuille<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>ik heb daar nog niets van gehoord<c type="kp">.</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Ik wou zoo graag dat er nog een paar <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>lui waren voor wie ik wat maken kon <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>op soortgelijke condities als C.M. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/><hi rend="italics">En vooral dat C.M<c type="kp">.</c> maar volhoudt</hi> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>want nu deze teekeningen zijn veel <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>beter dan de eersten en gaandeweg <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>zal ik er nog beteren leveren<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">En tegen dien prijs kan hij er toch zeker <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>geen kwaad mee.</p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Ge weet er alles van<c type="kk">,</c> indien <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>gij om reden van Sien mij niet <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>verlaat dan ben ik vol goeden <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>moed<c type="kp">.</c>– En ik zit klokke <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>4 al aan mijn werk dus <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>met wat sympathie van zulken die <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>mij kennen zal ik er mij boven op <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>werken.</p><lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Ik hoop op Uw brief – ontvang in <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>gedachten een handdruk maar <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>vooral<c type="kk">,</c> schrijf spoedig en verlos <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>mij van den huisheer.</p><lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">à Dieu<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">t. à t.</p><lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Today, Saturday, I had a visit from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>, and I’m glad that now he has been here. He also asked after you with great interest. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">He saw the drawings I’m doing for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">C.M.</rs> among other things, and they seem to please him, especially a large one of the courtyard or back yard at the house where Sien’s <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_464">mother</rs> lives.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I would like you to see that one, as well as another of a carpenter’s shed and yard with small figures at work.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> The perspective is rather more complicated than in the Laan van Meerdervoort I sent you,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and I’ve laboured long and hard on it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I must tell you that these days I’m already out of doors by 4 o’clock in the morning, because during the day it’s too difficult to be on the street on account of the passers-by and the urchins, and because that’s the best time to see the broad outlines while things still have tone.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">But, old chap, this has been an anxious fortnight for me. When I wrote to you around the middle of May,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> all I had left was 3 or 3.50 guilders after paying the baker. I had practically nothing else to eat but dry black bread with a little coffee, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> too. Because we’d bought linen for her <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_466">baby</rs> and she’d been to Leiden &amp;c. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">The rent is due on 1 June, and I have nothing, literally nothing. I hope you’ll send something. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">A week ago I was terribly weak due to constant sleeplessness. But now I’m making good progress with several drawings, so that the order for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> is well advanced, and as a result I’m in better spirits, I’m somewhat calmer again. Still, old chap, write to me soon and save me from the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_812">landlord</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> because, as you know, their kind brook no delay. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs>’s visit cheered me up; he seems to be working hard.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">He gave me 2.50 guilders because he saw a tear in a drawing and said, you should have that repaired. I know, I said, but I haven’t got the money and the drawing must be sent off. Then he said straightaway that he’d be glad to give it to me, and I could have had more but I didn’t want to, and I gave him a pile of woodcuts and a drawing<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> in return. It was one of those meant for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.,</rs> and so I was very glad to be able to get it repaired, because it was the best of them all. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">That same drawing may be sold later for 50 guilders or so, and now — I hadn’t got the money to have a tear in it repaired. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Anyway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">I do hope, brother, that you don’t think badly of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs> and me. That lass has put up with my disagreeable side, and in many respects she understands me better than others. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">She’s so willing to help in everything that I can’t tell you how useful she is to me. If I get angry while she’s posing or about something else, she knows how to take it, and has seen that it doesn’t go deep with me. Equally, if I fret or grumble about something that isn’t going well, she often manages to calm me down, which I couldn’t do myself. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">And she’s thrifty and accepts our piece of black bread if need be, without becoming despondent. And so do I, as long as we get by.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I hope that you’ve received the drawings I sent around 10 May, I think, two dozen in a portfolio.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I’ve heard nothing about it yet. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I do wish there were a few more people I could do work for on the same sort of conditions as for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> <hi rend="italics">And above all that C.M. perseveres</hi>, for these drawings are much better than the first, and gradually I’ll produce even better ones. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">And at that price, he can’t go wrong. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">You know all about it: I’ll be in good spirits as long as you don’t desert me because of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Sien</rs>. I’m at work on the dot of 4, so with a little sympathy from those who know me I’ll get on top of things. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">I’m hoping for your letter. Accept a handshake in thought, but above all write soon and save me from the landlord.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Adieu.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>The letter was written on a Saturday <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, and Vincent asks Theo urgently to send money because ‘The rent is due on 1 June’ <ref target="#l-29">(l. 29)</ref>. On the basis of this the letter can be dated to Saturday, 27 May 1882. This date corresponds with that assigned to the letter by Jo van Gogh-Bonger in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914 – she may have seen a postmark.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Second order for drawings from Uncle Cor <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The house in Slijkeinde, corner of Breedstraat 31a. There are two drawings of the court: <hi rend="italics">Sien’s mother’s house</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2373">F 941 / JH 146</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Sien’s mother’s house </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2374">F 942 / JH 147</rs>); the large one mentioned is the second, which measures 46 x 59.5 cm – the first is 29 x 45 cm. Cf. exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 50-51.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2375">F 939 / JH 150</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This drawing of the vegetable gardens in Laan van Meerdervoort sent in April is not known. <ref target="let218.xml">See letter 218</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The letter meant was <ref target="let229.xml">letter 229</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
 
<p>The landlord was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_63">A.J. van der Drift</rs>; <ref target="let222.xml">see letter 222</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The drawing in question would have been <hi rend="italics">Sorrow</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2364">F 929 / JH 129</rs>), which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Van Rappard</rs> had had in his possession. See also De la Faille 1970, p. 346.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘niets, geen cent’ (nothing, not a cent).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For the sending of these drawings and sketches, <ref target="let226.xml">see letter 226</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    