<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Saturday, 14 January 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let200"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b191 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>200</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>170</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>199</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1882-01-14">on or about Saturday, 14 January 1882</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0191" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0191" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000217_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Beste broer,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Net als ik wel meer gedaan heb schreef ik U in mijn <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>laatsten brief kort &amp; bondig een antwoord op een &amp; ander <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>maar in harde woorden die evenwel toch werkelijk <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>uitdrukken hoe ik er over denk doch gij moet <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>daarom niet denken dat ik altijd in een koude barre <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>stemming ben die Mauve misschien een groene <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>zeep<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> stemming of zoutwater stemming zou noemen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Nu maar al had ik nu eens een groenezeepbrief <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>of zoutwater brief geschreven<c type="kk">,</c> dat is toch niet erger <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>dan dat ik het al te sentimenteel had opgevat.–</p><lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Gij zegt<c type="kk">,</c> ge zult er eens erg spijt van hebben<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Kerel ik geloof dat ik veel van dien spijt &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c> gehad <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>heb vòòr dien tijd. Ik zag het aankomen &amp; zocht <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>het te coupeeren<c type="kk">,</c> nu dat is niet gelukt en enfin<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>wat gebeurd is is gebeurd. Zal ik er nu nog spijt over <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>hebben<c type="kp">.</c> neen<c type="kk">,</c> eigentlijk heb ik zelfs geen tijd om <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>spijt te hebben. Het teekenen wordt hoe langer hoe <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>meer een hartstogt bij me en dat is net een hartstogt <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>als die van een zeeman voor de zee<c type="kp">.</c> Mauve heeft <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>mij nu een nieuwen weg gewezen om iets te kunnen <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>maken<c type="kk">,</c> n.l. het aquarelleeren. Nu daar verdiep <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ik mij nu in en zit te smeeren &amp; weer uit te <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>wasschen<c type="kk">,</c> enfin te zoeken &amp; te streven.</p><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Puisqu’il faut faire des efforts de perdu.</p><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Puisque l’execution d’une aquarelle a quelque <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>chose de diabolique<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Puisqu’il y a du bon en tout mouvement énergique<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Dus ofschoon ik van plan was om U nog uitvoeriger <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>te schrijven over het voorgevallene t’huis en te probeeren <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>de zaken uiteen te zetten zoo als ze mij toeschijnen te <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>zijn<c type="kk">,</c> ofschoon ik bovendien graag ook nog over <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>andere onderwerpen U een &amp; ander zeggen wou<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>ik heb er nu geen tijd voor en ik vind het beter <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>ik U nog eens over het teekenen schrijf.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Ik ben dadelijk behalve een paar kleine <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>ook een groote aquarel begonnen<c type="kk">,</c> op zijn <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>minst zoo groot als een van die figuurstudies <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>die ik te Etten maakte.</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Nu spreekt het van zelf dat dat zoo maar niet in <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>eens goed &amp; grif van stapel loopt.</p><lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Mauve zelf zegt me dat ik op zijn minst <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>een stuk of 10 teekeningen verknoeien zal <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>voor ik zoowat het penseel weet te hanteeren<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>Nu maar daarachter zit een betere toekomst <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>dus werk ik door met zooveel koelbloedigheid <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>als ik verzamelen kan en ook door mijn fouten <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>laat ik me niet afschrikken.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Dit is een <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>schetsje <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>van een <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>van de <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>kleine aquarellen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>het is een hoekje <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>van mijn atelier <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>met een meisje <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>dat koffij zit te malen.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Gij ziet ik zoek naar toon<c type="kk">,</c> een kopje of een handje dat <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>gloeit en waar leven in zit en dat uitkomt tegen <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>een dommelenden achtergrond<c type="kk">,</c> schemerend<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>en dan brutaal daar tegen uit dat brok <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>schoorsteen en kagchel<c type="kk">,</c> ijzer &amp; steen, en een <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>planken vloer. Als ik die teekening naar <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>mijn zin kon krijgen dan zou ik er op zijn <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>minst 3/4 van in groenezeep stijl maken en 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>dan alleen dat hoekje waar dat kindje zit <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>teer en zacht en met sentiment behandelen. <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>Maar gij begrijpt ik kan dat alles nog niet zoo <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>uitdrukken zoo als ik het voel maar de zaak is maar<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>dunkt me<c type="kk">,</c> de moeielijkheden aangrijpen<c type="kk">,</c> en <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>het groenezeep gedeelte is nog niet groenezeepachtig <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>genoeg en de teerheid daar tegenover niet teer genoeg. <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Maar enfin de schets is er toch opgedonderd en <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>de opvatting is er en me dunkt die is raisonable. Nu spreekt het van zelf dat <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>men de techniek niet den eersten dag meester is.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Nu dit is ’t sujet van <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>de groote teekening<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>maar ik doe het in <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>haast en het schetsje is <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>afschuwelijk. Evenwel <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>mogelijk geeft het U een <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gedacht en het staat er <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>nu eenmaal op.</p><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Ik hoor dat er vandaag <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>iemand voor me geweest is<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>ik denk de Hr. Tersteeg. <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>Dat wou ik wel want <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>hij heeft me beloofd dat hij <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>zou komen opdokken <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>en ik wou hem wel <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>eens spreken over een <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>en ander.</p><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Hij zou morgen ochtend <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>terug komen.</p><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Theo ik heb veel <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>gescharrel met de modellen<c type="kk">,</c> ik zoek ze en als ik ze vind dan <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>is het een toer om ze op ’t atelier te krijgen en dan laten ze me <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>soms in den steek<c type="kp">.</c> Net als van morgen een smidsjongen<c type="kk">,</c> die kon <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>niet komen omdat zijn vader zei dat ik een gulden per uur <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>betalen moest<c type="kk">,</c> nu daar had ik natuurlijk geen trek in.</p><lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Morgen heb ik weer ’t model van het oud vrouwtje<c type="kk">,</c> maar 3 dagen <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>achtereen kon ze niet komen. Nu dan, als ik uitga zit ik nog al eens in <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>de volksgaarkeuken of in de wachtkamer 3<hi rend="super">e</hi> klasse<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> of dergelijke localiteiten te <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>krabbelen.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Maar buiten is het zoo verdomd koud<c type="kk">,</c> vooral voor mij die nog niet <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>zoo vlug teeken als meer geoefenden en mijn schetsjes eigentlijk meer uitvoerig moet afmaken <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>om er iets aan te hebben.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Zoodat ge ziet dat ik niet stilzit en mij voorloopig niet meer verdiep in Etten <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>maar zoek hier wortel te schieten. Het spreekt van zelf dat de modellen <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>me geld kosten en ik moet U zeggen dat ik zelf ook het noodige neem <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>ofschoon zoo goedkoop mogelijk. (ik ga in de gaarkeuken eten<c type="kp">.</c>) En toch <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>zult gij denk ik er geen bezwaar in zien dat ik doorga. Doch <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>’t geen ik in mijn vorigen brief reeds zeide dat herhaal ik nog eens<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>laat mij zoo naauwkeurig mogelijk weten waaraan ik mij te <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>houden heb en was het mogelijk dat gij met de Hr Tersteeg een <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>afspraak kondt maken zoodat ik in geval van moeielijkheid <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>zonder er al te veel tegenop te zien naar hem toe kan gaan<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>dat zou ik erg best vinden. Ik voor mij beloof U dat ik <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>werken zal wat ik kan doch het hangt b.v. met modellen <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>dikwijls af van het geld dat ik in mijn zak heb of <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>niet heb<c type="kk">,</c> of ik <hi rend="italics">full speed</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <hi rend="italics">half speed</hi> of <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>soms <hi rend="italics">in ’t geheel niet</hi> te werk kan gaan. Zoo <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>ben ik nu in besprek met een moeder met <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>een kindje<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> doch ik vrees het me te duur zou <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>uitkomen. Weet het wel dat ik het liefst full speed <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>ga maar.... enfin ge begrijpt er alles van<c type="kk">,</c> ik moet <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>mijzelven nog inhouden tot er wat meer ruimte <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>en vrijheid komt. Schrijf mij weer eens spoedig en <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>hoor eens<c type="kk">,</c> zend in Februarij het geld zoo spoedig <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>mogelijk want ik weet zeker dat ik tegen dien tijd <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>geen cent meer heb.</p><lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>
      
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Ik heb plan om toch tusschen de droppeltjes door<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>voortdurend kleine penteekeningetjes te gaan maken <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>maar op een andere manier dan die groote van dezen <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>zomer.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Wat vinniger en wat nijdiger<c type="kp">.</c> Dit is een schetsje </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">van de Schenkweg<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>het gezigt uit <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>mijn raam.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Nu adieu<c type="kk">,</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="138*" xml:id="l-138s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">t. à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">As I’ve often done, I sent you an answer in my last letter that was brief and to the point about one thing and another, yet in harsh words that nevertheless truly express what I think about things, but you mustn’t think that I’m always in a gruff, cold-hearted mood which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> would perhaps call a yellow soap<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> mood or saltwater mood. But even if I had written a yellow soap letter or a saltwater letter, surely that’s no worse than taking things too sentimentally.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">You say, ‘you’ll truly regret it some day’. Old chap, I believe that I’ve had many such regrets &amp;c. before now. I saw it coming and tried to nip it in the bud, well that didn’t work, and anyway, what happened, happened. Will I now regret it? No, actually I don’t have time for regrets. Drawing is becoming more and more of a passion, and it’s just like a sailor’s passion for the sea. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> has now shown me a new way to make something, namely watercolours. Well, now I’m immersed in that, and I’m daubing and washing out, in short, seeking and striving.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">For one must make desperate attempts.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Because there’s something diabolical about the execution of a watercolour.</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6"> Because there’s something good in all energetic movement.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">So although I was planning to write to you in even more detail about what happened at home, to try and explain how things stand from my point of view, even though I also wanted to tell you this and that about other subjects, I haven’t time for that now, and think it better to write to you again about drawing. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">In addition to a couple of small watercolours, I’ve just started a large one, at least as large as one of those figure studies I made at Etten.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Naturally it doesn’t automatically go well and easily straightaway.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> himself says that I’ll ruin at least 10 drawings or so before I know how to handle the brush a little. But it will lead to a brighter future, so I work on with as much cold-bloodedness as I can muster, and don’t let myself be deterred by my mistakes.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">This is a little sketch of one of the small watercolours, it’s a corner of my studio with a girl grinding coffee.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">You see I’m looking for tone, a head or a hand that glows, with life in it, and that stands out against a drowsy background, twilit, and standing out boldly against that, that fragment of fireplace and stove, iron and brick, and a wooden floor. If I could get that drawing the way I’d like it, I’d make at least 3/4 of it in yellow soap style and 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> treat only that corner where the child is sitting delicately and tenderly and with sentiment. But you understand that I still can’t express all of that as I feel it, but it seems to me the point is simply to attack the difficulties, and the yellow soap passage still isn’t yellow soapy enough and the contrasting tenderness still not tender enough. But anyway, the sketch is still chucked on and its conception is clear, and to me it seems fairly good. Of course one can’t master the technique the first day.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">This is the subject of the large drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> but I’m doing it in a hurry and the sketch is terrible. Even so, perhaps it gives you an idea, and in any case it’s already on paper.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I hear that someone called on me today, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs>, I think. I hope so, because he promised me he’d stop by, and I wanted to discuss some things with him.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">He’s supposed to be coming back tomorrow morning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Theo, I’m having a lot of trouble with the models, I search for them and when I find them it’s a struggle to get them to come to my studio, and sometimes they let me down. Like a smith’s boy this morning, who couldn’t come because his father said that I had to pay a guilder an hour, and of course I wasn’t inclined to do that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Tomorrow I have the little old woman as a model again, but she couldn’t come for 3 days running. Well then, when I go out, I quite often go to sketch in the soup kitchen or the 3rd-class waiting room<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> or such places.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> But it’s so damned cold outdoors, especially for me, since I don’t yet draw as fast as more practised draughtsmen, and actually have to work my drawings out in more detail for them to be of any use to me. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">So you see I’m not standing still and am no longer dwelling on Etten, but am trying to put down roots here. Naturally the models cost me money, and I must tell you that I buy what’s necessary for myself, though the cheapest possible. (I go to the soup kitchen to eat.) And yet I trust you won’t have any objections to my continuing. But I repeat what I said in my last letter: let me know as precisely as possible where I stand, and I think it would be fine if you could come to an agreement with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Mr Tersteeg</rs>, so that in case of difficulty I can go to him without too many misgivings. For my part I promise you that I’ll work as much as I can, though things like models often depend on the money I do or don’t have in my pocket, whether I can set to work at <hi rend="italics">full speed, half speed</hi> or sometimes <hi rend="italics">not at all</hi>. Now, for instance, I’m negotiating with a mother with a little child,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> though I’m afraid it will turn out to be too expensive for me. Be assured that I’d prefer to go full speed but... anyway, you understand it all, I have to restrain myself until I have more resources and freedom. Write to me again soon, and listen, send the money as soon as possible in February, because I’m sure I won’t have a penny by then.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">I’m planning to go on making small pen drawings whenever possible,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but different from the large ones I made this summer.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> A bit sharper and a bit angrier. This is a sketch</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">of Schenkweg, the view from my window.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">Well, adieu, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.25" n="25">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>The letter provides an account (cf. <ref target="#l-36">ll. 36</ref> ff.) of Van Gogh’s first working days since his previous letter of Sunday, 8 or Monday, 9 January 1881. The number of days cannot be determined exactly, but the letter appears to have been written at the latest during the weekend starting Saturday, 14 January, because the following letter (<ref target="let201.xml">201</ref> of Saturday, 21 January) tells about the <hi rend="italics">then</hi> past week. We have therefore dated the letter to on or about Saturday, 14 January 1882.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Vincent’s quarrel with his parents <ref target="let194.xml">(194)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Mauve gives Van Gogh advice <ref target="let192.xml">(192)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Yellow soap, a common soap made of linseed, rapeseed and other vegetable oils. It is a soft soap, and is also used to soften the skin to aid in the removal of a wood splinter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Because Van Gogh says in <ref target="let322.xml">letter 322</ref> that a ‘nice saying’ is ‘There’s something diabolical about watercolour’, there is a good chance that this is a quotation.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>This watercolour of a girl grinding coffee is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This watercolour of a woman knitting is not known, but it is assumed to be the watercolour <hi rend="italics">Woman at the window, knitting</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_687">F 910a / JH 90</rs>), which measures 33 x 26 cm. Although the motif is the same, the position of the knitting woman and the composition (with the chair) differ from the letter sketch (cf. Hulsker 1993-1, p. 35, and <ref target="let205.xml">see letter 205</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The Hague had various soup kitchens where the poor could get food: the so-called <hi rend="italics">’s-Gravenhaagsche Volksgaarkeukens</hi> at Torenstraat 19 and Stationsweg 26, and several private charitable institutions. Van Gogh is probably referring here to one of the municipal institutions (cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 211, and <hi rend="italics">Adresboeken 1882-1883</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The third-class waiting room in the Rijnspoor railway station, near Schenkweg in The Hague. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, p. 41. An example of a drawing made there is <hi rend="italics">Waiting room</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_688">F 909 / JH 94</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
      
<p>This ‘mother with a little child’ was most likely <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_463">Clasina Maria Hoornik</rs>, called ‘Christien’ or ‘Sien’, and her four-year-old daughter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_467">Maria Wilhelmina Hoornik</rs>; cf. <ref target="let207.xml#n-2">letter 207, n. 2</ref> and <ref target="let228.xml">letter 228</ref>: ‘at the end of January I met Christien’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            
      
<p>An expression meaning ‘to make use of opportune moments’ (translated in this letter as ‘whenever possible’), though in the context of this letter it could have been intended literally: in between the showers.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            
<p>In the summer of 1881 Van Gogh usually drew on large sheets, varying in size from c. 30-50 cm x c. 50-60 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The watercolour matching this description is <hi rend="italics">Meadows beside Schenkweg</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2354">F 910 / JH 99</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    