<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Monday, 11 June 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let352"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b315 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>352</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>292</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>354</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-06-11">on or about Monday, 11 June 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0315" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000396_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000396_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0315" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000396_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000396_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000396_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Uw brief &amp; inhoud was me <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>regt welkom, hartelijk dank er voor.</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">En deed ’t me genoegen te zien ge de dingen <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>bedaard opneemt<c type="kk">,</c> wat trouwens ik dan ook niet <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>anders dacht. ik bedoel betreffende de <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>gemaakte bezwaren.</p><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Nu<c type="kk">,</c> sedert ik laatst schreef heb ik erg getobt op <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>die teekening van den mestvaalt.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Het is <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>een prachtig geval<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">De eerste teekening er van heeft reeds zoo veel <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>veranderingen ondergaan – nu eens hier wit<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>dan weer zwart geweest op verschillende plaatsen – <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>dat ik het overgebragt heb op een tweede papier <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>omdat het eerste te gefatigueerd was<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> En ben nu daarop <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>op nieuw bezig. Ik moet er s’morgens vroeg <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>voor op want dan zie ik de effekten die ik <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>hebben moet. Kon ik ’t maar zóó krijgen als <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ik ’t in mijn gedachten heb.</p><lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Nu<c type="kk">,</c> die tweede is op de zelfde grootte als de <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>twee vroegeren van de veenderij &amp; zandgraving<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>&amp; kan in de lijst. Op dit moment is er <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>wel effekt in doch ik vrees ik ’t weer bederven <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>zal. Maar daar moet men ook al niet <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>bang voor zijn anders komt men er nooit. <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>En tusschen de bedrijven in heb ik nog een <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>groote studie van eene naaister gemaakt.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Maar ik heb eene teleurstelling gehad met het <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Weeshuis in dit opzigt dat de permissie om er te teekenen <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>mij <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> is gegeven – er waren<c type="kk">,</c> zeide men<c type="kk">,</c> geen <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>antecedenten van dien aard en bovendien ging <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>men schoonmaken en nieuwe vloeren leggen in <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>de zalen. Enfin dit is nu zoo erg niet want <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>er zijn meer weeshuizen<c type="kk">,</c> alleen in <hi rend="italics">dit</hi> ken ik <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>een man die ik geregeld tot model heb en dat <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zou me ’t maken van schetsen gemakkelijker hebben <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>gemaakt.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Verl. winter zag ik ’t Oude mannenhuis <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>te Voorburg.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Natuurlijk kleiner <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>maar haast nog typiger.</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Toen op dien dag<c type="kk">,</c> ’t was tegen den avond<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zaten de oudjes op banken &amp; stoelen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>rond een oude kolomkagchel<c type="kk">,</c> heel <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>echt.</p><lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Misschien ga ik dat te Voorburg probeeren <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>nu ik hier niet teregt kan.</p><lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Was ook een dag op Schevening &amp; <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>zag daar een mooi geval van kerels <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>met een wagen vol netten die getaand<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>waren &amp; op de duinen werden uitgespreid<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Ik zal dat of ’t netten <hi rend="italics">verstellen</hi> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>bepaald eens aangrijpen in groote <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>teekening.</p><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">’t Is wel een verbetering Theo<c type="kk">,</c> dat ik <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>die ramen &amp; lijst heb laten maken <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>voor fusains of wat ’t ook zij want dat <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>werkt pleizierig.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Wat ge zegt van te veel omgang met <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>schilders <hi rend="italics">niet</hi> goed maar eenigen omgang <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wel<c type="kk">,</c> vind ik wel waar. En ben om die <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>reden ook blij v.d. Weele komt<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Ja men kan wel eens ’t heimwee hebben <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>om met lui die wat weten te <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>praten er over<c type="kp">.</c> En vooral als <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>men in één zelfden geest werkt <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>en zoekt kan men elkaar zeer veel <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>sterken en animeeren en wordt niet zoo <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>ligt gedecourageerd.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">men kan niet altijd buiten het vaderland <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>leven<c type="kk">,</c> en ’t vaderland is niet de natuur <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>alleen maar er moet bij komen menschenharten <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>die ’t zelfde zoeken &amp; voelen<c type="kp">.</c> En dan is ’t vaderland <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>pas compleet &amp; voelt men zich t’huis.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Dit is nu de compositie van de mestvaalt<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>’K weet niet in hoever ge er uit wijs kunt worden. <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Voorop wijven die aschbakken leegen<c type="kk">,</c> daarachter de <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>loodsen waar de mest bewaard wordt en de kerels aan <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>’t werk met kruiwagens &amp;c.</p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">De eerste die ik maakte er van was eenigzins anders<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>er stonden n.l. twee andere kerels op den voorgrond <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>met zuidwesters die ze bij slecht weer dikwijls dragen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>en was de groep vrouwen meer in toon.</p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Doch dat lichteffekt is er werkelijk<c type="kk">,</c> daar ’t licht <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>van boven tusschen de loodsen invalt op de <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>figuren die in de gangpaden zich bevinden<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">’t Zou een prachtig geval zijn om te schilderen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Ik denk dat gij er alles van begrijpt<c type="kk">,</c> ik wou dat ik er eens <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>met Mauve over praten kon. Maar misschien <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>is ’t zelfs beter van niet<c type="kp">.</c> Want niet altijd helpt het iemand <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>vooruit als men raad krijgt van een ander<c type="kk">,</c> al is hij nog zoo <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>knap en de knapsten zijn niet altijd ook knap in het <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>duidelijk uitleggen van iets<c type="kp">.</c> Nog eens<c type="kk">,</c> ik weet het zelf <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>niet wat wenschelijk is<c type="kp">.</c> Vooreerst<c type="kk">,</c> het schilderen is geenszins <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>mijn hoofddoel en misschien krijg ik ’t alleen spoediger <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>klaar voor een illustratie dan als iemand die aan illustraties <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>volstrekt niet denken zou<c type="kk">,</c> mij er raad omtrent gaf.</p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Met Rappard kan ik nog ’t best opschieten van allemaal.</p><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">adieu kerel<c type="kk">,</c> ’t beste in alle dingen en dank voor <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>tijdigen zending<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="98*" xml:id="l-98s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">t. à t.</p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Your letter and the contents were truly welcome, many thanks for them. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">And I was pleased to see that you were taking things calmly, and indeed I had expected nothing else. I mean as regards the objections raised. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Well, since I last wrote I’ve slaved away at that drawing of the dung-heap.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It’s a splendid sight. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The first drawing of it has already undergone so many changes — now white here, then black again at various places — that I transferred it to a second paper because the first was too worn.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And am now working again on that. I have to get up early in the morning, for that’s when I see the effects I want. If only I could get it as I have it in my mind. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Well, the second is the same size as the two earlier ones of the peat-cutting and the sand quarry,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> and can go in the frame. There is effect in it at the moment, but I fear I’ll spoil it again. But one mustn’t be afraid of that, otherwise one will never get anywhere. And in the meantime I’ve also done a large study of a woman sewing.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">But I’ve had a disappointment with the Orphanage in that I have <hi rend="italics">not</hi> been given permission to draw there — there were, they said, no precedents of that kind and, furthermore, they were going to clean and lay new floors in the wards. Well, it’s not too bad for there are other orphanages, it’s just that in <hi rend="italics">this</hi> one I know a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">man</rs> who has modelled for me regularly, and that would have made it easier for me to do sketches.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">Last winter I saw the old men’s home at Voorburg.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Smaller, of course, but almost more typical. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">On that day, it was near evening, the old boys were sitting on benches and chairs around an old cannon stove, very real. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Perhaps I’ll try that one in Voorburg now I can’t do it here. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Also went to Scheveningen for a day and saw a fine sight of fellows there with a cart full of nets that had been tanned and spread out on the dunes. I’ll definitely tackle that or the nets being <hi rend="italics">mended</hi> in a large drawing sometime. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">It certainly is an improvement, Theo, that I had those stretching frames and frame made for charcoal drawings or whatever it may be, for working with them is a pleasure.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">What you say about spending too much time with painters being <hi rend="italics">not</hi> good but some time being all right is true, I believe. And for that reason, too, I’m glad <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> comes to call. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Yes, one sometimes feels a longing to discuss it with people in the know. And especially when one works and searches in the same spirit, one can give each other great strength and stimulus, and one isn’t easily discouraged.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">One can’t always live outside the fatherland, and the fatherland isn’t just nature; to that must be added human hearts that seek and feel the same. It’s only then that the fatherland is complete and one feels at home. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">This is now the composition of the dung-heap. I don’t know how much sense you can make of it. In the front women emptying dustbins, behind them the sheds where the dung is stored, and the fellows at work with wheelbarrows &amp;c. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">The first one I did was a little different:<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> there were two other fellows in the foreground with sou’westers, which they often wear in bad weather, and the group of women was more in the dark.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Yet that light effect really is there, since the light falls from above between the sheds onto the figures that are on the paths.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">It would be a splendid sight to paint. I think you understand all about it, I wish I could talk to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> about it. But perhaps it’s even better not to. For getting advice from another person doesn’t always help someone to make progress, however clever the person may be, and the cleverest aren’t always clever when it comes to explaining something clearly. Again, I don’t know myself what is desirable. For the present, painting is far from being my main goal, and perhaps I’d get it ready for an illustrated magazine quicker on my own than if someone who would never consider illustrated magazines gave me advice. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">I get on with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> best of all.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Adieu, old chap, best wishes in everything and thanks for the timely dispatch.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent thanks Theo for the ‘timely consignment’ with the remittance <ref target="#l-98">(l. 98)</ref>, which must have been the second in June. Moreover, some time must have passed between the previous letter to Theo (<ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>) and the present one, because he goes into Theo’s reaction to that letter <ref target="#l-3">(ll. 3-6)</ref>. We have therefore dated the letter on or about Monday, 11 June 1883. </p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Theo’s love for the ailing Marie (<ref target="let300.xml">300</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Van Gogh wants to draw inside the Old Men’s and Women’s Home in The Hague <ref target="let351.xml">(351)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This is the resumption of the unknown drawing that was also mentioned in <ref target="let350.xml">letters 350</ref> and <ref target="let351.xml">351</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The subject of the drawing is shown in the letter sketch in <ref target="let350.xml">letter 350</ref>. After several treatments and being ‘transferred’ to a new sheet, the drawing had been considerably altered in the process, as is evident from the letter sketch later in the present letter, <hi rend="italics">Rubbish dump (dung-heap)</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_97">F - / JH 370</rs>). The original drawing has not been preserved. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>These are the drawing <hi rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>), and an unknown drawing referred to in <ref target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref> as ‘team of workmen labouring’. The first measures c. 50 x 100 cm. Cf. <ref target="let348.xml#n-5">letter 348, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This study of a woman sewing is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The regular model was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_811">Adrianus Zuyderland</rs>; <ref target="let277.xml">see letter 277</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>The Diakonie Armhuis of the Nederlands Hervormde Gemeente in Kleine Laan, A 147, now Schoolstraat 1-3 (<hi rend="italics">Oudarchief gemeente Voorburg; inventaris der bezittingen van de Diakonie Armen der Nederlands Hervormde Gemeente</hi>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Means: ‘boiled in tannin – a brownish yellow dye – so that the nets become more durable and take on a yellow or brownish colour’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For the stretching frames Van Gogh had had made for large drawings, <ref target="let348.xml">see letter 348</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>For the first version of the subject, cf. the letter sketch in <ref target="let350.xml">letter 350</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    