<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 5 June 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let350"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b312 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>350</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>289</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>352</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1883-06-05">on or about Tuesday, 5 June 1883</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0312" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0312" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000391_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Wilde U eens vertellen dat dezen avond <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>v.d. Weele mijn teekeningen heeft gezien<c type="kk">,</c> zijn <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>opinie was gunstig en doet mij dit erg <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>pleizier<c type="kp">.</c> Weet ge wat ik heb gedaan – in <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>verband met de wenschelijkheid zoo mogelijk <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>wat geld te maken heb ik kleine schetsen van <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>de beide composities<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> eens opgezonden aan C.M<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Ik wenschte wel dat dit tot resultaat hebben <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>mogt hij misschien wilde medehelpen om <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>het geheel van ’t plan dat ik heb door te voeren<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>n.l. ’t maken eener serie teekeningen van <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>den duinarbeid.</p><lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Verder heb ik nog gedacht dat welligt <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>deze teekeningen iets zouden kunnen zijn <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>voor Cottier<c type="kp">.</c> Ik stel me voor ze <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>zich wel zouden prêteeren om<c type="kk">,</c> zooals <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>men in Engeland (en ook elders) wel eens <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>doet<c type="kk">,</c> te worden geplaatst in de paneelen <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>eener groote kast<c type="kk">,</c> boven een schoorsteen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>in een lambriseering<c type="kk">,</c> enfin in houtwerk. <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Maar ge weet hoe ’t is gesteld met <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Cottier<c type="kk">,</c> als er een zekere mate van stijl <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>in een Teek. is zoo is hij warm genoeg <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>er voor doch helaas betaalt meestal <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>weinig<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Toch<c type="kk">,</c> hij is een van diegenen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>die geloof ik er hart voor zouden <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>kunnen hebben en bovendien de teek. <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>eene goede plaats zoude kunnen <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>bezorgen. Zoo was mijn idée<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>zoudt ge de croquis niet eens aan <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>vriend Wisselingh laten kijken <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en hem spreken er over dat ik <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>meen ze goed zouden zijn voor <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>dat in houtwerk gevat worden<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Animeer hem in elk geval <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>eens op ’t atelier te komen als <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>hij eventueel in stad komen mogt<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="38a" xml:id="l-38a"/>Want gesteld hij vond ze voor bovenstaand doel geschikt<c type="kk">,</c> zoo <lb n="38b" xml:id="l-38b"/>was er misschien eene afspraak met hem te maken voor meerdere<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="38c" xml:id="l-38c"/>en wist ik hij er ooren naar had<c type="kk">,</c> zou ik ze misschien voor die bestemming nog doeltreffender <lb n="38d" xml:id="l-38d"/>kunnen maken <lb n="38e" xml:id="l-38e"/>als ik er <lb n="38f" xml:id="l-38f"/>bepaald op <lb n="38g" xml:id="l-38g"/>werkte er een <lb n="38h" xml:id="l-38h"/>decoratief karakter <lb n="38i" xml:id="l-38i"/>aan te geven.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Ik was van morgen 4 uur al buiten<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>Mijn plan is de Chiffonniers te <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>attaqueeren<c type="kk">,</c> of is liever de attaque <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>reeds begonnen. Deze teek<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> brengt mee <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>ik studies van paarden maken moet <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>en ik maakte er twee van daag in den <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>stal van de Rijnspoor<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en krijg ook <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>waarschijnlijk een oud paard aan <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>de aschvaalt<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Het geval daar aan de mestvaalt is <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>prachtig maar zeer gecompliceerd <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en moeielijk en zal veel strijd <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>kosten. Heel in de vroegte maakte <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>ik eenige plans<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Een waar men een <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>doorkijkje heeft op een heel klein schitterend <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>plekje frischheid van groen zal wel het <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>definitieve worden denk ik<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Het is iets als bovenstaand krabbeltje<c type="kk">,</c> alles<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>ook de vrouwen op den voorgrond en het witte paard <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>op den achtergrond<c type="kk">,</c> moet in clair obscur komen <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>tegen het vakje groen met een reetje lucht er <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>boven<c type="kp">.</c> Zoodat men de oppositie krijgt van <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>al die sombere loodsen die over elkaar schuiven in perspectief en al dat vuil en die <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>graauwe figuren<c type="kk">,</c> tegen iets reins en frischs. <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>In den toon van het clair obscur veroorzaken de groep <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>vrouwen en het paard lichtere partijen<c type="kk">,</c> en <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>de chiffonniers en de hoopen mest donkerder <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>vlakken<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Op den voorgrond allerlei gebroken en weggeworpen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>voorwerpen<c type="kk">,</c> stukken van oude manden<c type="kk">,</c> een verroeste <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>straatlantaarn<c type="kk">,</c> gebroken potten &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c> Gedurende <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>het maken dezer twee eerste teekeningen zijn zóóveel <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>gedachten en is zooveel lust voor nog anderen bij mij <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>opgekomen dat ik niet weet waaraan ’t eerst te beginnen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Maar heb me op den mestvaalt nu maar bepaald<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>Nu Theo<c type="kk">,</c> we moeten maar goeden moed houden <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>hoor, en zien we energiek voortsjouwen.</p><lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Al moeten we eens in de rats zitten en eens niet weten <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>hoe we er door komen<c type="kk">,</c> dat is niets en kan niet <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>anders<c type="kp">.</c> Wie volhoudt overwint dikwijls.</p><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">En juist terwijl nu het geld zenden U dubbel moeielijk <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>begint te vallen is er ook misschien werkelijk kans iets te plaatsen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Waart ge maar eens hier. Ik heb ook gedacht dat als <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>hij geen bepaald parti pris had niet met me te doen <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>te willen hebben<c type="kk">,</c> misschien Tersteeg in een kleiner formaat<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>b.v. met sepia<c type="kk">,</c> deze composities zou kunnen gebruiken<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Waart ge maar eens hier<c type="kp">.</c> Welligt ware het met hem te schipperen. <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Moeite te doen om iets te maken weiger ik zeker niet<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>Zoolang echter het met Tersteeg niet geredresseerd <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>is en met C.M<c type="kp">.</c><c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> en ik geen andere <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>ressource heb hoegenaamd dan het geld van U<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>doe gij Uw best want veel hangt er van af <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>dunkt mij dat ik juist nu flink doorwerk. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Ofschoon ik haast niets meer heb<c type="kk">,</c> ik heb toch afspraak <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>gemaakt met de modellen weer voor deze nieuwe <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>teekening<c type="kk">,</c> en hetgeen ik nog heb op ’t moment <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>zal ik misschien van daag een Scheveningschen <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>hoed en schoudermantel voor krijgen.</p><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Als ik den gelapten schoudermantel kan magtig <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>worden kerel<c type="kk">,</c> dan heb ik mijn vrouwenfiguren <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>voor het eerste plan van de teekening van de <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>chiffonniers. dat weet ik zeker.</p><lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">En is het een begin om andere vrouwenfiguren te <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>zoeken voor Scheveningsche teekeningen ook<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Wanted to tell you that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1440">Van der Weele</rs> saw my drawings this evening, his opinion was favourable and this gives me great pleasure. Do you know what I’ve done? Given the desirability of making some money if possible, I’ve sent small sketches of the two compositions<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> My hope is that this will perhaps result in his being ready to help carry out the whole of the plan I have, namely to do a series of drawings of work in the dunes. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I also thought that these drawings might perhaps be something for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_331">Cottier</rs>. I imagine they’d lend themselves to being placed, as one sometimes sees in England (and elsewhere too), in the panels of a large cabinet, above a fireplace, in panelling, in short in woodwork. But you know how it is with Cottier: if there’s a certain degree of style in a drawing, he’ll be enthusiastic all right, but alas he usually pays little.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Still, he’s one of those who might give warm support, I believe, and moreover could provide a good place for the drawings. My idea is: could you show the croquis to friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Wisselingh</rs> sometime, and mention to him that I think they’d be good for setting in woodwork?<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Encourage him in any event to come to the studio if he’s ever in town. For supposing he thought they were suitable for this purpose, it might be possible to come to an arrangement with him for more, and if I knew he was interested I could perhaps make them even more suitable for that use if I worked specially at giving them a decorative character.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">This morning I was out of doors at 4 o’clock already. My plan is to tackle the rag-pickers, or rather I’ve already begun tackling it. For this drawing<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> I must do studies of horses, and today I did two in the Rijnspoor stable,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and will probably get an old horse at the rubbish dump.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">The scene at the dung-heap is splendid but very complicated and difficult, and will be a hard struggle. I did several drawings at a very early hour.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> One in which one has a view through to a very small, glittering spot of green freshness is likely to be the ultimate one, I think. </p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">It’s something like the above scratch; everything, including the women in the foreground and the white horse in the background, must be in chiaroscuro against the green patch with a chink of sky above. So that one gets the opposition of all those sombre sheds overlapping each other in perspective, and all that rubbish and those grey figures against something clean and fresh. The group of women and the horse create lighter passages in the tone of the chiaroscuro, and the rag-pickers and the dung-heaps darker areas. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">In the foreground all kinds of broken and discarded objects, bits of old baskets, a rusty street-light, broken pots &amp;c. While making these first two drawings, so many ideas and such a strong desire to do yet more have come to me that I don’t know where to start. But finally I’ve concentrated on the dung-heap. Well, Theo, we must keep up our spirits, and see that we carry on toiling energetically. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Even if we’re anxious at times and don’t know how we’ll pull through, that is nothing and cannot be otherwise. Those who persevere often triumph. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">And just now, when sending the money is beginning to be doubly hard for you, there may perhaps be a real chance to place something. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">If only you were here. It also occurred to me that, were he not prejudiced against having anything to do with me, perhaps <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs> could make use of these compositions in a smaller format, with sepia for example.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">If only you were here. Perhaps something could be arranged with him. I certainly don’t refuse to take the trouble to make something. As long as there’s no reconciliation with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">Tersteeg</rs>, however, and with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> and I have virtually no other resource than the money from you, do your best, for it seems to me that, now especially, much depends precisely on my continuing to work hard. Although I have hardly anything left, I have again made an appointment with the models for this new drawing, and today I’ll perhaps get a Scheveningen hat and cape with what I still have at the moment. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">If I can get hold of the patched cape, old chap, then I’ll have my female figures for the foreground of the drawing of the rag-pickers, I’m sure of that. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">And it’s a start with looking for other female figures for Scheveningen drawings too. </p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>
  <ref target="let350.xml">Letter 350</ref> precedes 351 because the hoped-for acquisition of a cape mentioned here <ref target="#l-96">(l. 96)</ref> has taken place by <ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>. Both letters were written between 3 and on or about 11 June 1883 (the dates of <ref target="let348.xml">letters 348</ref>, <ref target="let349.xml">349</ref> and <ref target="let352.xml">352</ref> respectively). In <ref target="let350.xml">350</ref> Van Gogh writes about a sketch for Uncle Cor of the drawing of the sand diggers; Theo knew this drawing from an enclosed sketch in <ref target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref>. Moreover, it appears from <ref target="let352.xml">letter 352</ref> that Theo responded to <ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>. So at least a few days must have passed between these two letters; we therefore date <ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref> on or about Thursday, 7 June. Consequently, the present letter must date from on or about Tuesday, 5 June 1883.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>The letter has no ending and is not signed, so it is probably incomplete. </p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The ‘two compositions’ are the drawing <hi rend="italics">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>) and the unknown drawing of a ‘team of workmen labouring’ (see also <ref target="let348.xml">letter 348</ref>). A ‘small sketch’ of the first is unknown (except for the sketch <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_94">F 1030 / JH 364</rs>, which was sent to Theo with <ref target="let347.xml">letter 347</ref>); the sketch after the second drawing is probably <hi rend="italics">The sandpit at Dekkersduin near The Hague </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2439">F 1029 / JH 366</rs>), which measures 10 x 20.5 cm.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_821">Elbert Jan van Wisselingh</rs> had worked with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_331">Daniel Cottier</rs> (<ref target="let331.xml">see letter 331</ref>). He was now an independent art dealer at 52 rue Laffitte in Paris; he lived in the same street as Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh added the sentence ‘For supposing ... decorative character’ later.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The drawing of the rubbish dump is not known. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>One of the two drawings is probably <hi rend="italics">Old nag </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2441">F 1032 / JH 368</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>This rubbish dump was near to the gasworks, so just behind N.W. Binnensingel.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Later in the letter <ref target="#l-70">(l. 70)</ref> it becomes apparent that at that point Van Gogh had started two drawings of the rubbish dump; one of them is the one mentioned in <ref target="#l-42">l. 42</ref>. They are not known. After this, Van Gogh refers only to the one after which the letter sketch is made (with ‘a view’).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>In the spring of 1882 Van Gogh had quarrelled with both <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">Uncle Cor</rs> (C.M.) and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs>: his uncle reacted unkindly to drawings he had sent; Tersteeg objected to Van Gogh’s way of life and had no confidence in him as an artist (<ref target="let210.xml">letter 210</ref> ff.).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    