<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 15 January 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let422"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b393 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>422</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>360</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>430</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-01-15">on or about Tuesday, 15 January 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0393" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0393" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000516_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Gisteren avond ontving ik <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>Uw brief alsmede ingesl. f<hi rend="super">rs</hi> 100<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Ik kan U mededeelen dat<c type="kk">,</c> door mijn <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>tijdelijk verblijf hier minder <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>kosten gehad hebbende<c type="kk">,</c> ik nu sta op een punt <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>waar ik mijn te kort van verl. jaar dekken <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>kan<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Ik wijs U hier op als kunnende gij er uit <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>zien hoe ik evenzeer als gij ’t land zou <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>hebben aan wanordelijkheid in zaken en <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>tegenover de lui ook er op sta aan mijn <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>verpligtingen te voldoen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">En niet ben in een stemming om onverschillig <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>voor zaken te zijn – – <hi rend="italics">integendeel</hi> – <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>dat verzeker ik U.</p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Ik zal juist mijn werk wel degelijk trachten <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>door te voeren en gij moet ook niet meenen <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ik ten opzigte van dagelijks bezig zijn hier <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>anders ben dan vroeger<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Einde goed alles goed<c type="kk">,</c> zegt ’t spreekwoord<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">betreffende nu dat ik U heb geschreven over <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>bezwaren die ik had om op den zelfden voet <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>voort te gaan met geld aannemen van U<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>wij <hi rend="italics">kunnen</hi> nu sluiten op een moment <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>waar ik er af kom zonder te kort<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>en reden te meer ik niet anders kan doen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>of zal doen dan in ’t finantieele Uw <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>handelwijs met mij <hi rend="italics">genereus</hi> vinden. En indien <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>aan ’t eind v.h. jaar ik een te kort had<c type="kk">,</c> beweer ik <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ook geenszins dit Uw schuld was. Ik zeg echter ’t mij <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>verheugt tegenover leveranciers er nu op dit moment <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>niets onbetaald is. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Leveranciers van verf of wat ook <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>heb ik eerlijk behandeld en betaald<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Tegenover U echter heb ik een groote schuld<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>en ging ik voort precies op den zelfden voet <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>zoo zou ik dat erger en erger <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>maken.</p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Nu heb ik U een voorstel te doen voor <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>’t vervolg. Laat ik U van mijn <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>werk sturen en neem gij er van wat gij hebben <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>wilt doch het geld dat na Maart ik zou ontvangen <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>van U sta ik op ik moge beschouwen als door <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>mij verdiend geld. En ik vind het heel best <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>in ’t begin dit geringer zij dan het geen tot dusverre <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ik ontving.</p><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Van mijn kant zeg ik beslist <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>dat<c type="kk">,</c> wat gij ook denkt van het geen tot dusverre <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ik ontving van U<c type="kk">,</c> ik voor mij het beschouw <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>als iets dat zoo mogelijk ik zal rembourseeren<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Lukken de zaken mij<c type="kk">,</c> zoo zal ik het afdoen <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>wel degelijk. Vooreerst kan daar geen <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>kwestie van zijn en zullen we daar ook niet over <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>spreken.</p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Tegen Maart zal ik U eenige <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>aquarellen sturen van hier. Wilt ge die niet <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>hebben zoo ga ik er mee naar een ander <hi rend="italics">doch</hi> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/><hi rend="italics">liever doe ik zaken met U</hi>. Die aquarellen <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>zullen fouten hebben maar toch<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ik geloof niet dat het gek van mij is als ik een <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>begin maak mijn werk te laten kijken <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>om het de wereld in te sturen<c type="kp">.</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Rappard deed op een zeker moment ’t zelfde <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>en voerde het door van af dat hij ’t begon. <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Ik voor mij doe ’t betrekkelijk à contre coeur <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>doch ik moet het doen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">En van Maart af aan dus zal ik geregeld beginnen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>werk hier &amp; daar heen te zenden. En naar U <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>’t eerst – doch reken U niet verpligt <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>iets van me te nemen waar ge voor U <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zelf niet eenig hart voor zoudt hebben. <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Ik zou meenen dat dit zou maken <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>wij<c type="kk">,</c> welk verschil van gevoelen <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>er ook zijn mogt of komen mogt<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>er niet over hoefden te spreken zelfs<c type="kk">,</c> veel minder <lb n="75a" xml:id="l-75a"/>twisten.– <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Wat mijns inziens men <hi rend="italics">wel</hi> moet doen als men <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>eene relatie heeft met iemand <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>zoodanig als de onze is tot nu toe.</p><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Ik herzeg<c type="kk">,</c> ik zou bezwaren hebben om op <hi rend="italics">den zelfden</hi> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>voet voort te gaan<c type="kp">.</c> Maar regt gaarne wil <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>ik op eene eenigzins gewijzigde manier met <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>U in relatie blijven.</p><lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Ik zeg niet eens dat ik wil gij wat gij van <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>mij nemen mogt <hi rend="italics">dadelijk</hi> moet beschouwen als <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>iets wat gij zult trachten te verkoopen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Wilt gij voorloopig niet in Uw kwaliteit <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>van handelaar zoozeer maar meer in <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Uw kwaliteit van hart hebbende om juist ook voor <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>lui zooals ik<c type="kk">,</c> die nog in hun begin zijn<c type="kk">,</c> iets te doen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>werk van mij nemen<c type="kk">,</c> dat is mij genoeg<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>Maar ik wil na Maart niet of <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>althans absoluut zoo min mogelijk geld van U <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>aannemen voor ’t welk ik geen bepaald werk <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>zou leveren<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Met opgewektheid zou ik niet op <hi rend="italics">den zelfden</hi> voet <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>kunnen doorgaan – <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>maar met opgewektheid wil ik wel dat andere <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>beginnen op ’t zelfde moment<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> het eerste moet <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>worden gecoupeerd m.i.–</p><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Wilt gij in dat andere voorstel niet treden zoo <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>moet gij het laten<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Ik wil wel vrij zijn tegenover U doch tevens <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>wil ik <hi rend="italics">evenzeer gij vrij U voelt tegenover mij</hi><c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>Is er iets in mijn werk dat U bevalt<c type="kk">,</c> het zal me <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>veel pleizier doen en als ’t U niet bevalt en <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>gij er buiten zoudt wenschen te blijven kan <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>ik daar niets op zeggen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Bovendien wat er ook zij van verschil <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>in gevoelen betreffende dit of dat<c type="kk">,</c> dat wij <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>broers zijn en als broers ons zullen gedragen is iets dat hoop ik wel degelijk blijven <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>zal.</p><lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Ik hoop ook dat gij en Pa mij niet zult tegen <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>werken in dat ik voorloopig geen ander atelier <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>neem dan ’t mangelkamertje hier.</p><lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Ik zal een ander nemen en niet meer bij Pa in <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>huis zijn zoodra mijn werk mij genoeg oplevert <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>om weer op nieuw zelf een woning te <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>bekostigen.</p><lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Sedert ik hier ben is er geloof ik geen dag geweest <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>waarop ik niet bij de wevers of boeren van <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>s’morgens tot s’avonds zit te werken.</p><lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Indien ge goed vind wat ik voorstel zal <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>’t me veel pleizier doen. Alsdan worden m.i<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>extremes vermeden en het roer <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>regt gehouden. <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>Weet gij iets beters<c type="kk">,</c> gaarne wil ik ’t hooren<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>Gegroet en ik bedank U voor ’t gezondene.</p><lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">Met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="128*" xml:id="l-128s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.25" n="25">b. à t.</p><lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.26" n="26">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Yesterday evening I received your letter and the 100 francs enclosed. I can tell you that I’m now at a point where I can cover my deficit of last year, having had fewer expenses because of my stay here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I point this out to you so that you can see from it how I dislike disorderliness in affairs as much as you do, and also insist on meeting my obligations to people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">And am in no mood to be indifferent to affairs — — <hi rend="italics">on the contrary</hi> — that I assure you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’ll indeed really try to carry on with my work, and you mustn’t think that I’m any different from before as regards working every day here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">All’s well that ends well, says the proverb.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Now, as to qualms I wrote to you about, concerning continuing to accept money from you<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> on the same footing, we <hi rend="italics">can</hi> stop now at a moment when I can come away without a deficit; all the more reason that I cannot and will not do other than regard the way you’ve dealt with me financially as <hi rend="italics">generous</hi>. And if I had a deficit at the end of the year, I also in no way pretend that this was your fault. I say, however, that I’m glad that now, at this moment, there’s nothing unpaid to suppliers. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I’ve honestly dealt with and paid suppliers of paint or whatever else.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">I owe a great debt to you, though, and I would make it worse and worse were I to continue on exactly the same footing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Now I have a proposal to make for the future. Let me send you my work and you take what you want from it, but I insist that I may consider the money I would receive from you after March as money I’ve earned. And I don’t mind at all if it’s not as much at first as I’ve been receiving up to now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">For my part I say decidedly that, whatever you may think about what I’ve received from you so far, for myself I consider it as something that I’ll repay if possible. If things work out, I really will pay it off. There can be no question of that for the present, and so we won’t mention it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Towards March I’ll send you some watercolours from here. I’ll take them to somebody else if you don’t want them, <hi rend="italics">but I’d rather do business with you</hi>. These watercolours will have errors, but still, I don’t think it’s foolish of me if I make a start on getting my work seen in order to send it into the world. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1306">Rappard</rs> did the same at a certain point, and carried it through from the moment he started it. As for me, I do it rather reluctantly, but I must do it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">And from March onwards I’ll start to send work here and there regularly. And to you first — but don’t consider yourself obliged to take something from me if you don’t really care for it yourself. I should think that this would mean that, however much our feelings may differ or come to differ, we wouldn’t even have to talk about it, much less quarrel.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Which in my view one <hi rend="italics">does</hi> have to do if one has a relationship with someone such as ours has been up to now.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15"> I repeat, I’d have qualms about continuing <hi rend="italics">on the same</hi> footing. But I’d very willingly continue relations with you in a somewhat altered manner.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I’m not even saying that I want you to consider <hi rend="italics">immediately</hi> that anything you might take from me is something that you’ll try to sell.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">If, for the time being, you take work from me not so much in your capacity as a dealer but more in your capacity of having it in your heart to do something precisely for people like me, who are just setting out, that’s enough for me. But after March I don’t want to take money from you, or at least absolutely as little as possible, for which I haven’t supplied specific work. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">I couldn’t continue on <hi rend="italics">the same</hi> footing with enthusiasm — but I’ll start on that other with enthusiasm the moment I believe that the former has to be cut off.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">If you don’t want to enter into that other proposal, then you must leave it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">I do want to be free with you, but at the same time I want <hi rend="italics">you to feel you’re equally free with me</hi>. If there’s something in my work that you like, it will give me great pleasure, and if you don’t like it and you would want to stay out of it, I can have nothing to say about it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Moreover, whatever differences in feelings there may be about this or that, something that I hope really will remain is that we’re brothers and will conduct ourselves as brothers.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">I also hope that you and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> won’t oppose me if I don’t take any studio other than the little mangle room here for the time being.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">I’ll take another and no longer be in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs>’s house as soon as my work produces enough for me to pay for a house again myself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">I don’t think there’s been a day since I’ve been here when I haven’t sat working with the weavers or peasants from morning till night.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.25" n="25">I’ll be very pleased if you approve of my proposal. Then, in my view, we’ll avoid extremes and steer a steady course. If you know of something better, I’d like to hear it. Regards, and I thank you for what you sent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.26" n="26">With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.27" n="27">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.28" n="28">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>In <hi rend="italics">De brieven</hi> 1990 this letter is dated on or about 1 February 1884. There are, however, several reasons for placing it two weeks earlier. First of all, Van Gogh writes that since arriving in Nuenen he has spent every day from ‘from morning till night’ working among weavers and peasants <ref target="#l-119">(ll. 119-121)</ref>. This means that he must have been there for some time. And then he does not refer anywhere in this letter to Mrs van Gogh’s accident – which happened on 17 January – whereas he mentions it in every letter after this date. It therefore seems reasonable to assume that the letter dates from shortly before the seventeenth. The remittance for which he thanks Theo must have been the mid-January instalment (on 18 January Vincent also mentioned the money that Theo sent (<ref target="let425.xml">letter 425</ref>), and later he referred once again to money sent ‘about the middle of January’ (<ref target="let428.xml">letter 428</ref>). This means that the present letter was written on or about Tuesday, 15 January 1884. See also Dorn in exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 162 (nn. 2-3).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Van Gogh is given the mangle room to use as his studio <ref target="let413.xml">(413)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let420.xml">See letter 420</ref>, ll. 72 ff.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It would appear that this was Van Gogh’s<hi rend="italics"> intention</hi>, rather than a <hi rend="italics">fact</hi> at this time. In <ref target="let428.xml">letter 428</ref>, written at the beginning of February, we read: ‘<hi rend="italics">Before</hi> the accident happened, my arrangement with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> was that I would live here free of charge for a while, so as to get breathing space to settle some bills at the beginning of the year. And the money that you sent at New Year and about the middle of January was ready for that. Because I gave that to Pa when the accident happened, this time it’s those paint bills that are waiting their turn’ <ref target="let428.xml#l-43">(ll. 43-53)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Op hetzelfde moment waarop’ (at the moment when).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    