<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Tuesday, 21 April 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let495"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b440 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>495</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>402</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>499</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-04-21">Tuesday, 21 April 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0440" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0440" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000587_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Ge ontvangt met zelfde post <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>een aantal afdrukken van de lith.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Wil er M. Portier van geven zooveel hij <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>mogt begeeren. En ik voeg hierbij een <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>schrijven aan hem, dat U – denk ik – <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>eenigzins lang en gevolgelijk onpraktisch <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>zal voorkomen<c type="kp">.</c>– Maar hier van <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>dacht ik dat hetgeen te zeggen valt <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>niet in korter woorden kan gedrongen <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>worden en het er hier juist op aan <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>komt hem voor zijn eigen instinctieve <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>gevoelens redenen te geven<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">En trouwens ’t zelfde wat ik schrijf aan <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>hem zeg ik ook tot U<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Er is eene school – geloof ik – van – <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>impressionnisten. Maar ik weet daar niet <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>veel van.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> Wel weet ik echter wie <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>de oorspronkelijke en eigentlijke lui zijn <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>waarom – als om een as – de boeren- <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>en landschapschilders zullen draaijen. <lb n="20a" xml:id="l-20a"/>Delacroix<c type="kk">,</c> Millet<c type="kk">,</c> Corot en de rest. <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Dit is – in mijn eigen gevoel – niet <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>juist uitgedrukt.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Ik bedoel – er zijn (veeleer dan personen) regels of principes – <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>of grondwaarheden<c type="kk">,</c> voor zoowel <hi rend="italics">teekenen</hi> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>als <hi rend="italics">kleur</hi> – waar men – als men iets <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>waarachtigs <hi>vindt</hi> – <hi rend="italics">blijkt op neer te</hi> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/><hi rend="italics">komen</hi><c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Wat teekenen betreft – b.v. dat in kwestie <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>van het kringsgewijs – n.l. zich baseerende <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>op de ovale grondvlakken – <hi rend="italics">figuur</hi>teekenen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>’t Geen de oude Grieken reeds voelden <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>en wat tot aan ’t eind der wereld toe <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>zal blijven.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Wat kleur betreft – die eeuwige <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>kwesties – wat b.v. de eerste vraag was <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>die Corot rigtte tot Français toen <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Français (die reeds naam had) vroeg aan <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>Corot (die nog geen naam had dan alleen een <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>negatieven of vrij slechten) toen hij (F<c type="kp">.</c>) <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>kwam bij Corot om dingen te vragen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>– <hi rend="italics">Qu’est ce que c’est qu’un ton rompu?</hi> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/><hi rend="italics">Qu’est ce que c’est qu’un ton neutre?</hi><ptr target="#note-t-4"/><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/> Wat men beter op ’t palet wijzen kan <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>dan in woorden zeggen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Wat ik dus Portier verzekeren wil in dezen brief is <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>mijn – geloof – bepaald ook juist in Eug<c type="kp">.</c> Delacroix <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>en die oude lui<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">En tevens<c type="kk">,</c> waar b.v. ’t sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> waar ik aan doende <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ben<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> anders is dan lamplichten als Dou<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> of v. <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Schendel<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> – is ’t niet overbodig welligt <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>er eens op te wijzen hoe een van de <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>mooiste dingen van de schilders dezer eeuw <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>is geweest<c type="kk">,</c> het schilderen van <hi>donker</hi> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>dat toch <hi>kleur</hi> is. Enfin – lees mijn <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>schrijven maar eens &amp; ge zult zien ’t niet <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>onbegrijpelijk is. en – dat het – ERGENS <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>over is. en dat <hi rend="italics">ergens</hi> een kwestie die <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>juist bij het schilderen in mijn gedachten kwam.</p><lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Ik hoop dat het sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van die aardappel<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>eters wat zal vlotten. ben buitendien <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>ook nog aan een rooden zonsondergang <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>bezig<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Men moet om ’t boerenleven <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>te schilderen van zoo enorm veel <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>gegevens meester zijn.</p><lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Maar van den anderen kant – ik <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>weet niets waar men met zoo’n rust <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>aan werkt in den zin van <hi rend="italics">gemoedsrust</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>ook waar in ’t materieele men veel <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>strijd heeft.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Het verhuizen geeft me dezer dagen nog al <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zorg, want dat valt nooit mee<c type="kp">.</c>– Doch het <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>zou toch eens moeten gebeuren<c type="kk">,</c> indien niet nu <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>dan toch later<c type="kk">,</c> en op den duur is het beter in <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>zijn eigen gedoente te zitten<c type="kk">,</c> dat is zeker.</p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Om van iets anders te spreken – Wat is dat echt <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>gezegd van de figuren van Millet –<hi rend="italics"> son paysan</hi> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/><hi rend="italics">semble peint avec la terre qu’il ensemence!</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/> Wat is dat juist en waar. En hoezeer komt <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>het er op aan op ’t palet die kleuren <hi rend="italics">die</hi> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/><hi rend="italics">men niet noemen kan</hi> en waaruit eigentlijk <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>alles – als grondslag – bestaat<c type="kk">,</c> te weten te maken. <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>Misschien – ’k zou durven zeggen <hi rend="italics">zeker</hi> – <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>zullen de kwesties van <hi rend="italics">kleuren</hi><c type="kk">,</c> en bepaaldelijk <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>gebroken – en – neutrale – kleuren<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>U <hi rend="italics">op nieuw</hi> preoccupeeren<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">In den kunsthandel hoort men er m.i. zoo <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>vaag en arbitrair over spreken.</p><lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">En trouwens onder de schilders zelf ook<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Ik zag bij een kennis van mij<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> verl. week een bepaald <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>knappe realistische studie van een ouden vrouwenkop <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>van iemand die direct of indirect leerling is van <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>de Haagsche school. Maar zoowel in teekening als <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>in kleur zekere aarzeling<c type="kk">,</c> zekere klein<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>geestigheid veel meer – docht mij – dan dat men <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>ontwaart als men een oude Blommers of Mauve <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>of Maris<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> ziet<c type="kp">.</c>– En dit verschijnsel dreigt meer en <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>meer algemeen te worden. Als men realisme <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>opvat in den zin van <hi rend="italics">letterlijke</hi> waarheid – n.l. <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/><hi rend="italics">preciese</hi> teekening en <hi rend="italics">lokale</hi> kleur. Er is nog iets <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>anders dan dat<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Nu – gegroet – met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">b<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="101*" xml:id="l-101s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Vincent </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">You’ll receive a number of impressions of the lithograph by the same post.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Do give <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Mr Portier </rs>as many of them as he might want. And I enclose herewith a letter to him, which will seem to you — I think — rather long and consequently impractical. But I thought about it that what had to be said can’t be compressed into fewer words, and precisely what matters here is to give him reasons for his own instinctive feelings.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">And anyway, what I write to him, I also say to you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">There’s a school — I believe — of — Impressionists. But I don’t know much about it.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I do know, though, who the original and actual people are around whom — as around an axle — the peasant and landscape painters will revolve. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> and the rest. This is — in my own feeling — not correctly expressed. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I mean — (rather than people) there are rules or principles or basic values for both <hi rend="italics">drawing</hi> and <hi rend="italics">colour</hi> — which one<hi rend="italics"> — proves to arrive at</hi> — when one <hi>finds</hi> something true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">As regards drawing — for instance, that question of drawing <hi rend="italics">figures</hi> from the circle — that is, based on the fundamental oval planes, which the ancient Greeks already felt and which will continue to be until the end of the world.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">As regards colour — those eternal questions — what, for instance, was the first question that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_971">Corot</rs> addressed to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1033">Français</rs> when Français (who already had a reputation) asked Corot (who didn’t yet have a reputation, or only a negative or fairly bad one) when he (F.) came to Corot to ask things — <hi rend="italics">What is a broken tone? What is a neutral tone?</hi><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Which one can point out better on the palette than put into words.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">What I want to assure <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs> of in this letter is my — faith — precisely in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Eugène Delacroix</rs> and those old people.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">And at the same time, since, for instance, the painting I’m working on<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> is different from lamplights by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_997">Dou</rs><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1475">Van Schendel</rs><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> — it’s perhaps not superfluous to point out how one of the most beautiful things by the painters of this century has been the painting of <hi>darkness</hi> that is still <hi>colour</hi>. Anyway — just read my letter and you’ll see that it isn’t incomprehensible. And — that it — is about SOMETHING. And that <hi rend="italics">something</hi> is a question that just came into my mind when I was painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">I hope that the painting of those potato eaters will progress a bit. Besides that, am also working on a red sunset.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> To paint peasant life one has to be master of such an enormous number of things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">But on the other hand — I know of nothing that one works on with such peace, in the sense of <hi rend="italics">peace of mind</hi>, even when one has a great struggle in material things.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Moving is causing me some considerable concern these days, because it’s never straightforward. All the same, it will have to happen, if not now then later, anyway, and in the long run it’s better to be in one’s own place, that’s for sure.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">To change the subject. How rightly it was said of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>’s figures — <hi rend="italics">his peasant seems to be painted with the soil he sows!</hi><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> How accurate and true that is. And how much it comes down to knowing how to make on the palette those colours <hi rend="italics">that one cannot name</hi> and of which everything — fundamentally — actually consists. Perhaps — I dare say <hi rend="italics">certainly</hi> — the questions of <hi rend="italics">colours</hi>, and specifically broken — and — neutral — colours, will preoccupy you <hi rend="italics">once more</hi>.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">To my mind, one hears people in the art trade speak of them so vaguely and arbitrarily.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">And among the painters themselves, too, for that matter.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Last week I saw at an <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">acquaintance’s</rs><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> a decidedly clever, realistic study of the head of an old woman by someone who’s directly or indirectly a pupil of the Hague School. But both in drawing and in colour a certain hesitancy, a certain narrow-mindedness, much more — it seemed to me — than one discerns when one sees an old <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_872">Blommers</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1201 bio.xml#_1202 bio.xml#_1203">Maris</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> And this phenomenon is threatening to become more and more general. When people conceive of realism in the sense of <hi rend="italics">literal</hi> truth — namely <hi rend="italics">precise</hi> drawing and <hi rend="italics">local</hi> colour. There’s something other than that.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> Well, regards — with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent sent Theo several lithographs with this letter and asked him to give them to Portier. On 22 April 1885 Theo wrote to his mother from Paris: ‘Would you be so good as to tell Vincent that I just received his lithographs and his letter, that I will take them to Mr Portier tomorrow’ (FR b900). The present letter must therefore have been written on Tuesday, 21 April 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
    <p>Portier’s opinion of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let494.xml">(494)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
    <p>The move to the studio <ref target="let490.xml">(490)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>The lithograph <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2135">F 1661 / JH 737</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh remained ignorant of Impressionism for a long time: <ref target="let288.xml#n-4">see letter 288, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>A paraphrase of the quotation from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_613">Gigoux</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_407">Causeries sur les artistes de mon temps</ref></hi> which Van Gogh quoted in <ref target="let494.xml">letter 494</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This anecdote derives from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1809">Dumesnil</rs><hi rend="italics"> </hi>1875: <ref target="let419.xml#n-8">see letter 419, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The new version of <hi rend="italics">The potato eaters</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2510">F 82 / JH 764</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_997">Gerard Dou</rs>, known for his paintings with candlelit and lamplit effects, used strong chiaroscuro effects from the sixteen-fifties onwards in scenes of this type, like his <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_564">Night school</rs></hi>, c. 1623-1665 (Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1475">Petrus van Schendel</rs> painted small interiors with effects of candlelight and moonlight, which clearly reveal the influence of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_997">Gerard Dou</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This may be <hi rend="italics">Landscape with sunset</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2509">F 191 / JH 762</rs>), although the sky is more orange than red.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
    
<p>This sentence derives from something said by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_607">Théophile Gautier</rs> which Van Gogh found in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_737">Sensier</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_238">La vie et l’oeuvre de J.F. Millet</ref></hi>: ‘There is something imposing and stylish about this figure with its violent gesture, and proudly run-down bearing, which seems to be painted with the very soil which he sows’ (Il y a du grandiose et du style dans cette figure au geste violent, à la tournure fièrement délabrée, et qui semble peinte avec la terre qu’il ensemence) (Sensier 1881, p. 127). Quoted again in <ref target="let499.xml">letter 499</ref>, <ref target="let500.xml">500</ref>, <ref target="let505.xml">505</ref> and <ref target="let506.xml">506</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_475">Anton Kerssemakers</rs>, with whom Van Gogh was in touch in this period.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Matthijs</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jacob</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1201">Willem</rs> Maris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            
    
<p>There is an echo here of what <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_836">Emile Zola</rs> had written in ‘Les réalistes du Salon’ (<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_594">Mon Salon</ref>): ‘I have no time for realism, in the sense that the word has no clear meaning for me ... that all I ask of the artist is to be personal and powerful’ (Je me moque du réalisme, en ce sens que ce mot ne représente rien de bien précis pour moi ... que je demande uniquement à l’artiste d’être personnel et puissant), and: ‘Therefore no more realism than anything else. Truth, if you like, and life, but above all, different flesh and different hearts interpreting nature in different ways. The definition of a work of art can only be as follows: A work of art is a corner of creation seen through a temperament.’ (Donc pas plus de réalisme que d’autre chose. De la vérité, si l’on veut, de la vie, mais surtout des chairs et des coeurs différents interprétant différemment la nature. La définition d’une oeuvre d’art ne saurait être autre chose que celle-ci: Une oeuvre d’art est un coin de la création vu à travers un tempérament.) Zola 1966-1970, vol. 12, pp. 807-810.  Van Gogh alluded to this sentence on other occasions: <ref target="let361.xml#n-9">see letter 361, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    