<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Thursday, 5 and about Thursday, 26 February 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let483"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b432 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>483</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>394</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>487</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-02-05">between about Thursday, 5 and about Thursday, 26 February 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0432" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0432" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000577_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Wel bedankt voor Uwe bezending <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>illustrations<c type="kk">,</c> waar ge me regt veel pleizier mede <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>hebt gedaan.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> De diverse teekeningen van Renouard <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>vind ik allen mooi &amp; kende ze geen van allen. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Doch – maar dit is niet om U meerdere moeite <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>te geven maar wegens ik er dingen over schreef die <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>op de andere teekeningen van hem misschien niet <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>geheel &amp; al toepasselijk zijn – doch de eigentlijke <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>compositie van R<c type="kp">.</c> die ik bedoelde is er niet bij<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>welligt is dat N<hi rend="super">o</hi> uitverkocht. Het breede in <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>’t figuur was daar superbe in – het was een oud <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>man en eenige vrouwen &amp; een kind geloof ik<c type="kk">,</c> die <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>niets zaten te doen in een weversinterieur waar <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>de getouwen stil stonden.</p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Van Salon 84 had ik nog <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> in reproductie gezien <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>en kreeg nu althans eenig idee van sommige <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>interessante schilderijen door het Salon N<hi rend="super">o</hi><c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Onder anderen van die compositie van Puvis de <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Chavannes.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Ik verbeeld me dat de <hi rend="italics">Harpignies</hi> met die ondergaande <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>zon prachtig moet zijn geweest.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> En de schilderijen <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>van Feyen Perrin<c type="kk">,</c> waar croquis van in staan.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Wat mij ook trof was een meisjesfiguurtje van <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Emile Levy<c type="kk">,</c> Japonaise<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> en ’t Sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van Beyle<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/><hi rend="italics">Brûleuses de Varech</hi><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> en dat van Collin<c type="kk">,</c> l’Ete<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>3 naakte vrouwenfiguren.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Met ’t schilderen van die koppen ben ik druk <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>doende. ik schilder overdag en s’avonds <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>teekenen<c type="kp">.</c> Ik heb zoodoende er zeker reeds <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>een 30tal geschilderd &amp; evenveel geteekend.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Met dit resultaat dat ik kans zie om het over <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>een poosje hoop ik nog heel anders te doen. <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Ik denk dat het me voor ’t figuur in ’t algemeen <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>helpen zal. Vandaag had ik er een wit <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>&amp; zwart<c type="kk">,</c> tegen de vleeschkleur.</p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">En ik ben ook aan ’t zoeken naar blaauw <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>altijd. De boerenfiguren hier zijn in den <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>regel blaauw. Dat in ’t rijpe koren of tegen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>de dorre blaren van een beukenheg uit<c type="kk">,</c> zoodat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>de verscholen nuances van donkerder &amp; lichter blaauw weer <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>levend gemaakt worden &amp; aan ’t praten gebragt <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>door oppositie met goudtoonen of roodbruin<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>is erg mooi en heeft me van ’t begin <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>af hier getroffen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">De lui dragen hier instinktmatig al mee <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>van ’t mooiste blaauw dat ik ooit heb gezien. <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Het is grof linnen dat ze zelf weven<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>scheering zwart<c type="kk">,</c> inslag blaauw. waardoor <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>een zwart &amp; blaauw gestreept patroon ontstaat. <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Als dat verflenst en wat ontkleurd door weer <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>en wind<c type="kk">,</c> is het een oneindig stillen<c type="kk">,</c> fijnen <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>toon die juist de vleeschkleuren releveert. <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Enfin blaauw genoeg om <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>op alle kleuren waarin verborgen oranje <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>elementen zich bevinden te ageeren en <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>ontkleurd genoeg om niet te rammelen.</p><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Doch dit is een kwestie van kleur<c type="kk">,</c> en de <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>kwestie van den vorm is ’t geen er nog meer <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>op aan komt voor mij op ’t punt waar ik nu me <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>bevind. Den vorm uit te drukken gaat – geloof <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>ik – wel ’t best met een bijna monochroom koloriet <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>waarvan de toonen hoofdzakelijk in intensiteit en <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>in waarde verschillen. b.v. la Source van <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Jules Breton was geschilderd in een enkele kleur <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>bijna<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Maar <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>men dient wel iedere kleur op zich zelf te bestudeeren <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>in verband met haar tegenstelling<c type="kk">,</c> eer men <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>goed zeker van zijn zaak kan zijn om harmonieus <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>te wezen.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Toen er sneeuw lag heb ik nog een paar studies van <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>onzen tuin geschilderd.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Het landschap is sedert veel veranderd – we hebben <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>nu prachtige avondluchten van lilas met goud <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>boven toonige silhouetten van de woningen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>tusschen de massas hakhout<c type="kk">,</c> dat een rosse kleur heeft<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>waarboven ijle<c type="kk">,</c> zwarte populieren uitsteken – <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>terwijl de voorgronden verschoten en <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>verbleekt groen zijn<c type="kk">,</c> gevarieerd door strooken <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>zwarte aarde en dor<c type="kk">,</c> bleek riet aan de slootkanten<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Ik zie dat alles ook wel – ik vind het even superbe <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>als wie dan ook – maar mij interesseert nog meer <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>de proportie van een figuur<c type="kk">,</c> de verdeeling van <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>het eirond van een kop en ik heb geen houvast voor <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>de rest eer ik ’t figuur nog meer in mijn magt heb. <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Enfin – eerst het figuur – ik voor mij kan de rest <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>niet begrijpen zonder<c type="kk">,</c> en ’t is ’t figuur dat de stemming <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>er aan geeft. Ik kan me echter begrijpen dat er menschen <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>zijn als Daubigny en Harpignies en Ruysdael en zooveel <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>anderen die absoluut en onweerstaanbaar worden meegesleept door het landschap op zich zelf<c type="kk">,</c> hun werk voldoet ten volle omdat zij zelf voldaan <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>waren door lucht en grond en een plas water en een struik. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Ik vind het echter een almagtig aardig woord van <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>Israels dat hij zeide van een Dupré – het is net een figuurschilderij.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Gegroet, en nogmaals dank voor de illustraties<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">b. à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Many thanks for your parcel of L’Illustrations, with which you’ve given me great pleasure.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I like all of the various drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>, and didn’t know any of them. However — but this isn’t to put you to more trouble, but because I wrote things about it that are perhaps not altogether applicable to the other drawings by him — however, the actual composition by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">R.</rs> that I meant isn’t among them, that No. may be sold out. The breadth in the figure was superb in it — it was an old man and some women and a child, I think, who sat doing nothing in a weaver’s interior where the looms were still.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I hadn’t yet seen <hi rend="italics">anything</hi> from Salon 84 in reproduction, and now at least got some idea of a few interesting paintings from the Salon No. Among other things, of that composition by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I imagine that the <hi rend="italics"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_347">Harpignies</rs></hi> with the setting sun must have been magnificent.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> And the paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1022">Feyen-Perrin</rs>, of which there are croquis.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">What also struck me was a figure of a girl by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1174">Emile Lévy</rs>, Japonaise,<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> and the painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_859">Beyle</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Women burning seaweed</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> and the one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_955">Collin</rs>, Summer, 3 female nudes.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I’m hard at work on painting those heads. I paint during the day and draw in the evening. I’ve already painted at least 30 or so this way, and drawn as many.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">With the result that I see a chance, before long I hope, of doing it very differently. I think that it will help me with the figure in general. Today I had a white and black one, against the flesh colour.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">And I’m also always looking for blue. As a rule, the peasant figures here are blue. That, in the ripe wheat or against the withered leaves of a beech hedge, so that the hidden nuances of darker and lighter blue are brought alive again and made to speak by contrast with gold tones or reddish brown, is very beautiful, and has struck me here from the first.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">The people here instinctively wear the most beautiful blue that I’ve ever seen. It’s coarse linen that they weave themselves, warp black, weft blue, which creates a black and blue striped pattern. When it’s faded and slightly discoloured by wind and weather, it’s an infinitely calm, subtle shade that specifically brings out the flesh colours. In short, blue enough to react with all the colours in which there are hidden orange elements, and faded enough not to clash.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">But this is a question of colour, and the question of the form is what matters more to me at the point where I now find myself. Expressing the form — I think — works best with an almost monochrome colour scheme, the tones of which vary chiefly in intensity and in value. For instance, The well by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899">Jules Breton</rs> was painted in a single colour, almost.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> But one does have to study each colour individually in association with its opposite before one can be really sure of being harmonious.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">I painted a few more studies of our garden when there was snow on it.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">The landscape has changed greatly since then — we now have magnificent evening skies of lilac and gold, above the tonal silhouettes of the houses between the masses of the coppices, which are a ruddy colour, above which rise slender black poplars — while the foregrounds are blanched and bleached green, varied by strips of black earth and dry, pale reeds along the sides of the ditches. I see all that, too — I find it as superb as anyone else — but what interests me even more is the proportion of a figure, the division of the oval of a head, and I have no grasp on the rest until I have more mastery of the figure. In short — the figure first — for my part, I can’t understand the rest without it, and it’s the figure that creates the mood. I can understand, though, that there are people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_347">Harpignies</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1333">Ruisdael</rs> and so many others, who are absolutely and irresistibly carried away by the landscape itself; their work is totally satisfying because they themselves were satisfied by sky and soil and a pool of water and a bush. However, I think what Israëls said about a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_986">Dupré</rs> is a mighty clever saying — it’s just like a painting of a figure.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Regards, and thanks again for the illustrations.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Round about 2 February Vincent had not yet received the parcel of magazines from Theo (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref> (cf. <ref target="let482.xml">letter 482</ref>). Since in the next letter of about 2 March (<ref target="let484.xml">letter 484</ref>) Vincent thanks him for sending an engraving and does not refer again to the one from <hi rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi>, we assume that the parcel arrived between these two letters. There are no other indications for the dating of the letter, although Vincent does write more calmly than in <ref target="let482.xml">letter 482</ref>, which makes it likely that some time had passed since he wrote that one. On these grounds we have dated the letter between about Thursday, 5 and about Thursday, 26 February 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Vincent had twice asked his brother to send him a special edition of <hi rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> because it contained <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1292">Renouard</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_399">La crise industrielle à Lyon – Sans travail</rs></hi> (<ref target="let480.xml">letters 480</ref> and <ref target="let482.xml">482</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Theo sent <hi rend="italics">L’Illustration</hi> 83 (3 May 1884), no. 2149, because this is the one that featured all the reproductions referred to hereafter. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1286">Pierre Puvis de Chavannes</rs>,<hi rend="italics"> Le bois sacré, cher aux arts et aux muses</hi> (The sacred grove, dear to the arts and the muses), engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1570">Meisenbach</rs>, is on p. 289. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_323">Ill. 323</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_347">Henri Joseph Harpignies</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Lever de lune; Étang de Grand-Rue (Yonne)</hi> (Moonrise; The pond at Grand-Rue (Yonne)) is on p. 297 (as no. 8 of a page ‘Choix de paysages’ (Selection of landscapes). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_921">Ill. 921</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Armorica</hi> (Armorica) and <hi rend="italics">Le bain</hi> (The bath) by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1022">François Feyen-Perrin</rs>, engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1570">Meisenbach</rs>, are on p. 289. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_835">Ill. 835</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_836">Ill. 836</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1174">Emile Lévy</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Petite fille en robe japonaise</hi> (Girl in a Japanese robe), engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1570">Meisenbach</rs>, is on p. 292. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1051">Ill. 1051</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_859">Pierre Marie Beyle</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Brûleuses de Varech</hi> (Women burning seaweed), engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1570">Meisenbach</rs>, is on p. 305. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_581">Ill. 581</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_955">Louis Joseph Raphaël Collin</rs>, <hi rend="italics">L’été</hi> (Summer), engraved by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1570">Meisenbach</rs>, is on p. 301. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_698">Ill. 698</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>See for the studies of heads that Van Gogh made in this period: cat. Amsterdam 1997, pp. 124-133, cat. nos. 108-118.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>See for<rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_899"> Jules Breton</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_30">The spring</rs></hi>: <ref target="let464.xml#n-9">letter 464, n. 9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>We know of two paintings of this subject dating from around this time: <hi rend="italics">The parsonage garden in the snow</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2492">F 194 / JH 603</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2493">F 67 / JH 604</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had quoted this remark by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> before – in <ref target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    