<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 16 December 1884. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let476"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b428 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>476</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>390</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>478</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1884-12-16">on or about Tuesday, 16 December 1884</date>
                            <placeName>Nuenen</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0428" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0428" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000573_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">ik ben zeer druk werkende <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>aan de serie koppen uit het volk<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> die ik <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>me heb voorgenomen te maken<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">ik sluit hier nog een krabbeltje in van <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>de laatste<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – s’avonds krabbel ik ze uit <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>het hoofd meestal even op een vodje <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>papier<c type="kk">,</c> vandaar deze.</p><lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Ik zal ze misschien later in aquarel <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>maken ook<c type="kp">.</c>– Doch ze eerst schilderen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Hoor nu eens hier – weet gij dat heel <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>in ’t begin reeds ik U altijd sprak<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> over <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>mijn groot respect &amp; sympathie <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>voor ’t werk van vader de Groux<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Dezer dagen denk ik <hi rend="italics">meer dan ooit</hi> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>aan hem<c type="kp">.</c>– Men moet van hem niet <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>zien zijn enkele historiestukken – ofschoon <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ook die mooi zijn – ook niet in de eerste plaats enkele <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>schilderijen die in ’t sentiment van <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>b.v. den schrijver Conscience zijn<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Maar men moet zien van hem: <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>le benedicité<c type="kk">,</c> le pèlérinage<c type="kk">,</c> le banc des pauvres <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>en vooral<c type="kk">,</c> vooral de eenvoudige <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>brabantsche types<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">De Groux is evenmin geapprecieerd <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>als b.v. Thijs Maris<c type="kp">.</c>– Hij is evenwel <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>anders – doch – dit hebben ze gemeen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>dat zij woedende oppositie gehad <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>hebben.–</p><lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Nu – in dezen tijd – of ’t publiek <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wijzer is – weet ik niet – doch <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>dit weet ik wel – dat het volstrekt <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>niet overbodig is ernstig te wezen in <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>wat men wil en wat men doet<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">En ik zou U op dit moment eenige <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>nieuwe namen kunnen noemen <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>van lui die weer op ’t zelfde oude <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>aambeeld hameren waarop de Groux <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>heeft gehamerd.</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Indien de Groux – toen ter tijde – <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zijn brabantsche karakters in costumes <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>moyen age had believen te kleeden<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zoo zou hij met Leys evenwijdig hebben geloopen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>niet alleen wat genie maar misschien ook wat – fortuin – <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>aangaat<c type="kp">.</c>– Dit echter deed hij niet <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>en <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> – jaren later – is men <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>van ’t middeneeuwsche aanmerkelijk <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>teruggekomen – ofschoon Leys <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>altijd Leys blijft en Thijs Maris <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Thijs Maris – en Victor Hugo’s <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Notre Dame – Notre Dame<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Maar – ’t realisme – toen <hi rend="italics">niet gewild</hi> – <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>wordt nu – <hi rend="italics">geeischt</hi> – en – <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>er is meer dan ooit behoefte aan<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Aan dat realisme dat karakter <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>en een serieus sentiment heeft<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Ik wil U dit wel zeggen<c type="kk">,</c> dat mij aangaande <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>ik mijn roer zal trachten regt te <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>sturen – en het dood eenvoudige<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>meest alledaagsche – zal schilderen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">In godsnaam<c type="kk">,</c> hoe is het toch <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>mogelijk dat gij niet schijnt te <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>kunnen of willen begrijpen dat met mijn <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>atelier hier gevestigd te hebben en ’t er <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>voor als nog ook te houden<c type="kk">,</c> ik het me <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/><hi rend="italics">mogelijk</hi> heb gemaakt geld genoeg <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>voor ’t schilderen te hebben – en dat als <lb n="67a" xml:id="l-67a"/>ik anders gedaan had<c type="kk">,</c> noch voor mezelf noch voor anderen ’t goed ware <lb n="67b" xml:id="l-67b"/>uitgekomen<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Had ik dat niet gedaan zoo zou ik <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>misschien nog 3 jaar hebben moeten <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>scharrelen eer ik definitief door <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>den zuren appel van kleur en toon <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>hadde heen gebeten<c type="kk">,</c> ook bepaald wegens de kosten.</p><lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">’t Is nu een jaar net geleden ik <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>hier door den nood gedrongen <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>arriveerde<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Voor mijn <hi rend="italics">pleizier</hi> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>ben ik hier zeker niet in huis – <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>maar voor mijn schilderen – en als <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>zoodanig vind ik ’t zeer verkeerd <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>van U dat gij me een gelegenheid <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>zoudt ontnemen indien ik hier 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/><hi rend="italics">nu</hi> wegging – voor en aleer ik iets <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>nieuws heb<c type="kp">.</c>– <hi rend="italics">Ik moet voor mijn</hi> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/><hi rend="italics">schilderen</hi> hier nog een tijd zijn – <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>dan – zoodra dat meer definitief nog <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>overwonnen is ben ik content <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>te gaan waar dan ook waar ik <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>’t zelfde verdien wat ik nu hier heb.</p><lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Doch achteruitgaan – behoef of verdien ik niet – noch <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>heb ik den minsten trek in – ziet ge<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>En te <hi rend="italics">zoeken</hi> van U ontslagen te zijn<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>dat heb ik nooit gedaan doch waar gij <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>te duidelijk me hebt laten merken <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>hoe weinig kans er was dat wij werkelijke <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>zaken zouden doen zamen – accepteer <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>ik zulks voor de toekomst<c type="kk">,</c> dat wel. Weet dit eens en vooral<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>als ik U geld vraag<c type="kk">,</c> ik vraag het niet voor <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> – <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>mijn werk dat ik er mee maak kunt gij er voor krijgen <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>en indien <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> ik daarin ten <hi rend="italics">achter</hi> ben – ik ben op <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>een regten weg om er in <hi rend="italics">vóór</hi> te komen zelfs<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik schrijf dezen nog eens om de zelfde reden <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>als de vorige brieven – ik zit met mijn eind <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>van de maand vast want ik heb nog maar voor <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>2 à 3 dagen genoeg voor mijn model te betalen<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>En ik ben er beroerd over ik weer 10 dagen <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/><hi rend="italics">vast</hi> zal zitten<c type="kk">,</c> of 12<c type="kk">,</c> deze maand<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">En ten allerernstigste nog eens – kunt <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>ge er niet iets op vinden me te helpen aan frs 20 b.v. om dat <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>eindje te dekken<c type="kp">.</c>– Het is mijn tijd die <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>niet voldoende besteed is anders<c type="kk">,</c> die me aan ’t hart <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>gaat<c type="kp">.</c>– Gegroet<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="110*" xml:id="l-110s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">b<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I’m very busy working on the series of heads of the people<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> that I’ve resolved to make.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I enclose herewith another scratch of the last one<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> — I usually just scribble them from memory on a scrap of paper in the evening, hence this one.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I may perhaps do them in watercolour too, later on. But paint them first.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Now listen — do you remember that right at the very beginning I always spoke to you<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> of my great respect and sympathy for the work of <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs>? I think about him <hi rend="italics">more than ever</hi> these days. One mustn’t look at his few history pieces — although they’re fine, too — nor in the first place at a few paintings that are in the sentiment of the writer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_572">Conscience</rs>, for instance. But one must see his Saying grace, The pilgrimage, The paupers’ pew and, above all, above all, the simple Brabant types.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> is as little appreciated as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs>, for instance. He’s different, however — but — they have this in common, that they met with fierce opposition.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Now — in this age — whether the public is wiser — I don’t know — but I do know this — that it’s absolutely not superfluous to be serious in what one wants and what one does.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">And at this moment I could name you several new names of people who are hammering again on the same old anvil on which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> hammered.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">If <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Degroux</rs> — at that time — had chosen to dress his Brabant characters in medieval costumes, he would have run parallel to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1176">Leys</rs>, not just as regards genius but perhaps also — fortune. However, he didn’t do that and <hi rend="italics">now</hi> — years later — people have noticeably changed their minds about the medieval — although Leys will always be Leys and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs>, Thijs Maris — and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s Notre-Dame — Notre-Dame.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10"> But — realism — <hi rend="italics">not wanted</hi> then — is now — <hi rend="italics">demanded</hi> — and — there’s more need of it than ever. For that realism that has character and a sincere sentiment. I want to tell you this, that as for me, I’ll try to steer a straight course — and will paint — the dead simple, most everyday things.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">How, for God’s sake, is it possible that you don’t seem to be able or willing to understand that, by setting up my studio here and keeping it on for the time being, I’ve made it <hi rend="italics">possible</hi> for me to have enough money for painting — and that if I had acted differently, no good would have come of it either for me or for others?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Had I not done that, I would have had to muddle along for perhaps another 3 years before I had finally swallowed the bitter pill of colour and tone, also simply because of the expense.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">It’s now just a year since I arrived here, driven by necessity.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I’m certainly not at home for my <hi rend="italics">pleasure</hi> — but for my painting — and, this being so, I think it very wrong of you that you should deprive me of an opportunity if I were to leave here 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> <hi rend="italics">now</hi> — before ever I have something new. <hi rend="italics">I have to</hi> be here for a time <hi rend="italics">for my painting</hi> — then — as soon as I’ve conquered that more definitely, I’ll be happy to go anywhere I can earn the same as I now have here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">But I don’t need or deserve to go backwards — nor do I have the slightest desire to — you see? And to <hi rend="italics">seek</hi> to be rid of you — I’ve never done that, but where you have only too plainly let me see how little chance there was that we’d actually do business together — I accept it for the future, that’s true. Know this once and for all, when I ask you for money, I don’t ask it for <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> — you can have the work I make with it in return, and if I’m in <hi rend="italics">arrears</hi> with it<hi rend="italics"> now</hi> — I’m on the right road even to get <hi rend="italics">ahead</hi> of it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I write this yet again for the same reason as the previous letters — I’m stuck at the end of the month because I only have enough left to pay my model for 2 or 3 days. And I’m wretched because I’ll be <hi rend="italics">stuck</hi> again for 10 days, or 12, this month.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">And in the utmost seriousness, once again — can’t you find some way of helping me with 20 francs, say, to cover that little end? It’s my time that will otherwise not be sufficiently occupied that really pains me. Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>This letter follows <ref target="let475.xml">475</ref> in which Van Gogh said how concerned he was about his finances in the last month of the year. Now he writes: ‘I’m stuck at the end of the month because I only have enough left to pay my model for 2 or 3 days. And I’m wretched because I’ll be <hi rend="italics">stuck</hi> again for 10 days, or 12, this month.’ <ref target="#l-101">(ll. 101-105)</ref>. This means that the letter must have been written 14 or 15 days before 31 December, in other words on or about Tuesday, 16 December 1884.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh borrowed this title from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1080">Hubert von Herkomer</rs>’s series ‘Heads of the people’: <ref target="let235.xml#n-37">see letter 235, n. 37.</ref> He made numerous heads during this period; it is therefore impossible to establish precisely which one he means here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for the scratches that might possibly have been sent: <ref target="let475.xml#n-1">letter 475, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>This relates to the beginning of the Hague period in early 1882.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1063">Charles Degroux</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Saying grace</hi>: <ref target="let143.xml#n-16">letter 143, n. 16.</ref></p>

<p rend="indent">By <hi rend="italics">Le pélèrinage</hi> (The pilgrimage) Van Gogh most probably means the large canvas <hi rend="italics">De bedevaart van Sint-Guido te Anderlecht</hi> (The pilgrimage to Saint-Guidon in Anderlecht), c. 1856-1857 (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_140">Ill. 140</rs>. The Museum acquired this as early as 1870, whereas the two versions of the <hi rend="italics">Bedevaart naar Diegem</hi> (Pilgrimage to Diegem) did not enter public collections until 1904 (the Musée de Beaux-Arts, Doornik) and 1937 (the Koninklijk Museum voor Schone Kunsten in Antwerp). See exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 110-114, cat. nos. 123, 126, 130.</p>

<p rend="indent">See for <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_134">The paupers’ pew</rs></hi>: <ref target="let148.xml#n-12">letter 148, n. 12.</ref></p>

<p rend="indent">In his final remark Van Gogh is referring to the characteristic types that are depicted in these works.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_331">Notre-Dame de Paris</ref></hi> (1831).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh arrived in Nuenen on 5 December 1883 (<ref target="let409.xml">letter 409</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    