<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Paris, between about Sunday, 17 and Tuesday, 19 July 1887.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let571"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b501 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>571</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>461</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>574</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1887-07-17">between about Sunday, 17 and Tuesday, 19 July 1887</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0501" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0501" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000677_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher ami,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">ci inclus une lettre <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>qui est arrivée d’hier mais que le concierge <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ne m’a pas tout de suite remise<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">J’ai été au Tambourin<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> puisque si je <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>n’y allais pas on aurait pensé que <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>je n’osais pas<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Alors j’ai dit à la Segatori que <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>dans cette affaire je ne la jugerais pas <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>mais que c’etait à elle de se juger <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>elle-même<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Que j’avais dechiré le reçu des <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>tableaux – mais qu’elle devait <hi rend="italics">tout</hi> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>rendre.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Que si elle n’etait pas pour quelque <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>chose dans ce qui m’est arrivé elle <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>aurait été me voir le lendemain<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Que puisqu’elle n’est pas venue me <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>voir je considerais qu’elle savait <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>qu’on me chercherait querelle mais qu’elle <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>a cherché à m’avertir en me disant – <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>allez vous en – ce que je n’ai pas compris <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>et d’ailleurs n’aurais peut etre pas voulu <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>comprendre<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Ce à quoi elle a répondu <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>que les tableaux &amp; tout le reste<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>étaient à ma disposition<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Elle a maintenue que moi j’avais <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>cherché querelle – ce qui ne <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>m’étonne pas – sachant <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>que si elle prenait parti pour moi <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>on lui ferait des atrocités.–</p><lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">J’ai vu le garçon aussi en entrant mais il <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>s’est éclipsé<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Maintenant je n’ai pas voulu prendre <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>les tableaux tout de suite mais j’ai dit que <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>quand tu serais de retour on en <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>causerait<c type="kk">,</c> puisque ces tableaux <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>t’appartenaient autant qu’à moi et <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>qu’en attendant je l’engageais à <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>réfléchir encore une fois à ce qui <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>s’était passé<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Elle n’avait pas bien bonne mine <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>et elle etait pâle comme de la cire <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>ce qui n’est pas bon signe<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Elle ne savait pas que le garçon était <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>monté chez toi<c type="kp">.</c>– Si cela est vrai – <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>je serais encore davantage porté à croire <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>qu’elle a plûtot cherché à m’avertir qu’on <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>me chercherait querelle que de monter le coup <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>elle-meme<c type="kp">.</c>– Elle ne peut pas comme elle voudrait<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Maintenant j’attendrai ton retour pour <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>agir<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">J’ai fait deux tableaux depuis que <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>tu es parti<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Maintenant j’ai encore deux louis<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> et <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>je crains que je ne saurai comment <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>passer les jours d’ici jusqu’à ton <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>retour<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Car remarquez que lorsque j’ai <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>commencé à travailler à Asnieres<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>j’avais beaucoup de toiles et <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>que Tanguy était très bon pour <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>moi<c type="kp">.</c>– Cela à la rigueur il l’est <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>tout autant mais sa vieille <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>sorcière de femme<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> s’est aperçue <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>de ce qui se passait et s’y est <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>opposé<c type="kp">.</c>– Maintenant j’ai engueulé <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>la femme à Tanguy et j’ai dit <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>que c’etait de sa faute à elle si <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>je ne leur prendrais plus rien<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Le père Tanguy est sage assez pour 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>se taire et il fera tout de même <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>ce que je lui demanderai<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">mais avec tout cela le travail <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>n’est pas bien commode<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">J’ai vu de Lautrec aujourd’hui<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>il a vendu un tableau<c type="kk">,</c> je <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>crois par Portier<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">On a apporté une aquarelle de M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Mesdag <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>que je trouve très belle<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Maintenant j’espère que <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>ton voyage là-bas t’amusera<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>dites bien des chôses de ma part <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>à ma mère<c type="kk">,</c> à Cor &amp; à Wil<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Puis si tu peux faire de façon <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>que je ne m’embête pas trop <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>d’ici jusqu’à ton retour en <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>m’envoyant encore quelque chôse<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>je tâcherai de te faire encore <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>des tableaux – car je suis tout <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>à fait tranquille pour mon travail.</p><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Ce qui me gênait un peu dans cette <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>histoire c’est qu’en n’y allant pas (au Tambourin) <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>cela avait l’air lâche<c type="kp">.</c> Et cela <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>m’a rendu ma sérénité d’y être <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>allé.– Je te serre la main<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear friend,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Enclosed a letter that arrived yesterday but which the concierge didn’t pass on to me straightaway.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I’ve been to the Tambourin,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> because if I didn’t go there people would have thought I didn’t dare.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">So I told <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">Miss Segatori</rs> that I wouldn’t pass judgement on her over this affair, but that it was up to her to judge herself.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">That I’d torn up the receipt for the paintings — but that she had to give <hi rend="italics">everything</hi> back.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/><hi rend="italics"/> </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">That if <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">she</rs> hadn’t had something to do with what happened to me she would have come to see me the next day.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">That as she didn’t come to see me I would take it that she knew people were trying to pick a fight with me, but that she’d tried to warn me by saying — go away — which I didn’t understand, and besides would perhaps not have wanted to understand. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">To which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">she</rs> replied that the paintings and all the rest<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> were at my disposal.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">She claimed that I’d tried to pick a fight — which doesn’t surprise me — knowing that appalling things would be done to her if she took my side.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">I also saw the waiter on my way in, but he made himself scarce.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Now I didn’t want to take the paintings straightaway, but I said that when you got back we’d have a chat about it, because those paintings belonged to you as much as to me, and while waiting I urged her to think again about what had happened.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">She</rs> didn’t look well and she was as pale as wax, which isn’t a good sign. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">She didn’t know that the waiter had gone up to your place. If that’s true — I would be even more inclined to believe it was more the case that she’d tried to warn me people were trying to pick a fight with me, than that she’d been up to something herself. She can’t do as she’d like. Now I’ll wait till you get back before doing anything.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">I’ve done two paintings since you left.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Now I have two louis<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> left, and I fear I won’t know how to get through the days from now till you get back.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Because remember when I started working at Asnières<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I had lots of canvases and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> was very good to me. He still is, when it comes down to it, but his old witch of a <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_773">wife</rs><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> noticed what was going on and objected to it. Now I gave Tanguy’s wife a piece of my mind and said it was her fault if I wouldn’t buy anything else from them. <hi rend="italics">Père</hi> Tanguy’s wise enough to 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> keep quiet, and he’ll do what I ask of him all the same.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">But with all that it isn’t easy to work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">I saw <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Lautrec</rs> today, he’s sold a painting, through <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> I think. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Someone brought in a watercolour by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1217">Mrs Mesdag</rs>, which I find very beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Now I hope you’ll enjoy your visit over there, give my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Wil</rs> my warm regards. And if you can see that I’m not in too much trouble from now till you get back by sending me something more, I’ll try to make some more paintings for you — because I’m perfectly calm as far as my work goes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">What bothered me a bit in this business was that by not going (to the Tambourin) it looked cowardly. And having gone there restored my peace of mind. I shake your hand.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>This letter and the next one <ref target="let572.xml">(572)</ref> were written while Theo was in the Netherlands in the summer of 1887. The exact dates of this stay are not documented, but it was probably a period of 10 to 14 days. (Theo usually took two weeks’ holiday.) He was at his mother’s in Breda on Tuesday, 26 July and in any event was back at work in Paris on Thursday, 28 July (see <hi rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 63 and Welsh-Ovcharov 1976, p. 250). This would mean that his leave started on or about Thursday, 14 July. Earlier – and hence a three-week holiday – is virtually ruled out because on Sunday, 10 July Theo still did not know when he would be free. On that day he wrote to Caroline van Stockum-Haanebeek: ‘I’m going to Holland this summer, perhaps very soon’ (FR b727). This means that his holiday did not start that weekend. It is known that he went to see Jo Bonger in Amsterdam on Friday, 22 July, while from <ref target="let572.xml">letter 572</ref> it can be deduced that he also visited his mother in Breda prior to that.</p>
<p rend="indent">
  <ref target="let571.xml">Letter 571</ref> was certainly written before <ref target="let572.xml">572</ref> since in the present letter Vincent says that he has painted <hi rend="italics">two</hi> works since Theo left, and in <ref target="let572.xml">letter 572</ref> he refers to <hi rend="italics">four</hi>. It is also evident that the money he had received, which he refers to in <ref target="let572.xml">letter 572</ref>, is the money he asked for in <ref target="let571.xml">letter 571</ref>.</p>
<p rend="indent">Theo’s letter with the money did not contain any news about Jo Bonger’s refusal of his marriage proposal, and was therefore probably sent on 21 July at the latest, so Vincent must have written this by Tuesday, 19 July at the latest. Since Theo must have left around 14 July and this letter was written relatively soon after his departure – Vincent says he hopes Theo will enjoy the visit – we have dated it between about Sunday, 17 and Tuesday, 19 July 1887.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>Vincent wrote all his previous letters to Theo – with the exception of those from the Borinage – in Dutch; now he switches to French. The reason for this must have been that because they both spent most of their time with French-speakers in Paris, they had become accustomed to communicating in French.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>We do not know which letter Vincent forwarded to Theo.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Le Tambourin was a restaurant and cabaret at 62 boulevard de Clichy in Montmartre, run by the Italian <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">Agostina Segatori</rs>. It was very popular with artists. Van Gogh exhibited work there and for some time had an affair with Segatori, as can be deduced from <ref target="let572.xml">letter 572</ref>. In 1903 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote that Van Gogh had been very much in love with Segatori, and in his ‘Souvenirs sur Van Gogh’ of 1924 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> said that he courted her by giving her a flower still life every day (cf. also <ref target="#n-3">n. 3</ref> below). See Gauguin 1923, p. 177, and Bernard 1994, vol. 1, p. 242. We do not know how serious it was or how long it lasted. See also cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In 1908 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> wrote that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_749">Segatori</rs> gave Van Gogh free meals in exchange for paintings, mainly flower pieces, and the walls were covered in his studies. ‘That lasted for some months, then the business collapsed and was sold, and all these paintings, piled up in a heap, were auctioned for a derisory sum.’ (Cela dura quelques mois, puis l’établissement périclita, fut vendu, et toutes ces peintures, mises en tas, furent adjugées pour un somme dérisoire.) See Bernard 1994, vol. 1, p. 167. From <ref target="let572.xml">letter 572</ref> it appears that Segatori was no longer in charge at Le Tambourin and would probably lose the business; Van Gogh must have heard that his paintings had been seized.</p>

<p rend="indent">Contrary to what Bernard suggested later, the works were not Van Gogh’s way of paying for his meals. He had evidently decorated the café with flower still lifes in the hope of selling them to customers, albeit without making specific arrangements with Segatori. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_10">Maurice Beaubourg</rs> stated in 1890 that Van Gogh had left everything behind ‘as security for the proprietor’ (comme gage au propriétaire), while Bernard wrote that the still lifes were auctioned off in batches of ten. At the beginning of his time in Arles Van Gogh remarked on how few flower still lifes from Paris he had been able to keep (<ref target="let640.xml">letter 640</ref>). There is consequently every reason to assume that he did not collect the works that were decorating the café, and that they were then sold at auction, possibly as part of bankruptcy proceedings. For this see cat. Amsterdam 2011.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>By ‘the rest’ Van Gogh must mean the Japanese prints that he had exhibited at Le Tambourin. Cf. <ref target="let640.xml">letter 640</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
  
<p>We do not know which two paintings these are; cf. <ref target="let572.xml#n-5">letter 572, nn. 5</ref> and <ref target="let572.xml#n-6">6.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>A louis was a coin worth 20 francs.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Asnières was a village on the Seine immediately to the north of Paris, just a few miles from rue Lepic. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1350">Signac</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs> worked there too.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Julien Tanguy</rs> was married to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_773">Renée Julienne Tanguy-Briend</rs>. Unlike her husband, she was not well liked by artists, as <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_831">Bernard</rs>’s description of her makes plain: ‘Silent and shaking her incredulous head, like a featherless bird’s, <hi rend="italics">mère</hi> Tanguy, who reflected bitterly that there was nothing to put on the table, and that they owed three lots of rent, appeared from the height of her practical philosophy to despise that whole world of “light-minded fine talkers”.’ (Muette et branlant sa tête incrédule d’oiseau déplumé, la <hi rend="italics">mère Tanguy</hi>, qui songeait amèrement qu’il n’y avait rien pour la table et que l’on devait trois termes, semblait mépriser du haut de sa philosophie pratique tout ce monde “d’écervelés et de beaux parleurs”.) See Bernard 1994, vol. 1, p. 166. Van Gogh took his own work to Tanguy.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>We do not know which painting <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec</rs> sold through <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Alphonse Portier</rs>. At that time Julius Elias was in any event buying his work, as emerges from two letters that Toulouse-Lautrec wrote to Portier at the end of 1887. The painter had told Portier in July 1887 that he could receive him and his visitors every day. See <hi rend="italics">Letters of Toulouse-Lautrec</hi> 1991, pp. 115, 121 (nos. 145, 154-155).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>This may be the watercolour <hi rend="italics">Grapes and pears</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1217">Sina Mesdag-Van Houten</rs>, which survived in her estate (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1141">Ill. 1141</rs>. The reason why this was sent has not been ascertained.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    