<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Thursday, 18 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let564"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b496 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>564</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>456</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>567</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-02-18">Thursday, 18 February 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0496" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0496" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000672_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Het is op het oogenblik dat mijn <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>geld geheel op is – geheel – dat ik U nog eens <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>schrijf<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Als gij iets zenden kunt<c type="kk">,</c> al was het vijf francs<c type="kk">,</c> laat <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>het niet<c type="kk">,</c> er zijn nog 10 dagen in de maand en <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>hoe moet ik ze doorkomen<c type="kp">.</c>– Want ik heb absoluut <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/><hi rend="italics">niets</hi> meer. Zelfs bij den bakker <hi rend="italics">niets</hi> meer<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Ik weet alleen dat al die dingen mij beslist <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>doen zien dat ik niet anders kan dan <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>zoo als ik U heb geschreven. Namelijk <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>het naar Parijs gaan niet uitstellen.–</p><lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Gij zult overigens aan het laatste werk dat gij <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>nog niet hebt gezien wel merken dat als ik <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>het schilderen wat rusten laat ik dit heel kalm <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>doe want het werken met de kwast zal mij zoo ligt <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>niet ontgaan.–</p><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">De teekeningen naar het antiek<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> zal ik U ook sturen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>dat is mij ongewoon en ik zal het nog anders krijgen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>– Zoo als ik overigens van daag een vrouwentors<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> afmaakte <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>die van modelé meer gedistingueerd is en minder brusque <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>dan de eersten<c type="kk">,</c> waar de figuren onwillekeurig <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>iets van boeren of houthakkers hebben.</p><lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Als ik niet ziek geweest was &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c> zou ik overigens <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>meer hebben kunnen doen hier.</p><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Hetgeen wij te doen hebben is heel bedaard vooruit<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>gaan – maar aan dat teekenen is niets te doen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>en het heeft het meeste haast.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">En ik weet het zoo zeker<c type="kk">,</c> dat het mij helpen <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>zal bij Cormon als ik den tusschentijd aan <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>niets anders besteed dan aan teekenen. <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>Cormon zal met de anderen gemeen hebben <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>dat hij niet veel tijd heeft<c type="kk">,</c> hoe hij overigens ook <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>zijn moge<c type="kp">.</c>– En wie om raad wil gaan <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>bij die lui moet het zijne van zooveel <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>mogelijk reeds weten meebrengen<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>En dat zoogoed als allen die bij hem <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>op ’t atelier zijn heel wat antiek hebben door<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>gemaakt en dat men zich (hoe vrij<c type="kk">,</c> hoe <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>liberaal overigens ’t atelier ook zij) – <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>daarop nog al baseert<c type="kk">,</c> dat is bepaald <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>te voorzien. Laat ons dus het met verstand <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>doen. Om studies die men buiten maakt <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>geven zij wel iets maar niet veel. En de lui <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>die in Parijs geweest zijn zeggen mij allen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>datzelfde – Ik zal bij Cormon de een <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>of andere proef moeten schilderen van <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>een naakt figuur naar de natuur – denkelijk<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> – <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>en hoe meer ik van te voren de structuur <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>in ’t hoofd heb<c type="kk">,</c> hoe beter en hoe meer <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>hij mij dingen zal kunnen en willen <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>zeggen.–</p><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">En verder<c type="kk">,</c> wij kunnen dan eens zien <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>of wij het zamen kunnen vinden – <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ik hoop dat wel – maar viel het ons <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>eens niet mede<c type="kk">,</c> dan wisten wij daaromtrent <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>iets meer degelijks als wij eerst een <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>paar maanden die voorloopige proef <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>hadden gedaan.–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Ik geloof wel degelijk dat wij ons houden <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>kunnen en er boven op komen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Maar het zou gekkewerk zijn indien wij <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>het niet in alle bedaardheid en kalmte <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>overlegden<c type="kp">.</c> En op onze gezondheid <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>moeten we<c type="kk">,</c> zoowel gij als ik<c type="kk">,</c> letten<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">En wat ik zeg over direkt naar Parijs komen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>is een bezuiniging voor U want met <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>heen &amp; weer trekken<c type="kk">,</c> met betrekkelijk duur <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>werk in Brabant beginnen <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>komen wij er niet met het gewone<c type="kk">,</c> en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>te Parijs wel. En valt het mee met het <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>geld<c type="kk">,</c> des te beter<c type="kk">,</c> dan zijn we minder ge<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>gêneerd en konden tegen den zomer <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>vooruit ons wat voorzien van schildergerij <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>zoodat niet alles op eens komt<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Neem het mij niet kwalijk dat ik ook <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>eens bereken het mogelijke en het <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>onmogelijke<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Ik herlees weer het boek van Bracquemond.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>en ik vind het hoe langer hoe mooier.</p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik merk wel dat gij het direkt <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>naar Parijs komen niet met mij <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>eens zijt want anders hadt gij me 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>wel reeds geantwoord. En toch <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>is het beter het direkt gebeure – ik <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>ben hier in de gelegenheid er lui die <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>terdeeg goed werken over te raadplegen <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>en ik heb de volle overtuiging dat <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>het zoo ’t beste ware.</p><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Overigens ’t had al eer kunnen gebeuren. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Het ging in den laatsten tijd <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>te slecht en ik zat te veel vast<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>En wij moeten dus dien coup de <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>collier geven<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Til het overigens niet te <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>zwaar want we zullen <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>niet mislukken<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Maar wat ik U zeg is zoo – <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>van dat ik dezen brief wegstuur <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>tot dat ik uw antwoord ontvang<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>dat dezen echter hoop ik kruist<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>ben ik zonder iets en is ’t weer <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>vastendag–.</p><lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Enfin.– we willen hopen <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>dat over een poos we zamen <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>zijn – en het allerergste geleden<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-a"/></p><lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Gegroet<c type="kk">,</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">b. à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Ik las dezer dagen Dumas<c type="kk">,</c> Dame aux camelias<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/><lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/> dat is zeer mooi – kent ge het<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">ik vertrouw de lui niet waar ik woon<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/> als ge zoo als laatst een brief <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>met geld stuurt is het secuurder maar aan te teekenen om die reden.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">It’s at the moment when my money has entirely gone — entirely — that I write to you again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">If you can send anything, even if it were five francs, don’t neglect to do it; there are still 10 days in the month and how am I to get through them? For I have absolutely <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> left. <hi rend="italics">Nothing</hi> left even at the baker’s.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> I only know that all these things definitely make me see than I can do nothing other than act as I’ve told you. That’s to say, not postpone going to Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">For the rest, you’ll notice in the latest work which you haven’t seen yet that if I give painting something of a rest, I do it very calmly because working with a brush won’t easily elude me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’ll also send you the drawings from the plaster casts;<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> this is unfamiliar to me and I’ll get it differently. Like the female torso<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I finished today, which is much more distinguished in the modelling and less brusque than the first ones, where in spite of myself the figures have something of the peasant or woodcutter about them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">If I hadn’t been ill &amp;c., by the way, I’d have been able to do more here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">What we have to do is go forward very calmly — but no progress can be made with drawing, and yet that’s the most urgent. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">And I’m quite sure that it will help me at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>’s if I spend the interim doing nothing but drawing. Cormon will be like the others in that he won’t have much time, whatever he may be like otherwise. And anyone who wants to go to those fellows for advice must take with them as much prior knowledge as possible. And it’s definitely to be expected that almost all of them who are in his studio will have gone through a great many plaster casts, and that (no matter how free, how liberal the studio may be otherwise) one relies on that quite heavily. So let’s do it sensibly. They have some interest, but not a lot, in studies that one makes outdoors. And the fellows who’ve been in Paris all tell me the same thing. At Cormon’s I’ll have to paint some test or other of a nude figure from life — probably<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> — and the more I have the structure fixed in my mind in advance the better, and the more he’ll be able and willing to tell me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">And furthermore, we’ll see whether we can get on together — I hope so — but if it didn’t work, then we’d know something more definite about it if we’d had that provisional trial for a few months first. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">I definitely believe that we can manage and get back on our feet.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">But it would be folly if we didn’t discuss it quite coolly and calmly. And we must, both you and I, take care of our health.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">And what I’m saying about coming straight to Paris is a saving for you because, what with going back and forth, and starting relatively expensive work in Brabant, we won’t manage with the usual, and in Paris we will. And if it turns out better than expected with the money, so much the better, then we won’t be so hard up and could stock up on painting materials before the summer so that everything doesn’t come at once.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Don’t take it amiss of me if I also calculate what’s possible and impossible for once.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">I re-read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs>’s book<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> again, and I find it better each time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I do realize that you don’t agree with me about coming straight to Paris, otherwise you would 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> already have answered me. And all the same, it’s better that it should happen immediately — I have the opportunity here to consult fellows about it who do really good work, and I’m entirely convinced that this would be the best.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">For that matter, it could have happened sooner. Things have been too bad recently and I was too hard up. And so we must put our backs into it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Don’t worry about it too much, because we won’t fail.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">But what I tell you is true — from the time I send this letter off until I receive your reply, which I hope will cross this, I have nothing and it’s fasting time again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Anyway — we’ll hope that we’ll be together in a while — and that the worst will be over.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Regards, with a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">I’ve just read <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_584">Dumas</rs>’s Dame aux camelias,<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> it’s very good — do you know it?</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">I don’t trust the people where I live;<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> if you send a letter with money, as you did recently, it’s safer just to register it for that reason.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Van Gogh writes: ‘there are still 10 days in the month’ <ref target="#l-5">(l. 5)</ref>. This means that the letter dates from Thursday, 18 February 1886. Jo van Gogh-Bonger also gave it this date in <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914 – she may have had a postmark.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Plan to move to Paris <ref target="let555.xml">(555)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Plan to study with Cormon <ref target="let556.xml">(556)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had previously had credit at the baker’s; <ref target="let563.xml">see letter 563</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had officially enrolled for the Classical Statues evening class taught by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1419">François Vinck</rs>, where shaded drawings were made after plaster torsos, limbs and complete casts of classical statues. See cat. Amsterdam 2001, pp. 13-15.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
    
<p>On the torso of a woman (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_642">F1693h / JH 1002</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_643">F 1693i / JH 1003</rs>): <ref target="let563.xml#n-4">letter 563, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Little is known about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>’s admission procedure. A recommendation (from a painter) was sometimes enough for someone to be accepted, but it was not essential. See Gauzi 1992, pp. 16-17, Galbally 1977, p. 29, and Destremau 1997.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_894">Bracquemond</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_418">Du dessin et de la couleur</ref></hi>: <ref target="let531.xml#n-2">letter 531, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘geleden zal zijn’ (will be over).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>In the novel <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_444">La dame aux camélias</ref></hi> (1848) by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_584">Alexandre Dumas fils</rs>, the courtesan Marguerite Gautier is reformed by the love of Armand Duval, who comes from a good family. The plot culminates in a love tragedy. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>See for the people who lived downstairs from Van Gogh in Beeldekensstraat: <ref target="let544.xml#n-1">letter 544, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    