<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Monday, 22 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let565"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b497 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>565</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>457</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>568</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-02-22">on or about Monday, 22 February 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0497" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0497" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000673_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">ik heb een brief verscheurd <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>dien ik U eerst schreef en daarom ontvangt <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>ge mijn antwoord wat later<c type="kp">.</c> Ik begin <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>met U te bedanken voor de frs 50<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Die ik apprecieer zoo als trouwens al wat gij <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>voor mij doet. Maar zooals ik begon <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>te zeggen<c type="kk">,</c> Uw brief stelt mij te leur waar <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>gij mijn verzoek niet inwilligt<c type="kk">,</c> omdat ik <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>toch zoozeer blijf meenen dat de redenen <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>welke ik U in vorig schrijven gaf <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>om liever reeds vroeger te komen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>regt van zijn hadden<c type="kp">.</c> Maar daar <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>ik er niet over wil twisten après tout<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>wilde ik U alleen verzoeken nog eens op <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>nieuw het te overwegen.</p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Met het oog op Cormon is ’t gedecideerd beter <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>ik doorga met antiek teekenen<c type="kk">,</c> liever dan buiten <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>werken<c type="kk">,</c> omdat hoe meer ik de structuur van ’t <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>figuur in ’t hoofd heb hoe beter ik zal kunnen <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>volgen. Ik krijg te doen met lui die <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/><hi rend="italics">jaren</hi> antiek geteekend hebben<c type="kk">,</c> als ik ’t <hi rend="italics">maanden</hi> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>doe is niet te veel<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Ik ben stouter misschien dan veel anderen<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>omdat ik steeds naar de natuur heb gewerkt<c type="kk">,</c> om <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>het er op te zetten en een ensemble aan te grijpen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>Maar de anderen hebben ligt<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> meer kennis <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>van ’t naakt<c type="kk">,</c> waar ik de gelegenheid niet zoo <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>voor heb gehad<c type="kp">.</c>– Werk ik dat bij – hoe eer hoe <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>liever – des te meer zal ik aan Cormon hebben<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Verder<c type="kk">,</c> mijn gezondheid – als ik buiten <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>schilder eet ik niet – en <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>overwin ik het niet<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Want ik zak nog telkens terug<c type="kk">,</c> ik <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>ben er nog lang niet boven op met mijn <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>gestel<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">En nu wat de kosten betreft<c type="kk">,</c> ik geloof zoo <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>dat het zusje en broertje is.<ptr target="#note-t-b"/></p><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Dus denk er nog eens goed over<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Wij moeten <hi rend="italics">handelen</hi> want er is een coup <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>de collier te geven.</p><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Terwijl ik hier was – al dien tijd – had ik een <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>kameraad in een ouden Franschman<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>ik heb zijn portret geschilderd<c type="kk">,</c> dat Verlat goed <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>vond.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en dat ge zien zult.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Voor dien was den winter nog harder dan voor <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>mij en de arme duivel is er heel wat erger aan <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>toe dan ik daar zijn leeftijd het zeer critiek <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>maakt.</p><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Ik was vandaag met hem bij den zelfden <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>dokter dien ik ook heb gehad<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en hij zal <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>denkelijk naar ’t gasthuis moeten om een <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>operatie te ondergaan. wat zich morgen <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>beslissen zal. Ik heb hem er eindelijk toe <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>gekregen maar hij zag er zoo tegen op dat <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>het lang geduurd heeft eer ik hem er toe kon <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>overhalen zijn vonnis te gaan hooren. <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Hij wist dat het iets nog al ergs zou zijn en durfde <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>zich niet aan den gasthuisdokter te vertrouwen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>Ik ben nieuwsgierig wat er beslist zal worden. <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Het is mogelijk ik om zijnentwil eenige dagen <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>langer in Maart hier blijf.</p><lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Après tout is er op de wereld niets zoo interessant <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>als de menschen. en men is er nooit in uitgestudeerd<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>En daarom zijn lui als Tourguenew groote meesters<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>omdat zij iemand leeren kijken<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">De boeken van nu<c type="kk">,</c> sedert Balzac b.v.<c type="kk">,</c> zijn anders <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>dan al wat in andere eeuwen geschreven is – en <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>mooier misschien<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Ik ben juist naar Tourgueneff erg verlangend <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>omdat ik een stuk van Daudet over hem heb gelezen <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>waar én hij zelf als karakter én zijn werk <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>geanalyseerd werden – fameus mooi<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Want als mensch is hij een exempel <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>en op zijn ouden dag was hij nog altijd jong <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>wat betreft <hi rend="italics">doorwerken</hi><c type="kk">,</c> wat betreft altijd <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>onvoldaan zijn over zich zelf en het al beter <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>en beter zoeken te doen.</p><lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Gegroet – maar denk nog eens <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>goed er over<c type="kk">,</c> het zou mij veel <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>geruststellen indien gij de kwestie <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>zien kondt zoo als ik.</p><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">En ik zou er zoo niet op aandringen indien <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>ik niet meende het noodig was<c type="kk">,</c> met het oog juist op Juni<c type="kk">,</c> dat ik <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>met antiek teekenen direkt doorging<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Enfin schrijf mij spoedig<c type="kk">,</c> ik zou voor <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>mijn pleizier liever iets anders schilderen <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>maar wat praktisch nut betreft is het <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>niet te ontwijken. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">b<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Het is juist omdat après tout ik nut van mijn <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>naar Antwerpen gaan meen te hebben dat ik <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>geloof wij regt door moeten gaan<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I tore up a letter that I wrote to you first, and that’s why you’re receiving my reply a little later. I’ll start by thanking you for the 50 francs.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Which I appreciate as, for that matter, I do everything you do for me. But as I started to say, your letter disappoints me since you don’t accede to my request, because I still continue to believe so strongly that the reasons which I gave you in my last letter for preferring to come even sooner were justified. But since I don’t want to argue about that, after all, I just wanted to ask you to reconsider it again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">With a view to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>, it’s decidedly better for me to go on drawing plaster casts rather than working outdoors, because the more I have the structure of the figure in my head, the better I’ll be able to follow. I’ll be dealing with fellows who’ve been drawing plaster casts <hi rend="italics">for years</hi>; if I do it <hi rend="italics">for months</hi>, it’s not too much. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Because I’ve always worked from nature, I may perhaps be more daring than many others in dashing things off and tackling a group of things. But the others will most likely have more knowledge of the nude, for which I haven’t had so much opportunity. If I make up for that — the sooner the better — the more benefit I’ll get from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>. Moreover, my health — when I paint outdoors I don’t eat — and I won’t overcome it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">For I keep relapsing; my constitution is still far from strong.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">And now as regards the cost, I believe it’s six of one and half a dozen of the other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">So think it over carefully again.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">We must <hi rend="italics">act</hi>, because we have to put our backs into it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">While I’ve been here — all this time — I’ve had a comrade, an old Frenchman. I’ve painted his portrait, which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1420">Verlat</rs> liked<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and which you will see. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">The winter was even harder for him than for me, and the poor devil is in a much worse state than I am, since his age makes it very critical.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Today I went with him to the same <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_330">doctor</rs> I went to myself,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and he’ll probably have to go into hospital and undergo an operation, which will be decided tomorrow. I eventually got him to that point, but he was dreading it so much that it took a long time before I could persuade him to go and hear the verdict. He knew that it was likely to be something quite serious and dared not entrust himself to the hospital doctor. I’m curious as to what will be decided. It’s possible I may stay here a few days longer in March for his sake.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">After all, there’s nothing in the world as interesting as people, and one is never done with studying them. And that’s why people like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_837">Turgenev</rs> are great masters, because they learn to look at a person.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">The books of the present, since <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_519">Balzac</rs>, say, are unlike anything written in other centuries — and better perhaps. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">I’m really looking forward to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_837">Turgenev</rs> just now because I’ve read a piece about him by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs> in which both the man himself as a character and his work were analyzed — extremely good.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> For he’s an example as a person, and in his old age he was still young as regards <hi rend="italics">continuing to work</hi>, as regards always being dissatisfied with himself, and trying to do it better and better all the time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Regards — but do think about it again carefully; it would greatly reassure me if you could see the matter as I do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">And I wouldn’t insist on it like this if I didn’t think it was necessary, with a view to June, specifically, for me to go on drawing plaster casts at once.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Anyway, write to me soon. For my own pleasure I’d rather paint something else, but as far as practical use is concerned, it’s unavoidable. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">It’s precisely because I think, after all, that I’ve derived benefit from coming to Antwerp that I believe we should go straight on.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent thanks Theo for the extra 50 francs. Assuming that Theo sent it shortly after the urgent request in <ref target="let564.xml">letter 564</ref> of 18 February, and taking into account the delay Van Gogh mentions in <ref target="#l-2">ll. 2-3</ref>, the present letter must have been written on or about Monday, 22 February 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Plan to move to Paris <ref target="let555.xml">(555)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Plan to study with Cormon <ref target="let556.xml">(556)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘allicht’ (most likely).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Saying: that it essentially makes no difference.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">Portrait of an old man</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2541">F 205 / JH 971</rs>); we do not know who this was.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_330">Dr Cavenaille</rs> <ref target="let558.xml#n-2">letter 558, n. 2.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            
      
<p>See for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_583">Daudet</rs>’s article ‘<ref target="biblio.xml#lit_440">Mémoires d’un homme de lettres. Tourguéneff</ref>’ on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_837">Turgenev</rs>: <ref target="let560.xml#n-5">letter 560, n. 5.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            
      
<p>Van Gogh was assuming that he and Theo would move to a new apartment in June, where he would have his studio, so that he could go and study with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>. Until then he wanted to practise drawing after plaster casts in the Louvre or in the Ecole des Beaux-Arts.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    