<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Tuesday, 16 or Wednesday, 17 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let563"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b495 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>563</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>455</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>566</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1886-02-16">Tuesday, 16 or Wednesday, 17 February 1886</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0495" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0495" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000671_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Zeer verlangend ben ik om van U te hooren<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>Want de tijd dat ik moet beslissen is er.</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Wij hebben nog maar een dag of 10 voordat de maand <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>om is en ik dien toch te weten hoe of wat.–</p><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Maar overigens<c type="kk">,</c> ik voor mij ben besloten – alleen het zou <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>mij aangenaam zijn als gij het ook zoo kondt inzien <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>als ik.–</p><lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Indien gij het goedvindt dat het plan doorgaat zoodra mogelijk <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>naar Parijs te komen – dus nadat ik een korten tijd in Brabant <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>geweest ben – dan stuur ik U van hier uit nog die studies &amp; <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>teekeningen die ik hier heb.</p><lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Ik wilde daar echter mede voortmaken<c type="kp">.</c> Want anders moet <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>ik alweer langer hier zijn.</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Ik zou ook zoo geducht graag die karwei aan mijn tanden <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>klaar hebben.</p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Wat moet ik doen.–</p><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">In alles heb ik nog een franc vijftig – en wat het eten betreft <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>heb ik nog voor vijf francs tegoed tot ’t einde der maand. <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Het is voor zooveel dingen wenschelijk dat wij spoedig dien <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>maatregel van veranderen nemen.</p><lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Ge begrijpt dat er niet overschiet om van hier schilderbehoeften <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>mede te nemen naar Brabant – ik zit ginder dus <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>dubbel vast waarschijnlijk<c type="kk">,</c> en met model en met verf. <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Er is dus geen keus – trouwens wat ware er voor keus noodig<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>want wat het meest presseert moet het eerst worden afgedaan <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>en dat is dien tijd naakt en antiek teekenen.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Ik schrijf U wat kort af misschien maar <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>het mag niet op den langen weg worden <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>geschoven.–</p><lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Overigens<c type="kk">,</c> eigentlijk spreekt het van zelf dat er geen enkel <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>bezwaar kan zijn om in Parijs voorloopig direkt een <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>mansarde te vinden den eersten den besten dag dat ik <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>er kom – en dan<c type="kk">,</c> ik kan in de Louvre of ecole <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>des Beaux arts teregt voor dat teekenen<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> en <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>het zal zoodoende des te beter bij Cormon lukken<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Dus laat ons niet talmen of in langdradigheden <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>vervallen.–</p><lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Wij moeten een coup de collier geven<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>welnu we zullen dien geven<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Willen we ooit iets goeds doen<c type="kk">,</c> reken er op dat hoe <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>langer hoe meer het op beslistheid en op vrij snel <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>handelen zal aankomen<c type="kk">,</c> en dat<c type="kk">,</c> waar toch <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>met alle moeite die men zich geven mogt <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>niemand vooruit den uitslag zijner ondernemingen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>kan weten met zekerheid<c type="kk">,</c> wat durven en <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>doortastend zijn geen kwaad kan.</p><lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Als het dus eenigzins kon wou ik nog deze <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>maand de andere helft van die karwei aan <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>mijn tanden laten doen. ik wou mijn <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>studies inpakken en ze U toezenden en <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>den laatsten van deze maand vertrekken <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>of zelfs een paar dagen eer.</p><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Maar niet weer in Maart blijven<c type="kk">,</c> ter wille <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>van de huur.–</p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Zou daar mogelijkheid op zijn. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Dan kan ik t’huis helpen inpakken indien <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>het hun tot iets nuttig kan zijn<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">En kan ik er nog wat schilderen of teekenen<c type="kk">,</c> des <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>te beter.</p><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Maar – hoe eer en hoe energieker <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>wij af doen dien tijd teekenen te Parijs<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>hoe beter voor de heele toekomst<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Zelfs hetgeen ik er in deze weinige weken <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>hier aan gedaan heb<c type="kk">,</c> voel ik mij helpt<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>En deed ik het niet dan zou ik er<c type="kk">,</c> al vond ik ’t op <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>een andere manier in de natuur zelf<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>dan zou ik er altijd last van houden met <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>lui die op de akademie of ergens anders geweest <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>waren – dat ik niet teekenen kon<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> – volgens hun<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Hoe het definitief hier op de akademie met mij <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zal afloopen weet ik nog niet – ik schreef U dat <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>laatst niet waar<c type="kk">,</c> van dat zij een standje met mij <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>bepaald <hi rend="italics">gezocht</hi> hadden.–<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Sibert – de leeraar – had<c type="kk">,</c> hoorde ik gisteren<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>ergens gezegd dat ik een goed begrip had van <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>teekenen en dat hij wat te haastig was geweest<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Daar hij niet druk in de klas komt heb ik hem in <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>eenige dagen niet gezien.</p><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Ik werk aan een vrouwentors op ’t moment<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Gegroet – maar schrijf zoo spoedig ge <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>kunt. Het blijft al mee ’t zelfde met mijn <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gestel maar toch geloof ik het aan ’t teregt komen <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>is. Met een handdruk<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">b<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">Als ik het niet deed – naar Parijs <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>gaan n.l. – dan werd ik ook <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>niet beter – want ik moet <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>er wat aan doen dat ik meer <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>verdien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>ik abimeer me nu te veel <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>– als er niets af hoefde <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>kon men best leven van frs 150 <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>maar er moet steeds te veel af<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>Maar het gaat toch vooruit <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>met mijn gezondheid – en het <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>zal teregt komen.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I’m really looking forward to hearing from you. For the time when I have to decide has come.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">We only have about 10 days until the end of the month, and I do need to know what’s what.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">But anyway, for my part I’ve decided — only it would be pleasant for me if you could see it the same way as I do.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">If you agree that the plan of coming to Paris should go ahead as soon as possible — in other words after I’ve been in Brabant for a short while — then I’ll send you from here the studies and drawings I have here.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I wanted to get on with that, though. Because otherwise I’ll have to be here for even longer.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">I’d also so very much like to get the work on my teeth finished.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">What should I do?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Altogether I’ve got one franc fifty left — and as for food, I’ve still got five francs credit until the end of the month. It’s desirable for so many reasons that we take the step of changing quickly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">You understand that I can’t afford to take painting materials with me from here to Brabant — so I’ll probably be in a double fix there, both for models and for paint. So there’s no choice — for that matter what need is there for a choice, for what’s most pressing has to be done first, and that’s this period of drawing nudes and plaster casts. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">I write to you rather curtly, perhaps, but it may not be put off.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">For the rest, it actually goes without saying that  there can’t be a single objection to finding a temporary garret in Paris right away, on the very first day I arrive — and then I can go to the Louvre or L’Ecole des Beaux-Arts for that drawing,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> and that way it’ll be all the more successful at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>’s. So let’s not delay or get involved in long-winded discussions.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">We have to put our backs into it; well then, we’ll do that.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">If we ever want to do anything good, depend upon it that it will increasingly come down to decisiveness and to quite swift action and that, while despite all the effort one might put in, no one can know with certainty the results of his enterprises in advance, some courage and promptness of action can do no harm.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">If it were in any way possible, I’d like to have the second half of that work on my teeth done this month. I’d like to pack up my studies and send them to you, and leave on the last day of this month or even a few days earlier.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">But not stay on into March, on account of the rent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Would there be a possibility of that? 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Then I can help with the packing at home if it could be of any use to them.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">And if I could do a little painting or drawing there, so much the better.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">But — the sooner and more energetically we get through that period of drawing in Paris, the better for the whole future. Even what I’ve done in these few weeks here has helped, I feel. And if I didn’t do it, then I would, even though I found it in a different way in nature itself, then I’d always have trouble with fellows who had been at some academy or other — that I couldn’t<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> draw — according to them. I still don’t know how things will turn out for me in the end at the academy here — I wrote and told you recently, didn’t I, about how they’d deliberately <hi rend="italics">picked</hi> a quarrel with me.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">I heard yesterday that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1351">Siberdt</rs> — the teacher — had said somewhere that I had a good understanding of drawing and that he’d been rather too hasty. Since he doesn’t come into the class all that often, I haven’t seen him in several days.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">I’m working on a female torso at the moment.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Regards — but write as soon as you can. My constitution is more or less the same, but still I think it’s beginning to improve. With a handshake.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.25" n="25">If I didn’t do it — go to Paris, that is — then I wouldn’t get any better — for I have to do something about earning more. I’m doing myself no good at all now — if nothing had to be taken off, one could live perfectly well on 150 francs, but there’s always too much to come off. But still, my health is improving — and it will come right.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Van Gogh writes: ‘We only have about 10 days until the end of the month’ <ref target="#l-3">(ll. 3-4)</ref>. This month must have been February. <ref target="let564.xml">Letter 564</ref> of 18 February was written after the present one, because in it, in contrast to the present letter, Vincent no longer has any doubts about his going to Paris; we have therefore dated it Tuesday, 16 or Wednesday, 17 February 1886.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Plan to move to Paris <ref target="let555.xml">(555)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
    <p>Van Gogh has problems with his teeth <ref target="let557.xml">(557)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            <p>Plan to study with Cormon (<ref target="let556.xml">556</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In <ref target="let559.xml">letter 559</ref> Van Gogh had already suggested that he could spend his time in Paris, before going to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_944">Cormon</rs>, drawing in the Louvre and the Ecole des Beaux-Arts.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘kan’ (can) rather than ‘kon’ (could).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for this ‘quarrel’: <ref target="let561.xml">letter 561</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>The female torso he refers to is not known; it may have been the same torso he drew twice in a sketchbook: <hi rend="italics">Plaster torso of a woman</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_642">F1693h / JH 1002</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Plaster torso of a woman seen from the side</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_643">F 1693i / JH 1003</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    