<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Thursday, 17 December 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let548"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b480 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>548</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>440</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>551</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1885-12-17">on or about Thursday, 17 December 1885</date>
                            <placeName>Antwerp</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0480" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0480" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000649_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Waarde Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">het is vandaag voor ’t eerst dat <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>ik me wat flaauw voel<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> – ik had een <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>schilderij gemaakt van het Steen<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en ben <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>er mede uit geweest naar de handelaars<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Ik vond er twee niet thuis en een <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>vond het niet goed en een lamenteerde <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>op een gruwelijke manier dat er in 14 dagen <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>letterlijk niemand een voet bij hem in den <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>winkel had gezet. Dit is niet heel opwekkend<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>vooral als het kil en triest weer is en men <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>zijn laatste 5 francstuk reeds geentameerd <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>heeft en staat voor 14 dagen waar men <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>geen gat in ziet.</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Maar enfin. Alleen zie dat gij me <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>voor die 14 dagen nog wat aan den gang <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>houdt want ik wil nog iets in figuur <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>zien te krijgen<c type="kp">.</c> Ik hoorde echter van <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>morgen zeggen dat er nog al uit de hand <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>verkocht was van die schilderijen waar ik U <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>over schreef<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/> men noemde ’t cijfer 21 mille<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Ik weet niet of ’t waar is<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Maar in alle geval<c type="kk">,</c> het was er vol met <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>kijkers toen ik ze gezien heb en het was ook <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>vol op de tentoonstelling van de verloting.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Als men meer en beter liet kijken zou <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>er meer omgaan. Maar de winkels zien <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>er lugubre uit.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Het sch<hi rend="super">ij</hi> van het Steen is nog al uitvoerig <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>en ik zal er nog een bij maken van een ander <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>punt van de kaai<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Toch<c type="kk">,</c> ik schilder zooveel liever figuur – <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ik geloof ook dat de markt wat vol <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>landschappen zou kunnen raken <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>en al heeft men veel meer bezwaren <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>voor figuur wegens de modellen – <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>toch is ’t misschien een betere kans<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Wat de handelaars zeggen is dat zij <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>vrouwenkoppen of vrouwenfiguren nog <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>’t beste achten voor den verkoop<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Ik zal dit voorjaar moeten beslissen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>of ik al dan niet in de buurt van <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Nuenen zou blijven. Ik wou wel <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>dat ge over die kwestie eens uw gedachten <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>liet gaan<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Ik kan ’t me toch zoo slecht begrijpen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>dat Portier na zoo duidelijk zich te <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>hebben uitgedrukt over mijn werk – <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>sedert blijkbaar radicaal onverschillig is <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>geworden<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Ik ga er niet op vooruit als ik <hi rend="italics">meer</hi> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>moet verschilderen dan ik ontvang<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>En ik heb ’t hier nog niets<c type="kk">,</c> letterlijk niets <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>beter voor me zelf dan jaren terug toen <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ik dien winter in Brussel was<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Ik had toen frs 50 minder doch het schilderen <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>eischt veel meer dan frs 50<c type="kk">,</c> dat er <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>direkt af moet.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Zoolang ik schilder voel ik me niet flaauw <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>maar op den duur – zijn de <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>tusschenruimten wel wat erg <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>triest soms<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">En het gaat mij aan ’t hart als ik de zaken <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>niet wat uitbreiden kan en het altijd een <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>tusschen hangen &amp; wurgen is<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Want ge moet wel begrijpen dat b.v. zoolang ik nu hier <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>ben<c type="kk">,</c> ik slechts 3 keer wat warm eten heb gezien en dat de rest <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>altijd maar brood is. Zoo wordt men meer <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>vegetarier dan nuttig is<c type="kp">.</c> Vooral waar <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>in Nuenen het wel een half jaar lang ook zoo moest <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>gaan en ik daar nog niet eens toekwam met mijn <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>verfrekening<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Het schilderen is duur en men moet veel schilderen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Ik heb een halve belofte om een model te krijgen <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>voor een portret<c type="kk">,</c> ik zal dat door zien te drijven.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Hetgeen ik me nu niet begrijpen kan is <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>dat b.v. iemand als Portier<c type="kk">,</c> als Serret – <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>indien zij dan niet verkoopen kunnen – <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>niet althans eens een idee krijgen om <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>werk te bezorgen<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Hoor eens Theo, nog iets – ik geloof dat het U niet <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>onbegrijpelijk zal voorkomen dat ik niet de aller<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>geringste ambitie heb om aan t’huis te schrijven <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>als zij bij mijne lieftallige zuster Anna en andere <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>voor mij zoo lieftallige leden der familie zijn<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Een brief ontvangen hebbende van Moe die mij <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>vraagt om te schrijven en van U mijn adres <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>gevraagd zeide te hebben<c type="kk">,</c> wil hun doen weten <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>dat ik niet schrijf<c type="kk">,</c> zooals ik trouwens zelf reeds <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>eenvoudig hun bij mijn vertrek te kennen gaf<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>Ge begrijpt dat waar het in Maart <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>gegaan is zoo als ’t ging<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/> dit van die <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>dingen zijn die beslissend zijn.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">ik ben toen ’t huis uitgegaan &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>daar volgt van zelf uit dat<c type="kk">,</c> zij <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/><hi rend="italics">hun</hi> zin hebbende gehad<c type="kk">,</c> ik verder <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>al bitter en bitter weinig aan hun denk<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="96a" xml:id="l-96a"/>trouwens ook niet begeer dat zij aan mij denken. <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>Zeker is het een ongelukkig ding als het zoo <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>gaan moet. Maar daar hebt ge nu van <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>die herinneringen als b.v. dat Pa tot ’t laatste <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>toe tegen mij eveneens sprak &amp; deed<c type="kk">,</c> ja<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>als de pastoor<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p><lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Begrijpen zij dat dan zelf niet<c type="kk">,</c> dat juist <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>als men ophoudt er boos om te zijn<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>het definitief een vreemder dan vreemden <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>voor elkaar zijn is geworden<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Zeg het Moe zoo als ge wilt want ik spreek <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>er ook niet hard tegen<c type="kk">,</c> maar schrijven <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>begin ik niet aan. En Moe is oud dus ik wil niet <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>schrijven dat ik niet schrijf op een scherpe manier<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>Het is met meer schilders ’t geval geweest en er <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>zijn dingen waar men <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>verder niet aan tornen moet.–</p><lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Er is op ’t museum een portret van Delaroche<c type="kk">,</c> geschilderd <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>door Portaels.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Wat leek hij<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> veel bij zijn leven. <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>wat bleek hij hol en ledig geweest te zijn later<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>Manet en Courbet<c type="kk">,</c> die tijdens hun leven niet serieus <hi rend="italics">leken</hi><c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>wat <hi rend="italics">waren</hi> zij ’t inderdaad als schilder<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p><lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Met ’t portret van Delaroche is door een curieus toeval <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>een ongeluk gebeurd zoo dat er een gat vlak midden <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>in ’t voorhoofd is gevallen<c type="kp">.</c>– Dat doet wel goed en hoort <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>er eigentlijk zoo bij. Ah – er is een heel curieus <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>ras van personen van wie men op zekere <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>momenten niet denken zou dat inderdaad zij <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>goed secuur hol en leeg zijn<c type="kp">.</c>– Men kan zich <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>vergissen<c type="kp">.</c>– En – het lucht wel eens op als men <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>merkt dat men zich vergist heeft – al moet men dan van <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>voren af aan beginnen.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Gegroet<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">b<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Today, for the first time, I feel rather dejected<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> — I’d made a painting of Het Steen<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and took it round the dealers. Two of them were out, and one didn’t like it, and one lamented in a dreadful manner that literally no one had set foot in his shop in a fortnight. This isn’t very cheering, particularly when the weather’s cold and bleak, and one has already broken into one’s last 5 franc piece and is faced with a fortnight in which one sees no way ahead.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">But anyway. Only see that you keep me going for this fortnight because I want to get something more in figures. I heard it said this morning, though, that quite a few of those paintings I wrote to you about<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> were sold privately. A figure of 21 thousand was mentioned. I don’t know whether it’s true.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">But in any event it was crowded with visitors when I saw it, and the exhibition for the lottery was crowded, too.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> If they showed more and better things, more would sell. But the shops look grim.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">The painting of Het Steen is quite elaborate, and I’ll make another one from a different point on the quay.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">All the same, I’d so much rather paint figures — I also think that the market could get rather full of landscapes, and although one has far more difficulties with figures because of the models — all the same, it may be a better chance. What the dealers say is that they still think women’s heads or figures of women are most likely to sell.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">This spring I’ll have to decide whether or not I’ll stay in the Nuenen area. I’d like you to give the question some thought.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I really can’t understand why <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs>, having expressed himself so clearly about my work — has since apparently become deeply indifferent.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">I won’t make progress if I have to spend <hi rend="italics">more</hi> on paint than I receive. And for myself I’m no better, literally no better off than I was years ago when I spent that winter in Brussels.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">I had 50 francs less then, but painting costs much more than 50 francs, and has to be laid out immediately.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">I don’t feel dejected as long as I’m painting, but in the long run — the periods in between can sometimes be very depressing.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">And it grieves me when I can’t develop things a little, and one’s always between the devil and the deep sea.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">For you have to understand, for instance, that ever since I’ve been here I’ve only had some hot food 3 times, and that otherwise it’s always just bread. Thus one becomes more of a vegetarian than is good for one. Particularly when it had to be the same in Nuenen for a good six months, and I still couldn’t even manage to settle my paint bill.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">Painting is expensive and one has to paint a lot. I have a half promise of getting a model for a portrait; I’ll try to push that through.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Now, what I can’t understand is that someone like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_601">Portier</rs>, say, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1354">Serret</rs> — if they can’t sell — don’t at least come up with an idea to market work.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">Listen Theo, something else — I believe that it won’t seem incomprehensible to you that I don’t have the slightest desire to write to the people at home while they’re with my charming sister <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and other members of my family who are also so charming to me.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> As I’ve received a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs>, who asks me to write and said she’d asked you for my address, will you let them know that I won’t write, which for that matter I already made quite plain when I left? You’ll understand when something happens as it did in March,<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> it’s one of those things that is decisive. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I left the house then &amp;c. It follows automatically that, since they got <hi rend="italics">their</hi> way, I hardly think about them at all, hardly at all; for that matter don’t want them to think about me either. Certainly it’s an unfortunate thing that it has to be like this. But then there are those memories like, for instance, that until the end <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">Pa</rs> also spoke and acted towards me, yes, like the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_565">priest</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">Don’t they understand that themselves — that precisely when one has ceased to be angry about it, it has definitely become a matter of stranger than strangers to one another?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">Tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Ma</rs> this if you like, for I don’t wish to be harsh to her, but I don’t intend to start writing. And Ma is old, so I don’t want to write that I won’t write in a sharp way. It’s been the same with other painters, too, and there are things one shouldn’t meddle with any further.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">At the museum there’s a portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs>, painted by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1273">Portaels</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> How important he<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> seemed in life. How hollow and empty he proved to be later. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1182">Manet</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_962">Courbet</rs>, who didn’t <hi rend="italics">seem</hi> to be serious during their lifetimes, how much so they actually <hi rend="italics">were</hi> as painters.<ptr target="#note-t-13"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">By a curious chance, an accident to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs>’s portrait has left it with a hole in the middle of the forehead. It looks good and actually seems to belong there. Ah — there’s a very curious race of people whom one wouldn’t think at certain times are indeed absolutely and utterly hollow and empty. One can be mistaken. And it’s a relief when one realizes that one has been mistaken — even if one then has to start from the beginning again.<ptr target="#note-t-14"/> Regards.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Yours truly,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>When Van Gogh wrote this letter there was still ‘a fortnight’ of the month left to go <ref target="#l-11">ll. 11-13</ref>). We have therefore dated the letter on or about Thursday, 17 December 1885.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Portier’s indifferent attitude <ref target="let546.xml">(546)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>In view of what follows this means: ‘in a depressed mood’ (cf. <ref target="#l-58">l. 58</ref>); it must have been exacerbated by the fact that Van Gogh felt physically weak because he had had virtually no hot food <ref target="#l-66">(l. 66)</ref> and, as he says a week or two later, his appetite was suppressed during this period (<ref target="let550.xml">letter 550</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>A painting of Het Steen Castle on the Scheldt in Antwerp is not known, although two drawings of it (possibly preliminary sketches) have survived: <hi rend="italics">View of Het Steen</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_625">F 1350 / JH 976</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_626">F 1351 / JH 977</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>See for this sale of paintings <ref target="let547.xml#n-11">letter 547, n. 11.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>See for this lottery <ref target="let547.xml#n-10">letter 547, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>This work is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh was in Brussels from early October 1880 until 12 April 1881. <ref target="let159.xml">See letters 159</ref>-<ref target="let165.xml">165</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>In the end this came to nothing.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and her daughter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Willemien</rs> were evidently staying in Leiderdorp with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_412">Anna</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_413">Joan van Houten-Van Gogh</rs> and their two daughters <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_415">Sara</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_414">Annie</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            
    
<p>See for the frictions surrounding Van Gogh’s departure from his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524 bio.xml#_526">parents</rs>’ house <ref target="let490.xml#n-8">letter 490, nn. 8</ref> and <ref target="let490.xml#n-9">9.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_565">Andreas Pauwels</rs>, the priest in Nuenen, had frustrated Van Gogh’s endeavours by forbidding his Catholic parishioners to model for him. <ref target="let531.xml">See letter 531</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1273">Jean François Portaels</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Paul Delaroche</hi>, c. 1850 (Antwerp, Koninklijk Museum voor Schone Kunsten). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1220">Ill. 1220</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Paul Delaroche</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="13" xml:id="note-t-13">
                            

<p>Van Gogh could have read about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_962">Courbet</rs>’s ‘caprices burlesques’ in <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_742">Silvestre</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_416">Histoire des artistes vivants français et étrangers</ref></hi> (see Silvestre, <hi rend="italics">Histoire</hi>, pp. 242-277 (quotation on p. 247).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="14" xml:id="note-t-14">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is also referring here to his own change of heart about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_983">Delaroche</rs>, whom he had previously greatly admired.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    