<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Monday, 6 August 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let656"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b559 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>656</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>518</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>660</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1888-08-06">Monday, 6 August 1888</date>
                            <placeName>Arles</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0559" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0559" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000752_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">mon cher Theo,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">il me semble que tu aies bien fait de te rendre à l’enterrement de l’oncle <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>puisque la mère semblait t’attendre. le meilleur moyen de mourir autrement c’est <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>de gober l’illustre défunt tel quel comme étant le meilleur homme du meilleur des <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>mondes possible où tout va toujours pour le mieux.–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Ce qui étant incontesté <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>et par conséquent incontestable<c type="kk">,</c> il nous demeure après sans doute loisible <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>de retourner à nos affaires. Cela me fait plaisir que notre frère Cor soit devenu <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>plus gros &amp; plus fort que nous autres. Et il doit être <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>stupide s’il ne se marie pas car il n’a que ça et ses bras. Avec ça et <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>ses bras ou ses bras &amp; ça et ce qu’il sait des machines<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> moi pour un voudrais être à <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>sa place si j’avais des désirs quelconques d’être quelqu’un.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">En attendant je suis dans ma peau et ma peau dans <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>l’engrenage des <hi rend="italics">Beaux Arts</hi> comme le grain entre les <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>meules.</p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">T’ai je dit que j’ai envoyé des dessins à l’ami Russell.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Dans ce <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>moment je refais à peu près les mêmes pour toi<c type="kk">,</c> il y en aura <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>12 également.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Tu vas voir mieux alors ce qu’il y a dans les études <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>peintes comme dessin. Je t’ai déja dit que j’ai toujours à lutter <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>contre le mistral qui empêche absolument d’être le maitre de <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>sa <hi rend="italics">touche</hi><c type="kp">.</c> De là le “hagard” des études. Tu me diras <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>qu’au lieu de les dessiner je devais les repeindre sur d’autres <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>toiles chez moi<c type="kp">.</c>– C’est à quoi je songe parfois car c’est pas de ma <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>faute que dans le cas donné l’exécution manque de touche plus <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>spirituelle. Qu’en dirait Gauguin s’il était ici<c type="kk">,</c> serait-il d’avis de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>chercher un endroit plus abrité?</p><lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Je dois maintenant te dire une chôse désagréable encore pour <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>l’argent<c type="kk">,</c> c’est que je n’arriverai <hi rend="italics">pas</hi> cette semaine car aujourd’hui <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>même je paye 25 francs<c type="kk">,</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> j’aurai de l’argent pour 5 jours <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>et pour sept <hi rend="italics">non</hi><c type="kp">.</c> Nous avons lundi – si Samedi matin <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>j’ai ta prochaine lettre<c type="kk">,</c> inutile d’augmenter alors le <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>contenu.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Semaine derniere j’ai non seulement fait un mais meme <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>deux portraits de mon facteur<c type="kk">,</c> un mi corps <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>avec mains &amp; une tête grandeur nature<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p><lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">le bonhomme n’acceptant pas d’argent <hi rend="italics">etait plus cher</hi> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>mangeant<c type="kk">,</c> buvant avec moi et je lui donne en outre <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>La Lanterne de Rochefort.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Enfin voila un mal faible <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>et sans importance en comparaison de ce qu’il a fort bien <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>posé cela<c type="kk">,</c> et que je compte aussi peindre son nouveau <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>né sous peu. Car sa femme vient d’accoucher.</p><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Je t’enverrai en même temps que les dessins que j’ai en <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>train deux lithographies de de Lemud<c type="kk">,</c> “le vin” et “le café”;<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>dans “le vin” il y a un espèce de Méfisto qui fait un peu penser à C<c type="kp">.</c>M<c type="kp">.</c> plus jeune<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>et dans le café – .. c’est absolument Raoul – tu sais cet <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>espèce d’étudiant vieux bohème encore que <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>j’ai connu l’année passée.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Quel talent à la Hoffmann <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ou Edgard Poe<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> il a ce de Lemud. En voilà un dont <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>on parle si rarement pourtant. Tu n’aimeras peut être <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>pas énormement ces lithographies à première vue – mais c’est <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>justement en les regardant plus longtemps que cela gagne<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Je n’ai plus ni toile ni couleurs &amp; ai deja dû <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>acheter ici<c type="kp">.</c> Et il me faut encore en reprendre<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Je te prie donc d’envoyer ta lettre de façon que je l’aie Samedi matin<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Je vais aujourd’hui probablement commencer <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>l’intérieur du café où je loge<c type="kk">,</c> le soir au gaz<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-12"/> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>C’est ce qu’on appelle ici un “café de nuit” (ils sont assez fréquents ici) <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>qui restent ouverts toute la nuit<c type="kp">.</c>– Les “rodeurs de nuit” <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>peuvent y trouver un asile donc<c type="kk">,</c> lorsqu’ils n’ont <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>pas de quoi se payer un logement ou qu’ils soient <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>trop souls pour y être admis.</p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Toutes ces chôses<c type="kk">,</c> famille<c type="kk">,</c> patrie<c type="kk">,</c> sont peutetre plus <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>charmantes dans l’imagination de tels que nous – qui nous passons passablement bien de patrie ainsi que <lb n="61a" xml:id="l-61a"/>de famille – <lb n="61"/>que dans <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>aucune réalité<c type="kp">.</c> Il me semble toujours être un voyageur <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>qui va quelque part &amp; à une destination<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Si je me dis<c type="kk">,</c> le quelque part<c type="kk">,</c> la destination n’existent <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>point<c type="kk">,</c> cela me semble bien raisonné et véridique.</p><lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Le souteneur du bordel lorsqu’il fout quelqu’un à la porte <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>en a une pareille de logique<c type="kk">,</c> raisonne bien aussi et a toujours <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>raison. Je le sais<c type="kp">.</c> Aussi à la fin de la carrière <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>j’aurai tort. Que soit. Je trouverai alors que <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>non seulement les beaux arts mais le reste aussi <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>n’étaient que des rêves<c type="kk">,</c> que soi-même on était rien du tout<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Si nous sommes <hi rend="italics">si légers que ça</hi> tant mieux pour <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>nous<c type="kk">,</c> rien ne s’opposant alors à la possibilité illimitée <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>d’existence future. D’où vient que dans le cas présent de <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>la mort de notre oncle le visage du mort était calme<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>serein et grave<c type="kp">.</c> Lorsque c’est un fait que vivant il n’était <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>guère ainsi ni étant jeune ni vieux<c type="kp">.</c>– Si souvent j’ai constaté <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>un effet comme cela en regardant un mort comme pour <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>l’interroger. Et cela est pour moi <hi rend="italics">une</hi> preuve – non pas <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>la plus sérieuse – d’une existence d’outre tombe.</p><lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Un enfant dans le berceau egalement<c type="kk">,</c> si on le regarde <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>à son aise<c type="kk">,</c> a l’infini dans les yeux. En somme <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>je n’en sais rien mais justement ce sentiment <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>de <hi rend="italics">ne pas savoir</hi> rend la vie reelle que nous vivons <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>actuellement comparable à un simple trajet en chemin <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>de fer. On marche vite mais ne distingue aucun objet de très près et surtout on <lb n="86a" xml:id="l-86a"/>ne voit pas la locomotive.</p><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Il est assez curieux que notre oncle comme notre pere <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>croyaient à la vie future. Sans parler de notre père <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>j’ai plusieurs fois entendu l’oncle raisonner là-dessus<c type="kp">.</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>Ah – par exemple ils étaient plus sûrs que nous et <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>affirmaient<c type="kk">,</c> se fâchant si on osait approfondir<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">La vie <hi rend="italics">future</hi> des artistes <hi rend="italics">par leurs oeuvres</hi> je n’en vois pas grand chôse<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>Oui les artistes se continuent en se passant le flambeau<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>Delacroix aux impressionistes &amp;c<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Mais est ce là tout?–</p><lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Si une bonne vieille mère de famille à idées passablement bornées <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>et martyrisées dans le système crétien serait immortelle ainsi <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>qu’elle le croit – et cela <hi rend="italics">sérieusement</hi>. Et moi pour un n’y contredis point<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Pourquoi un cheval de fiacre poitrinaire ou nerveux comme Delacroix <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>et de Goncourt<c type="kk">,</c> aux idees larges cependant<c type="kk">,</c> le seraient ils moins<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>Vu qu’il parait que juste les gens les plus vidés sentent <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>naître cette indefinissable espérance<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Suffit<c type="kk">,</c> à quoi bon s’en préoccuper. Mais en vivant <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>en pleine civilisation<c type="kk">,</c> en plein Paris et plein beaux arts<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>pourquoi ne garderait on pas ce moi de vieille femme<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>Si les femmes elles-même sans leur croyance de “<hi rend="italics">ca y est</hi>” instinctif <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>ne trouveraient pas la force de créer et d’agir<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">Alors les medecins nous diront que non seulement Moise<c type="kk">,</c> Mahomet<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>le Christ<c type="kk">,</c> Luther<c type="kk">,</c> Bunyan et autres etaient fous mais egalement <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>Frans Hals<c type="kk">,</c> Rembrandt<c type="kk">,</c> Delacroix et egalement toutes <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>les vieilles bonnes femmes bornees comme notre mère. <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>Ah – c’est grave cela<c type="kp">.</c>– On pourrait demander à ces <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>medecins où alors seraient les gens raisonables<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">Sont ce les souteneurs de bordel ayant toujours raison<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>Il est probable<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Alors que choisir. heureusement il n’y a pas à choisir<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>Poignée de main &amp;</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.23" n="23">t<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="118a" xml:id="l-118a"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Theo,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">It seems to me that you did well to go to our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">uncle</rs>’s funeral, as our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> seemed to expect you. The best way of dying otherwise is to esteem the illustrious departed just as he is, as being the best man in the best of possible worlds, where everything is always for the best.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Which being uncontested and thus incontestable, we are then no doubt at liberty to return to our own business afterwards. I’m pleased that our brother <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> has grown bigger and stronger than the two of us. And he’ll be stupid if he doesn’t marry, because he has only that and his hands. With that and his hands, or his hands and that, and what he knows about machines,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I for one would like to be in his position if I had any sort of desire to be somebody.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Meanwhile, I’m in my skin, and my skin in the gear-wheels of the <hi rend="italics">Beaux-Arts </hi>like the grain between the millstones.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">Did I tell you that I sent some drawings to our friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>?<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> At the moment I’m doing the same ones, more or less, for you; there’ll be 12 of them too.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> You’ll see better then what there is in the painted studies in the way of drawing. I’ve already told you that I always have to struggle against the mistral, which absolutely prevents one being in control of one’s <hi rend="italics">touch</hi>. Hence the ‘wild’ look of the studies. You’ll tell me that instead of drawing them I ought to repaint them at home on other canvases. That’s what I sometimes think about, because it’s not my fault that in the case given the execution lacks a more spiritual touch. What would <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> say about it if he was here? Would he be in favour of looking for a more sheltered place?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I must now tell you something disagreeable again about money; it’s that I <hi rend="italics">won’t </hi>manage this week, because this very day I pay 25 francs;<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> I’ll have money for 5 days and <hi rend="italics">not </hi>for seven. It’s Monday — if I have your next letter on Saturday morning, no need then to increase the contents. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Last week I did not only one but even two portraits of my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">postman</rs>, one half-length, with hands, and a life-size head.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">The chap, not accepting money, <hi rend="italics">was more expensive,</hi> eating, drinking with me, and in addition I gave him <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_731">Rochefort</rs>’s La Lanterne.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> But there you are, a minor and unimportant problem compared with the fact that he posed for it very well, and that I also plan to paint his newborn <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_651">baby</rs> shortly. Because his <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_648">wife</rs> has just given birth.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">At the same time as the drawings that I have on the go I’ll send you two lithographs by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1167">De Lemud</rs>, ‘Wine’ and ‘Coffee’;<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> in ‘Wine’ there’s a Mephisto character who makes you think a little of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_422">C.M.</rs> when younger, and in Coffee —.. it’s absolutely Raoul — you know that perpetual old bohemian student type whom I knew last year.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> What a talent, in the style of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_645">Hoffmann</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_723">Edgar Poe</rs>,<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> this De Lemud has. And yet there’s somebody who’s spoken of so rarely. You’ll perhaps not like these lithographs very much at first glance — but it’s precisely when looking at them longer that they grow on you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">I have no more canvas or paint and have already had to buy here. And I have to get even more. So I beg you to send your letter so that I have it on Saturday morning.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Today I’m probably going to start on the interior of the café where I’m staying, in the evening, by gaslight.<ptr target="#note-t-12"/> It’s what they call a ‘night café’ here (they’re quite common here), that stay open all night. This way the ‘night prowlers’ can find a refuge when they don’t have the price of a lodging, or if they’re too drunk to be admitted. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">All these things, family, native country, are perhaps more appealing in the imagination of such as us — who do fairly well without a native country, as well as a family — than in any reality. It always seems to me that I’m a traveller who’s going somewhere and to a destination.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">If I say to myself, the somewhere, the destination don’t exist at all, that seems well argued and truthful to me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">When he kicks somebody out, the brothel-keeper has a logic of the same kind, argues well, too, and is always right. I know that. And at the end of my career I’ll be wrong. So be it. Then I’ll find that not only the fine arts but the rest as well were nothing but dreams, that we were nothing at all ourselves. If we’re <hi rend="italics">as lightweight as that</hi>, so much the better for us, as nothing would then stand in the way of the limitless possibility of future existence. Which is why in the present case of our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">uncle</rs>’s death, the dead man’s face was tranquil, serene and grave. When it’s a fact that, while living, he was scarcely like that, neither when young nor when old. So often I’ve noticed an effect like that when looking at a dead man as if to question him. And that’s <hi rend="italics">one </hi>proof for me — not the most weighty — of an existence beyond the grave.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">And a baby in its cradle, also, if you look at it at your ease, has the infinite in its eyes. In fact, I know nothing about it, but precisely this feeling of <hi rend="italics">not knowing </hi>makes the real life that we’re living at present comparable to a simple journey by train. You go fast, but you can’t distinguish any object very close up, and above all, you can’t see the locomotive. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">It’s rather odd that our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_423">uncle</rs>, like our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_526">father</rs>, believed in the future life. Not to mention our father, I’ve heard our uncle debating it several times. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>Ah — for example, they were more certain than us, and asserted themselves, getting angry if one dared go into it more deeply.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">I don’t see much of the <hi rend="italics">future </hi>life of artists <hi rend="italics">through their works</hi>. Yes, artists perpetuate themselves, passing on the torch, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> to the Impressionists, &amp;c. </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">But is that all?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">If a kind old mother of a family, with pretty limited ideas that are tormented in the Christian system, were immortal, just as she believes — and this <hi rend="italics">seriously.</hi> And I for one in no way deny it. Why should a consumptive or nervous cab-horse, like <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> or <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617 bio.xml#_618">De Goncourt</rs>, with broad ideas though, be any less so? Seeing that it appears that it is precisely the most worn-out people who feel the germ of this indefinable hope.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">That’s enough, what’s the use of worrying about it? But living in the heart of civilization, in the heart of Paris and the heart of the fine arts, why shouldn’t one keep this self of an old woman? If women themselves, without their instinctive belief in an ‘<hi rend="italics">it’s there</hi>’, wouldn’t find the strength to create and to act?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Then the doctors will tell us that not only Moses, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_531">Mohammed</rs>, Christ, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_494">Luther</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_558">Bunyan</rs> and others were mad, but also <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1073">Frans Hals</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_982">Delacroix</rs> and all the good, narrow-minded old ladies like our <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">mother</rs> as well. Ah — that’s serious, that is. We could ask these doctors, where, then, are the sensible people?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">Are they, the brothel-keepers, always in the right? It’s probable.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">What to choose, then? Fortunately we don’t have to choose. Handshake and</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.24" n="24">Vincent</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Since Theo has already returned from attending Uncle Vincent’s funeral and has reported on it (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>) the letter must date from early August (Uncle Vincent died on Saturday, 28 July). The letter was written on a Monday <ref target="#l-28">(l. 28)</ref> and Vincent was going to pay the rent for August that day <ref target="#l-26">(ll. 26-27)</ref> as he had promised to do (<ref target="let654.xml">see letter 654</ref> of about 3 August). The letter must therefore have been written on Monday, 6 August 1888.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
  <p>Uncle Vincent’s death <ref target="let652.xml">(652)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="ogt_3">
                            
<p>The birth of Marcelle Roulin <ref target="let653.xml">(653)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="ogt_4">
                            
<p>Van Gogh is staying at the Café de la Gare <ref target="let606.xml">(606)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="ogt_5">
                            
  <p>The batch of drawings for Russell <ref target="let652.xml">(652)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let568.xml#n-3">See letter 568, n. 3,</ref> for this quotation from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_445">Candide</ref></hi>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            
  
<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_420">Cor</rs> had been apprenticed to an engineering works in Helmond (<ref target="let443.xml#n-3">see letters 443, n. 3</ref> and <ref target="let471.xml#n-6">471, n. 6</ref>), and had been working for a similar company in Lincoln, England, since 1887.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let550.xml#n-12">See letter 550, n. 12,</ref> for the expression ‘to be someone’, taken from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_617">Edmond de Goncourt</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_422">Chérie</ref></hi>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let654.xml#n-1">See letter 654, n. 1,</ref> for the 12 drawings for <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1334">Russell</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  <ref target="let657.xml">See letters 657</ref> and <ref target="let663.xml">663</ref> for this batch of drawings for Theo. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had had to ask the landlord for more time to pay (<ref target="let654.xml">see letter 654</ref>). The rent for the Yellow House was 15 francs a month (<ref target="let664.xml">see letter 664</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><hi rend="italics">Joseph Roulin </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2672">F 432 / JH 1522</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Joseph Roulin</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2673">F 433 / JH 1524</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>Exactly what Van Gogh gave <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_647">Roulin</rs> is not clear. It may have been one or more copies of the popular political satire weekly <hi rend="italics">La Lanterne</hi>, founded by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_731">Henri Rochefort</rs>, which appeared in 1868 and 1869, or of the radical socialist anticlerical daily of the same title, which had been published since 1877 and with which Rochefort was associated for some time. See Henri Rochefort, <hi rend="italics">Nouméa to Newcastle. The story of an escape</hi>. Translated from the French by Kenneth R. Dutton. Newcastle 2002. Introduction, p. 1.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>The two lithographs (pendants) <hi rend="italics">Le café</hi> (The coffee) and <hi rend="italics">Le vin</hi> (The wine) by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1167">Aimé de Lemud</rs> were published in Paris by Goupil and Vibert (Paris, BNF, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2215">Ill. 2215</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1047">Ill. 1047</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>Nothing is known about this Raoul, whom Van Gogh met in Paris.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>Van Gogh likewise bracketed the writers <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_645">Hoffmann</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_723">Poe</rs> together in <ref target="let361.xml">letter 361</ref>. A mysterious, demonic atmosphere permeates their fantastic tales.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>Van Gogh put this plan into effect a month later; <ref target="let676.xml">see letter 676</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    