<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>Arnold Koning to Vincent van Gogh. The Hague, Friday, 15 February 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let746"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b1083 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>746</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>750</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Arnold Koning</rs>
                            <date when="1889-02-15">Friday, 15 February 1889</date>
                            <placeName>The Hague</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001001253_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001253_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-3" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001253_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001001253_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="VGM001001253_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="Sheet number 2 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001001254_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-4" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001254_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="Sheet number 2 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="VGM001001254_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-5">
<graphic url="VGM001001254_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">den Haag 15 Februari 1889.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Waarde Vincent</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Je brief heb ik laatst ontvangen <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>terwijl ik te Winschoten ver<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>toefde.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Hoewel de brief mij <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>veel genoegen deed zoo vond <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>ik je mededeeling minder <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>aangenaam dat je ziek <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>in ’t hospitaal had gelegen<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Heb je misschien ook te <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>veel gewerkt; want met <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>zoo’n drang tot werken als gij <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>hebt, is het licht mogelijk <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>dat men te veel doet<c type="kk">,</c> en dan <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>in zoo’n warm klimaat<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Maar wat de zomer daar <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>te overvloedig geeft moet <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>volgens allen die in ’t Zuiden <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>van Frankrijk hebben vertoefd <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>overheerlijk zijn<c type="kk">,</c> namelijk <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>de heerlijke warmte in de <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>winter. Ik denk er dan <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ook sterk over je op te zoeken <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>als er niets tusschen beiden <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>komt. Voorloopig heb ik met <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>een kennis een plan ge<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>maakt, om in de late herfst <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>als men hier niet meer 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>buiten kan schilderen, naar Parijs te gaan<c type="kk">,</c> ook al om <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>de tentoonstelling te zien<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> en dan zijn we toch dicht in <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>je buurt en zullen er niet gauw toe komen ons kille <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>waterland weer op te zoeken. ’t Is hier op ’t oogenblik <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>dan ook hondeweer, hagel<c type="kk">,</c> sneeuw en regenvlagen <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>geen gebrek. Ik werk er maar staag op los en <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>schilder tegen de klippen aan, dikwijls dingen <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>die ik zelf nu zoo bijzonder mooi niet vind maar <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>waarvoor ik betaald word. Dit is minder plezierig <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>doch ik heb nog geen klagen want er blijft heel wat <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>tijd over dat ik voor mijzelf kan werken. Volgens <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>’t zeggen van de menschen hier ben ik erg krach<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>tig van kleur geworden. Mijn verblijf te Parijs<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>heeft een gansche reorganisatie teweeg gebracht <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>betreffende mijne denkwijze over de kleuren <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>en hunne onderl. verhouding, en ik blijf maar <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>stil voortgaan op de weg die ik ingeslagen ben en <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>die ik denk de beste te zijn. De kennis van <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>mij waarmee ik naar Parijs ga en misschien <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>naar ’t Zuiden is een jong mensch van groote <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>bekwaamheid en originaliteit<c type="kk">,</c> groot beminnaar <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>van Claude-Monet. A propos<c type="kk">,</c> van laatstgenoemde <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>meester gesproken – Eenige dagen geleden was ik <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>bij mijn familie Roessingh te Haarlem en als ge<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>woonlijk ging het gesprek over de kunst en de kunste<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>naren toen mijn nicht Cato van der Stadt opeens <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>zegt “Ja wij kennen ook een Franschen Schilder <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>en zijne vrouw die vroeger in Zaandam kwamen 
<pb f="1r" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-3" facs="#zone-pb-1r-3"/><lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>schilderen. Het zijn van <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>ons en onze familie te Zaan<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>dam groote vrienden”,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> en <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>hoe kan het toeval er mee <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>spelen<c type="kk">,</c> daar vind ik in <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>het album mijner nicht <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>te Haarlem de portretten <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>van Claude-Monet en zijn <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>vrouw;<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> van iemand <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>wiens werk ik te Parijs zoo <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>heb bewonderd. Volgens <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>Theo was Breitner het <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>grootste Hollandsche genie<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Het doet mij goed door <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>een kenner als Theo, een <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Hollander van zoo groot <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>reputatie tot zijn recht te <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>hooren komen, doch zijn <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Jaap en Willem en Thijs <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Maris en Israëls geen <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>lui die de roem van <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>de Hollandsche schilder<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>school met eere handhaven? <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Ik heb laatst een studie <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>van Israëls gezien<c type="kp">.</c> Op de <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>tentoonstelling te Rotterdam<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>een impressie van een <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>stormachtige buiige <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>avond met een herder <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>met schapen<c type="kk">,</c> een 
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/><lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>overweldigend mooi ding. <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Het is verkocht las ik onlangs <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>(in ’t Handelsbl.?) voor vier dui<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>zend gulden, en dit is voor <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>een studie zeker zeer veel.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Als een groot vertolker van <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>de fijne grijze Hollandsche <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>natuur staat Mauve <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>zeker wel bovenaan. Laatst <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>hebben Edzard (mijn broer) en <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>ik eenige reproducties van <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>teekeningen van de ontsla<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>pen meester kunnen <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>machtig worden, een <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>houtboeldag naar een <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>aquarel.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> voorts twee <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>aquarellen met schapen <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>in de hei.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Als ik eens in <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>Amsterdam kom, zoek ik <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>Breitner stellig eens op, doch <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>ik kom bijna nooit te A. als <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>ik er niet<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> noodig heb. Ik <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>vind Amsterdam nog grooter <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>rotstad als den Haag. Wat <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>betreft het overzenden van <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>een of meer mijner studies: <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>Dit wil ik volgaarne doen <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>ofschoon het een heele af<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>stand is.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> Ik doe tegenwoordig <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>ook aan de kunstkooperij <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>in vereeniging met mijn 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/><lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>broer. We hebben een schilderij van Willem Maris<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>een groote aquarel van Roelofs<c type="kp">.</c> Voorts heb ik nog ver<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>scheidene teekeningen van Bauer en een van de <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>Zwart en een van Thorn Prikker (allemaal kranen)<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-11"/> <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>Kent gij misschien ook Tholen<c type="kk">,</c> iemand met erg veel <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>talent waarmee ik nog al bevriend ben. En nu <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>krijg ik mij daar laatst van Theodoor een kennis<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>geving van zijn voorgenomen huwelijk met <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>Mej. Bonger. Het doet mij verbazend veel plezier <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>voor die goeie kerel dat hij gaat trouwen. Ik <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>heb hem een brief geschreven tijdens zijn verblijf <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>te A. Ik was toen juist in Winschoten aange<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>komen, anders was ik er in persoon vertegen<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>woordigd geweest. Nu schei ik voorloopig maar <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>eens uit<c type="kk">,</c> je van harten een goede gezondheid toe<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>wenschende noem ik mij</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">je toegen<c type="kp">.</c> vriend</p><lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">A.H. Koning.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">163 van Diemenstraat</p><lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">den Haag</p><lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Hollande</hi></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">The Hague 15 February 1889.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I recently received your letter while I was staying in Winschoten.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Although the letter gave me great pleasure, I found your report that you had been ill in hospital much less pleasant. Have you perhaps been working too much; because with a compulsion to work such as you have it’s quite possible that one does too much, and then in such a hot climate. But according to everyone who’s stayed in the south of France, what the summer there gives in too much abundance is glorious, that’s to say the wonderful warmth in the winter. I’m therefore thinking very seriously of visiting you if nothing comes up to prevent it. For the time being I’ve made a plan with a friend to go to Paris in the late autumn, when one can no longer 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> paint outdoors here, also to see the exhibition,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and then we’ll be very close to you and won’t be much inclined to go back to our chilly watery country. It’s filthy weather here at the moment, no shortage of hail, snow and squalls. I’m steadily extricating myself and paint despite the snags, often things that I don’t find particularly good myself, but for which I’m paid. This is less enjoyable, but I don’t have any complaints yet, because there’s a great deal of time left when I can work for myself. According to what people are saying here, I’ve become very forceful in my colour. My stay in Paris<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> has brought about a wholesale reorganization as regards my thinking about the colours and their mutual relationship, and I just keep quietly going on along the road I’ve taken and which I think to be the best. The friend of mine with whom I’m going to Paris, and perhaps to the south, is a young man of great skill and originality, great admirer of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs>. Apropos, speaking of the latter master — some days ago I was with my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_751 bio.xml#_223">Roessingh</rs> relations in Haarlem and, as usual, the conversation turned to art and artists, when my cousin <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_223">Cato van de Stadt</rs> suddenly says, ‘Yes we also know a French painter and his wife who used to come and paint 
<pb f="1r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-3" facs="#zone-pb-1r-3"/> in Zaandam. They’re great friends of ours and our family in Zaandam,’<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> and, what a coincidence, there in my cousin’s album in Haarlem I find the portraits of Claude Monet and his wife;<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> of someone whose work I so admired in Paris. According to Theo, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> was the greatest Dutch genius.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> It does me good to hear a connoisseur like Theo do justice to a Dutchman of such a great reputation, all the same aren’t <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1203">Jaap</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1201">Willem</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1202">Thijs Maris</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Israëls</rs> fellows who uphold the fame of the Dutch school of painting with honour? I recently saw a study by Israëls. At the exhibition in Rotterdam, an impression of a stormy, showery evening with a shepherd and sheep, a 
<pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/> tremendously fine thing. It’s sold, I read recently (in the Handelsblad?), for four thousand guilders, and this is certainly a very great deal for a study.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> As a great interpreter of the fine grey Dutch countryside, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> is certainly at the top. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1144">Edzard</rs> (my brother) and I were recently able to acquire some reproductions of drawings by the deceased master, a timber auction after a watercolour.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Also two watercolours with sheep on the heath.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> If I ever go to Amsterdam I’ll be sure to look <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_903">Breitner</rs> up, but I almost never go to A. if I don’t need anything there. I think Amsterdam’s an even lousier city than The Hague. As regards sending one or more of my studies: I’ll be delighted to do so, even though it’s a great distance.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> I’m also engaged in the art trade nowadays in association with my 
<pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1144">brother</rs>. We have a painting by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1201">Willem Maris</rs>, a large watercolour by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1318">Roelofs</rs>. Further, I also have various drawings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_387">Bauer</rs> and one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1832">De Zwart</rs> and one by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1290">Thorn Prikker</rs> (all top cracks).<ptr target="#note-t-11"/> Do you happen to know <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1376">Tholen</rs> too, someone with a great deal of talent I’m quite good friends with? And now I just get an announcement from Theodoor of his forthcoming marriage to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Miss Bonger</rs>. I’m immensely pleased that the good fellow’s getting married. I wrote him a letter during his stay in A. I had just then arrived in Winschoten, otherwise I would have been represented there in person. Well, I’ll just leave it at that for the time being, with sincere wishes for your good health, I am</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">your affectionate friend</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">A.H. Koning</rs></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">163 van Diemenstraat</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">The Hague</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8"><hi rend="italics">Holland</hi></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘den Haag 15 Februari 1889.’</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let740.xml">letter 740</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It is not known who this friend was. In any case, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>’s plan never came to fruition: he would never return to France.</p>

<p rend="indent">The World Exhibition was held in Paris from 5 May to 5 November 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>From September 1887 to the end of May 1888 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> stayed in Paris, where he lived for a time with Theo (<ref target="let578.xml#n-8">see letter 578, n. 8</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_751">Hendrik Roessingh</rs>, probably a cousin of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs>, was married to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_223">Catharina (Cato) van de Stadt</rs>. During his stay in Zaandam, from June to October 1871, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Monet</rs> had painted Cato’s sixteen-year-old niece Guurtje van de Stadt. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1986, pp. 42, 46 (n. 22), 142-143, cat. no. 25.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>The portrait photographs of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1222">Claude Monet</rs> and his wife Camille Monet-Doncieux, taken in 1871 by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1722">Albert Greiner</rs> in Amsterdam, are still in the possession of the Van de Stadt family. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2276">Ill. 2276</rs> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2277">Ill. 2277</rs>. </p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written this in <ref target="let740.xml">letter 740</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>, <hi rend="italics">The shepherd</hi> (The Hague, Gemeentemusem). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_189">Ill. 189</rs>. It was shown at the exhibition <hi rend="italics">Levende Meesters</hi> (Living Masters) in Rotterdam (cat. no. 94). Goupil’s Hague branch bought it on 17 July 1888 for 3,500 guilders and sent it on to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs> in London, where it was sold in April 1889 for £ 400 (4,800 guilders) to C. Roberts of Leeds. See <hi rend="italics">RKD</hi>, <hi rend="italics">Goupil</hi> <hi rend="italics">Ledgers</hi> and exhib. cat. Groningen 1999, p. 216, cat. no. 42. The newspaper in which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1145">Koning</rs> could have read this article has not been traced.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>This reproduction is probably of the well-known <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_801">Timber auction</rs></hi> (The Hague, The Mesdag Collection). See cat. The Hague 1996, p. 298, cat. no. 219.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_323">Mauve</rs> made many watercolours of this subject. One of the best known is <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_802">Flock of sheep on the heath at Laren</rs></hi> (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). It can no longer be ascertained which drawings or reproductions of drawings are referred to here.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘niets’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>In <ref target="let740.xml">letter 740</ref> Van Gogh had again mentioned this intended exchange (<ref target="let614.xml#n-3">see letter 614, n. 3</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>It could not be discovered which works by these artists the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1144 bio.xml#_1145">Koning brothers</rs> owned. It is possible that the Dutch word ‘kranen’ used by Koning should be taken literally as ‘cranes’ (the birds).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    