<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Wednesday, 18 September 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let802"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b744 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>802</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>T17</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>803</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1889-09-18">Wednesday, 18 September 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0744 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0744 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001007_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0744 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001001008_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic url="VGM001001008_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0744 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="VGM001001008_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic url="VGM001001008_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Paris le 18 Sept<c type="kp">.</c> 1889</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Mon cher Vincent,</p><lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">J’ai tardé de répondre <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>à ta dernière lettre comme <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>j’espérais rencontrer le père Pissarro<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Il est reparti chez lui<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> mais <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>doit revenir prochainement à <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Paris. Le père Tangui &amp; moi en <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>causant de toi nous avions déjà <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>remué la question s’il n’y aurait <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>pas moyen de l’arrangement dont <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>tu parles et alors est arrivé la <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>mort de sa mère<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> &amp; n’était ce pas 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>le moment. L’année dernière <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>de Haan a voulu aller chez lui &amp; <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>alors il a dit qu’il n’avait pas <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>de place &amp; a t il cherché pour lui <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>chez les voisins, mais cela n’a pas <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>donné de résultats. J’en ai parlé <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>à Jouve qui m’a promis de voir <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>s’il ne trouvait pas un arrangement <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>car demeurer chez lui ne se peut pas faute de place. <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>mais il a son atelier. Lui il a l’air <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>de remonter sur l’eau, il a trouvé <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>des travaux de décoration.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> C’est un <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>homme de beaucoup de bon sens. Mais <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>pour ce qui est l’essentiel, savoir <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>si ta santé ira mieux quand tu <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>sera chez l’un ou l’autre de ces gens<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>voilà la grande question. Quand tu 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>parles de vaincre ta maladie par <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>le travail, mon vieux tu n’as jamais <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>fait que cela &amp; tu n’as donc pas besoin <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>de changer pour cela. Au contraire <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>la seule chose qui pourra te guerir <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>c’est je crois que tu ne cherches <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>rien de plus que de te fortifier <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>le corps et les idées noires s’en iront <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>quand tu auras un peu plus de sang <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>dans le corps. J’ai peur quand tu <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>travailles comme cela avec rage car <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>forcément tu t’épuises. Je comprends <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>que l’oisiveté te pèse surtout quand <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>tu n’as pas de société à ton gout. <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>mais en venant içi c’est le danger <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>d’une société qui t’énerve. Je dirais<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>va à la campagne dans un coin où <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>il y a quelque artiste oublié, mais 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>tu sais comme tu supportes difficilement <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>le froid &amp; tant que tu ne sois pas <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>absolument mieux il faut aussi que <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>tu ne sois pas seul. Selon Rivet &amp; <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>aussi selon ce que j’ai compris des <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>lettres de M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Peyron il se peut que tu <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>n’auras pas de crise, mais il faut <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>absolument que tu ne fasse aucune <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>imprudence &amp; que tu sois sous la <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>surveillance d’un médecin. Veux tu <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>venir à une maison de santé d’içi jusqu’à <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ce que l’hiver soit passé &amp; veux tu <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>après aller à la campagne pour peindre<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/><hi rend="italics">Réponds moi cathégoriquement à cela</hi>. <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Pourquoi restes tu enfermé &amp; ne vas tu <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>pas prendre l’air<c type="kk">,</c> cela ne pourra que te <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>faire du bien, tandis qu’une vie assis <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>ne vaut rien pour toi<c type="kk">,</c> aussi faut-il <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>que tu manges de la viande.– Tu auras <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>probablement reçu les couleurs de chez <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Tasset<c type="kk">,</c> pour le second envoi de blanc 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>il t’arrivera très prochainement car <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>il n’en avait pas en magasin.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Il <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>y a à l’exposition trois tableaux <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de Meunier qui t’auraient fait <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>plaisir de voir. L’un est une étude <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>de toits rouges surmontés de cheminées <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>d’usine qui toutes ont leur lourd <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>panache de fumée qui se détache <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>contre un ciel laiteux du matin<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-5"/> <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>N° 2 est un groupe d’ouvriers <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>marchant deux à deux en se rendant <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>à l’usine à travers des tas de scorilles<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>et de charbon<c type="kk">,</c> des pieux<c type="kk">,</c> des morceaux <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>de noir menacent le ciel.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> N° 3 <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>La hercheuse. Avant de dessendre <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>elle cause avec un jeune gas<ptr target="#note-t-b"/>. Ils sont 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/><lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>vêtus de même mais elle est bien femme<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>au-dessus de leurs têtes un gros poutre <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>découpe une partie du ciel contre <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>lequel ils se détachent.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Encore celui <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>là si ce n’est ni impressionniste ni <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>la peinture du jour c’est beau tout <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>de même<c type="kk">,</c> tous les trois tableaux <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>sont hissés en haut de la salle. <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>Il a aussi un pudeleur<ptr target="#note-t-c"/> grandeur <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>nature en bronze, qui ressemble à <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>une figure de Millet, très beau aussi.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Jo se porte bien<c type="kk">,</c> elle est presqu’à la <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>moitié de sa grossesse. Jusqu’à présent <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>cela va bien, elle est grosse ce qui la gène <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>un peu mais à part quelquefois des nausées <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>cela va bien. Elle n’est plus inquiète &amp; <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>n’a pas peur. J’espère que tu vas mieux <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>&amp; que tu ne te sentes pas trop malheureux. <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>Nous parlons &amp; nous pensons souvent à toi<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">bien bonjour de Jo &amp; bonne poignée de mains et</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">t<c type="kp">.</c> à t<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Theo</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Paris 18 Sept. 1889</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I put off replying to your last letter as I was hoping to meet <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Pissarro</rs>. He’s gone back home<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> but is to return to Paris soon. While talking about you, <hi rend="italics">père</hi> <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_772">Tanguy</rs> and I had already touched on the question of whether there couldn’t be some way of making the arrangement of which you speak, and then his mother died,<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> and it wasn’t 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> the moment. Last year <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> wanted to go and stay with him, and then he said that he didn’t have room and he asked around among the neighbours, but without result. I’ve spoken of it to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1123">Jouve</rs>, who has promised to see if he couldn’t arrange something, since staying at his place is impossible because of a lack of space. But he has his studio. He looks as if he’s on the way up, he’s found decorative work.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> He’s a man with a lot of common sense. But as regards what is vital, knowing if your health will improve when you’re staying with one or other of these people, that’s the big question. When you 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> speak of overcoming your illness through work, old chap you’ve never done anything else, and so you have no need to move for that. On the contrary, I think that the only thing that can cure you is that you don’t try to do anything more than fortify your body, and the dark thoughts will go away when you have a bit more blood in your body. I’m afraid when you work furiously like that, for you’re bound to wear yourself out. I understand that idleness weighs heavily on you, especially when you have no company to your taste. But in coming here it’s the danger of company that annoys you. I’d say, go to the country, to a corner where there’s some forgotten artist, but 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> you know how difficult you find it to bear the cold, and as long as you’re not completely better you must also not be alone. According to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_640">Rivet</rs>, and also from what I have understood of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs>’s letters, it’s possible that you won’t have a crisis, but it’s absolutely essential that you do nothing imprudent and that you’re under the supervision of a doctor. Do you want to come to an asylum here until the winter is over, and afterwards do you want to go to the country to paint? <hi rend="italics">Give me a categorical answer to this.</hi> Why do you stay shut away, and why don’t you go out and get some fresh air, it can only do you good, whereas a sedentary life is no good for you, you must also eat meat. You’ll probably have received the colours from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs>’s, as for the second consignment of white, 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> it will reach you in a very short time, for he didn’t have any in the shop.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> In the exhibition there are three paintings by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1209">Meunier</rs> which you would have enjoyed seeing. One is a study of red roofs above which rise factory chimneys, which all have their heavy plumes of smoke standing out against a milky morning sky.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> No. 2 is a group of workmen walking two by two on their way to the factory across heaps of slag and coal, props, black pieces threaten the sky.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> No. 3, Female coal-pit drawer. She’s chatting with a young lad before going underground. They’re 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> dressed the same, but she’s definitely feminine, above their heads a big beam cuts out part of the sky against which they stand out.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Even if the latter is neither Impressionistic nor the painting of the day, it’s beautiful all the same, all three paintings have been hoisted high up in the room. There’s also a life-size puddler in bronze, which resembles a figure by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1226">Millet</rs>, also very beautiful.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> is well, she’s almost halfway through her pregnancy. Up to now it’s going well, she is big, which hinders her a little, but apart from occasional spells of nausea it’s going well. She isn’t anxious any more, and isn’t afraid. I hope that you’re better and that you don’t feel too unhappy. We often speak about and think of you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Warm regards from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and good handshake, and</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">Theo</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 18 Sept_ 1889’.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Vincent’s suggestion that he live with Pissarro <ref target="let801.xml">(801)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            
 
<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1268">Camille Pissarro</rs> lived with his family in Eragny-par-Gisors (Val-d’Oise).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Pissarro’s mother, Rachel Pommié-Manzana, died on 30 May 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In <ref target="let801.xml">letter 801</ref> Van Gogh had suggested putting the idea to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1123">Jouve</rs>. Regarding his studio, <ref target="let801.xml#n-32">see letter 801, n. 32.</ref> Jouve produced ‘enamel-covered lava and ceramic frescoes’ (émaux sur lave et fresques céramiques) (<hi rend="italics">Almanach du commerce de Paris</hi> 1888).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had ordered the paint in <ref target="let800.xml">letter 800</ref> and the extra shipment of white in <ref target="let801.xml">letter 801</ref>. The paints Theo ordered in September 1889 from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_785">Tasset</rs> cost 174 francs (<hi rend="italics">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 44).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            
 
<p>Theo is referring to the paintings <hi rend="italics">The black region</hi>, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_892">Female coal-pit drawers (the coupling point)</rs></hi> and <hi rend="italics">Return from the pit (black)</hi> by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1209">Constantin Meunier</rs> at the 1889 World Exhibition. See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-3, p. 66, cat. nos. 127-129. The first is <hi rend="italics">Black region, Borinage</hi> (Brussels, Musée Constantin Meunier). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1150">Ill. 1150</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            
 
<p>Read: ‘scories’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
 <hi rend="italics">Return from the pit (black)</hi> is the painting <hi rend="italics">The return of the miners </hi>(Brussels, Musée Constantin Meunier). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1146">Ill. 1146</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            
 
<p>Read: ‘gars’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_892">Female coal-pit drawers (the coupling point)</rs></hi>, cf. the depiction <hi rend="italics">Three female coal-pit drawers</hi>, 1885? (private collection) in exhib. cat. Brussels 1998, p. 124, cat. no. 45.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="c" xml:id="note-t-c">
                            
  
<p>Read: ‘puddleur’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>At the World Exhibition, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1209">Meunier</rs> exhibited the bronze statue <hi rend="italics">Puddler </hi>(Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_1149">Ill. 1149</rs>. See exhib. cat. Paris 1889-3, p. 70, cat. no. 321.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    