<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Le Pouldu, on or about Friday, 17 January 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let840"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b870 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>840</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>GAC 38</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>842</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                            <date when="1890-01-17">on or about Friday, 17 January 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Le Pouldu</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0870" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0870" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001001164_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher Vincent </p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">La vie est bien longue et bien <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>triste. Depuis votre dernière lettre <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>j’ai tellement broyé du noir que <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>je ne pouvais écrire, désirant le <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>jour voir le soir et la nuit atten<c type="shy">-</c><lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>dant le matin. La terre une <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>fois labourée<c type="kk">,</c> l’homme jette la <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>semence et chaque jour se défendant <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>contre les chances du mauvais temps, <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>il arrive à récolter. Mais nous<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>pauvres artistes? où va le grain <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>que nous plantons et quand vient <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>la récolte<c type="kp">.</c>– Depuis 3 mois que <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>je suis au Pouldu j’ai eu 30<hi rend="super">f</hi> dans <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ma poche; décidemment j’ai <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>beau y mettre de l’énergie<c type="kk">,</c> je ne <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>peux continuer à peindre<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/><lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">En outre de ces ennuis d’argent j’ai <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>eu d’autres causes de chagrin<c type="kp">.</c>– J’ai <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>failli perdre un de mes enfants <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>qui est tombé du 3<hi rend="super">em</hi> étage dans <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>la rue.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Vous comprenez qu’à Copenhague <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>la maison a été bouleversée et que <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>les dépenses faites pour cet accident <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>jettent le désordre (désordre auquel <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>je suis impuissant à remédier en ce <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>moment)<c type="kp">.</c>– Tout celà me rend <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>malade de spleen et je n’ose ni <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>peindre ni écrire<c type="kp">.</c>– Et pourquoi <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>peindre?</p><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">J’aime beaucoup les 2 dessins que <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>vous m’avez envoyé<c type="kk">,</c> surtout celui <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>des femmes qui cueillent des olives<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Je suis content que vous ayez <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>exposé à Bruxelles; avez vous des <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>nouvelles de cette exposition<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>Faites-m’en part.</p><lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Vous avez comme nous l’hiver 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>en ce moment et je sais que c’est <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>pour vous une rude époque à <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>traverser. Vous devez attendre <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>la chaleur avec impatience pour <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>pouvoir travailler dehors.</p><lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Je fais tout mon possible en ce moment <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>pour partir au Tonkin aux frais du <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>gouvernement,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> mais ce n’est pas <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>facile, surtout parceque je suis un <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>artiste et qu’à ceux là on ne croit <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>aucune capacité pour les affaires<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Il y a dans les colonies quelque chose <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>à faire pour nous autres de l’occident, <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>et j’espère y apprendre du nouveau <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>en art tout en étant débarrassé <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>quelque temps des tracas d’argent.</p><lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">de Haan travaille toujours ici <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>avec moi et fait de sérieux <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>progrets<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> mais ne veut retourner <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>en Hollande que quand 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/><lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>il se sentira assez fort pour <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>river le clou à ses compatriotes <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>qui vont lui en dire de dures <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>à propos de sa transformation<c type="kp">.</c>– Ces <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>nouvelles questions de couleur l’avaient <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>beaucoup tourmenté, mais aujourd’hui <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>qu’il commence à voir clair dans <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>cette nouvelle voie, il est plein d’ardeur.</p><lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Excusez mon retard dans la <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>correspondance et croyez moi <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>toujours</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="70*" xml:id="l-70s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">T<c type="kp">.</c> à V<c type="kp">.</c> cordialement</p><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Paul Gauguin</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Vincent</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Life is very long and very sad. Since your last letter I’ve been so deep in the doldrums that I couldn’t write, in the daytime wishing to see the evening, and at night awaiting the morning. Once the land is ploughed, the man casts the seed, and each day defending himself against the vagaries of the bad weather he manages to harvest. But what of us poor artists? Where does the seed we plant go, and when does the harvest come? In the 3 months I’ve been at Le Pouldu I’ve had 30 francs in my pocket; it’s obviously pointless my putting energy into it, I can’t carry on painting. 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Apart from these money troubles I’ve had other causes for sorrow. I almost lost one of my <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">children</rs>, who fell from the 3rd floor into the street.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> You will understand that in Copenhagen the household was overwhelmed, and that the expenses occasioned by this accident are throwing things into chaos (chaos which I’m powerless to remedy at the moment). All of this makes me sick with spleen, and I dare neither paint nor write. And why paint?</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I very much like the 2 drawings you sent me, especially the one of the women who are picking olives.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">I’m pleased that you’ve exhibited in Brussels; have you any news of this exhibition. Let me know.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">Like us you have winter 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> at the moment, and I know that for you it’s a harsh time to get through. You’re probably awaiting the heat with impatience so that you can work out of doors.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">I’m doing everything I can at the moment to leave for Tonkin at government expense,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> but it isn’t easy, especially because I’m an artist and people don’t believe that they have any capacity for business. In the colonies there’s something for us westerners to do, and I hope to learn something new there in art at the same time as being relieved of financial worries for a time.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> is still working here with me and making serious progress, but doesn’t want to return to Holland until 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/> he feels strong enough to silence his compatriots; they’re going to say harsh words to him about his transformation. These new questions of colour had greatly tormented him, but today, when he’s beginning to see clearly in this new way, he’s full of ardour.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">Excuse my delay in writing, and believe me always</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Ever yours cordially,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>In <ref target="let841.xml">letter 841</ref> of 20 January, Van Gogh writes to Willemien that he had sent Gauguin a drawing ‘just recently’ and that Gauguin had ‘thought it good’. This means that Vincent received Gauguin’s reaction to his drawing only a few days after sending it, and that Gauguin’s letter arrived shortly before Vincent wrote to Willemien about it. We have therefore dated the present letter to about Friday, 17 January 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s son <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_79">Jean-René</rs>; <ref target="let830.xml#n-14">see letter 830, n. 14.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>It is not known which drawings Van Gogh sent to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>. One of them had been made after the painting <hi rend="italics">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2879">F 655 / JH 1869</rs>), as emerges from <ref target="let841.xml">letter 841</ref>, though such a drawing is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>In January 1890 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote from Pont-Aven to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1357">Schuffenecker</rs>, saying that in Paris he hoped to arrange a position as a painter in Tonkin. ‘And if I don’t succeed with Tonkin I’ll try to work at something other than painting, because I have to heave to for a time. Or otherwise, I’ll press the finance minister to give me something or other in France’. (Et si je ne réussi pas pour le Tonkin je vais tâcher de travailler en dehors de la peinture, car il faut tenir la cape pendant quelques temps. Ou bien encore je pousserai le ministre des finances pour me donner en France n’importe quoi). See <hi rend="italics">Gauguin lettres </hi>1946, p. 181. Nothing ever came of his plan.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘progrès’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    