<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
    <title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Le Pouldu, on or about Friday, 13 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let828"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b869 a-b V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>828</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>GAC 36</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>812</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                            <date when="1889-12-13">on or about Friday, 13 December 1889</date>
                            <placeName>Le Pouldu</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0869 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001001162_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="VGM001001162_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0869 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001001162_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="VGM001001162_02_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0869 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
<graphic url="VGM001001163_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-3">
<graphic url="VGM001001163_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0869 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
<graphic url="VGM001001163_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-4">
<graphic url="VGM001001163_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher Vincent</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">Depuis longtemps je devais vous répondre à votre longue lettre;<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> je sais <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>combien vous êtes isolé en Provence et que vous aimez à recevoir des <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>nouvelles des copains qui vous intéressent, et cependant beaucoup de <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>circonstances m’en ont empêché. Entre autres un assez grand travail <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>que nous avons entrepris en commun de Haan et moi: une <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>décoration de l’auberge où nous mangeons<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> On commence par <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>un mur puis on finit par faire les quatre, même le vitrail.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>C’est une chose qui apprend beaucoup, par conséquent utile<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>De Haam<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> a fait sur le plâtre même un grand panneau <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de 2<hi rend="super">mètres</hi> sur 1,50 de haut. Je vous envoie ci-joint <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>un croquis fait sommairement de la chose<c type="kp">.</c>– Paysannes d’ici <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>travaillant au chanvre sur un fond de meules de paille<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Je trouve celà très bien et très-complet, fait aussi <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>sérieusement qu’un tableau<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">J’ai fait à la suite une paysanne en train de filer sur <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>le bord de la mer, son chien et sa vache<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Nos deux <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>portraits sur chaque porte<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> Dans la fièvre du travail, <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>et la hâte de voir tout terminé, le moment de se <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>coucher arrivait aussitot et je remettais ma lettre à <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>plus tard – maintenant causons<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">de tableaux religieux je n’en ai fait qu’un cette année,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>et celà il est bon de faire quelquefois des <hi rend="italics">essais</hi> de toute <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>sorte, afin d’entretenir ses forces imaginatives, et <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>on revoit la nature après avec plaisir. Enfin tout celà <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>est affaire de tempérament<c type="kp">.</c>– Moi ce que j’ai fait <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>surtout cette année, ce sont de simples enfants de 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>paysan, se promenant indifferents sur le bord de la mer <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>avec leurs vaches.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Seulement comme le trompe l’oeil <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>du plein air et de quoique ce soit ne me plaît pas<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>je cherche à mettre dans ces figures désolées, le sauvage <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>que j’y vois et qui est en moi aussi<c type="kp">.</c>– Ici en Bretagne <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>les paysans ont un air du moyen âge et n’ont pas <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>l’air de penser un instant que Paris existe et qu’on soit <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>en 1889 – tout le contraire du midi<c type="kp">.</c>– Ici tout est rude <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>comme la langue Bretonne, bien fermé (il semble à <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>tout jamais)<c type="kp">.</c>– Les costumes sont aussi presque symbolique<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>influencés par les superstitions du catholicisme<c type="kp">.</c>– Voyez le <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>dos<c type="kk">,</c> corsage une croix,</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="39*" xml:id="l-39s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">la tête envelopée d’une marmotte <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>noire comme les religieuses – avec celà <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>les figures sont presque asiatiques<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>jaunes et triangulaires, sévères.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="42*" xml:id="l-42s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Que diable<c type="kk">,</c> je veux <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>aussi consulter la nature mais je ne veux pas en <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>retirer ce que j’y vois et ce qui vient à ma pensée<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>Les roches, les costumes sont noirs et jaunes; je ne <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>peux pourtant pas les mettre blonds et coquets<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Encore craintifs du seigneur et du curé les bretons <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>tiennent leurs chapeaux et tous leurs ustensiles comme <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>s’ils étaient dans une église; je les peins aussi en <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>cet état et non dans une verve méridionale<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">En ce moment je fais une toile de 50, des <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>femmes ramassant du goëmon sur le bord de <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>la mer<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> Ce sont comme des boîtes étagées de <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>distance en distances, vêtements bleus et coiffes noires 
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>et celà malgré l’âpreté du froid<c type="kp">.</c>– Fumier qu’ils <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>ramassent pour fumer leurs terres, couleur ocre de <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>ru avec des reflets fauve<c type="kp">.</c>– Sables <hi rend="italics">roses</hi> et non jaunes <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>à cause de l’humidité probablement – mer sombre. <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>En voyant celà tous les jours il me vient comme une <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>bouffée de lutte pour la vie, de tristesse et <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>d’obéissance aux lois malheureuses<c type="kp">.</c>– Cette bouffée je cherche <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>à la mettre sur la toile, non par hazard, mais par <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>raisonnement en exagérant peut être certaines rigidités <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>de pose, certaines couleurs sombres etc... Tout celà est <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>peut être <hi rend="italics">manieré</hi> mais dans le tableau<c type="kk">,</c> où est <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>le naturel?– <hi rend="italics">Tout</hi> depuis les âges les plus reculés est <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>dans les tableaux, tout à fait conventionel, voulu, <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>d’un bout à l’autre et bien loin du naturel<c type="kk">,</c> par <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>conséquent bien manieré<c type="kp">.</c>– Ils ont, les maîtres anciens<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>direz-vous<c type="kk">,</c> le genie<c type="kp">.</c>– C’est vrai et nous ne l’avons pas, <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>mais ce n’est pas une raison pour ne pas procéder <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>comme eux<c type="kp">.</c>– Pour un Japonais ce que nous faisons est <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>manieré et vice versâ; celà provient qu’il y a entre <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>les deux un écart notable dans la vision<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>les usages et les types<c type="kp">.</c>– Donc si un homme par <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>suite de race<c type="kk">,</c> tempérament ou autre cause, voit<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>sent<c type="kk">,</c> pense different de la masse il est peu naturel <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>et par suite manieré<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Vous avez-vu à Arles le portail de S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Trophine,<ptr target="#note-t-b"/> vu <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>et exécuté bien différent des hommes du nord avec <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>des <hi rend="italics">proportions</hi> bien loin de la nature, et celà vous l’avez <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>admiré, sans cauchemar<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – non en art (la verité <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>est ce que l’on sent, dans l’état d’âme où on est)<c type="kp">.</c>– <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>Rêve qui veut ou qui peut<c type="kp">.</c>– S’y laisse aller <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>qui veut ou qui peut<c type="kp">.</c>– Et le rêve vient toujours de <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>la realité dans la nature<c type="kp">.</c>– Un Indien sauvage ne <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>verra jamais en rêve un homme habillé comme à <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Paris – etc....</p><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">de Haam travaille toujours au Pouldu, vous <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>remercie de votre bon souvenir et vous dit <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>bien des choses<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Il est (seul) l’auteur d’Uriel, le tableau dont <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>vous avez parlé dans une lettre à Isaacson<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p><lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Je n’ai pas trace de votre dessin d’après Rembrandt <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>dont vous me proposiez échange (que je ferai avec <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>plaisir)<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p><lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Vous serre cordialement la main<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">T<c type="kp">.</c> à V<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">P. Gauguin.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear Vincent,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">I should have replied to your long letter<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> ages ago; I know how isolated you are in Provence and that you like to receive news from the pals who interest you, and yet many circumstances have prevented me from doing so. Among others, a rather large job which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> and I have undertaken together: a decoration for the inn where we eat<ptr target="#note-t-2"/>. You begin with one wall, then you end up doing all four, even the stained-glass window.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> It’s something that teaches you a lot, and so it’s useful. De Haan has done a large panel on the actual plaster, 2 metres by 1.50 high. Enclosed I’m sending you a swift croquis of the thing. Peasant women from around here working with hemp against a background of ricks of straw.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">  I consider it very good and very complete, done as seriously as a painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4"> After that I did a peasant woman spinning at the sea’s edge, her dog and her cow.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Our two portraits on each door.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> In the fever of work, and the haste to see it all finished, bedtime arrived all of a sudden and I postponed my letter until later – now let’s chat.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">  I’ve only done one religious painting this year,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> and it’s good sometimes to make <hi rend="italics">attempts</hi> of every sort, so as to sustain one’s imaginative powers, and afterwards one looks at nature with pleasure again. Anyway, that’s all a matter of temperament. What I myself have done most of all this year are simple peasant children, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> walking indifferently beside the sea with their cows.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> But because I don’t like the <hi rend="italics">trompe l’oeil</hi> of the outdoors and of whatever else, I try to put into these desolate figures the savagery that I see in them, and that’s in me too. Here in Brittany the peasants have a medieval look about them and don’t appear to think for a moment that Paris exists and that we’re in the year 1889 – quite the opposite of the south. Here everything is rough like the Breton language, very closed-in (for evermore, it seems). The costumes are also almost symbolic, influenced by the superstitions of Catholicism. Look at the back, bodice a cross, </p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">the head wrapped in a black kerchief like nuns – in addition the figures are almost Asiatic, yellow and triangular, severe.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">What the devil, I want to consult nature too, but I don’t want to take from it what I see there and what comes into my mind. The rocks, the costumes are black and yellow; I can’t put them down as blond and coquettish, can I? Still fearful of Our Lord and the priest, the Breton men hold their hats and all their utensils as if they were in a church; I also paint them in that state and not with a southern verve.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11"> At the moment I’m doing a no. 50 canvas, of women gathering wrack at the sea’s edge.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> They’re like boxes stacked up here and there, blue clothing and black coifs 
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/> and this despite the bitterness of the cold. Manure which they gather to fertilize their land, red-brown ochre with ruddy highlights. <hi rend="italics">Pink</hi> sands, not yellow, because of the damp probably – dark sea. Seeing this every day I get a kind of gust of wind for life, of sadness and obedience to unfortunate laws. I try to put this gust of wind on canvas, not haphazardly but rationally, perhaps exaggerating a certain rigidity of pose, certain sombre colours etc... All of this is <hi rend="italics">mannered</hi> perhaps, but where’s the natural in a painting? <hi rend="italics">Everything</hi> in paintings since the most distant ages has been completely conventional, deliberate throughout and very far from the natural, consequently very mannered. You’ll say that they, the ancient masters, have genius. That’s true, and we don’t have it, but that’s no reason not to proceed like them. To a Japanese person what we do is mannered and vice versa; this comes from the fact that there’s a notable distance between the two in vision, customs and types. So if a man sees, feels, thinks differently from the mass because of race, temperament or other cause, he is unnatural and consequently mannered.
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">  You’ve seen the doorway to St Trophime in Arles, perceived and executed very differently from the manner of the northerners, with <hi rend="italics">proportions</hi> far removed from nature, and you admired that, without any nightmare<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> – no, in art (the truth is what one feels, in the state of mind one’s in). Let him who wishes or who can, dream. Let him who wants to or who can, drift along. And the dream always comes from the reality in nature. In a dream, an Indian savage will never see a man dressed the way they are in Paris – etc...</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">  <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> is still working at Le Pouldu, thanks you for your kind regards and sends his best wishes.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">  He (alone) is the creator of Uriel, the painting you spoke of in a letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-11"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">  I know nothing about your drawing after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs> which you were proposing to exchange with me (which I’ll do with pleasure).<ptr target="#note-t-12"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16"> I shake your hand cordially.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17">
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">Ever yours,</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">P. Gauguin</rs>.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>This letter was previously dated to about 20 October, but it must have been written two months later. Gauguin, who had wanted to answer a letter from Van Gogh ‘ages ago’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, talks about the decoration he is making together with Meijer de Haan for an inn in Le Pouldu. In his letter of 22 October to Theo, De Haan makes no mention whatsoever of a decoration; on the contrary, he is planning to devote himself completely to studies in the coming year (FR b1042). Nor did Gauguin mention it in a letter he wrote to Vincent (<ref target="let817.xml">letter 817</ref>) some time between about Sunday, 10 and Wednesday, 13 November. Robert Welsh therefore suggested another date, on the basis of a letter from De Haan to Theo of 13 December 1889 (FR b1319), in which De Haan writes that the four walls have been painted. This agrees with what Gauguin says in the present letter (see Welsh 1989, p. 37 and n. 20). According to Welsh, Gauguin and De Haan did not begin work on the decoration until mid-November. </p>
<p rend="indent">Van Gogh says in <ref target="let823.xml">letter 823</ref> of 26 November that he has written to Gauguin; the present letter must be Gauguin’s reply, in which he says that it took him a long time to get around to answering it <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>. Moreover, Van Gogh says in <ref target="let829.xml">letter 829</ref> of about 19 December that he has received a letter from Gauguin: ‘a letter thoroughly impregnated with the proximity of the sea, I think he must be doing fine, rather savage things’; this, too, must refer to the present letter. Another argument for reversing the order of the letters is Gauguin’s reference to <hi rend="italics">Christ in the Garden of Olives </hi>(<ref target="#n-7">see n. 7</ref>). All things considered, we have dated the letter to about Friday, 13 December 1889. Pickvance dated it to about Thursday, 12 December (see exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 56).</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>Gauguin enclosed a sketch with colour annotations, which is not known. Cf. <ref target="#n-4">n. 4.</ref></p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was the (unknown) letter mentioned by Van Gogh in <ref target="let823.xml">letter 823</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>The decoration for the dining room of Marie Henry’s inn at Le Pouldu (Brittany) was a collaborative effort by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1854">Paul Sérusier</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1824">Charles Filiger</rs>. For the decorative programme, see Welsh 1989 and <hi rend="italics">Gauguin’s Nirvana: painters at Le Pouldu, 1889-1890</hi>. Ed. E. M. Zafran. Hartford and London 2001, pp. 61-101.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>The window in the dining room, which <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs> painted with rustic motifs in oil paint, has not been preserved. Maxime Maufra recalled a decoration with white geese and blue and yellow ornaments, ‘imitating stained glass’. See Maxime Maufra, ‘Souvenirs de Pont-Aven et du Pouldu’, <hi rend="italics">Bulletin des amis du Musée de Rennes. Numéro spécial “Pont-Aven”</hi>. Rennes 1978, p. 24.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Haan’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>’s fresco, transferred to canvas, is <hi rend="italics">Breton women scutching flax: Labour</hi>, 1889 (private collection). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2295">Ill. 2295</rs>. The sketch <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> made after it is not known. It emerges from Meijer de Haan’s letter of 13 December 1889 to Theo that Gauguin also wrote an ‘explanation of the colours’ on the sketch. De Haan, who remarks that Gauguin is very pleased with the mural, describes it as follows: ‘it is a depiction titled <hi rend="italics">Labour</hi>, Pouldu at the height of the harvest, with many figures 1.25 metres high, the whole is 3 by 2 and I finished such a thing very quickly. Also 5 large, detailed still lifes. So that this little room looks truly cosy, since we’ve decorated all the walls with ornaments in character and style’ (FR b1319).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Joan of Arc</hi>, 1889 (W329) (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2296">Ill. 2296</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            
      
<p>The two portraits are <hi rend="italics">Self-portrait</hi>, 1889 (W323) (Washington, National Gallery of Art (Chester Dale Collection)), <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2145">Ill. 2145</rs>, and <hi rend="italics">Meijer de Haan</hi>, 1889 (W317) (private collection). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2146">Ill. 2146</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s previous letter contained a description and a sketch of this painting, <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_101">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs></hi>. <ref target="let817.xml#n-10">See letter 817, n. 10.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>In 1889 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> made several paintings of this subject, such as <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_906">Breton girls in front of the sea</rs> </hi>(W340) (Tokyo, Museum of Western Art) and <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_907">Cowherdess</rs></hi> (W344) (Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, <hi rend="italics">Women collecting kelp <hi>ii</hi></hi>, 1889 (W349) (Essen, Museum Folkwang). <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_111">Ill. 111</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="b" xml:id="note-t-b">
                            

<p>Read: ‘Trophime’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            

<p>In a letter to Theo, Vincent compared this Romanesque portal to ‘a Chinese nightmare’. <ref target="let588.xml#n-8">See letter 588, n. 8.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="11" xml:id="note-t-11">
                            

<p>For <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">Meijer de Haan</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_916">Uriel Acosta</rs></hi>, <ref target="let708.xml#n-2">see letter 708, n. 2.</ref> Van Gogh had sent his letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1103">Isaäcson</rs> in care of Theo on about 8 October (<ref target="let810.xml">see letter 810</ref>); apparently Isaäcson, who was staying in Paris, had sent it on to De Haan in Le Pouldu.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="12" xml:id="note-t-12">
                            

<p>There is no known drawing by Van Gogh after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1295">Rembrandt</rs>. It is possible that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs> was mistaken, and that Van Gogh had suggested exchanging his painting <hi rend="italics">Angel (after ‘Rembrandt’)</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_908">F 624 / JH 1778</rs>) for one of Gauguin’s works. Gauguin had written earlier about a reproduction of an angel by Rembrandt, of which Van Gogh had a copy (<ref target="let817.xml">letter 817</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    