<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Sunday, 4 May 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let868"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b680 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>868</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>631</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>869</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-05-04">Sunday, 4 May 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0680" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0680" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000926_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Mon cher frère,</p><lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">merci de ta bonne lettre et du portrait de Jo qui est <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>fort joli &amp; très réussi comme pose.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Voici je serai dans ma réponse <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>très simple &amp; aussi pratique que possible. D’abord j’écarte cathégoriquement <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ce que tu dis qu’il faudrait me faire accompagner tout le trajet. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Une fois dans le train je ne risque plus rien, je ne suis pas de ceux <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>qui soient dangereux – même supposition<ptr target="#note-t-a"/> qu’il m’arrive une <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>crise<c type="kk">,</c> n’y a-t-il pas d’autres passagers dans le wagon et <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>d’ailleurs ne sait-on pas dans toutes les gares comment faire dans <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>pareil cas<c type="kp">.</c>– Tu te fais là des inquiétudes qui me pèsent si <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>lourdement que cela me découragerait directement.</p><lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Je viens de dire la même chôse à M. Peyron et je lui <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>ai observé que les crises comme je viens d’en avoir une <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>ont toujours été suivi de trois ou quatre mois de calme <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>complet. Je désire profiter de cette période pour <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>changer – je veux changer dans tous les cas, mon <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>désir de partir d’ici est maintenant absolu.–</p><lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Je ne me sens pas compétent pour juger la façon de traiter <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>les malades ici, je ne me sens pas d’envie d’entrer dans <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>des détails – mais veuilles te souvenir que je t’ai averti il <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>y a 6 mois à peu près que si une crise me reprenait avec <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>le même caractère je désirais changer de maison.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>et j’ai trop tardé déjà ayant laissé passer une attaque <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>entre temps, j’étais alors en plein travail et je voulais <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>finir des toiles en train, sans cela je ne serais déjà <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>plus ici.– Bon je vais donc te dire qu’il me semble <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>qu’une quinzaine tout au plus (une huitaine me serait pourtant <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>plus agréable) pourrait suffire pour prendre les mesures <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>nécessaires pour changer. Je me ferai accompagner <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>jusqu’à Tarascon – même une ou deux gares plus loin <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>si tu y tiens. arrivé à Paris (à mon depart d’ici j’expédierai <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>une dépêche) tu viendrais me prendre à la gare de Lyon<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Maintenant il me semblerait préférable d’aller voir ce <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>médecin à la campagne aussitôt que possible et nous laisserions <lb n="33a" xml:id="l-33a"/>les bagages en gare<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">Je ne resterais donc chez toi que mettons 2 ou 3 jours <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>puis je partirais pour ce village. où je commencerais par loger <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>à l’auberge<c type="kp">.</c>–</p><lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Voici ce qu’il me semble que tu pourrais de ces jours ci – <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>sans tarder – écrire à notre ami futur le médecin <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>en question: “mon frère désirait beaucoup faire votre <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>connaissance et préférant vous consulter avant de prolonger <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>son sejour à Paris, espère que vous trouverez <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>bien qu’il passe quelques semaines dans votre village <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>où il viendra faire des études; il a toute confiance <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>de s’entendre avec vous<c type="kk">,</c> croyant que par un retour dans <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>le nord sa maladie diminuera alors que par un séjour <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>davantage prolongé dans le midi son état menacerait de <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>devenir plus aigu.”</p><lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Voilà<c type="kk">,</c> tu lui écrirais de la sorte<c type="kk">,</c> on lui enverrait une <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>dépêche le lendemain ou surlendemain de mon arrivée <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>à Paris et probablement il m’attendrait à la gare.</p><lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">L’entourage ici commence à me peser plus que <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>je ne saurais l’exprimer – ma foi j’ai patienté <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>plus d’un an – il me faut de l’air<c type="kk">,</c> je me sens <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>abimé d’ennui et de chagrin.–</p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Puis le travail presse<c type="kk">,</c> je perdrais mon temps <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>ici. Pourquoi donc, je te le demande<c type="kk">,</c> crains <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>tu tant les accidents – c’est pas cela qui doive t’effrayer, <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>ma foi depuis que je suis ici j’en vois tomber ou <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>s’égarer tous les jours – ce qui est plus sérieux <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>c’est de chercher de faire une part au malheur<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Je t’assure que c’est déjà quelque chôse de <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>se résigner à vivre sous de la surveillance<c type="kk">,</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>même en cas qu’elle serait sympathique<c type="kk">,</c> et de <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>sacrifier sa liberté<c type="kk">,</c> se tenir hors de la société <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>et de n’avoir que son travail<c type="kk">,</c> sans distraction<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>Cela m’a creusé des rides qui ne s’effaceront <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>pas de sitôt<c type="kp">.</c>– Maintenant qu’ici cela commence <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>à me peser <hi rend="italics">trop lourd</hi> je crois qu’il n’est que juste <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>qu’il y ait un halte-là.–</p><lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Veuille donc écrire à M. Peyron qu’il me laisse <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>partir mettons le 15 au plus tard.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> Si j’attendais <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>je laisserais passer le bon moment de calme entre <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>deux crises et partant à présent j’aurai le <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>loisir nécessaire pour faire la connaissance de <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>l’autre médecin. Alors si dans quelque temps <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>d’ici le mal reviendrait ce serait prévu et selon <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>la gravité nous pourrions voir si je peux continuer <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>en liberté ou bien s’il faut se caser dans une <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>maison de santé pour de bon. Dans le dernier <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>cas – ainsi que je te l’ai dit dans ma dernière <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>lettre j’irais dans une maison où les malades <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>travaillent aux champs &amp; à l’atelier. Je crois <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>qu’encore davantage qu’ici je trouverais alors <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>des motifs pour la peinture<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">Réfléchis donc que le voyage coûte cher<c type="kk">,</c> que <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>cela est inutile et que j’ai bien le droit de changer <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>de maison si cela me plait<c type="kk">,</c> ce n’est pas ma <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>liberté absolue que je réclame<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">J’ai essayé d’être patient jusqu’ici<c type="kk">,</c> je n’ai fait <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>du mal à personne<c type="kk">,</c> est ce juste de me faire <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>accompagner comme une bête dangereuse<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Merci<c type="kk">,</c> je proteste<c type="kp">.</c>– S’il arrive une crise<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>dans toutes les gares on sait comment faire <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>et alors je me laisserais faire.</p>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">Mais j’ose croire que mon aplomb ne me <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>manquera pas. J’ai tant de chagrin de quitter <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>comme cela<c type="kk">,</c> que le chagrin sera plus fort que <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>la folie<c type="kk">,</c> j’aurai donc j’ose croire l’aplomb nécessaire<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>M. Peyron dit des chôses vagues pour dégager <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>dit-il sa responsabilité mais ainsi on n’en finirait <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>jamais jamais<c type="kk">,</c> la chôse trainerait en longueur et <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>on finirait par se fâcher de part et d’autre<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Moi ma patience est à bout<c type="kk">,</c> à bout mon cher frère<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>je n’en peux plus<c type="kk">,</c> il faut changer même pour <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>un pis aller.–</p><lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.16" n="16">Cependant il y a une chance réellement que le <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>changement me fasse du bien – le travail marche bien<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>j’ai fait 2 toiles de l’herbe fraiche dans le parc dont <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>il y en a une d’une simplicité extrême. en voici un croquis <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>hatif.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="110*" xml:id="l-110s"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.17" n="17">Un tronc de pin <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>violet rose et puis de l’herbe <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>avec des fleurs blanches et <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>des pissenlits<c type="kk">,</c> un petit rosier <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>et d’autres troncs d’arbre dans <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>le fond<c type="kk">,</c> tout en haut de la <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>toile. Je serai là-bas dehors<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>Je suis sûr que l’envie de <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>travailler me dévorera <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>et me rendra insensible <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>à tout le reste et de bonne humeur. Et je m’y laisserai <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>aller non pas sans réflexion mais sans m’apesantir sur <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>des regrets de chôses qui auraient pu être.</p><lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.18" n="18">Ils disent que dans la peinture il ne faut rien chercher ni <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>espérer qu’un bon tableau et une bonne causerie et un bon <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>diner comme maximum de bonheur<c type="kk">,</c> sans compter <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>les parenthèses moins brillantes<c type="kp">.</c>– C’est peutêtre vrai et <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>pourquoi refuser de prendre le possible surtout si ainsi faisant <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>on donne le change à la maladie.</p><lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.19" n="19">Bonne poignée de main à toi et à Jo<c type="kk">,</c> je crois que <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>je vais faire une peinture pour moi d’après le motif du portrait<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>cela ne sera pas ressemblant peutêtre mais enfin je chercherai<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.20" n="20">J’espère à bientôt – et voyons<c type="kk">,</c> epargnez moi ce compagnon <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>de voyage forcé<c type="kp">.</c>–</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.21" n="21">t. à t.</p><lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.22" n="22">Vincent.</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">My dear brother,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2">Thanks for your kind letter and for the portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, which is very pretty and is very successful as a pose.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Well, I’ll be very simple and as practical as possible in my reply. First, I categorically reject what you say that I should be accompanied throughout the journey. Once on the train I no longer run any risk, I’m not one of those who are dangerous – even supposing I have a crisis, aren’t there other passengers in the carriage, and besides, don’t they know what to do in all the stations in such a case? You’re giving yourself worries here that weigh on me so heavily that it might directly discourage me.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">I’ve just said the same thing to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs>, and I pointed out to him that crises like the one I’ve just had have always been followed by three or four months of complete calm. I wish to take advantage of this period to move – I want to move in any event, my desire to leave here is now absolute.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">I don’t feel competent to judge the way they treat patients here, I don’t feel any desire to enter into the details – but please remember that I warned you around 6 months ago that if I was seized by a crisis of the same nature I’d wish to change asylums.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> And I’ve delayed too long already, having allowed an attack to go by in the meantime, I was then right in the middle of work, and I wanted to finish canvases in progress, otherwise I would no longer be here by now. Right, so I’m going to tell you that it seems to me that a fortnight at the most (a week, though, would please me more) should be enough to take the necessary steps to move. I shall have someone accompany me as far as Tarascon – even one or two stations further if you insist. Once I’ve arrived in Paris (I’ll send a telegram when I leave here) you would come and pick me up at the Gare de Lyon.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Now it would seem preferable to me to go and see this doctor in the country as soon as possible, and we’d leave the luggage at the station.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">So I would only stay at your place for let’s say 2 or 3 days, then I’d leave for this village. Where I would start off by lodging at the inn.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">This, it seems to me, is what you could do in the next few days– without delay – write to our future friend, that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">doctor</rs>: ‘my brother would very much like to make your acquaintance, and as he would prefer to consult you before prolonging his stay in Paris, hopes that you will approve of his spending a few weeks in your village, where he will come to make some studies; he has complete confidence that he will reach an understanding with you, believing that with a return to the north his illness will abate, whereas by staying on in the south his condition would be in danger of becoming more acute.’</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">There, you could write to him like that, we’d send him a telegram the day after my arrival in Paris, or the day after that, and he’d probably wait for me at the station.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">The surroundings here are starting to weigh on me more than I could express – my word, I’ve waited patiently for over a year – I need air, I feel damaged by boredom and grief.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Then work is pressing, I’d be wasting my time here. Why then, I ask you, do you fear accidents so much – it isn’t that that ought to frighten you, my word, since I’ve been here I’ve seen people fall over or lose their mind every day – what’s more serious is to try and take misfortune into account. I assure you that it’s already something to resign oneself to living under guard, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> even in the event of it being sympathetic, and to sacrifice one’s freedom, to stand outside society and to have only one’s work, without distraction. That has carved out wrinkles that won’t be rubbed off in a hurry. Now that it’s beginning to weigh <hi rend="italics">too heavily</hi> upon me here, I think that it’s only right to put a stop to it.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">So please write to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> that he should let me leave, let’s say on the 15th at the latest.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> If I waited I would let the good moment of calm between two crises pass, and leaving now I’ll have the free time necessary to make the other <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">doctor</rs>’s acquaintance. Then, if in a while from now the illness were to recur it would be foreseen, and according to how serious it was we could see if I can continue at liberty or if I must stick myself in an asylum for good. In the latter case – as I told you in my last letter I would go into an institution where the patients work in the fields and in the workshop. I think that even more than here I’d then find subjects for painting.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Consider, then, that the journey costs a lot, that it’s pointless and that I do have the right to change asylums if I please, it isn’t my absolute freedom that I’m demanding.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">I’ve tried to be patient up to this point, I haven’t done any harm to anyone, is it fair to have me accompanied like a dangerous animal? No thank you, I protest. If a crisis occurs, they know what to do in every station, and then I’d let them do it. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">But I dare believe that my composure won’t desert me. I have so much distress at leaving like this, that the distress will be stronger than the madness, I’ll therefore have the necessary nerve, I dare believe. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_568">Mr Peyron</rs> says vague things, to free himself from responsibility he says, but that way we’d never, never get to the end of it, the thing would drag on and on, and in the end we’d get angry with each other.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15">As for me, my patience is at an end, at an end, my dear brother, I can’t go on, I must move, even if as a stopgap.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.16" n="16">However, there really is a chance that the change will do me good – work is going well, I’ve done 2 canvases of the fresh grass in the park, one of which is extremely simple. Here’s a hasty croquis of it.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.17" n="17"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.18" n="18">The trunk of a pine tree violet pink, and then grass with white flowers and dandelions, a little rose bush and other tree-trunks in the background, in the uppermost part of the canvas. I’ll be out of doors there. I’m sure that the desire to work will devour me and make me insensible to everything else and in a good mood. And I’ll let myself go there, not without consideration but without dwelling on regrets for things that might have been.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.19" n="19">They say that in painting one must seek nothing and hope for nothing but a good painting and a good talk and a good dinner as the height of happiness, not counting the less brilliant interludes. Perhaps it’s true, and why refuse to take what is possible, especially if by doing so one gives the illness the slip.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.20" n="20">Good handshake to you and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>, I think I’m going to do a painting for myself after the subject of the portrait, it may not be a resemblance perhaps, but anyway I’ll try.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.21" n="21">More soon, I hope – and come on, spare me this forced travelling companion.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.22" n="22">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.23" n="23">Vincent.</p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Vincent thanks Theo for his letter with the enclosed portrait photograph of Jo and Vincent Willem; this was <ref target="let867.xml">letter 867</ref> of 3 May. Assuming that he responded immediately to Theo’s suggestion to let himself be accompanied on his railway journey (which he thought unnecessary), and given his determination to carry out his plans to go to Auvers as soon as possible (preferably within a week than in a fortnight), we have dated the present letter to Sunday, 4 May 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Fourth attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let857.xml">(857)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="ogt_2">
                            
<p>Vincent considers settling in Auvers and putting himself in the care of Dr Gachet <ref target="let808.xml">(808)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref target="let867.xml">letter 867</ref>. For the portrait photograph, <ref target="let867.xml#n-12">see n. 12</ref> to that letter.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="a" xml:id="note-t-a">
                            

<p>Meaning ‘even supposing’.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Van Gogh had written this in <ref target="let805.xml">letter 805</ref> of about Friday, 20 September 1889.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh finally left Saint-Rémy on 16 May and arrived in Paris on Saturday, 17 May.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
      <hi rend="italics">The garden of the asylum with dandelions and tree-trunks</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2899">F 676 / JH 1970</rs>), after which Van Gogh made the letter sketch of the same name <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_226">F - / JH 1971</rs>, and <hi rend="italics">Meadow in the garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2902">F 672 / JH 1975</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    