<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2025-01-22T15:29:03.2623616+01:00 
-->
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Auvers-sur-Oise, on or about Thursday, 10 July 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt>
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let898"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b697 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>898</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>649</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>903</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-07-10">on or about Thursday, 10 July 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface n="b 0697" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_01_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_01_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_01_n"/></zone></surface>
<surface n="b 0697" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_02_n"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_02_n"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3" ulx="50" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
<graphic url="VGM001000946_02_n"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/><lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.1" n="1">Chers frère &amp; soeur,</p><lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.2" n="2">la lettre de Jo <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>a été pour moi réellement comme <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>un évangile<c type="kk">,</c> une délivrance d’angoisse <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>que m’avaient causée les heures <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>un peu difficiles &amp; laborieuses pour nous <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>tous que j’ai partagées avec vous<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>C’est pas peu de chôse lorsque tous <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>ensemble nous sentons le pain <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>quotidien en danger<c type="kk">,</c> pas peu <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de chôse lorsque pour d’autres <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>causes que celle là aussi nous <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>sentons notre existence fragile<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p><lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.3" n="3">Revenu ici<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> je me suis senti moi <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>aussi encore bien attristé et avais <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>continué à sentir peser sur moi <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>aussi l’orage qui vous menace. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Qu’y faire – voyez vous je cherche <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>d’habitude à être de bonne humeur <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>assez mais ma vie à moi aussi <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>est attaquée à la racine même<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>mon pas aussi est chancelant<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>J’ai craint – pas tout à fait – <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>mais un peu pourtant – que <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>je vous étais redoutable étant <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>à votre charge – mais la lettre <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>de Jo me prouve clairement que 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/><lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>vous sentez bien que pour ma <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>part je suis en travail et peine <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>comme vous.</p><lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.4" n="4">Là – revenu ici je me suis remis <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>au travail – le pinceau pourtant <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>me tombant presque des mains <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>et – sachant bien ce que je <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>voulais j’ai encore depuis <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>peint trois grandes toiles<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Ce sont d’immenses étendues <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>de blés sous des ciels troublés <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>et je ne me suis pas gêné pour <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>chercher à exprimer de la <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>tristesse<c type="kk">,</c> de la solitude extrême.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> Vous verrez cela j’espère <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>sous peu – car j’espère vous <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>les apporter à Paris le plus tôt <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>possible puisque je croirais <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>presque que ces toiles vous <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>diront ce que je ne sais <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>dire en paroles<c type="kk">,</c> ce que <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>je vois de sain et de fortifiant <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>dans la campagne.</p><lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.5" n="5">Maintenant la troisieme <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>toile est le jardin de 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/><lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Daubigny<c type="kk">,</c> tableau que <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>je méditais depuis que je suis <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ici<c type="kp">.</c>–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.6" n="6">J’espère de tout mon coeur <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>que le voyage projeté puisse <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>vous procurer un peu de <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>distraction<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.7" n="7">Souvent je pense au petit<c type="kk">,</c> je crois <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>que certes c’est mieux d’élever <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>des enfants que de donner <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>toute sa force nerveuse à faire <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>des tableaux mais que voulez <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>vous<c type="kk">,</c> je suis moi maintenant<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>au moins me sens<c type="kk">,</c> trop vieux <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>pour revenir sur des pas ou <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>pour avoir envie d’autre chôse<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>Cette envie m’a passée quoique <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>la douleur morale m’en <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>reste.</p><lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.8" n="8">Je regrette beaucoup de ne <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>pas avoir revu Guillaumin <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>mais cela me fait plaisir <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>qu’il aie vu mes toiles<c type="kp">.</c></p><lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.9" n="9">Si je l’avais attendu j’aurais <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>probablement resté à causer 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/><lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>avec lui de façon à perdre <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>mon train.</p><lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.10" n="10">Vous soushaitant de la <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>chance et bon courage <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>et prosperité relative<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>je vous prie de dire une fois <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>à la mère et à la soeur que <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>je pense à elles bien souvent<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>d’ailleurs j’ai ce matin une <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>lettre d’elles et répondrai sous <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>peu.</p><lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.11" n="11">Poignées de main en pensée<c type="kp">.</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.12" n="12">t. à v.</p><lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.13" n="13">Vincent</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>

<p xml:id="p.orig.14" n="14">mon argent ne me durera pas <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>bien longtemps cette fois ci<c type="kk">,</c> ayant <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>à mon retour eu à payer les frais <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>de bagages d’Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> Je garde de ce <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>voyage à Paris de bien bons souvenirs<c type="kp">.</c> <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>il y a quelques mois j’osais peu esperer <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>revoir encore les amis. j’ai trouvé bien <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>du talent à cette dame hollandaise<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-8"/> </p><lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.orig.15" n="15">Le tableau de Lautrec<c type="kk">,</c> portrait de <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>musicienne<c type="kk">,</c> est bien etonnant<c type="kk">,</c> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>je l’ai vu avec émotion<c type="kp">.</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.1" n="1">Dear brother and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">sister</rs>,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.2" n="2"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s letter was really like a gospel for me, a deliverance from anguish which I was caused by the rather difficult and laborious hours for us all that I shared with you.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> It’s no small thing when all together we feel the daily bread in danger, no small thing when for other causes than that we also feel our existence to be fragile.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.3" n="3">Once back here<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> I too still felt very saddened, and had continued to feel the storm that threatens you also weighing upon me. What can be done – you see I usually try to be quite good-humoured, but my life, too, is attacked at the very root, my step also is faltering. I feared – not completely – but a little nonetheless – that I was a danger to you, living at your expense – but <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs>’s letter clearly proves to me that 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> you really feel that for my part I am working and suffering like you.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.4" n="4">There – once back here I set to work again – the brush however almost falling from my hands and – knowing clearly what I wanted I’ve painted another three large canvases since then. They’re immense stretches of wheatfields under turbulent skies, and I made a point of trying to express sadness, extreme loneliness.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> You’ll see this soon, I hope – for I hope to bring them to you in Paris as soon as possible, since I’d almost believe that these canvases will tell you what I can’t say in words, what I consider healthy and fortifying about the countryside.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.5" n="5">Now the third canvas is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>’s garden, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> a painting I’d been thinking about ever since I’ve been here.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.6" n="6">I hope with all my heart that the planned journey may provide you with a little distraction.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.7" n="7">I often think of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">little one</rs>, I believe that certainly it’s better to bring up children than to expend all one’s nervous energy in making paintings, but what can you do, I myself am now, at least I feel I am, too old to retrace my steps or to desire something else. This desire has left me, although the moral pain of it remains.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.8" n="8">I very much regret not having seen <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> again, but it pleases me that he’s seen my canvases.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.9" n="9">If I’d waited for him I would probably have stayed to talk 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> with him in such a way as to miss my train.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.10" n="10">Wishing you luck and good heart and relative prosperity, please tell <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_524">Mother</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_407">Sister</rs> sometime that I think of them very often, besides this morning I have a letter from them and will reply shortly.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.11" n="11">Handshakes in thought.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.12" n="12">Ever yours,</p>
<p xml:id="p.trans.13" n="13">Vincent</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.trans.14" n="14">My money won’t last me very long this time, as on my return I had to pay the baggage costs from Arles.<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> I retain very good memories of this trip to Paris. A few months ago I little dared hope to see our friends again. I thought that Dutch <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1381">lady</rs> had a great deal of talent.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.trans.15" n="15"><rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Lautrec</rs>’s painting, portrait of a female musician, is quite astonishing, it moved me when I saw it.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p>Van Gogh looks back on his visit to Paris on Sunday, 6 July (<ref target="let897.xml">see letter 897</ref>). Since then he has painted three large canvases <ref target="#l-36">(l. 36)</ref>. Knowing that in Auvers he achieved the high level of production of around one canvas a day, we have dated the present letter to about Thursday, 10 July 1888. See also Hulsker 1998, p. 49.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p>The earlier version of this letter, <ref target="RM24.xml">RM24</ref>, was never sent. </p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p>Theo considers leaving the firm of Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie <ref target="let894.xml">(894)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> is not known.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>Vincent is referring here to his own fragile health, as well as the health problems of Theo and his family.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Vincent had visited Theo and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> in Paris on Sunday, 6 July (<ref target="let897.xml">see letter 897</ref>). Jo wrote in the introduction to her edition of the letters: ‘In the first days of July, Vincent came again to see us in Paris; we were worn out by the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">child</rs>’s serious indisposition – Theo had again conceived the plan to leave Goupil in order to start a business of his own, Vincent was not satisfied with the room the paintings are stored in, so we talked about moving to a larger apartment, so they were days of worry and tension.</p>

<p rend="indent">There were also constant visitors for Vincent, including <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_521">Aurier</rs>, who had written his famous article about Vincent shortly before this, and now looked at all the work again with the painter himself, and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Toulouse-Lautrec</rs>, who stayed to have lunch with us and had the biggest laugh with Vincent about an undertaker’s assistant, whom they met on the stairs. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1065">Guillaumin</rs> would also have come, but it was too much for Vincent, he didn’t wait for his visit, and went back to Auvers in great haste; overfatigued and overwrought, as appears from his last letters and from his last paintings, in which one feels imminent disaster, coming closer like the black birds that race across the field in the storm’ (<hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, pp. <hi>lxii</hi>-<hi>lxiii</hi>).</p>

<p rend="indent">Vincent’s visit did not go smoothly. On 31 July 1890, Jo wrote to Theo: ‘If only I’d been a bit kinder to him when he was with us!’ and on 1 August: ‘How sorry I was for being impatient with him the last time’ (FR b4245 and b2060; <hi rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 276-277).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>Van Gogh later added ‘de la solitude extrême’ (extreme loneliness). Judging by the description, the most likely possibilities are <hi rend="italics">Wheatfield under troubled skies</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2936">F 778 / JH 2097</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Wheatfield with crows</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2942">F 779 / JH 2117</rs>); they are, moreover, the same format as the third canvas (<ref target="#n-5">see n. 5</ref>). Cf. also exhib. cat. New York 1986, pp. 275-276.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh painted two large canvases of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_976">Daubigny</rs>’s garden: <hi rend="italics">Daubigny’s garden</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2939">F 776 / JH 2104</rs>) and <hi rend="italics">Daubigny’s garden</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2940">F 777 / JH 2105</rs>). The one referred to here is the first version, <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2940">F 777 / JH 2105</rs>. See exhib. cat. New York, pp. 284-285.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>Theo, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_416">Jo</rs> and little <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_418">Vincent</rs> left on 15 July for Leiden. Jo then travelled on to Amsterdam to stay with her family while she and the baby regained their strength. Theo was most likely in The Hague on 16 July. He then travelled via Antwerp to Brussels, returning to Paris on Friday evening, 18 July. He was planning to go again to the Netherlands and spend his holidays there with his family (see <hi rend="italics">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, pp. 245-248, and <ref target="let901.xml">letter 901</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>Van Gogh’s furniture from Arles had been sent by the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_382 bio.xml#_383">Ginouxs</rs> to Auvers (<ref target="let882.xml">see letter 882</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The sculptor <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1381">Elisabeth Sara Clasina de Swart</rs> (see <hi rend="italics">Brieven</hi> 1914, vol. 3, p. 461). Vincent had met her on Sunday, 6 July.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1392">Toulouse-Lautrec</rs>’s <hi rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_431">Mademoiselle Dihau at the piano</rs></hi>, about which Theo had written earlier, <ref target="let858.xml#n-8">see letter 858, n. 8.</ref> Van Gogh must have seen it during his visit to Paris. His surprised reaction can perhaps be explained by the fact that he had painted the same subject a short while before in <hi rend="italics">Marguerite Gachet at the piano</hi> (<rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2932">F 772 / JH 2048</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    