<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>Passages copied from the Bible. Dordrecht, probably February-March 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/RM10"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b1465 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>RM10</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno/></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>-</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1877-02">probably February-March 1877</date>
                            <placeName>Dordrecht?</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Theo van Gogh</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1465" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001353_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001353_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 1465 V/1962" xml:id="surf-extra-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001001353_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="nl" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.1" n="1">Wees sterk en Hij zal Uw hart versterken.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Zie, de Satan heeft onze ziel zeer begeerd om ons te ziften als de tarwe.–<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <hi rend="italics">En nog is het einde niet</hi><c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.2" n="2"><hi rend="italics">1 Cor XI:23</hi>. Want ik heb van den Heer ontvangen hetgeen ik ook U overgegeven heb, dat de Heer Jezus, in den nacht in welken Hij verraden werd, het brood nam, en als Hij gedankt had brak Hij het en zeide: Neemt, eet, dat is mijn ligchaam dat voor U verbroken wordt, doet dit tot Mijne gedachtenis. Des<c type="shy">-</c>gelijks nam Hij ook den drinkbeker, na het eten des Avondmaals, en zeide Deze drinkbeker is het Nieuwe Testament in Mijn bloed, dat voor U vergoten wordt <hi rend="italics">tot vergeving van zonden</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> doet dat, zoo dikwijls als Gij dit brood zult eten en dezen drinkbeker drinken tot Mijne gedachtenis, en verkondigt den dood des Heeren totdat Hij komt.–<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.3" n="3"><hi rend="italics">Lukas XXII</hi>. En uitgaande, vertrok Hij, gelijk Hij gewoon was<c type="kk">/</c> naar den Olijfberg, en Hem volgden ook Zijne discipelen. En als Hij aan die plaats gekomen was, zeide Hij tot hen: Bidt, dat gij niet in ver<c type="shy">-</c>zoeking komt.– En hij scheidde zich van hen af, omtrent eenen steenworp; en knielde neder, en bad, zeggende: Vader! of Gij wildet dezen drinkbeker van Mij wegnemen! doch niet Mijn wil maar Uw wil geschiede. En van Hem werd gezien een Engel die Hem versterkte. En in zwaren strijd zijnde, bad Hij des te ernstiger. En Zijn zweet werd als groote droppelen bloeds die op de aarde afliepen. En als Hij van het gebed opgestaan was, kwam Hij tot Zijne discipelen, en vond hen slapende van droefheid.–<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.4" n="4">En Pilatus vraagde Hem met vele woorden,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> doch Hij antwoordde hem niets. En Pilatus zeide<c type="kk">/</c> Weet Gij dan niet dat ik magt heb om U te kruisigen en magt heb om U los te laten, en Jezus antwoordde<c type="kk">/</c> Gij zoudt geene magt tegenover Mij hebben indien ze U niet van Boven gegeven ware.–<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.nl.5" n="5">Jezus dan kwam uit, dragende de doornen kroon en het purperen kleed. En Pilatus zeide tot hen: Zie, den mensch.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> </p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/></div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">Be of good courage, and He shall strengthen thine heart.<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> Behold, Satan hath desired to have our soul, that he may sift us as wheat.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> <hi rend="italics">And the end shall not be yet</hi>.<ptr target="#note-t-3"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2"><hi rend="italics">1 Cor XI:23</hi>. For I have received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus the same night in which He was betrayed took bread: and when He had given thanks, He brake it<hi rend="italics">,</hi> and said, Take, eat: this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of Me. After the same manner also He took the cup, when He had supped, saying, This cup is the new testament in My blood, which is shed for you<hi rend="italics"> for the remission of sins</hi>,<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> this do ye, as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, in remembrance of Me, and do shew the Lord’s death till he come.<ptr target="#note-t-5"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.3" n="3"><hi rend="italics">Luke XXII</hi>. And He came out, and went, as He was wont, to the mount of Olives; and His disciples also followed Him. And when He was at the place, He said unto them, Pray that ye enter not into temptation. And he was withdrawn from them about a stone’s cast, and kneeled down, and prayed, saying, Father! if Thou be willing, remove this cup from Me! nevertheless not My will, but Thy will, be done. And there appeared an angel unto Him, strengthening Him. And being in an agony He prayed more earnestly: and His sweat was as it were great drops of blood falling down to the ground. And when He rose up from prayer, and was come to His disciples, He found them sleeping for sorrow.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Then Pilate questioned Him in many words,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but He answered him nothing. And Pilate saith, Knowest Thou not that I have power to crucify Thee, and have power to release Thee? And Jesus answered, Thou couldest have no power at all against Me, except it were given thee from Above.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And Pilate saith unto them, Behold the man.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">It is impossible to date this precisely, but considering Van Gogh opens here with Psalm 27:14, and he does the same at the beginning of two letters written from Dordrecht – dating from 28 February and 8 March 1877 (<ref target="let104.xml">letters 104</ref> and <ref target="let106.xml">106</ref>) – we think it likely that this loose leaf originated in February-March 1877.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>
  Ps. 27:14.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
  Luke 22:31.
</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>
  Mark 13:7.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>
  Matt. 26:28.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>
  1 Cor. 11:23-26.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
  Luke 22:39-45.
</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>
  Luke 23:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>
  John 19:9-11.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>
  John 19:5.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    