<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!--
            This XML is the result of a conversion of the Van Gogh letter XML to another format. 
            It is work in progress. 
            The conversion was done at 2024-04-04T13:28:07.787066+02:00 
        -->
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
        <?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/MD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
        <?editem template="letter" adaptation="vg"?>
        <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:md="http://mondrian.huygens.knaw.nl/" xmlns:file="http://expath.org/ns/file" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<title>To Paul Gauguin, Auvers-sur-Oise, on or about Tuesday, 17 June 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor></titleStmt>
                    

                    <publicationStmt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<publisher><name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name></publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p></licence></availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/RM23"/></publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                
                                
                                        <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                                        <institution>Van Gogh Museum</institution>
                                        
                                        <idno>b691 V/1962</idno>
                                    
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="jlb"><idno>RM23</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="collectedletters"><idno>643</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                                    

                                    <altIdentifier type="brieven1990"><idno>893</idno></altIdentifier>
                                
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                    <correspDesc>
                        <correspAction type="sent">
                            
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Vincent van Gogh</rs>
                            <date when="1890-06-17">on or about Tuesday, 17 June 1890</date>
                            <placeName>Auvers-sur-Oise</placeName>
                        </correspAction>
                        <correspAction type="received">
                            <rs ref="bio.xml#_0" type="person">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                        </correspAction>
                    </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            
            <facsimile>
                
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0691" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000939_01_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000939_01_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
<surface xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" n="b 0691" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000939_02_n/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000939_02_n/pct:0,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic url="https://example.com/iiif/VGM001000939_02_n/pct:50,0,50,100/max/0/default.jpg"/></zone></surface>
            </facsimile>
            
            <text>
                <body>
                    <div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="fr" type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.1" n="1">Mon cher ami Gauguin</p>

<p xml:id="p.fr.2" n="2">merci de m’avoir de nouveau écrit,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> mon cher ami, et soyez assuré que depuis mon retour j’ai pensé à vous tous les jours. Je ne suis resté à Paris que trois jours<c type="kk">/</c> et le bruit &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> Parisien me faisant une bien mauvaise impression j’ai jugé prudent pour ma tête de ficher le camp pour la campagne – sans cela j’aurais bien vite couru chez vous. Et cela me fait énormément plaisir que vous dites que le portrait d’arlésienne fondé rigoureusement sur votre dessin vous a plu<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-2"/> J’ai cherché à être fidèle à votre dessin respectueusement et pourtant prenant la liberté d’interpréter par le moyen d’une couleur dans le caractere sobre<c type="kk">/</c> et le style du dessin en question<c type="kp">_</c></p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.3" n="3">C’est une synthèse d’arlésienne si vous voulez; comme les syntheses d’arlésiennes sont rares prenez cela comme oeuvre de vous et de moi<c type="kk">/</c> comme resumé de nos mois de travail ensemble. Pour le faire j’ai payé moi pour ma part encore d’un mois de maladie<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> mais aussi je sais que c’est une toile qui sera comprise par vous<c type="kk">/</c> moi et de rares autres<c type="kk">/</c> comme nous voudrions qu’on comprenne. Ici mon ami le D<hi rend="super">r </hi>Gachet y est après deux trois hesitations venu tout à fait et dit: “comme c’est difficile d’être simple”<c type="kp">_</c> Bon – je vais encore souligner la chôse en la gravant à l’eau forte<c type="kk">/</c> cette chôse-là puis basta.– l’aura qui voudra<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-4"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.4" n="4">Avez vous aussi vu les oliviers?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Maintenant j’ai un portrait du D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gachet à expression navrée de notre temps.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <hi rend="italics">Si vous voulez</hi> quelque chose comme vous disiez de votre Christ au jardin des oliviers<c type="kk">/</c> pas destiné à être comprise<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> mais enfin là jusque-là je vous suis et mon frère saisit bien cette nuance.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.5" n="5">J’ai encore de là-bas un cyprès avec une étoile<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.6" n="6">un dernier essai – un ciel de nuit avec une lune sans éclat<c type="kk">/</c> à peine le croissant mince émergeant de l’ombre projetée opaque de la terre – une étoile à éclat exageré, si vous voulez, éclat doux de rose &amp; vert dans le ciel outremer où courent des nuages. En bas une route bordée de hautes cannes jaunes derrière lesquelles les basses Alpines bleues<c type="kk">/</c> une vieille auberge à fenêtres illuminées orangées et un très-haut cyprès tout droit<c type="kk">/</c> tout sombre.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.7" n="7">Sur la route une voiture jaune attelée d’un cheval blanc et deux promeneurs attardés.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Tres romantique si vous voulez mais aussi je crois “de la Provence”. Probablement je graverai à l’eau forte celle là et d’autres paysages et motifs<c type="kk">/</c> souvenirs de Provence<c type="kk">/</c> alors je me ferai une fête de vous en donner un tout<c type="kk">/</c> un résumé un peu voulu et étudié. Mon frère dit que Lauzet<c type="kk">/</c> qui fait les lithographies d’après Monticelli<c type="kk">/</c> a trouvé bien la tête d’Arlesienne en question<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-9"/></p>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.8" n="8">Alors vous comprenez qu’etant arrivé à Paris un peu ahuri je n’ai pas encore vu de vos toiles. Mais bientôt j’espère y retourner pour quelques jours. Très content d’apprendre par votre lettre que vous retournez en Bretagne avec de Haan. Il est fort probable que – si vous me le permettez – je viendrai pour un mois vous y rejoindre pour y faire une marine ou deux mais surtout pour vous revoir et faire la connaissance de de Haan. De ces jours-<c type="shy">-</c>là nous chercherons à faire quelque chôse de voulu et de grave comme cela serait probablement devenu si nous eussions pu continuer là-bas.</p>

<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.fr.9" n="9">Tenez<c type="kk">/</c> une idée qui peutetre vous ira. je cherche à faire des études de blé ainsi<c type="kk">/</c> je ne peux cependant pas dessiner cela –</p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>

<p xml:id="p.fr.10" n="10">rien que des épis<c type="kk">/</c> tiges bleus verts<c type="kk">/</c> feuilles longues comme des rubans vert &amp; rose par le reflet<c type="kk">/</c> épis jaunissant légerement bordés de rose pâle par la floraison poussiereuse. un liseron rose dans le bas enroulé autour d’une tige. Là-dessus<c type="kk">/</c> sur un fond bien vivant et pourtant tranquille je voudrais peindre des portraits<c type="kp">_</c> C’est des verts de différente qualité<c type="kk">/</c> de même valeur<c type="kk">/</c> de facon à former un tout vert qui ferait par sa vibration songer au bruit doux des épis se balançant à la brise<c type="kp">_</c><ptr target="#note-t-10"/> C’est pas commode du tout comme coloration<c type="kp">_</c></p>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/>
<space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
</div>

                    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.1" n="1">My dear friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs></p>
<p xml:id="p.en.2" n="2">Thanks for writing to me again,<ptr target="#note-t-1"/> my dear friend, and be assured that since my return I’ve thought about you every day. I only stayed in Paris for three days, and as the Parisian noise &amp;c. made a pretty bad impression on me I judged it wise for my head to clear off to the countryside – otherwise I would have swiftly run round to your place. And it gives me enormous pleasure that you say that you liked the portrait of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs> based rigorously on your drawing.<ptr target="#note-t-2"/> I tried to be respectfully faithful to your drawing while taking the liberty of interpreting through the medium of a colour the sober character and the style of the drawing in question.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.3" n="3">It’s a synthesis of an Arlésienne if you like, as syntheses of Arlésiennes are rare, take it as a work by you and me, like a summary of our months of work together. To do it I, for my part, paid with another month of illness,<ptr target="#note-t-3"/> but I also know that it’s a canvas that will be understood by you, me and just one or two others, as we’d like it to be understood. Here my friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs> came to it completely after two, three hesitations and says: ‘how difficult it is to be simple’. Right – I’m going to emphasize the thing even more by etching it, that thing, then that’s enough. Whoever wants it can have it.<ptr target="#note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.4" n="4">Have you also seen the olive trees?<ptr target="#note-t-5"/> Now I have a portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs> with the deeply sad expression of our time.<ptr target="#note-t-6"/> <hi rend="italics">If you like</hi> something like you were saying about your Christ in the Garden of Olives, not destined to be understood,<ptr target="#note-t-7"/> but anyhow up to that point I follow you, and my brother clearly grasps this nuance.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.5" n="5">I also have a cypress with a star from down there.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.6" n="6"><figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.7" n="7">A last try – a night sky with a moon without brightness, the slender crescent barely emerging from the opaque projected shadow of the earth – a star with exaggerated brightness, if you like, a soft brightness of pink and green in the ultramarine sky where clouds run. Below, a road bordered by tall yellow canes behind which are the blue low Alpilles, an old inn with orange lighted windows and a very tall cypress, very straight, very dark.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.8" n="8">On the road a yellow carriage harnessed to a white horse, and two late walkers.<ptr target="#note-t-8"/> Very romantic if you like, but also ‘Provençal’ I think. I’ll probably make etchings of this one, and of other landscapes and subjects, reminiscences of Provence, then I’ll look forward to giving you an ensemble, a rather deliberate and studied summary. My brother says that <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Lauzet</rs>, who’s doing the lithographs after <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1240">Monticelli</rs>, liked that head of the <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_383">Arlésienne</rs>.<ptr target="#note-t-9"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/></p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.9" n="9">So you’ll understand that having arrived in Paris a little confused I haven’t yet seen any of your canvases. But soon I hope to return there for a few days. Very pleased to learn from your letter that you’re returning to Brittany with <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1075">De Haan</rs>. It’s highly likely that – if you allow me – I’ll come for a month to join you there to do a seascape or two, but especially to see you and make the acquaintance of De Haan. Then we’ll try to do something deliberate and serious, as it would probably have become if we’d been able to continue down there.</p>
<p rend="indent" xml:id="p.en.10" n="10">Look, an idea which will perhaps suit you. I’m trying to do studies of wheat like this, however I can’t draw it –</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.11" n="11"><figure facs="zone-sketch-2" n="B"/></p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.12" n="12">nothing but ears, blue-green stems, long leaves like ribbons, green and pink by reflection, yellowing ears lightly bordered with pale pink due to the dusty flowering. A pink bindweed at the bottom wound around a stem. On it, on a very alive and yet tranquil background, I would like to paint portraits. It is greens of different quality, of the same value, in such a way as to form a green whole which would by its vibration make one think of the soft sound of the ears swaying in the breeze.<ptr target="#note-t-10"/> It’s not at all easy as a colour scheme.</p><space unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
<p xml:id="p.en.13" n="13"><figure facs="zone-sketch-3" n="C"/></p>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <standOff>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="typednotes">
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_transcrSource" type="transcrSource">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Original manuscript</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_dating" type="dating">
                    	    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">This unfinished letter is a response to Gauguin’s letter <ref target="let884.xml">(884)</ref>, which probably dates from about Friday, 13 June. Van Gogh writes here, as well as in a letter to Theo of 17 June <ref target="let889.xml">(889)</ref>, that he is working on a painting of wild plants, thistles and ears of wheat. We have therefore dated the present letter to about Tuesday, 17 June 1890.</p>
                    	</note>
                    
                    
                    
                    	<note xml:id="n_remarks" type="remarks">
                    	    
                                    
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">The letter is unfinished and was never sent. Jo van Gogh-Bonger noted above the letter in <hi rend="italics">Brieven </hi>1914: ‘Onvoltooide brief uit deze dagen onder zijn papieren gevonden’ (Unfinished letter from this time found under his papers). The sent version is not known. See Hulsker 1998, pp. 44-45.</p>
                                    
                                
                    	</note>
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="ogtnotes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="ogt_1">
                            
<p xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">Visit to Paris <ref target="let872.xml">(872)</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
                <listAnnotation xml:lang="en" type="notes">
                    
                        <note n="1" xml:id="note-t-1">
                            

<p>This was <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let884.xml">letter 884</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="2" xml:id="note-t-2">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2893">F 542 / JH 1894</rs>); <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let884.xml#n-2">see letter 884, n. 2.</ref> With regard to <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s drawing, , <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_97">Madame Ginoux (study for ‘Night café, Arles’)</rs></hi>, on which Van Gogh based the portrait, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let856.xml#n-4">see letter 856, n. 4.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="3" xml:id="note-t-3">
                            

<p>Van Gogh is referring to the attack he suffered on 22 February 1890; <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let857.xml#n-1">see letter 857, n. 1.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="4" xml:id="note-t-4">
                            

<p>This plan to make an etching after the Arlésienne never materialized; the only etching Van Gogh made in Auvers was the one after the portrait of <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_389">Dr Gachet</rs> (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="#n-5">see n. 5</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="5" xml:id="note-t-5">
                            

<p>Van Gogh's paintings of olive trees that were at Theo's, see letters <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let823">823</ref>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let834">834</ref>, and <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let863">863.</ref></p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="6" xml:id="note-t-6">
                            

<p>
      <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Doctor Gachet</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2916">F 753 / JH 2007</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="7" xml:id="note-t-7">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_101">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml#n-10">see letter 817, n. 10.</ref> In that letter Gauguin told Van Gogh that ‘this canvas isn’t destined to be understood’ <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let817.xml#l-49">(l. 49)</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="8" xml:id="note-t-8">
                            

<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Road with a cypress and a star</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_241">F - / JH 1983</rs>) was made after the painting of the same name <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2907">F 683 / JH 1982</rs>.</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="9" xml:id="note-t-9">
                            

<p>For <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1149">Lauzet</rs>’s edition of <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><ref target="biblio.xml#lit_517">Adolphe Monticelli</ref></hi>, <ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let825.xml#n-7">see letter 825, n. 7.</ref> Theo’s remark about the portrait could refer to either Lauzet or <rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="person" ref="bio.xml#_1039">Gauguin</rs>; we assume, however, that he was referring to the latter (<ref xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" target="let888.xml#n-7">see letter 888, n. 7</ref>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                    
                        <note n="10" xml:id="note-t-10">
                            
      
<p>The letter sketch <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics"><rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_242">Ears of wheat</rs></hi> was made after <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ears of wheat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2925">F 767 / JH 2034</rs>). It is not known whether the sketch at the end of the letter, <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Ears of wheat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#_243">F - / JH -</rs>), was also made after a painting. Van Gogh painted two portraits against a background of wheat: <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl against a background of wheat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ill_2933">F 774 / JH 2053</rs>) and <hi xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" rend="italics">Girl against a background of wheat</hi> (<rs xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#noill_933">F 788 / JH 2055</rs>).</p>
                        </note>
                        
                            

                        
                    
                </listAnnotation>
            </standOff>

        </TEI>    
    